<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b310282c" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Microfluidic flow transducer based on the measurement of electrical admittance</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">A new flow transducer for measuring the flow rate of a conducting fluid in a microchannel is reported.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">In this paper, the measure of flow of such fluid under laminar flow conditions based on the change of electrical admittance is established with the aid of a pair of electrodes parallel to the line of flow in a glass–PDMS microfluidic device.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">This flow sensor is simple in design and can be integrated to most of the microfluidic platforms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The effect of flow rate of the electrolyte, the frequency of the applied ac voltage, the voltage applied across the detector electrodes, and the conductivity of the electrolyte are varied to optimize for high sensitivity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The optimized values are then used to demonstrate the measurements of very low flow rates (&lt;1 nL s<SP>–1</SP>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">This flow sensor can be extended towards the measurement of chemical and biochemical buffers and reagents.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The development of multifunctional, high throughput lab-on-a-chip devices depends heavily on the ability to measure flow rate and perform quantitative analysis of fluids in minute volumes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Traditionally, there have been many MEMS-based (MEMS = microelectromechanical system) flow sensors for gaseous flows.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In recent times, there has been some advancement in measuring micro-flows of liquids.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Examples of sensing principles explored in the measurement of microfluidic flow are heat transfer detection,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2 cit3 cit4">2–4</REF> molecular sensing,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF> atomic emission detection,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF> streaming potential measurements,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF> electrical impedance tomography,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF> ion-selective field-effect transitors<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF> and periodic flapping motion detection.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Flow sensors form the integral part of micrototal analysis systems<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF> with multisensors.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Conversely, a measure of electric current is used for pumping a measurable flow rate of fluids in electro-osmotic flow (EOF).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Flow sensors based on sensing the temperature difference between two points in the microchannel<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2 cit3 cit4">2–4</REF> can sense very low flows.</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="No">However, such flow sensors require a complicated design and the integration of the heater, temperature sensors and membrane shielding is difficult to implement.</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="No">Moreover, the sensitivity and accuracy of the flow sensors depend on the environment associated in the heat transfer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="No">Most other methods are not capable of measuring very low flow rates.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">We consider flow sensing by directly measuring the electrical admittance of the fluid using two surface electrodes.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In electrolytes flowing in a microchannel under laminar flow conditions, a parabolic velocity profile exists and so the ions in the middle of the channels travel faster than those near the walls.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This results in the redistribution of ions within the electric double layer (EDL) formed in the channel.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ac voltage across the channel electrodes (Fig. 3) drives the ions back and forth across the electrodes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ionic redistribution develops electrokinetic effects and contributes to change in electric admittance.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">Thus the flow of fluid is very sensitive to the admittance across microelectrodes<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14 cit15">14,15</REF> in the flow channels, and measuring the increase in admittance precisely accounts for the flow rate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">Our flow sensor operating with optimized electric parameters can be efficient and accurate for precise values of flows.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">This method is relatively simple and suitable for most of the chemical and biochemical microfluidic applications since most of the reagents used are electrolytes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">In this paper, we present such a flow sensor based on the measurement of electrical admittance.</annotationART></s></P><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Principle</HEADER><P><s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In hydrodynamic conditions, forced convection dominates the transport of ions to the electrodes within the flow channels.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">When the width of the microfluidic channel is very small compared to the length of the channel, the lateral diffusion of the ions is significant under laminar flow.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Under an ac electrical signal applied across the channel, the equivalent circuit<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF> of the microsystem is shown in Fig. 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The electrical double layer<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF> formed across the channel is formed from two capacitances namely diffuse layer capacitance (<IT>C</IT><SB>s</SB>) and the outer Helmholtz plane capacitance (<IT>C</IT><SB>e</SB>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The former is due to ion excess or depletion in the channel, and the latter is due to the free electrons at the electrodes and is independent of the electrolyte concentration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The smaller of these capacitances dominates the admittance since these two capacitances are in series.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The frequency of the applied ac voltage, flow rate and conductivity of the fluid are the factors affecting the admittance of the fluidic system and our flow sensing principle is based on the optimization of these parameters.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">For an electrochemical oxidation of a species A to A<SP>+</SP> in a microchannel, the convective–diffusive equation for mass transport under steady state conditions is given by eqn. (1):where [A] is the concentration of the species, <IT>D</IT><SB>A</SB> is the diffusion coefficient and <IT>v<SB>x</SB></IT> is the velocity in the direction of flow.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The first term is the lateral diffusion in the microchannel and the second term is the transport along the length of the channel.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Under steady state flow conditions the boundary condition is given by eqn. (2).</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The solution of this equation predicts the mass transport limited current (<IT>i</IT><SB>L</SB>)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF> as a function of flow rate, <IT>Q</IT> as given by eqn. (3):where <IT>n</IT> is the number of electrons transferred, <IT>F</IT>, the Faraday constant, <IT>x</IT><SB>e</SB> is the electrode length, <IT>h</IT>, the cell half-height, <IT>d</IT>, the width of the cell and <IT>w</IT>, the electrode width.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is to be noted that the current due to flow of electrolyte is directly proportional to the cube root of volume flow rate of the fluid.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ac voltage signal is considered rather than dc voltage since the application of an ac voltage in the flow sensor does not promote any electrode reaction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Optimization of the electrical parameters like voltage and frequency of the ac signal are considered as an operating condition for measuring low flow rates.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">This optimizes the distance of movement of ions and their relaxation behavior across the channel electrodes so that the current admittance suffered is maximum.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Experiment</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Fabrication</HEADER><P><s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The flow sensor is fabricated<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19">19</REF> on a glass substrate with gold surface electrodes (Fig. 2a) and the microfluidic channel is made on PDMS.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Gold metal of thickness 100 nm is deposited on an adhesion layer of titanium with thickness 20 nm using e-beam deposition.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">A spinned layer of Shipley photoresist (1827) is used for patterning (Fig. 2b) the metal.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The electrodes are patterned by etching gold and titanium with potassium iodide solution (KI + I<SB>2</SB> + H<SB>2</SB>O = 4:1:40) and 2% HF respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Shipley photoresist is removed with acetone.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The distance between the electrodes is 100 µm and the length of the electrodes is 5 mm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Gold electrical lines are patterned on the glass as shown in Fig. 2a for the electrical measurement.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Measurement is performed across one of the three electrodes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">PDMS channels of width 500 µm are made from an SU8 mold.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Glass and PDMS are bonded together after treatment with oxygen plasma for 1 min.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fluidic channel is aligned with the parallel electrodes using a stereo microscope.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Measurements</HEADER><P><s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The measuring instrumentation is similar to that used in strain gauge or thermocouple interfaces.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">An ac voltage is applied across the channel electrodes in series with a standard resistor.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The voltage across the resistor is fed to a National Instrument's data acquisition card (NI DAQ PCI 6024E) through the signal conditioner (SCXI 1100) as shown in Fig. 3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rms values of voltage across the standard resistor are measured in Labview with a scanning rate of 20 000 samples per s and averaging every 10 000 samples.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Sodium hydroxide (NaOH) solutions with conductivities ranging from 5 to 200 mS cm<SP>–1</SP> (corresponding to 0.01 M to 1 M) are prepared with NaOH pellets bought from Fisher Scientific.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The concentration of the NaOH solution is chosen at 0.8 M and experiments are carried out for frequency and current response.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Microfluidic flow is maintained at a constant flow rate using a Harvard Picoplus Syringe pump.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">An ac signal of rms voltage 0.05 V is applied in the circuit by a signal generator.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rms voltage across the parallel microelectrodes increases to 0.04 V after wetting the channel (with no flow of electrolyte through it).</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">With some trials of experiments it was found that the current values grow and decay exponentially and stay constant after 1 min.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to keep the uniformity in all the experiments, the fluid is allowed to flow in the channel for 1 min and the flow is switched off for 1 min before any other measurement.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The current flowing across the pair of electrodes is calculated from the measured voltage across the standard resistor of 1 kΩ.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The current exponentially grows when the flow is switched on and then stays constant.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">After switching off the flow, the current again decays exponentially until it reaches a constant value.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The difference between two constant values of current gives the current increase due to flow and is measured in all the experiments.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Results and discussion</HEADER><P><s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Flow of fluid is quantitatively analyzed for the flow sensor characteristics in steps of 5 µL min<SP>–1</SP>, and an almost linear response was shown (as in Fig. 4) for the currents measured with flow rates.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ac frequency used in this case is 500 Hz at 0.05 V. As pointed out earlier, the current increase, which is a measure of admittance is proportional to the cube root of volume flow rate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="New" advantage="None">NaOH is used in this paper as a convenient test solution to demonstrate the flow sensor.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="New" advantage="No">The problem with higher concentration NaOH is that it tends to absorb the atmospheric CO<SB>2</SB> and form carbonic acid.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is reflected in the drift of the baseline in Fig 4a.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">The drift in the baseline can be calibrated with respect to time.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">However this drift in baseline is not seen for biochemical solutions that are buffered.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In another experiment, the frequency of the ac signal is swept from 10 Hz to 5 kHz in steps of 10 Hz in the 10–100 Hz range, 100 Hz in the 100–1000 range and 1 kHz in the 1–5 kHz range.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the equivalent circuit of the microchannel is capacitive dominant, the base current (with no flow) increases with frequency.</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">At each frequency, the measurement of current before and after flow is brought to a constant value by waiting for 1 min.</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The redistribution of ions in the channel causes an increase or decrease of current.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is observed that the admittance is maximized at 500 Hz as shown in Fig. 5.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is due to the competitive capacitive effects of the <IT>C</IT>e and <IT>C</IT>s as described earlier.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is to be understood that the efficiency of the flow sensor is found to be high at this frequency.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ac voltage applied has a great influence on the flow driven current.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Higher voltage increases the diffusive region in the channel which in turn decreases the diffusive capacitance (<IT>C</IT>s).</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">But the contribution of the capacitance at outer Helmholtz plane becomes more prominent and the admittance increases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, at voltages more than 400 mV, partial electrolysis takes place and the effective current decreases with voltage.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 6 shows the optimization of voltage of the ac signal used in the flow sensor.</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The V–I characteristic of the flow sensor (with no flow) shows a parabolic response similar to the conductivity measurement of electrolytes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus the flow sensor is tuned for the ac voltage of 400 mV.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">NaOH solution of different concentrations were studied in the flow sensor.</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is found that there is an optimum value of the concentration of the electrolyte for the flow sensor to be at its maximum efficiency.</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 7 shows that the concentration of the flow sensor is optimized at 0.2 M. At lower concentrations the admittance increases with more numbers of ions in the fluid system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">When the ionic concentration is too large the flow of fluid does not further increase the admittance because of inter-ionic interactions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">However generally the buffers or electrolytes used in microfluidic application are in mM concentration and the optimization of concentration is not necessary.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Using the optimized electrical parameters (<IT>f</IT> = 500 Hz, <IT>V</IT> = 0.4 V and concentration = 0.2 M), the flow sensor is designed for measuring very low values of flow rate starting at 0.05 µL min<SP>–1</SP> (&lt;1 nL s<SP>–1</SP>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The response shows a cube root behavior even at very low flow rates as shown in Fig. 8.</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The sensitivity at these optimizations is 5.2 × 10<SP>–4</SP> mA/(µL/min).</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In another experiment, fluorescent beads of diameter 2.5 µm are mixed with NaOH and sent through the channel.</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The motion of the beads at the flow rates .05, 0.1, 0.2, 0.4, and 0.6 µL min<SP>–1</SP> are recorded using optical video microscopy at 30, 60, 120, 250, 250 frames per s respectively, and the beads at a particular stream are analyzed and averaged to predict the velocity response at very low flow rates.</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The sensor results are compared with the velocity of beads (the symbol * in Fig. 8) and shows similar response.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus the calibration of the flow sensor is accomplished using the velocity measurements with beads.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Though this paper presents NaOH as the fluid used for demonstration of this flow sensor, different electrolytes and biochemical buffers have been tested for the sensitivity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">CaCl<SB>2</SB>, KCl and KOH (from Fisher Scientific) and a concentration of 0.8 M is used.</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Dulbecco's Phosphate Buffered Saline (D-PBS) solution and Modified Eagle Medium (D-MEM) (high glucose) buffer are bought from GIBCO and are used in the same concentration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Optimization of frequency of the ac signal alone is done for the fluids at 50 mV rms applied voltage.</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The typical increase of currents is measured for the flow rate of 10 µL min<SP>–1</SP> and the sensitivity values are tabulated in Table 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">These buffers and reagents are used in chemical and biochemical experiments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">When these fluids are used in lab-on-chips, the flow rates of the fluids can be determined using the flow sensor we described in this paper.</annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">It is to be noted that though we optimized the conductivity of the electrolyte for this study, it is not required and therefore the sensor can be used with arbitrary concentrations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="No">Conductivity depends on the constituent materials and changing the conductivity of certain buffers/reagents will alter the biochemical reaction.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">The principle of measuring electrical admittance laid out in this paper can be used to decipher parameters other than flow.</annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">There have been several reports<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21 cit22">21,22</REF> on the detection of biomelecules and cells in lab-on-chip devices based on impedance spectroscopy of the solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="No">In these methods, the measurements are done with static fluids.</annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">By measuring impedance change due to different conditions of flow it is possible to investigate the constituents of the solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the future, impedance spectroscopy based on differential flow can thus be used to characterize electrolytes including biomolecules, cells or microbes under laminar flow.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Conclusions</HEADER><P><s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">A novel microfluidic flow sensor based on electrical admittance measurement is designed, fabricated and characterized.</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The efficiency of the flow sensor is maximized by the optimization of electrical parameters such as frequency and voltage of the applied ac signal.</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">These optimized values are then used to measure flow rates as low as 1 nL s<SP>–1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The response of the flow sensor is compared with the velocity of microbeads in the same channel using video microscopy and image processing.</annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">Some of the advantages of the flow sensor include simplicity in design, integration to most microfluidic platforms, high signal-to-noise ratio, measurements of a wide range of liquids including biochemical buffers and compatibility with micromachining processes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This flow sensor has the potential to measure a broad range of liquid properties, including the characterization of biomolecules and microbes in microfluidic channels.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
