<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b312984e" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Pressure induced phase transition and amorphization of Na<SB>3</SB>ONO<SB>2</SB></annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">The high pressure behavior of Na<SB>3</SB>ONO<SB>2</SB> has been investigated by Raman spectroscopy and angle-dispersive X-ray diffraction from synchrotron radiation by using the diamond anvil cell technique.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Pressure induced phase transitions and finally amorphization are observed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Starting from cubic symmetry at ambient conditions Na<SB>3</SB>ONO<SB>2</SB> transforms to a rhombohedral high pressure phase at 0.7 GPa.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Beyond 14.1 GPa, the crystalline structure destabilizes and amorphous state is achieved.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="1.">Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Na<SB>3</SB>NO<SB>3</SB>, known since 1937, was first regarded as sodium orthonitrite.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In 1977, using single crystal X-ray diffraction, the true nature of the compound was discovered to be sodium oxide nitrite, Na<SB>3</SB>O(NO<SB>2</SB>), with a cubic anti-perovskite type structure.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2 cit3 cit4">2–4</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The NO<SB>2</SB><SP>–</SP> ion, disordered at room temperature, occupies the cuboctahedral intersticies formed by the 12 Na<SP>+</SP> ions of the (Na<SB>3</SB>O)<SP>+</SP> framework.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Recent neutron scattering studies<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF> have shown that, upon cooling, Na<SB>3</SB>ONO<SB>2</SB> undergoes crystallographic phase transitions from a cubic (space group <IT>Pm</IT>3̄<IT>m</IT>) to a tetragonal M-Na<SB>3</SB>ONO<SB>2</SB> (space group <IT>I4</IT>/<IT>mcm</IT>) structure at 240 K, then to a tetragonal T-Na<SB>3</SB>ONO<SB>2</SB> (space group <IT>P</IT>4/<IT>mbm</IT>) structure at 178 K, and to a tetragonal TT-Na<SB>3</SB>ONO<SB>2</SB> (space group <IT>P</IT>4̄2<SB>1</SB><IT>m</IT>) structure around 68 K, due to one discontinuous and two continuous ordering processes of the nitrate ion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The high pressure behavior of Na<SB>3</SB>ONO<SB>2</SB>, particularly with regard to the possibility of pressure induced formation of the still unknown NO<SB>3</SB><SP>3–</SP> ion, has not been examined.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">This Communication reports the results of X-ray powder diffraction studies of Na<SB>3</SB>ONO<SB>2</SB> at high pressures up to 18 GPa at room temperature and 573 K, respectively.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.">Experimental</HEADER><P><s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Na<SB>3</SB>ONO<SB>2</SB> was prepared by the solid state reaction of sodium oxide (Na<SB>2</SB>O) and sodium nitrite (NaNO<SB>2</SB>) as previously described.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The crystal structure has been determined at ambient conditions using X-ray and neutron diffraction data.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2 cit3 cit4 cit5">2–5</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The high pressure experiments were carried out in a diamond anvil cell (DAC) apparatus.</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The sample was loaded in a hole of T301 steel gasket in a glove box and no pressure transmitting medium was used due to the severely hygroscopic character of the sample.</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The pressure was calibrated by the ruby luminescence method.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The angle-dispersive X-ray powder diffraction experiments (<IT>λ</IT> = 0.4154 Å) in a DAC were performed at the beam line ID9 of the European Synchrotron Radiation Facility (ESRF), Grenoble, France.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Diffraction patterns were recorded on an image plate and then integrated by using the program FIT2D.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Raman spectra were collected at room temperature by a Jobin-Yvon LabRAM laser microscope Raman system using a CCD detector with excitation line 632.8 nm (He–Ne laser).</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.">Results and discussion</HEADER><P><s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The change of Raman spectra of the sample with increasing pressure is shown in Fig. 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">At ambient condition, two Raman modes, the <IT>δ</IT> mode and the <IT>ν</IT><SB>as</SB> mode of the NO<SB>2</SB><SP>–</SP> ion,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF> are observed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both Raman modes show a trend to higher frequencies as a function of pressure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the <IT>δ</IT> mode, the ratio of d<IT>ω</IT>/d<IT>P</IT> is estimated as 2.13 cm<SP>–1</SP> GPa<SP>–1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The <IT>ν</IT><SB>as</SB> mode is located near the Raman peak of diamond, which was used as the high pressure cell anvils, and overlaps with the diamond peak during the compressing process after 10.3 GPa and the d<IT>ω</IT>/d<IT>P</IT> is estimated as 1.44 cm<SP>–1</SP> GPa<SP>–1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This enables us to determine the mode Grüneisen parameter , which is evaluated at zero pressure as .</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The zero pressure bulk modulus, <IT>K</IT><SB>0</SB>, is estimated as 47.5 GPa for the high pressure phase which is obtained from X-ray diffraction analysis (see later).</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Then <IT>γ</IT><SB>G</SB> are calculated as 0.125 for the <IT>δ</IT> mode and 0.052 for the <IT>ν</IT><SB>as</SB> mode, respectively.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The intensity of the <IT>δ</IT> mode decreases with increasing pressure, it is observed up to 12.4 GPa, and it completely disappears at 14.1 GPa.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">None of the Raman peaks recover and no Raman active peak, <IT>i.e.</IT> neither the Raman modes of NO<SB>2</SB><SP>–</SP> nor the hypothetical NO<SB>3</SB><SP>3–</SP>, which are possible reaction products, could be observed during the decompressing process from 17.4 GPa to 0.2 GPa.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">These results indicate that bonds between N–O in the sample are cleaved above a pressure of 14.1 GPa, and imply that the pressure induced structural conversion is an irreversible process.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 2 shows the typical XRD patterns of the sample under various pressures during the compressing processes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Using the program GSAS,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF> the Rietveld refinements were carried out for all of the diffraction patterns.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The 4th profile function in GSAS was adopted since this function uses the microstrain broadening description<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF> and is more suited to high pressure conditions than other profile functions in GSAS.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results reveal that Na<SB>3</SB>ONO<SB>2</SB> loses its cubic (space group <IT>Pm</IT>3̄<IT>m</IT>) symmetry and transforms to a rhombohedral (space group <IT>R</IT>3̄<IT>m</IT>) high pressure phase (R–Na<SB>3</SB>ONO<SB>2</SB>) at about 0.7 GPa.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The main structural feature of the anti-perovskite structure remains unchanged during the pressure induced phase transition process due to the similarities of the diffraction patterns to the cubic structure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 3 shows a typical refinement result of the powder pattern at 1.3 GPa during compression, in which the background of diffraction pattern is removed first and the refinement converged to <IT>R</IT><SB>p</SB> = 14.3%, <IT>R</IT><SB>wp</SB> = 18.7%.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 4 shows the lattice parameters of R–Na<SB>3</SB>ONO<SB>2</SB> as a function of pressure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">As a result of the pressure induced distortion the perfect cubic framework of (Na<SB>3</SB>O)<SP>+</SP> transforms to a rhombohedral symmetry, the unit cell angle changes from 90° at ambient conditions to 90.92° at 0.7 GPa, and then gradually to 94.68° at 10.1 GPa.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">When the pressure is increased up to 11.9 GPa, the ratio between intensities of reflections and background in the diffraction pattern decreases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">After 14.5 GPa the crystalline structure of Na<SB>3</SB>ONO<SB>2</SB> is destabilized and an X-ray diffraction amorphous state is achieved.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The sample remains amorphous when the pressure was increased up to 18 GPa, as it does upon decompressing down to 0.5 GPa.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">This behavior of pressure induced amorphization is in agreement with the high pressure Raman results.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reason for the change from crystalline state to an amorphous one seems to be a proceeding decomposition of the sample.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">This decomposition proceeds <IT>via</IT> cleavage of N–O bonds instead of structural separation into the normal decomposition products Na<SB>2</SB>O and NaNO<SB>2</SB> which is shown by the missing reflections in the X-ray diffraction patterns as well as the lack of any NO<SB>2</SB><SP>–</SP><IT>ν</IT> or <IT>δ</IT> modes in the Raman spectra of the sample after it was compressed with more than 14.5 GPa.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">As another result from the lack of Raman modes we can exclude the desired formation of the hypothetical NO<SB>3</SB><SP>3–</SP> ion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The product, possibly a mixture of different phases, does not crystallize again during decompressing and may be inhibited by its topological features because of the lack of activation energy which is necessary for the rearrangement in the solid state.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The pressure induced amorphization has attracted intensive attention from a fundamental viewpoint over the last two decades.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10 cit11 cit12 cit13">10–13</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Amorphous solids, which have no long-range order and are frozen into a particular structural arrangement, are metastable with respect to crystalline phases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The different mechanisms of pressure induced amorphization were proposed pertaining to special compounds.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">One mechanism suggests a negative pressure dependence of the melting temperature, thus the extension of the melting curve would pass through the amorphization pressure at room temperature, as observed in ice-I, SiO<SB>2</SB>, and Ca(OH)<SB>2</SB> cases of pressure induced amorphization.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10 cit11 cit12">10–12</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">For Na<SB>3</SB>ONO<SB>2</SB>, a slow decomposition instead of melting occurs on heating up to 623 K at normal pressure, this encouraged us to perform high temperature high pressure experiments in order to check the possible negative pressure dependence of the decomposition temperature.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Using an internal heating DAC device, the high pressure angle-dispersive X-ray powder diffraction experiments at a temperature of 573 K were carried out to compare with the room temperature results.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Firstly we increased the pressure up to 5 GPa, then heated to 573 K and remained at this temperature, then increased the pressure up to 15 GPa.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The impurity peaks of Na<SB>2</SB>O and NaNO<SB>2</SB>, which are products of decomposition at ambient condition, are observed together with those of Na<SB>3</SB>ONO<SB>2</SB> in the XRD patterns measured under a pressure range of 5–12 GPa.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Compared to room pressure where the decomposition temperature is 623 K, the relative lower decomposition temperature under higher pressure conditions reveals the characteristic of pressure induced structural destabilization of Na<SB>3</SB>ONO<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The X-ray reflections disappear upon compression beyond 13 GPa at 573 K, this pressure is a little lower than the amorphization pressure of 14.5 GPa at room temperature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore the negative pressure dependence of decomposition and amorphization temperature was observed.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition to some general interest in the high pressure behavior of Na<SB>3</SB>ONO<SB>2</SB>, the orientational disorder of nitrite ion inside the sodium oxide framework is of special interest.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The orientational disorder is expected to be reduced under high pressure while the sodium oxide framework transforms from cubic symmetry to the lower rhombohedral symmetric structure, then it has lost its translational symmetry in the amorphous state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the diffraction methods could not really distinguish dynamic disorder phenomena due to the measured patterns being averaged over space and time.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The relative poor quality of the high pressure diffraction data, due to stress distribution in the high pressure cell without pressure transmitting medium as well as strong preferred orientation phenomena of the sample, hampered us from obtaining clear information on the evolution of orientational disorder of NO<SB>2</SB><SP>–</SP> under pressure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore the change of the orientational disorder, if present, in the pressure induced decomposition remains unclear.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Very recently, solid state nuclear magnetic resonance techniques have been used to study the NO<SB>2</SB><SP>–</SP> disorder phase transition behavior change upon cooling,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF> and this technique may be applied to disclose the corresponding orientational disorder behavior for the high pressure phase in the future.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The behavior change of the relative unit cell volume of R–Na<SB>3</SB>ONO<SB>2</SB> with pressure is shown in Fig. 5.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The equation of state of R–Na<SB>3</SB>ONO<SB>2</SB> could be fitted into the second order Birch equation of state, in which the pressure derivative of the bulk modulus <IT>K</IT><SB>0</SB>′ remains as .4<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The zero pressure bulk modulus (<IT>K</IT><SB>0</SB>) is estimated as 47.5 GPa.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">It indicates that R–Na<SB>3</SB>ONO<SB>2</SB> is a soft high pressure phase, which could work well as a pressure transmitting medium itself in DAC during high pressure experiments.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.">Conclusion</HEADER><P><s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">In summary, Na<SB>3</SB>ONO<SB>2</SB> has been investigated by <IT>in situ</IT> high pressure angle-dispersive X-ray diffraction from synchrotron radiation and Raman spectroscopy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">A phase transition from cubic symmetry at ambient conditions to a rhombohedral phase at a pressure of around 0.7 GPa is observed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Beyond 14.1 GPa, the crystalline structure destabilizes and an amorphous state is achieved.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The negative pressure dependence of the decomposition temperature of the sample reveals the mechanism of the pressure induced amorphization.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
