<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b313691d" hasDoc="yes" version="1168" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Ultrafast temporary charge transfer in pyrrolidinyl–benzonitrile and pyrrolyl–benzonitrile in the gas phase</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">4-(<IT>N</IT>-pyrrolidinyl)benzonitrile and 4-(<IT>N</IT>-pyrrolyl)benzonitrile were excited by an ultrashort pulse at 270 nm to their L<SB>a</SB> (S<SB>2</SB>) states and then probed by ionization at long wavelengths.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Parent and fragment ion signals show components with time constants &lt;100 fs which we attribute to ultrafast relaxation to the L<SB>b</SB> (S<SB>1</SB>) state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">From this short time we infer a conical intersection between the L<SB>b</SB> and L<SB>a</SB> surfaces.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The wave packet can branch there, one part going temporarily to a strongly displaced state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Its shift was concluded from an anisotropy observed only there.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The only excited state known to have a large displacement is the charge-transfer (CT) state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The positive anisotropy indicates that the CT state belongs to the 2A species for both molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">For pyrrolylbenzonitrile, this is in contrast to previous assignments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The anisotropy, and a coherent oscillation observed in pyrrolidinylbenzonitrile, support the idea that the amino-group twist is an important component of the CT reaction coordinate.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="1.">Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">On UV excitation in solvents of suitable polarity, many donor–acceptor substituted aromatics such as 4-dimethylaminobenzonitrile (DMABN) show dual fluorescence, originating from an L<SB>b</SB>-like and a charge-transfer (CT) state (reviews.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2 cit3 cit4">1–4</REF>)</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The pathway for charge transfer is still controversial (see <IT>e.g</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6 cit7">refs. 5–7</REF>.)., although the amino-group twist is most popular as the reaction coordinate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Gas-phase investigations with femtosecond time resolution have resulted in new insights, revealing the key role of a conical intersection (CI),<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit9 cit10">8–10</REF> a feature only beginning to be considered in CT reactions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">Furthermore, coherent oscillations observed with this method gave evidence of the relaxation direction and thus also provides information about components of the reaction coordinate.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9 cit10">9,10</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The method involves exciting such a molecule by a weak femtosecond UV pump pulse (in our case at 270 nm) and then probing it by ionization by an intense IR pulse, measuring the ion yields mass-selectively as a function of pump–probe delay.</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Using various probe wavelengths (810, 1300 and 2100 nm), we investigated in this work 4-(<IT>N</IT>-pyrrolidinyl)–benzonitrile (PYRBN) and 4-(<IT>N</IT>-pyrrolyl)–benzonitrile (PBN).</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">The donor group in the former is a saturated amino group, whereas in the latter it is the aromatic pyrrole. </annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">According to spectroscopy in cold molecular beams (PYRBN,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11 cit12 cit13">11–13</REF> PBN;<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF> see also the work on pyrrolylbenzene<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF>), the longest-wavelength absorption leads to the L<SB>b</SB> state (1B<SB>2</SB> in the idealized symmetry <IT>C</IT><SB>2v</SB>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The transition is weak and polarized perpendicularly to the long molecular axis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">This band is insensitive to para-substituents (since the latter are in a node of the L<SB>b</SB> wavefunction) and the medium (due to the small transition moment and little change of dipole moment).</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">A much stronger absorption, parallel-polarized and partially covering the weaker one in solution (solution spectra of PYRBN:,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF> of PBN:<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17 cit18 cit19">17–19</REF>) leads to the L<SB>a</SB> state (symmetry 2A<SB>1</SB>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The excitation wavelength is near the absorption maximum of this band.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">As will be further discussed in sec.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">4, in the compounds with a saturated amino group the L<SB>a</SB> state involves promotion of an electron from the HOMO to the LUMO, the former being π-antibonding and the latter weakly π-bonding between the amino group and the benzene ring (see <IT>e.g.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20 cit21">refs. 20 and 21</REF>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">As to conclude from the fluorescence polarization, the CT state also belongs to the A species in these cases;<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF> the L<SB>a</SB> and CT states are thus just two locations on the same 2A surface.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit4 cit8 cit21 cit23 cit24">1,4,8,21,23,24</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">This surface is lowered from L<SB>a</SB> to CT by interaction with a higher π-antibonding <IT>n</IT>A state on excursion along certain coordinates, a candidate for which is the amino-group twist.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit21">8,21</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Along the same coordinates, the lower L<SB>b</SB> state rises and crosses the 2A surface in a symmetry-allowed conical intersection (CI).</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">After initial excitation to L<SB>a</SB>, a wave packet can thus rapidly reach the CI and branch there to the CT and L<SB>b</SB> states.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The temporary population in CT is then depleted towards L<SB>b</SB><IT>via</IT> a path leading around the lower cone of the CI (see sec.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">4).</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">We found this scheme to apply for DMABN and PIPBN<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit9 cit10">8–10</REF> and present evidence that it is also suitable for PYRBN.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Surprisingly, it seems also to apply for PBN.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">This was not expected, because quantum chemical calculations predicted a 2B symmetry for the CT state, involving excitation from another pyrrole orbital to the LUMO.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20 cit25">20,25</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the other hand, another calculation<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26">26</REF> only reported on a CT state of 2A type.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">In pyrrolylbenzene two CT states, one with B and the other with A symmetry, were found very close-by.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27">27</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The pyrrole ring is slightly twisted <IT>versus</IT> the benzene ring in S<SB>0</SB> and L<SB>b</SB> of pyrrolylbenzene<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF> and probably similarly in PBN (symmetry group <IT>C</IT><SB>2</SB>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both rings are expected to be planar.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">In PYRBN, however, the amino N is slightly pyramidal, and the two rings are not twisted against each other (symmetry group <IT>C</IT><SB>s</SB>) according to a DFT calculation.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28">28</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">This was also inferred from photoelectron spectra.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">(Such spectra were reported for PBN, too.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17 cit29">17,29</REF>)</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">A previous prediction of a slight twist and puckering of the pyrrolidino ring by molecular mechanics<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF> is probably less reliable than the DFT calculation.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28">28</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The kinetics and fluorescence of PYRBN<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30 cit31 cit32 cit33 cit34 cit35 cit36">30–36</REF> and PBN<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17 cit18 cit29 cit37">17,18,29,37</REF> were previously investigated in solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">It was found that the L<SB>b</SB> → CT charge-transfer reaction required a solvent of at least medium polarity (to lower the CT state) for PYRBN, whereas PBN shows this reaction already in alkanes.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.">Experimental</HEADER><P><s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The preparation of PYRBN and PBN is described in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17 cit29 cit33">refs. 17, 29 and 33</REF>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The two species were investigated in the gas phase in the set-up (details described in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit38">ref. 38</REF>) heated to 130 °C to avoid adsorption; the substances themselves were at 20 °C.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The molecules were pumped by a frequency-tripled pulse of a Ti:sapphire laser system (270 nm, 75 fs, 10<SP>9</SP> W cm<SP>–2</SP>) and then probed by nonresonant dissociative ionization at the fundamental wavelength (810 nm, 50 fs, 10<SP>13</SP> W cm<SP>–2</SP>); in further experiments, probing was done by the output of a parametric generator (Topas) at 1300 and 2100 nm (40 fs, 10<SP>13</SP> W cm<SP>–2</SP>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The two beams had linear polarizations with an angle of 55° (“magic angle”) between each other in order to avoid time dependences induced by molecular rotation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In some experiments at 810 nm we also compared the signals at parallel and perpendicular polarizations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">More experimental details are described in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit10">refs. 8 and 10</REF>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The shape of the signals did not depend on the <IT>pump</IT> intensity (varied by a factor of about three).</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">This proves that they are produced by a single pump photon.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Varying the <IT>probe</IT> intensity by a similar factor did not change the time constants, although the later parts of the signals (coming from lower molecular states) were raised at higher probe intensities.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.">Results</HEADER><P><s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The UV spectra of PYRBN and PBN (not shown), measured in the gas phase at 80 °C, look very similar to that of DMABN.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit39">39</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The strong structureless L<SB>a</SB> band has a maximum at 273 (PYRBN) and 270 nm (PBN) (4.54 and 4.59 eV).</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">A weak precursor at longer wavelengths is certainly the L<SB>b</SB> band for both molecules; according to the supersonic-beam spectra, their 00 bands are at 32 018<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11 cit12 cit13">11–13</REF> and 34 424 cm<SP>–1</SP><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF> (3.97 and 4.26 eV), respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hence the initial excitation at 270 nm places the molecules at an energy of 0.57 and 0.33 eV above the L<SB>b</SB> minimum.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ion signals investigated with time resolution were the parent ion (M<SP>+</SP>) and the most intense fragment (about 10% of M<SP>+</SP>), which was M<SP>+</SP> – 1 for PYRBN and M<SP>+</SP> – 28 for PBN.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Time dependent signals at different probe wavelengths are shown for the first few picoseconds in Figs. 1 and 2 for PYRBN and 3 for PBN.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Similarly as found in PIPBN<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10 cit40">10,40</REF> and DMABN,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF> PYRBN exhibits a periodic modulation of the signals between about 0.5 and 3 ps which is extracted (see below) and Fourier-transformed in Fig. 2 from the data for the parent ion with 1.3 µm probing.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">By contrast, although the PBN signals show some irregularities, an oscillation could not unambiguously be extracted from them.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The time evolution was measured up to 600 ps (not shown); in this part, the signals simply decayed doubly exponentially.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In a first step, we simulated the nonperiodic part of the signals by a sum of exponentials with time constants <IT>τ</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB> (Table 1), convoluted with pump and probe pulses.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Subtracting this part from the PYRBN data left the oscillating part (Fig. 2), whose Fourier transformation (Fig. 2 bottom) gave the wavenumber and period <IT>τ</IT><SB>osc</SB> also reported in Table 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This part could also be simulated by a damped oscillation of the type exp(–<IT>t</IT>/<IT>τ</IT><SB>deph</SB>)cos(2π<IT>t</IT>/<IT>τ</IT><SB>osc</SB> + <IT>ϕ</IT>)Using <IT>τ</IT><SB>osc</SB> from the Fourier transform, we deduced the dephasing time and phase from this simulation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The simulation procedure is described in detail in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10 cit38">refs. 10 and 38</REF>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">For a given molecule, the set of time constants is the same, independent of probe conditions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Only the coefficients of the exponentials depend on the probe wavelength and the ion mass observed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is interpreted by population <IT>L</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB> flowing consecutively from one observation window L<SB><IT>i</IT></SB> to the next.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">This flow is described by rate equations, whose solution is a sum of exponentials for each population (the same, independent of probe conditions).</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Each L<SB><IT>i</IT></SB> has a mass spectrum of its own, and their dependence on the probing conditions help to distinguish the signals from the different L<SB><IT>i</IT></SB>; the spectra are represented by the relative ionization cross sections <SP><IT>m</IT></SP><IT>σ</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB>, <IT>i.e.</IT> the probabilities to produce an ion of mass <IT>m</IT> from window L<SB><IT>i</IT></SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">They are simulation parameters and are also given in the table.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The data are redundant for deducing the <IT>τ</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB> and the populations <IT>L</IT><SB>i</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 2 shows by the thin lines the simulation components (<SP><IT>m</IT></SP><IT>σ</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB> × <IT>L</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB>), whose sums for all <IT>i</IT> add up to the signals for mass <IT>m</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The very short <IT>τ</IT><SB>1</SB> is needed to reproduce the steep rise of the parent signals.</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None"><IT>τ</IT><SB>2</SB> causes, for instance, the delayed rise of the fragment as compared to the parent, clearly visible at 1300 nm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None"><IT>τ</IT><SB>3</SB> represents the decay of the initial spike, which is evident in particular at the longer probe wavelengths.</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The flat part of the signals extending from &lt;1 ps to beyond the range shown is due to contributions from L<SB>3</SB> and L<SB>4</SB>, the former decaying in the same time <IT>τ</IT><SB>3</SB> as the latter rises.</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The decays in the range up to 600 ps (<IT>τ</IT><SB>4</SB>, <IT>τ</IT><SB>5</SB>) are not shown.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 4 shows the anisotropies <IT>r</IT> calculated for the two molecules from the signals at 810 nm (other wavelengths not investigated) with the probe polarization parallel and perpendicular to that of the pump: <IT>r</IT> = (<IT>S</IT><SB>∥</SB> – <IT>S</IT><SB>⊥</SB>)/(<IT>S</IT><SB>∥</SB> + 2<IT>S</IT><SB>⊥</SB>).Obviously, for both molecules <IT>r</IT> ≈ 0 for the parent ion, whereas for the fragment <IT>r</IT> begins with positive values and decays in the picosecond range.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The asymptotic value, which is difficult to determine, is set to 0 in the figure.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.">Discussion</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.1.">Relaxation path for PYRBN</HEADER><P><s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The PYRBN signals are very similar to those for DMABN and PIPBN.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit10">8,10</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Because also the molecules are very similar, we can directly take over the assignments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Consequently we also use the same scheme of potential surfaces and relaxation paths (Fig. 5).</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Similarly as in DMABN, an evidence for transient population of the CT state is based on the anisotropy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">This can be seen as follows: The ionization itself is isotropic, which is confirmed by the zero-anisotropy observed for the parent ion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Photodissociation of the parent ion by absorption of an additional probe photon can, however, give rise to an anisotropy of the fragment ions, which will be positive if there is a resonant ionic transition at 810 nm (1.53 eV) polarized parallel to the pump laser, that is parallel to the long axis of the molecule.</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">After vertical ionization from a state with near-equilibrium geometry, there is no such resonance, as to judge from the energy difference of photoelectron bands.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore a substantial distortion is necessary in the neutral molecule to reach a geometry with such a resonance in the ion; the only low-lying excited state with strong displacement is the CT state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">This assignment implies that the anisotropy decay of Fig. 4 contains a contribution from this internal relaxation (time constant <IT>τ</IT><SB>3</SB>) and is not purely due to rotation; evidence for such a double origin was presented for DMABN in .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">ref. 9</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">As already discussed previously,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF> the temporary population of the CT state implies that low-quantum yield CT emission should be detectable from the gas phase and in nonpolar solvents; the latter has indeed been observed in DMABN.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit41 cit42">41,42</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is interesting in this context that a recent work on spectroscopy of similar molecules in cold supersonic beams also suggested population of the CT state, if the excess energy is sufficient.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit43">43</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is instructive to have a closer look to the ionic resonance.</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Energy differences of ion states are just equal to orbital energy differences in the neutral molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Orbitals and their energies are easy to understand by the help of their nodal pattern.</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The HOMO of PYRBN has the symmetry species b<SB>1</SB> and is π-antibonding between donor and acceptor moieties (Fig. 6).</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ground state of the parent ion (<SP>2</SP>B<SB>1</SB>) has a hole in this orbital (single occupancy).</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The HOMO – 1 has a node containing the amino group; it has the species a<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">An ionic <SP>2</SP>A<SB>2</SB> → <SP>2</SP>B<SB>1</SB> transition would be perpendicularly polarized, which would disagree with our parallel anisotropy in observation window L<SB>3</SB> (or the strongly displaced state claimed to correspond to CT).</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">HOMO – 2 provides the right symmetry (b<SB>1</SB>), since an ionic <SP>2</SP>B<SB>1</SB> → <SP>2</SP>B<SB>1</SB> transition would be parallel; it is π-bonding between amino donor and the benzonitrile parts.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">A displacement coordinate drastically weakening this π interaction may approach the two b<SB>1</SB> orbitals sufficiently, so that a resonant transition in the ion will be possible, as indicated in Fig. 6.</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">There are not many coordinates with this property.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">A twist of the amino group was predicted to do it,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16 cit20">16,20</REF> and Figs. 5 and 6 were therefore drawn assuming that the twist is an important (but not the only, see below) component of the reaction coordinate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">A strong pyramidalization of the amino group would probably be less effective, and planarization would do the opposite.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">So, as in PIPBN<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF> and DMABN,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit9">8,9</REF> we assign for PYRBN the times below 100 fs (<IT>τ</IT><SB>1</SB>, <IT>τ</IT><SB>2</SB>) to departure from the Franck–Condon region and further relaxation through a conical intersection (CI) to both the L<SB>b</SB> and CT minima (Fig. 5).</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The conclusion that the path leads through a CI can again be obtained from the shortness of <IT>τ</IT><SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The next time constant (<IT>τ</IT><SB>3</SB>) corresponds to L<SB>b</SB> ↔ CT equilibration around the lower cone of the CI.</annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">As before, the much longer <IT>τ</IT><SB>4</SB> is ascribed to intersystem crossing, probably to T<SB><IT>n</IT></SB>, which then can rapidly equilibrate with T<SB>1</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">From there, the molecule decays within <IT>τ</IT><SB>5</SB> to the ground state, from which ionization was too weak to be detected.</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">(Any excited state would be detectable).</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">This process may be accompanied by decomposition such as H elimination, as suggested in PIPBN<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.2.">The oscillation in PYRBN</HEADER><P><s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The observed oscillation period is 530 fs.</annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Its damping (dephasing) time is 1.4 ps.</annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">The only excited state with sufficiently long lifetime is L<SB>b</SB> (or the observation window L<SB>4</SB>, representing the L<SB>b</SB>-CT equilibrium.</annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">This equilibrium is expected to lie on the L<SB>b</SB> side, because the CT state is higher in energy).</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">So the oscillation must be a vibration in the L<SB>b</SB> well.</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">In fact, converting the period <IT>τ</IT><SB>osc</SB> to wavenumbers <IT>ν</IT> by <IT>ν</IT> = 1/<IT>cτ</IT><SB>osc</SB>, one receives 64 cm<SP>–1</SP>, very close to a value (69 cm<SP>–1</SP>) observed in supersonic-beam spectra of the L<SB>b</SB> state of PYRBN.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11 cit12 cit13">11–13</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">There are not many vibrations with such a low wavenumber in this molecule.</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">According to semiempirical PM3 calculations for S<SB>0</SB>, there are only three below 100 cm<SP>–1</SP>: (1) arching (42 cm<SP>–1</SP>), where the CN and pyrrolidine groups bend in phase out of plane <IT>versus</IT> the benzene ring, (2) amino group twist (54 cm<SP>–1</SP>) and (3) another arching (85 cm<SP>–1</SP>), where the CN and pyrrolidino-N bend in phase out of plane, whereas the C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>4</SB> end group moves out of phase.</annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">Because the electronic interaction of the benzene with its substituents is only minor in the L<SB>b</SB> state, these wavenumbers are not expected to be very different in this excited state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hence, the observed oscillation should be assigned to the lower-frequency arching or to the twist vibrations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Arching involves the inversion motion of the amino nitrogen.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, both vibrations deserve a little more scrutiny, taking the symmetry of PYRBN into account: According to DFT calculations,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28">28</REF> in the ground state, the twist angle <IT>θ</IT> = 0 and the wagging angle (angle between the benzene and pyrrolidine planes) is only <IT>ω</IT> = 8°.</annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Any barrier at <IT>ω</IT> = 0 will be smaller than in DMABN (where <IT>ω</IT> = 15° in S<SB>0</SB><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit44">44</REF>), where it has recently been reevaluated and found to be &lt;100 cm<SP>–1</SP> in S<SB>0</SB> and &lt;50 cm<SP>–1</SP> in L<SB>b</SB>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit45">45</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">(As mentioned in the Introduction, a molecular-mechanics calculation predicted <IT>θ</IT> = 15° in S<SB>0</SB>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">This would imply also a minor barrier at <IT>θ</IT> = 0°.</annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">It would not much change the following considerations).</annotationART></s> <s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">The L<SB>b</SB> potential must be very similar, since the 00 transition is by far stronger than the adjacent bands in the vibrational structure.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11 cit12 cit13">11–13</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore both types of vibration will occur between two turning points that are symmetry-equivalent.</annotationART></s> <s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Also the ion is expected, due to the partial double bond between the amino group and the benzene ring, to have its potential minimum at <IT>θ</IT> = 0 and <IT>ω</IT> ≈ 0, not displaced <IT>versus</IT> that of L<SB>b</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">A vibration (belonging to an antisymmetric species) in such a symmetric potential will therefore give rise to signal maxima twice in each period.</annotationART></s> <s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">(This is the equivalent to the spectroscopic selection rule Δ<IT>v</IT> = 2 for antisymmetric vibrations in electronic transitions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">It will also apply for the 69-cm<SP>–1</SP> structure in the PYRBN supersonic beam spectrum,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11 cit12 cit13">11–13</REF> if our assignment is correct).</annotationART></s> <s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore we should divide by two to convert the observed period to wavenumbers: <IT>ν</IT> = (2<IT>cτ</IT><SB>osc</SB>)<SP>–1</SP>We thus calculate <IT>ν</IT> = 32 cm<SP>–1</SP> for the vibration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">At present we cannot decide between the two possible assignments to twist or arching.</annotationART></s> <s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">In DMABN we observed both types of oscillations,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF> whereas in PIPBN we attributed a strong modulation to the arching vibration.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Its assignment was based on a substituent mass effect observed for it.</annotationART></s> <s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">In PIPBN, the neutral and ion potentials are displaced against each other (due to the nonplanar piperidine ring), so that the factor of two in (3) does not apply, although it does apply in PYRBN for symmetry reasons: The potential is symmetric to <IT>ω</IT> = 0 in this molecule.</annotationART></s> <s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">(We assume that the vibration takes place above any barrier)..</annotationART></s> <s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">The wavenumber thus calculated for PIPBN was 31.4 cm<SP>–1</SP>, very close to that calculated by (3) for PYRBN.</annotationART></s> <s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore we tend to the assignment as arching (involving amino group inversion).</annotationART></s> <s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The other vibration might be excited, too, even if it is not observed because possibly the L<SB>b</SB> and ion potentials are parallel in this direction, so that this vibration would not be Franck–Condon active and would not give rise to a signal modulation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" advantage="None">The wavenumber observed by us (0.5 × 64 cm<SP>–1</SP>) deviates from that in the cold supersonic jet (0.5 × 69 cm<SP>–1</SP>) by much more than the experimental error (0.5 cm<SP>–1</SP>, see Table 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="143"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">A plausible interpretation assumes that levels with v ≫ 1 are excited in our experiment, and the wavenumber difference is due to an anharmonic shift.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="144"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Also the L<SB>a</SB> potential will be symmetric to <IT>θ</IT> = 0 and <IT>ω</IT> = 0, again due to the partial double bond.</annotationART></s> <s sid="145"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore these vibrations will not (or nearly not) be Franck–Condon active in the pump transition.</annotationART></s> <s sid="146"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp10" novelty="None" advantage="None">They are thus not expected to be excited by the pump laser.</annotationART></s> <s sid="147"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Instead, they will be stimulated by acceleration on the last slope on entering the L<SB>b</SB> well from the CI.</annotationART></s> <s sid="148"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The direction of this slope therefore contains either <IT>θ</IT> or <IT>ω</IT> as an important component.</annotationART></s> <s sid="149"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both can be justified (and would be supported by an assignment): It was argued above (see also Fig. 5) and previously<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit9 cit10">8–10</REF> that a CI is probably displaced from the L<SB>b</SB> minimum towards a direction with <IT>θ</IT> as a component.</annotationART></s> <s sid="150"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp12" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the other hand, a b-type vibration such as the inversion (<IT>ω</IT>) could be stimulated by the 2A → 1B relaxation in the CI, which needs a symmetry-breaking distortion.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="151"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is remarkable that such oscillations can be understood as described, by considering a pathway with intermediate excursion of the wave packet <IT>via</IT> a conical intersection (as also recommended in .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit46">ref. 46</REF>)</annotationART></s> <s sid="152"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">A previous model<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit47">47</REF> would only consider electronic matrix elements and Franck–Condon factors between L<SB>a</SB> and L<SB>b</SB>; the latter factors are ≈ 0, because the potentials are not shifted against each other in the <IT>θ</IT> and <IT>ω</IT> directions.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.3.">Relaxation path for pyrrolylbenzonitrile</HEADER><P><s sid="153"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None">The kinetic behavior of PBN is very similar to that of PYRBN: There seems to be the same number of steps or observation windows, and the time constants differ by not more than a factor of 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="154"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None">This similarity is not expected, because PBN has 4 more π electrons than PYRBN, so that the level scheme could be different.</annotationART></s> <s sid="155"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac20" novelty="None" advantage="None">In fact, the lowest-energy CT state was predicted to belong to the 1B species<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20 cit25">20,25</REF> (in contrast to the 2A CT state of DMABN or PYRBN; see also the reviews<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2 cit4">2,4</REF><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">Ref. 17</REF>. found evidence that two different CT states play a role in PBN, depending on the solvent).</annotationART></s> <s sid="156"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac20" novelty="None" advantage="None">This state involves a transition from the HOMO of a<SB>2</SB> symmetry (localized on the carbons of pyrrole, node containing the nitrogen) to the b<SB>1</SB> LUMO of the benzonitrile moiety.</annotationART></s> <s sid="157"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac20" novelty="None" advantage="None">The orbital energies thus calculated<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF> are shown as functions of the twist angle <IT>θ</IT> in Fig. 6.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="158"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp13" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this scheme, ionization from the CT state would leave a hole in the a<SB>2</SB> orbital, giving an ion ground state <SP>2</SP>A<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="159"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The positive anisotropy found (Fig. 4) indicates a resonance in the ion parallel to the molecular axis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="160"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp14" novelty="None" advantage="None">We thus would need a <SP>2</SP>A<SB>2</SB> → <SP>2</SP>A<SB>2</SB> transition in the ion or the corresponding transition between a pair of a<SB>2</SB> orbitals.</annotationART></s> <s sid="161"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res29" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is obvious from Fig. 6 that the available orbital pair does not approach each other along the twist, and it seems hard to imagine any other coordinate, relevant to a charge transfer reaction, that could do so: Both orbitals have a node containing the substituents.</annotationART></s> <s sid="162"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res30" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the other hand, the pair of b<SB>1</SB> orbitals just does the required energy approach along the twist coordinate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="163"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp15" novelty="None" advantage="None">If we postulate that the CT state observed by us involves excitation of a b<SB>1</SB> electron (HOMO – 1 in Fig. 6b), certainly to the LUMO (b<SB>1</SB>) so that a 2A state would result, then the positive anisotropy would be understood by an ionic <SP>2</SP>B<SB>1</SB> → <SP>2</SP>B<SB>1</SB> transition in much the same way as for PYRBN (Fig. 6a).</annotationART></s> <s sid="164"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac21" novelty="None" advantage="None">This postulate is very much encouraged by a CASPT2 calculation which predicts practically degenerate CT states of 2B and 2A symmetry in pyrrolylbenzene at perpendicular geometry.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27">27</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="165"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp16" novelty="None" advantage="None">We suppose that attaching a para-cyano substituent (resulting in PBN) will lower the 2A state more than the 2B state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="166"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac22" novelty="None" advantage="None">In fact, another CASPT2 calculation reports for PBN at low energy only a 2A state with CT character.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26">26</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="167"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" advantage="None">We therefore interpret our anisotropy data as a support that the lowest CT state of PBN belongs to the 2A species and is thus on the same potential energy surface as the initially excited L<SB>a</SB> state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="168"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This implies that the same scheme for the surfaces and relaxation paths can be used as for PYRBN (Fig. 5).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="169"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast to PYRBN, no oscillations were observed in PBN (although some irregularities in the signals might indicate that there are some).</annotationART></s> <s sid="170"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res32" novelty="None" advantage="None">It may be that the L<SB>b</SB> potential and that of the ion are better parallel in PBN than in PYRBN, so an existing vibration would cause less signal modulation in PBN, because it would not be Franck–Condon active in ionization.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="5.">Concluding remarks</HEADER><P><s sid="171"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">It was surprising that the same potential energy scheme and relaxation paths (Fig. 5) could be used for PYRBN and PBN.</annotationART></s> <s sid="172"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res33" novelty="None" advantage="None">Apparently the states arising from the additional π electrons in PBN are higher in energy, including also a CT state of B symmetry.</annotationART></s> <s sid="173"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is also remarkable how little the early times <IT>τ</IT><SB>1</SB>–<IT>τ</IT><SB>3</SB> differ between the molecules DMABN,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF> PIPBN,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF> PYRBN and PBN investigated by our method.</annotationART></s> <s sid="174"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None">The largest variation was found in <IT>τ</IT><SB>3</SB>, which was 1.0, 1.9, 0.53 and 0.91 ps for the four compounds, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="175"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None"><IT>τ</IT><SB>3</SB><SP>–1</SP> is the sum of the forward (L<SB>b</SB> → CT) and backward (CT → L<SB>b</SB>) rates in the L<SB>b</SB>/CT equilibration, with the rate for the exothermic backward reaction dominating.</annotationART></s> <s sid="176"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res34" novelty="None" advantage="None">The CT → L<SB>b</SB> reaction is less exothermic in the gas phase for PBN than for PYRBN.</annotationART></s> <s sid="177"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">This can be concluded from the fact that CT fluorescence is already observed in nonpolar environments for PBN, whereas at least medium polar solvents are needed for PYRBN.</annotationART></s> <s sid="178"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res34" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hence, the longer <IT>τ</IT><SB>3</SB> for the former is not surprising.</annotationART></s> <s sid="179"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res35" novelty="None" advantage="None">The same can be said about the pair PIPBN and DMABN.</annotationART></s> <s sid="180"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res36" novelty="None" advantage="None">It seems also natural that reverse differences of rates were found in solution for the forward (L<SB>b</SB> → CT) reactions, whose reaction enthalpy is the negative of that of the CT → L<SB>b</SB> reaction.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="181"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac23" novelty="None" advantage="None">It may be worth repeating<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit9 cit10">8–10</REF> a comment on the amino-group twist as a component of the reaction coordinate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="182"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Whereas this twist gives rise to observable consequences such as the anisotropy (in this work) or a coherent oscillation (this work and <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9 cit10">refs. 9 and 10</REF>) and many others,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2 cit3 cit4">1–4</REF> it will not be the only component: It seems natural that the electron transferred in the CT state to the benzonitrile moiety causes CC bond lengthening there.</annotationART></s> <s sid="183"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac24" novelty="None" advantage="None">A CASPT2 calculation for PBN in fact found such effects.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26">26</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="184"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Because bond stretching is energetically more effective than twisting, such components can give rise to steep slopes, which may explain our very fast initial relaxations (<IT>τ</IT><SB>1</SB>,<IT>τ</IT><SB>2</SB>).</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
