<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b314263a" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Absence of fast precursor dynamics of low-density amorphous ice around its hypothetical glass transition temperature</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Elastic fixed window scans have been performed at the high-<IT>Q</IT> backscattering neutron scattering spectrometer IN13 (ILL) on low-density amorphous (LDA) ice between 2 K and up to 170 K, <IT>i.e.</IT>, above the phase transformation to crystalline ice I<SB>c</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Within the experimental accuracy no anomaly of the Debye–Waller factor is found below the recrystallization temperature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The data rule out the existence of fast precursor processes as they have been predicted by the mode coupling theory of the glass transition and found in molecular glass formers.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">There is a controversial discussion about the physical nature of the two known amorphous ice states, low-density amorphous (LDA) and high-density amorphous (HDA) ice.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">From computer simulations<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2 cit3">1–3</REF> it has been deduced that LDA and HDA represent the glassy states of two corresponding liquids, low-density water (LDW) and high-density water (HDW), respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">A number of experimental results seem to support this view: Structures similar to LDA and HDA can be produced by extremely fast quenching of microdroplets or the gas phase;<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit5 cit6 cit7">4–7</REF> calorimetry experiments<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit9 cit10 cit11">8–11</REF> indicate an endothermic “glass transition” around 130–135 K; and from D<SB>2</SB>O–H<SB>2</SB>O interlayer mixing upon heating<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF> of LDA-type vapour deposited water an increased mobility around 150 K has been found.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="No">On the other hand the above results are neither obtained in bulk samples nor do they constitute unequivocally a glass transition temperature in water.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Endothermal transitions have been observed under the same thermodynamic conditions in transformations of high-density crystalline ice phases to ice I<SB>c</SB> and understood as entropy driven order-to-disorder transitions in the proton sublattice,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF> a feature equally detected in ice I<SB>c</SB>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast to interlayer mixing effects ion diffusion experiments<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF> have not shown any higher mobility of guest molecules in the amorphous ice matrix.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Also, isotopic exchange experiments<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF> show no translational water motion but rather a defect promoted proton mobility responsible for the endothermic transition.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">A recently postulated<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17 cit18 cit19">17–19</REF> “shadow glass transition” at 165 K, and therefore unobservable, is invoked to explain the observed phenomena, thus being an issue of current controversial debates<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20 cit21 cit22">20–22</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Experiment</HEADER><P><s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The observable, the Debye–Waller factor as measured in neutron scattering, occasionally also called Mössbauer–Lamb factor if incoherent neutron scattering is considered, has been measured by fixed window experiments at zero energy transfer at the thermal backscattering spectrometer IN13 at the ILL Grenoble.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the present experiment, an IN13 standard setting with incident neutron energy of 16.5 meV and an energy resolution of 8 µeV has been used.</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The latter value means that any dynamic process faster than about 10 ns should lead to a decrease of the Debye–Waller factor.</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">Most important for the present purpose, IN13 offers the unique possibility to measure the elastic intensity <IT>I</IT><SB>el</SB> up to <IT>Q</IT>-values of more than 5 Å<SP>–1</SP>, thus being highly sensitive at small amplitude dynamics.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The <IT>Q</IT>-range is sampled by 32 detectors giving a resolution in <IT>Q</IT> of ±0.2 Å<SP>–1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">Using this combination of high energy resolution and large accessible <IT>Q</IT>-values we focus onto eventual glass transition phenomena of LDA in the best possible way.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">In the following, we will present the measured strict elastic intensity <IT>I</IT><SB>el</SB>(<IT>Q</IT>,<IT>T</IT>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The sample under consideration has been partially deuterated (60 vol% D<SB>2</SB>O) water.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The partial deuteration has been chosen for better control of the sample state due to the pronounced coherent Bragg scattering contributions in the crystalline state as will become obvious in the following section.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The sample has been prepared by compressing crystalline ice I<SB>h</SB> at 77 K (in liquid N<SB>2</SB>) in a piston-cylinder apparatus up to about 18 kbar.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The thus produced HDA is recovered at ambient pressure, filled in aluminium holders used as standard in neutron scattering and placed into a precooled (75 K) standard cryostat.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">After careful removal of remaining N<SB>2</SB> the thermal history of the sample has been as follows: (a) Cooling down to 2 K; (b) heating up the HDA sample to 125 K and observing the transformation of LDA.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">(c) Cooling down the LDA sample back to 2 K. (d) Performing a temperature scan up to 170 K where the LDA transformed to ice I<SB>c</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">(e) After cooling down to 2 K a third temperature scan is taken from the ice I<SB>c</SB> sample.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Elastic scans were performed during the heating intervals.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The temperature was increased in steps of 3.5 K each followed by one hour of data aquisition.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">In the frame of this communication we restrict the discussion below on the results obtained for <IT>I</IT><SB>el</SB>(<IT>Q</IT>,<IT>T</IT>)/<IT>I</IT><SB>el</SB>(<IT>Q</IT>, 2 K) from the temperature scan of the LDA sample exclusively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">The properties of analogous scans on HDA and ice I<SB>c</SB> and a general comparison of HDA with LDA will be the subject of a forthcoming publication<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25">25</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Results and discussion</HEADER><P><s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Being aware of the above controversial discussion the motivation for our present experiments is the following: If LDA and HDA do constitute glasses and if there exists a glass transition around 135 K, one may have a good chance to see dynamic precursor effects as, <IT>e.g.</IT>, postulated by mode coupling theory (MCT) of the glass transition.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26">26</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Such processes can be interpreted as fast overdamped rattling motions with increasing amplitudes as one approaches a critical temperature <IT>T</IT><SB>c</SB> above <IT>T</IT><SB>g</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">They manifest themselves by a pronounced deviation of the Debye–Waller factor from its harmonic behaviour, visible as an excess-loss of elastic intensity, in a temperature range above the glass transition temperature <IT>T</IT><SB>g</SB> (Fig. 1).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In favourable cases the onset of these deviations is already observable at temperatures significantly below the glass transition temperature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Experimentally, anomalies in the Debye–Waller factor have been found<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27 cit28">27,28</REF> in several molecular glass formers.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 2, top shows the static structure factor obtained for ice I<SB>c</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In our partially deuterated sample the coherent signal is strongly supressed and the <IT>Q</IT>-dependence of the normalized elastic intensites is relatively flat (Fig. 2, bottom).</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Nevertheless, the elastic intensity of the crystalline state (solid line) still shows modulations with broad maxima remaining at the <IT>Q</IT>-values of the Bragg-reflections in the high resolution static structure factor of ice I<SB>c</SB>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fact that the elastic intensity of the crystalline state is “oscillating” around the values from the amorphous LDA state will be a central point in the argumentation presented below.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results of the present study on LDA are contained in Fig. 3 which shows the temperature dependence of <IT>I</IT><SB>el</SB>(<IT>Q</IT>,<IT>T</IT>)/<IT>I</IT><SB>el</SB>(<IT>Q</IT>, 2 K) at those selected <IT>Q</IT>-values which are marked by arrows in Fig. 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that these <IT>Q</IT>-values have been chosen such that the intensities of the crystallized sample are alternatingly above or below the intensities of the amorphous sample.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is clearly seen from the figure that below 135 K the temperature dependence of this normalized elastic intensity behaves as expected for the Debye–Waller factor of a harmonic system, <IT>i.e.</IT>, ln[<IT>I</IT><SB>el</SB>(<IT>Q</IT>,<IT>T</IT>)/<IT>I</IT><SB>el</SB>(<IT>Q</IT>, 2 K)] ∝ –<IT>T</IT> for all <IT>Q</IT>-values.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Above 135 K, anomalies occur, and at some <IT>Q</IT>-values (open symbols in Fig. 3) the elastic intensity indeed decreases for temperatures above the glass transition temperature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">But from the observation that at those <IT>Q</IT>-values where the elastic intensity of the crystalline state is above the value of the amorphous state the elastic intensity goes up we can infer that crystallization takes place (shaded temperature interval).</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that from all curves shown in Fig. 3 the <IT>Q</IT> = 1.7 Å<SP>–1</SP> data gives the highest evidence for the onset of crystallization because (i) the best S/N-ratio is obtained at small <IT>Q</IT>-values and (ii) the 1.7 Å<SP>–1</SP> coincide with a strong Bragg peak of ice I<SB>c</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This obviously excludes any other interpretation which at the first sight might be tempting.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, the conclusion of our work is straightforward:</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None"><IT>Below</IT> the onset of recrystallization around 135 K there is no anomaly in the Debye–Waller factor of LDA.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Clearly, this result cannot be taken as an obvious, unambiguously proof that any glass transition scenario can be excluded.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">But it might be taken as another indication that a glass transition in LDA ice at about 135 K is still questionable and that the amorphous behaviour of LDA ice might be different from that known from other typical glass formers.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
