<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b315893d" hasDoc="yes" version="1190" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Using real-valued multi-objective genetic algorithms to model molecular absorption spectra and Raman excitation profiles in solution<XREF TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" /></annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The empirical modeling of the absorption spectra and resonance Raman excitation profiles of a large molecule in solution requires adjustment of a minimum of dozens of parameters to fit several hundred data points.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is a difficult optimization problem because all of the observables depend on all of the parameters in a highly coupled and nonlinear manner.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Standard nonlinear least-squares fitting methods are highly susceptible to becoming trapped in local minima in the error function unless very good initial guesses for the molecular parameters are made.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Here, we demonstrate a method that employs a real-valued genetic algorithm to force a broad search through parameter space to determine the best-fit parameters.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The multiobjective genetic algorithm is successful at inverting absorption spectra and Raman excitation profiles to determine molecular parameters.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">When vibronic structure is evident in the absorption profile, the algorithm returns nearly quantitative results.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">For broad, featureless profiles, the algorithm returns the correct slope of the excited state surface but cannot independently determine the excited-state frequency and the equilibrium geometry change.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Compared with manual adjustment of parameters to obtain a best fit, the genetic algorithm is computationally less efficient but requires less human time.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="1">Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Optical absorption spectra and resonance Raman excitation profiles contain information about a variety of important molecular parameters including the excitation energy, transition moment, excited state vibrational frequencies, and geometry changes along each coupled normal mode.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">We<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2 cit3 cit4">1–4</REF> and others<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6 cit7 cit8">5–8</REF> have utilized Raman excitation profiles to quantify excited state parameters and deepen our understanding of electronic processes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 1 illustrates a related pair of optical spectra and molecular parameters.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Chemical physicists have developed powerful theoretical and computational techniques that allow spectra to be calculated given knowledge of the potential energy surfaces, dynamics, and radiation-matter couplings of a particular system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Spectroscopists address the related problem of measuring the spectra and <IT>inverting</IT> the spectral observables to extract the physical parameters.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Within a given theoretical framework, it can be quite easy to calculate the optical spectra of even very large polyatomic molecules in the condensed phase.</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, it is difficult to objectively find the set of parameters that best fits the data, and it is particularly hard to justify those instances when it is necessary to go beyond the simplest assumptions and consider Duschinsky rotation or vibrational coordinate dependence of the electronic transition moment, for example.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Traditionally the “intelligently guided random search” has been employed by our group<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2 cit9 cit10 cit11 cit12">2,9–12</REF> and others.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13 cit14 cit15 cit16 cit17 cit18 cit19">13–19</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">This method involves guessing a set of parameters, calculating the spectra, comparing with experiment, modifying the parameters, recalculating the spectra, and continuing iteratively until a best fit between simulation and experiment is found.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="No">Since the spectra depend on the molecular parameters in a highly nonlinear fashion and the Raman data usually carry significant uncertainties, converging on a best fit set of parameters is slow, and it is rarely possible to be certain that the best fit has been found or that the best-fit parameters are unique.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In this paper, we use real-valued genetic algorithms to automate this iterative process of parameter optimization <IT>and</IT> simultaneously determine the uniqueness of the best-fit parameters.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">Genetic algorithms have been applied to a variety of problems in chemistry and physics that involve optimization in a large parameter space.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">These include determination of mechanisms and rate coefficients for complex reactions,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF> determination of structures from NMR spectra,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21 cit22">21,22</REF> molecular and cluster geometry optimization,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23 cit24 cit25 cit26">23–26</REF> parameter optimization in semiempirical electronic structure methods,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27">27</REF> numerical solution of the Schrödinger equation,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28">28</REF> optimization of vibrational force fields,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29">29</REF> and modeling of vibronic<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30 cit31">30,31</REF> and rovibronic<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit32">32</REF> molecular spectra.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Previously in our group, the absorption spectra of molecules with one vibrational mode were used to quantitatively determine molecular parameters in a three-step process.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit31">31</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">First, a neural network which had been trained to associate spectral patterns with their underlying molecular parameters was used to obtain an estimate of the relevant parameters.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">This initial guess was used to select the range of parameter space to be searched by a micro-genetic algorithm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The range was discretized into 2<SP>10</SP> bits in each dimension, and a random population was allowed to evolve toward the solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Since convergence of the population slowed as it neared the extremum, a traditional Levenberg–Marquardt nonlinear least squares search was grafted on to locate the true minimum.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="No">The method worked well, but training the neural network is a slow process which does not scale well for larger systems and the Levenberg–Marquardt steps add an extra layer of computational complexity and time.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our goal here is to develop a stand-alone genetic algorithm which can efficiently solve the spectral inversion problem for sets of absorption spectra and resonance Raman excitation profiles.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In Section 2 we describe a theoretical framework for calculating absorption spectra and Raman excitation profiles from fundamental molecular parameters, provide a physical interpretation of the parameters and define the objective functions which we seek to minimize in determining the best fit.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">We develop the simplest implementation of a real-valued genetic algorithm in Section 3 which is designed to meet a single objective (<IT>e.g.</IT>, fitting the optical absorption spectrum).</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The algorithm is successful at quantitatively fitting absorption spectra for one-mode systems.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">As the number of modes increases, the “uniqueness” of the fit is sacrificed but a range of parameters which provide quantitative fits can still be determined.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In Section 4, we extend our treatment to multiobjective problems in which there are several properties of interest (<IT>e.g.</IT>, the absorption spectrum and Raman excitation profiles for several fundamental, overtone and combination bands) which depend on the same set of parameters in different ways.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">The inclusion of Raman data enables reliable parameter optimization for multimode systems.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The largest calculations attempted describe a simplified <IT>p</IT>-nitroaniline molecule with five modes coupled to the electronic transition.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Finally, in Section 5 we comment on the strengths and weaknesses of genetic algorithms for inverting spectroscopic data.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2">Electronic spectroscopy</HEADER><P><s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The traditional approach to calculating Raman excitation profiles involves approximations to the energy-frame Kramers-Heisenberg-Dirac sum-over-states formula.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="No">These calculations quickly become intractable with even a few degrees of freedom when there are significant Franck–Condon displacements.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Instead, working directly in the time domain exploits the short-time nature of Raman scattering and leads to efficient calculations: The propagation time required to determine the Raman cross sections stays constant, or even decreases, as the number of degrees of freedom and displacements grows.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The computational method is based on the time-dependent formulation of Raman scattering<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit33">33</REF> which expresses the exact Raman amplitude in terms of a half-Fourier transform of the overlap between the initial ground state wavepacket propagating on the excited state surface |<IT>ϕ</IT><SB>i</SB>(<IT>t</IT>)〉 and the final stationary state |<IT>ϕ</IT><SB>f</SB>〉.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The scattering amplitude is given by where the frequency <IT>Ω</IT> = <IT>ω</IT><SB>i</SB> + <IT>ω</IT><SB>L</SB> − <IT>ω</IT><SB>0–0</SB> is the vibrational frequency of the initial state plus the incident laser frequency minus the purely electronic transition frequency.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The time correlation function is modulated by a solvent-induced spectral broadening <IT>g</IT>(<IT>t</IT>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the most naïve approximation, this damping can be modeled as a simple Lorentzian function governed by an electronic dephasing rate <IT>Γ</IT>, <IT>g</IT>(<IT>t</IT>) = <IT>Γ</IT><IT>t</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">We employ an overdamped Brownian oscillator in the high temperature limit<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit34 cit35">34,35</REF> to more carefully describe solvent interaction.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Following <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit36 cit37 cit38">refs. 36, 37 and 38</REF>, we assume that the initial population is in the vibrational ground state and for clarity consider a single coupled vibrational mode, where <IT>q</IT> is the ground-state dimensionless normal coordinate with conjugate momentum <IT>p</IT>. When the molecule is excited, the wavefunction propagates along the upper surface according to the excited state Hamiltonian, |<IT>ϕ</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB>(<IT>t</IT>)〉 = exp(−i<IT>H</IT><SB>e</SB><IT>t</IT>/<IT>ħ</IT>)|<IT>ϕ</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB>〉 with where <IT>q</IT>′ is the excited-state normal coordinate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The excited state surface is displaced <IT>Δ</IT>′ along the normal coordinate <IT>q</IT>′.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The general expression for the final state is where <IT>H</IT><SB><IT>n</IT></SB> is the <IT>n</IT>th Hermite polynomial with <IT>n</IT> = 0 for absorption, <IT>n</IT> = 1 for fundamental Raman scattering and <IT>n</IT> = 2 for overtone Raman scattering.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The explicit form of the overlap of the propagated initial wavepacket and the final stationary state is where<IT>ω</IT><SB>±</SB> = <IT>ω</IT><SB>e</SB> ± <IT>ω</IT><SB>g</SB>Here <IT>Δ</IT> is the displacement in ground-state dimensionless normal coordinates (<IT>Δ</IT> = (<IT>ω</IT><SB>g</SB>/<IT>ω</IT><SB>e</SB>)<SP>1/2</SP><IT>Δ</IT>′).</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">For molecules with more than one coupled vibrational mode, the total overlap function is a simple product of the single-mode overlaps as long as the ground- and excited-state normal coordinates are parallel (no Duschinsky rotation).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">For comparison to experiment, we calculate the Raman cross section according to where <IT>ω</IT><SB>S</SB> is the frequency of the scattered photon and <IT>M</IT> is the electronic transition length integral, assumed independent of vibrational coordinate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">A similar expression can be derived for the absorption cross section: where <IT>n</IT> is the solution refractive index.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Absorption is governed by the real part of the Fourier transform of the time autocorrelation function damped by solvent interaction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Many generalizations of these expressions have been developed<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit37 cit38 cit39">37–39</REF> which allow for greater complexity in the system including thermal population of initial vibrational levels, Duschinsky rotation, and coordinate dependent transition moments.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this work, the condensed-phase optical absorption spectrum and resonance Raman excitation profiles of a molecule having a single, isolated electronic transition between two harmonic potential energy surfaces are considered.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The calculations are performed within the Condon approximation (no vibrational coordinate dependence of the electronic transition moment), and it is assumed that the ground and excited state normal modes are the same (no Duschinsky rotation).</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Different frequencies in the ground and excited electronic states are allowed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ground state vibrational frequencies are assumed to be known from IR or Raman spectroscopy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The solvent-induced vibronic line broadening function is modeled by a single Brownian oscillator in the overdamped, high temperature limit<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit35">35</REF> with the lineshape parameter fixed at <IT>κ</IT> = 0.05.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Within these approximations, the absorption spectrum and Raman excitation profiles can be exactly determined given the following parameters.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">(<IT>i</IT>) <IT>Δ</IT>, the displacement for each normal mode between ground and excited state potential minima in ground state dimensionless normal coordinates which is needed to calculate the correlation function.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">(<IT>ii</IT>) <IT>ω</IT><SB>e</SB>/<IT>ω</IT><SB>g</SB>, the ratio of the excited and ground state vibrational frequencies for each normal mode which is needed to calculate the correlation function.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">(<IT>iii</IT>) <IT>Γ</IT>, the vibronic linewidth which is incorporated in the solvent-induced broadening governed by the Brownian oscillator damping function <IT>g</IT>(<IT>t</IT>).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">(<IT>iv</IT>) <IT>ω</IT><SB>0–0</SB>, the purely electronic transition frequency which governs the position along the frequency axis.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">(<IT>v</IT>) <IT>M</IT>, the electronic transition length which determines the integrated intensity (oscillator strength).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The goal of this work is to invert experimental spectra to determine these parameters for systems with several coupled vibrational modes.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">While the spectroscopic model employed to generate the calculated spectra involves common approximations suited to our molecular systems, the time-dependent approach to determine the absorption and Raman excitation profiles does not generally require them.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The algorithm presented here could easily be extended beyond these approximations to allow, for example, vibrational coordinate dependence of the transition moment, inhomogeneous broadening, or more than one contributing resonant excited state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The concomitant increase in the number of molecular parameters would, however, place even more stringent requirements on the quality and quantity of the Raman data.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">To monitor the progress of our fit, we compare the target spectra (analogous to experimental data) to calculated spectra which correspond to a particular set of parameters {<IT>a</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB>}.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The error associated with a calculated spectrum is governed by the mean absolute difference between calculated and target spectra where <IT>σ</IT>cA,R(<IT>ω</IT><SB><IT>j</IT></SB>) and <IT>σ</IT>tA,R(<IT>ω</IT><SB><IT>j</IT></SB>) are the calculated and target absorption or Raman cross sections at frequency <IT>ω</IT><SB><IT>j</IT></SB>, and <IT>N</IT> is the number of points in the target spectrum.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our choice of the absolute error in eqn. 12 instead of the relative error (where each term in the sum is divided by <IT>σ</IT>tA,R(<IT>ω</IT><SB><IT>j</IT></SB>) as used in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit31">ref. 31</REF>) does not overemphasize the lowest intensity points where experimental error may be more significant in the Raman excitation profiles.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The goal of the optimization is to find the {<IT>a</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB>} which minimize the error functions.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3">Genetic algorithms</HEADER><P><s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Genetic algorithms<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit40 cit41 cit42 cit43">40–43</REF> are global optimization methods that mimic the mechanisms of evolution: reproduction, natural selection, and diversification.</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">In biological systems, genetic information is encoded in the quaternary alphabet of DNA base pairs.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Sequences of base pairs comprise individual genes which correspond to traits in the developed organism; the genes are grouped into chromosomes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Through meiosis, the parental chromosomes crossover and recombine to form genetically unique children with qualities inherited from both parents.</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Random mutations further diversify the next generation though these events are infrequent and rarely beneficial.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Children develop and compete for resources and the opportunity to mate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Only the most fit phenotypes are expected to survive and propagate; they represent better solutions to adaptive problems.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod13" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the current problem of fitting molecular spectra, we consider the molecular parameters described in Section 2 to be analogous to the genes which determine each individual's characteristics.</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The phenotypes are the calculated spectra, analogous to the physical and behavioral characteristics of biological organisms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fitness of each individual is a measure of its similarity to the target spectrum.</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Only the best solutions are allowed to reproduce to drive the population toward the optimum solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this section, we detail our application of genetic algorithms to invert a target absorption spectrum, that is, to derive the molecular parameters that produce it.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The extension to include resonance Raman data is described in Section 4.</annotationART></s></P><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.1">Encoding</HEADER><P><s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod13" novelty="None" advantage="None">In recasting the optimization problem in terms of an evolutionary system, we kept the problem conceptually close to the real parameter space by constructing each chromosome from <IT>N</IT> floating-point numbers which directly correspond to the <IT>N</IT> parameters.</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Traditional genetic algorithms encode each parameter in an <IT>n</IT>-bit binary gene which has the unphysical property of assigning equal importance to (for example) the most and least significant bits.</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">Real-valued genetic algorithms have been shown to be robust, accurate, and efficient.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit44 cit45 cit46 cit47">44–47</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">A further advantage for this application is the relative compactness of <IT>N</IT> floating point numbers as compared to <IT>N</IT> × <IT>n</IT> zeros and ones.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">For complex systems with several parameters, the arrangement of genes within the chromosomes is important.</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Genetic algorithms are believed to rely on the conservation of successful patterns to guide the evolutionary process.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit40">40</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Successive evolutionary steps juxtapose these independent “building blocks” to construct the optimal solution.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit41">41</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The variables of our system are highly correlated and do not act independently in determining the phenotype.</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">When epistasis, or interaction among design parameters, occurs, convergence of the genetic algorithm is much more difficult.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit48">48</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Grouping entangled genes in the chromosome promotes the formation of robust, quasi-independent building blocks which have a high probability of being propagated to the next generation.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod14" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the conjugated organic molecular systems of interest to our group, we chose the parameter ranges shown in Table 1 for the normal-mode displacement, the relative excited-state frequency and the vibronic linewidth.</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Systems with resolved vibronic progressions and relatively narrow linewidths are best described in terms of the displacements and frequencies of each electronically coupled normal mode individually {<IT>Δ</IT><SB>1</SB>,<IT>ω</IT><SB>1</SB>,<IT>Δ</IT><SB>2</SB>,<IT>ω</IT><SB>2</SB>…}.</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod15" novelty="None" advantage="None">When the inner-sphere reorganization energy or vibronic linewidth increases, the vibronic progression becomes difficult to resolve.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Physically, the spectrum becomes more appropriately described in terms of the overall reorganization energy (width) and shape (asymmetry) of the curve.</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod15" novelty="None" advantage="None">To speed convergence, we recast the variables <IT>Δ</IT> and <IT>ω</IT><SB>e</SB>/<IT>ω</IT><SB>g</SB> into the mode-specific inner-sphere reorganization energy <IT>λ</IT> = <IT>ω</IT>2e<IT>Δ</IT><SP>2</SP>/2<IT>ω</IT><SB>g</SB> and a shape factor <IT>ρ</IT>, the ratio of <IT>Δ</IT><SP>2</SP> and <IT>ω</IT><SB>e</SB>/<IT>ω</IT><SB>g</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The overall width is a collective function of the reorganization energies and the linewidth.</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Convergence is accelerated by forming parameter blocks of the collective shape and width {<IT>ρ</IT><SB>1</SB>,<IT>ρ</IT><SB>2</SB>,…,<IT>λ</IT><SB>1</SB>,<IT>λ</IT><SB>2</SB>,…}.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The comparison of the target and calculated spectra is conducted in an energy window which extends from 2500 cm<SP>−1</SP> below to 5000 cm<SP>−1</SP> above the target spectrum maximum at 50 cm<SP>−1</SP> intervals.</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">To guarantee that the absorption features of the calculated spectrum occur within the observation window we adjust the pure electronic excitation frequency, <IT>ω</IT><SB>0–0</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">For systems with well-resolved vibronic structure and a dominant peak, the maxima of the target and calculated spectra are aligned.</annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="Old" advantage="None">All other spectra are adjusted such that the first moments of the calculated and target spectra coincide.</annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In both cases, we equate the integrated intensity of the absorption curves within the window to determine the transition moment.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.2">Evolution</HEADER><P><s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Upon randomly generating an initial population, we assume that the genetic pool contains the solution, or a better solution, to the adaptive problem of fitting the spectrum.</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod16" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the solution is not “active” because the optimal genetic combination is split among several members.</annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Just as in nature where individuals more successful in competing for resources are more likely to survive and propagate their genetic material, the algorithm's fitness function transforms the performance of each member into an allocation of reproductive opportunities.</annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The random crossover of these “most fit” partial solutions enables the algorithm to approach, and eventually find, the optimum.</annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Mutations allow the emergence of new configurations which widen the pool and improve the chances of finding the optimal solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod16" novelty="None" advantage="None">This process of evaluation, selection, recombination and mutation forms one generation in the execution of a genetic algorithm.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fitness of each member of the population is inversely proportional to the objective function defined in eqn. 12.</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod16" novelty="None" advantage="None">We take The simplest algorithm for selection maps the population onto a roulette wheel where each individual is represented by a space proportional to its fitness as in Fig. 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Individuals are entered into the mating pool by repeatedly spinning the roulette wheel.</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod17" novelty="None" advantage="None">This method leads to genetic drift, or a loss of population diversity, which is overcome using stochastic universal sampling.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit41">41</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod17" novelty="None" advantage="None">To prevent the domination of a single individual, after each spin of the wheel several (in our case, four) parents are selected and copied into the mating pool.</annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Parents are randomly chosen from this intermediate population to reproduce and are then discarded.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">In nature, crossover occurs when two parents exchange parts of their corresponding chromosomes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The most common approach for recombination of two parents represented by a vector of real numbers is flat crossover, a gene-by-gene weighted average, to give two children.</annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Each gene in the children <IT>c</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB> is expressed as a linear combination of their parents, where <IT>γ</IT> is a random number on the interval [0,1].</annotationART></s> <s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Flat crossover (see Fig. 2) explores more of the parameter space than the more traditional single-point crossover.</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod18" novelty="None" advantage="None">To maintain some consistency between successive generations, 20% of the population is generated by asexual reproduction, or with <IT>γ</IT> = 0.</annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the selection and crossover processes are stochastic, there is no guarantee that the algorithm will monotonically approach the optimum.</annotationART></s> <s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod18" novelty="None" advantage="None">To prevent backward steps, the best 10% of the solutions (the elite members<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit49">49</REF>) are allowed to survive into the next generation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The difference between asexual reproduction and survival of elite members is that elite chromosomes do not undergo mutation.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Successful convergence depends on a delicate balance between exploration of the parameter space and exploitation of good solutions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod19" novelty="None" advantage="None">This balance is governed by the mutation operator.</annotationART></s> <s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fitness proportionate selection exploits fit members to generate fit children.</annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod19" novelty="None" advantage="None">To avoid premature convergence to a non-optimal solution, and maintain population diversity, we use a dynamically updated mutation operator.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit50">50</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Each gene has an adaptive mutation rate <IT>δ</IT> normally distributed about zero according to ±<IT>δ</IT> = 1 − exp{−(0.5 − <IT>x</IT>)<SP>2</SP>/2.373}which takes a random <IT>x</IT> on the interval [0,1] and maps it to a percent deviation between 0 and 10% of the allowed parameter range.</annotationART></s> <s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod19" novelty="None" advantage="None">We choose <IT>δ</IT> to be negative if <IT>x</IT> &lt; 0.5.</annotationART></s> <s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Every ten generations, adaptation occurs by narrowing the allowed parameter range to the parameter average plus or minus two standard deviations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Generally, an at-first-sight needlessly large search region is sampled by the initial population to avoid missing the global minimum.</annotationART></s> <s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod19" novelty="None" advantage="None">During the optimization, we narrow the search toward the most promising region of the parameter space to increase the role of exploitation as the optimum is approached.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.3">Results</HEADER><P><s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="Old" advantage="None">A simple test of the efficacy of our algorithm is to construct target spectra with known parameters within the ranges given in Table 1 and then to invert the spectra.</annotationART></s> <s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Comparing the actual parameters to those returned by the algorithm affords a measure of our success.</annotationART></s> <s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">As expected, systems with few parameters and substantial vibronic structure are easiest to invert.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">For systems with a single mode coupled to the electronic transition, we always achieve a quantitative fit to the absorption spectrum for the parameter ranges in Table 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod20" novelty="None" advantage="None">Six randomly generated target spectra are shown in Fig. 3; the corresponding parameters are the bold entries in Table 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="143"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod20" novelty="None" advantage="None">To invert these spectra, the population size was fixed at 30 chromosomes which were allowed to evolve for 30 generations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="144"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The calculated spectra are superimposed on the target spectra in Fig. 3 and no differences are visible.</annotationART></s> <s sid="145"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Comparing the parameters (plain-type entries in Table 2) demonstrates that inversion of the spectra yields ∼1% error in the parameter values.</annotationART></s> <s sid="146"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Comparable results were obtained in our previous work<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit31">31</REF> by combining an integer valued genetic algorithm with Levenberg–Marquardt refinement.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="147"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="No">As we move to larger systems, the inversion becomes more difficult.</annotationART></s> <s sid="148"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod21" novelty="None" advantage="None">For example, the width of the absorption spectrum is governed by both the inner-sphere reorganization energy, a function of <IT>Δ</IT> and <IT>ω</IT><SB>e</SB>/<IT>ω</IT><SB>g</SB>, and the outer-sphere reorganization energy which depends on <IT>Γ</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="149"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="No">The non-separability of the parameters in the model plagues optimization techniques which typically rely on parameter additivity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="150"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">In the one-mode case this “epistasis” does not hinder inversion of the spectrum.</annotationART></s> <s sid="151"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">For multi-mode systems, the increase in both the number of parameters and the complexity of the relationship between them place much more stringent demands on the optimization technique.</annotationART></s> <s sid="152"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="New" advantage="None">It is also in this regime where an automated, objective fitting algorithm is most necessary.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="153"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod22" novelty="None" advantage="None">A “difficult” target absorption spectrum of a two-mode system was synthesized (closed circles in Fig. 4) from the parameters shown in the bottom, bold line of Table 3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="154"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod22" novelty="None" advantage="None">This absorption spectrum is relatively broad and the vibronic patterns of the individual normal modes cannot be distinguished.</annotationART></s> <s sid="155"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="New" advantage="None">Four attempts to invert this spectrum were made.</annotationART></s> <s sid="156"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="New" advantage="None">In each, the 60 member population was allowed to evolve for 60 generations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="157"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results are shown as the solid lines in Fig. 4 with the corresponding parameters entered in Table 3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="158"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">While it is only in the inset that the small errors in the calculated spectra are visible, the calculated parameters do not correspond to the target parameters.</annotationART></s> <s sid="159"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Generally, the algorithm fails to correctly invert spectra which are broad or lack clear vibronic progressions because the fits are not unique.</annotationART></s> <s sid="160"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">As the number of parameters increases and the resolution of spectral features decreases, several parameter sets produce nearly identical, good fits to the absorption spectrum.</annotationART></s> <s sid="161"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">More data are required to find a single best solution.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4">Multiobjective genetic algorithm</HEADER><P><s sid="162"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">More insight into the molecular parameters may be achieved with resonance Raman intensities.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2 cit3 cit4 cit5 cit6 cit7 cit8">1–8</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="163"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">For each mode coupled to the electronic transition, an experimental profile of the Raman cross section <IT>vs.</IT> laser frequency may be obtained.</annotationART></s> <s sid="164"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Each resonance Raman profile isolates the contribution of a single vibrational mode to the often unresolved vibronic structure of the absorption.</annotationART></s> <s sid="165"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Incorporating these data into the calculation of a fitness function is not straightforward, as typically there are many fewer data points with much higher uncertainties than in the linear absorption spectrum.</annotationART></s> <s sid="166"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">A direct statistical combination of the absorption and Raman data would fail to assign enough importance to the Raman experiments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="167"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">These data are incommensurate (cannot be measured on the same scale) and should not be combined into a single objective function.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="168"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this section, we describe an algorithm which simultaneously optimizes several objectives.</annotationART></s> <s sid="169"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">We begin by discussing multiobjective problems and defining Pareto-optimality.</annotationART></s> <s sid="170"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Next, we present a modified version of the strength Pareto evolution algorithm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="171"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Finally, we show results for a series of randomly generated target spectra which typify the spectroscopy of conjugated organic molecular materials.</annotationART></s></P><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.1">Background</HEADER><P><s sid="172"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Real-world design problems require the simultaneous optimization of multiple objectives which are often incommensurate, and sometimes competing.</annotationART></s> <s sid="173"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">These multiobjective problems typically do not have a single utopian solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="174"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Instead, they are solved by determining the tradeoff, or Pareto-optimal surface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="175"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Solutions along this surface are optimal in the sense that no other solutions in the search space are superior to them with respect to every objective.</annotationART></s> <s sid="176"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod23" novelty="None" advantage="None">To make the conditions of Pareto-optimality mathematically rigorous, we state that chromosome <SUP TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn2" /> if the fitness of <IT>x</IT> is greater than or equal to the fitness of <IT>y</IT> with respect to every objective, and that the fitness of <IT>x</IT> is greater than the fitness of <IT>y</IT> for at least one objective.</annotationART></s> <s sid="177"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 5 shows the approximate Pareto-optimal surface of a two-dimensional optimization problem as a solid line at the lower left of each panel.</annotationART></s> <s sid="178"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Nondominated solutions are indicated with solid circles, while dominated chromosomes are shown as open circles.</annotationART></s> <s sid="179"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">As the system evolves, the nondominated front approaches the Pareto-optimal surface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="180"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">For an arbitrary dominated chromosome, in the upper-right-hand panel, the dominated solutions are shown in light gray while the dominant solutions are shown in a darker gray.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="181"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In general, the goal of multiobjective problems is to find as many nondominated solutions as possible along the Pareto-optimal surface and then to allow a higher-level decision maker, who may possess additional information, to choose among them.</annotationART></s> <s sid="182"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the absorption spectrum and Raman excitation profiles are experimental data from the same molecule, they must be produced by a common set of molecular parameters–there should be a single best solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="183"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, there need not be a utopian solution if approximations such as separable harmonic vibrations are included in the model, or when spectral noise is considered.</annotationART></s> <s sid="184"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">The range of good solutions will provide information about the error tolerance for each molecular parameter and the appropriateness of the model.</annotationART></s> <s sid="185"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">The absence of an adequate fit indicates either an insufficient model or experimental noise.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="186"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod24" novelty="None" advantage="None">A problem which illustrates the Pareto-optimal surface can be artificially constructed by adding 25% rms noise to the Raman excitation profiles of a hypothetical two-mode system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="187"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod24" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since there is no longer an optimal solution which would generate the exact absorption and Raman spectra, we may examine the algorithm's ability to approach and sample the Pareto-optimal front.</annotationART></s> <s sid="188"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod24" novelty="None" advantage="None">(The algorithm is presented in detail in Section 4.2).</annotationART></s> <s sid="189"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod25" novelty="None" advantage="None">For this example, we fixed the population size at sixty chromosomes, each composed of seven floating point numbers {<IT>Δ</IT><SB>1</SB>,<IT>ω</IT><SB>1e</SB>/<IT>ω</IT><SB>1g</SB>,<IT>Δ</IT><SB>2</SB>,<IT>ω</IT><SB>2e</SB>/<IT>ω</IT><SB>2g</SB>,<IT>Γ</IT>,<IT>ω</IT><SB>0–0</SB>,<IT>M</IT>}, and allowed the population to evolve for sixty generations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="190"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod25" novelty="None" advantage="None">The two, simultaneous objectives are (1) to fit the absorption spectrum and (2) to fit the “noisy” Raman excitation profiles of the two coupled modes.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="191"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The evolution of the population toward the Pareto-optimal surface is shown in Fig. 5 where each chromosome is represented by a point in fitness space (<IT>O</IT><SB>A</SB>,<IT>O</IT><SB>R</SB>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="192"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Noise added to the Raman excitation profiles obviates a perfect solution which would be located at the origin.</annotationART></s> <s sid="193"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Initially, the nondominated chromosomes (filled circles) approach and spread out along the Pareto-optimal surface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="194"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">As evolution continues, the dominated chromosomes (open circles) approach the nondominated front.</annotationART></s> <s sid="195"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Even with fitness sharing<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit51 cit52 cit53 cit54 cit55">51–55</REF> (see Section 4.2) to minimize genetic drift toward a specific region of the tradeoff surface, the converged solution has reduced diversity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="196"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The two extreme nondominated solutions are designated by a star and asterisk with their corresponding spectra shown in Fig. 6 and parameter values in Table 4.</annotationART></s> <s sid="197"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The best solution with regard to absorption is shown in the bottom panel while the best solution with regard to the Raman excitation profile is shown in the top panel.</annotationART></s> <s sid="198"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">There is a clear trade-off in optimizing the two objectives.</annotationART></s> <s sid="199"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Instead of allowing the inversion algorithm to choose between these extreme solutions, we allow the decision maker to examine <IT>all</IT> of the nondominated solutions within the parameter space.</annotationART></s> <s sid="200"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">We find that neither solution shown in Fig. 6, and none of the other solutions along the Pareto-optimal surface, fit both objectives well.</annotationART></s> <s sid="201"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Generally, we can use this negative result to assert that either the data are noisy or the model is inadequate!</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.2">Algorithm</HEADER><P><s sid="202"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Genetic algorithms are particularly well suited to multiobjective optimization.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit56 cit57 cit58">56–58</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="203"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Multiple individuals can search for multiple solutions in parallel.</annotationART></s> <s sid="204"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod26" novelty="None" advantage="None">By incorporating the concept of Pareto-domination into the selection procedure, and applying a niching pressure to spread the population out along the tradeoff surface, the genetic algorithm described in Section 3 can be modified to handle multiple objective functions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="205"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod26" novelty="None" advantage="None">Below, we present a modified version of the strength-Pareto evolution algorithm.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit53 cit59">53,59</REF> </annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="206"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod26" novelty="None" advantage="None">An initial population of <IT>P</IT> chromosomes is randomly generated within the allowed parameter space.</annotationART></s> <s sid="207"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod26" novelty="None" advantage="None">With a single objective we are able to unambiguously order the chromosomes in terms of their fitness and allocate reproductive opportunities accordingly.</annotationART></s> <s sid="208"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod26" novelty="None" advantage="None">With several objectives, the population is not totally ordered since chromosomes can be indifferent to one another.</annotationART></s> <s sid="209"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod26" novelty="None" advantage="None">To order these systems, we define the concept of strength<SUP TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn3" /> to represent the number of chromosomes a particular individual dominates.</annotationART></s> <s sid="210"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod26" novelty="None" advantage="None">As in Fig. 6, nondominated chromosomes do not generally have the same strengths.</annotationART></s> <s sid="211"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod26" novelty="None" advantage="None">To give the nondominated individuals the same reproductive opportunities, we define the raw fitness of a chromosome using the sum of the strengths of all the chromosomes which dominate it.</annotationART></s> <s sid="212"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod26" novelty="None" advantage="None">The negative sign guarantees that the raw fitness of dominated chromosomes is less than that of nondominated chromosomes which all have <IT>R</IT> = 0.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="213"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod26" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fitness sharing is incorporated to spread the population out along the tradeoff surface by adding large “niching penalties” to chromosomes in crowded regions of parameter space.</annotationART></s> <s sid="214"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod26" novelty="None" advantage="None">The local density is defined in terms of <IT>σ</IT>*<SB><IT>i</IT></SB>, the distance from chromosome <IT>i</IT> to its √<IT>P</IT>th nearest neighbor with <IT>P</IT> denoting the total population size.</annotationART></s> <s sid="215"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod26" novelty="None" advantage="None">We measure the distance between chromosomes <IT>i</IT> and <IT>j</IT> in genotype (parameter) space according to <IT>σ</IT><SB><IT>ij</IT></SB> = ∑<SB><IT>n</IT></SB>|<IT>a</IT><SB><IT>i,n</IT></SB> − <IT>a</IT><SB><IT>j,n</IT></SB>|/<IT>r</IT><SB><IT>n</IT></SB> so that the distance along each coordinate <IT>n</IT> is normalized by its allowed range, <IT>r</IT><SB><IT>n</IT></SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="216"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod26" novelty="None" advantage="None">The density around each individual is <IT>D</IT>(<IT>i</IT>) = 1/(<IT>σ</IT>*<SB><IT>i</IT></SB> + 2) where the 2 in the denominator ensures <IT>D</IT>(<IT>i</IT>) &lt; 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="217"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod26" novelty="None" advantage="None">Subtracting <IT>D</IT>(<IT>i</IT>) from the raw fitness yields the overall fitness <IT>F</IT>(<IT>i</IT>) = <IT>R</IT>(<IT>i</IT>) − <IT>D</IT>(<IT>i</IT>).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="218"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The principle of natural selection dictates that individuals should be given reproductive opportunities according to their fitness.</annotationART></s> <s sid="219"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since a ranking scheme is used to provide the strength-Pareto fitness, we cannot base our selection criteria on the magnitude of the each individual's fitness.</annotationART></s> <s sid="220"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod27" novelty="None" advantage="None">Instead, we force the chromosomes to compete: Binary tournament selection with replacement is used to select parents.</annotationART></s> <s sid="221"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod27" novelty="None" advantage="None">Each member of the mating pool is selected by randomly choosing two members of the population, comparing their fitness, copying the winner into the pool, and replacing both members into the population.</annotationART></s> <s sid="222"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod27" novelty="None" advantage="None">Once the mating pool is full, pairs are randomly chosen, allowed to reproduce, and discarded.</annotationART></s> <s sid="223"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod27" novelty="None" advantage="None">To prevent backward steps in evolution, we again allow elite members of the population to survive from one generation to the next.</annotationART></s> <s sid="224"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod27" novelty="None" advantage="None">The top ten percent of the solutions are chosen based on their raw fitness value <IT>R</IT>(<IT>i</IT>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="225"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod27" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of a tie, the most redundant solution<SUP TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn4" />, the solution closest in genotype space to the other candidates, is iteratively removed from the list of elites.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.3">Results</HEADER><P><s sid="226"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">To test our multiobjective genetic algorithm we construct target spectra with known parameters, invert them, and compare the calculated parameters to those used to construct the target spectrum.</annotationART></s> <s sid="227"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In our study of the single-objective algorithm, we found that as the number of parameters increased the absorption spectrum failed to provide enough information to uniquely determine the molecular parameters which generated it.</annotationART></s> <s sid="228"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this section, we will show that including data from Raman excitation profiles enables a more complete characterization of the underlying molecular parameters.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="229"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">First, we revisit the “difficult” target absorption spectrum of the two-mode system from Section 4.3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="230"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod28" novelty="None" advantage="None">Using the same parameters, we synthesized Raman excitation profiles by calculating the Raman cross section of each mode at seven frequencies resonant with the broad electronic transition.</annotationART></s> <s sid="231"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod28" novelty="None" advantage="None">To invert the target spectra (the points in Fig. 7), we add a second objective to minimize the error at these points.</annotationART></s> <s sid="232"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="New" advantage="None">Four attempts were made.</annotationART></s> <s sid="233"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="New" advantage="None">In each, the 60 member population was allowed to evolve for 60 generations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="234"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results are shown as the solid lines in Fig. 7 with representative parameters entered in Table 5.</annotationART></s> <s sid="235"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod28" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since there are multiple objectives there can be several nondominated chromosomes in the final population and only one is entered for each replicate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="236"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The best calculated parameters correspond closely to the target parameters, though some large variations (≈20%) exist among the nondominated chromosomes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="237"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Again, only in the inset are the small errors in the calculated absorption spectra visible.</annotationART></s> <s sid="238"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Raman excitation profile of mode 2 is about five times more intense than that of mode 1 and the algorithm does an excellent job at fitting the experimental points.</annotationART></s> <s sid="239"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the less Raman-active mode, there is some variability in the excitation profiles, but each passes very close to the target at the prescribed wavelengths.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="240"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod29" novelty="None" advantage="None">When two coupled modes are considered, we must choose how many objective functions to optimize: we can either lump the two fundamental Raman excitation profiles together into a single objective function, or treat them separately.</annotationART></s> <s sid="241"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">As the number of objective functions increases the number of non-dominated chromosomes increases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="242"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Horn and Nafpliotis<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit52">52</REF> illustrate the effects of too little and too much dominance pressure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="243"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">When too much of the population is comprised of non-dominated solutions (<IT>t</IT><SB>non</SB> ≫ 20%), the algorithm prematurely converges to a small portion of the front.</annotationART></s> <s sid="244"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">When there are too few non-dominated solutions (<IT>t</IT><SB>non</SB> ∼ 1%), there is not enough dominance pressure to exploit fit solutions and convergence is slow.</annotationART></s> <s sid="245"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Their empirically-derived, best case is <IT>t</IT><SB>non</SB> ≈ 10% which yields a tight and complete distribution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="246"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Keeping the ratio of nondominated to dominated solutions around 0.1, two mode calculations were generally best solved with two objective functions.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="247"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod30" novelty="None" advantage="None">A more impressive demonstration of the multiobjective genetic algorithm is achieved with a five-mode calculation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="248"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod30" novelty="None" advantage="None">The bold parameters in Table 6 were used to synthesize an absorption spectrum and Raman cross section at seven frequencies for the fundamental, overtone, and combination bands of the system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="249"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod30" novelty="None" advantage="None">Using three objective functions (the error in the absorption spectrum, the fundamental Raman excitation profiles, and the Raman excitation profiles of the most intense overtones and combinations), we inverted the data to determine the parameters in Table 6 and the corresponding spectra in Figs. 8 and 9.</annotationART></s> <s sid="250"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The algorithm is quite successful at inverting these spectra: fewer than 300 data points (more than half from the absorption spectrum) are used to find 13 free parameters!</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="251"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">When a spectrum with less structure is chosen, inversion becomes challenging because solvent-induced broadening smears out the signatures of individual modes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="252"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Using objective functions which consider the collective deviation of all modes from the target Raman data, as above, many disparate chromosomes (parameter sets) have similar error values and the population does not converge to the optimal solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="253"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The possibility of increasing the number of objective functions to distinguish the behavior of particular modes may be considered, however the cost can be prohibitive since the number of nondominated chromosomes increases very quickly and the population size must grow concomitantly.</annotationART></s> <s sid="254"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">To focus the population more effectively, the objective functions must be chosen to capture the nuance of the data.</annotationART></s> <s sid="255"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The best parceling of experimental data into objective functions strongly depends on the specifics of the system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="256"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Generally, schemes for breaking the problem down into smaller pieces and identifying useful objective functions are more physically relevant and intuitive than the iterative search for molecular parameters.</annotationART></s> <s sid="257"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met14" novelty="New" advantage="None">Our specific recommendations for this problem are to group vibrational modes with similar experimental cross sections.</annotationART></s> <s sid="258"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met14" novelty="New" advantage="None">When more modes are considered, our strategy will be to group similar vibrational modes (<IT>i.e.</IT>, symmetric or asymmetric stretches).</annotationART></s> <s sid="259"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">While the genetic algorithm has removed some degree of subjectivity in the inversion of small systems, with larger problems the spectroscopist still has to be clever.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="260"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod31" novelty="None" advantage="None">A more typical five-mode system presents a much more difficult problem.</annotationART></s> <s sid="261"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod31" novelty="None" advantage="None">The broad and featureless absorption spectrum and fundamental Raman excitation profiles are shown in Fig. 10.</annotationART></s> <s sid="262"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met14" novelty="New" advantage="None">Splitting the Raman active modes into two groups with independent error functions (the intense profiles from modes 2, 3, and 5 and the less intense profiles from modes 1 and 4), we attempt to determine the molecular parameters from three objective functions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="263"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">With a population size of 100, within five generations there are 20–30% nondominated chromosomes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="264"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">While the fit to the absorption spectrum is generally good, the Raman excitation profiles are poorly represented by these nondominated chromosomes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="265"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The range of parameters that provide nearly quantitative fits to the structureless absorption spectrum is large and spans regions of parameter space which do not produce acceptable Raman excitation profiles.</annotationART></s> <s sid="266"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod32" novelty="None" advantage="None">To focus the search on promising regions of parameter space, all of the absorption profiles with an error function below some tolerance value are set equal after 10 generations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="267"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Using only the error functions associated with the Raman excitation profiles to determine domination quickly hones the population toward an optimal solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="268"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Three representative nondominated chromosomes are shown in Table 7 with a typical fit in Fig. 10.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="269"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">While the parameters corresponding to all nondominated chromosomes fit the data well, some of the parameters deviate considerably from the target ones.</annotationART></s> <s sid="270"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The errors associated with mode 1, for example, exceed 20%.</annotationART></s> <s sid="271"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">This seemingly paradoxical result occurs because, when the spectra are completely unstructured, the Raman profiles are not sensitive to the excited state frequencies and displacements independently.</annotationART></s> <s sid="272"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The slope of the excited state surface along each normal coordinate is the principal factor in determining the intensity of the Raman excitation profiles.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit3 cit33">1,3,33</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="273"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">In Table 8, the slopes of the calculated and target excited state surfaces at the ground state minimum are compared.</annotationART></s> <s sid="274"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although the algorithm cannot reliably extract the displacement <IT>Δ</IT> and the frequency ratio <IT>ω</IT><SB>e</SB>/<IT>ω</IT><SB>g</SB> independently, the slope of the excited state surface can be determined even when the spectra have no structure.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="275"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The most useful test of our genetic algorithm is to measure its ability to invert the absorption spectrum and Raman excitation profiles of a randomly generated system against that of a human performing the “intelligently guided random search” methodology.</annotationART></s> <s sid="276"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met15" novelty="New" advantage="None">An independent third party was recruited to design a five-mode system with parameters falling within the ranges given in Table 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="277"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met15" novelty="New" advantage="None">The absorption spectrum and Raman intensities shown in Fig. 11, but not the generating parameters, were presented to the authors.</annotationART></s> <s sid="278"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met15" novelty="New" advantage="None">One attempted to extract the parameters manually while the other employed the genetic algorithm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="279"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">In approximately 25 iterations requiring a total of 1.5 h of work, the manual search produced a good fit to the data and reasonable agreement with the target parameters; however, the excited-state frequencies could not be determined with any reliability, and were left equal to the ground-state frequencies for all but the most strongly coupled mode.</annotationART></s> <s sid="280"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The genetic algorithm from Section 4.3 found a marginally better fit after 25 generations, with a reduced population of 50 chromosomes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="281"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Using a 600 MHz G3 processor, each generation of 50 calculations took about 10 min.</annotationART></s> <s sid="282"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Plainly stated, it took the algorithm 50 times as many calculations, and about twice as long, to find an optimal fit but it required almost no “human time”.</annotationART></s> <s sid="283"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The genetic algorithm was able to return reasonably good values for the excited-state frequencies as well as the displacements and can therefore be judged more successful than the manual method, although we suspect that the introduction of experimental noise would reduce or eliminate this advantage.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="5">Conclusions</HEADER><P><s sid="284"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Overall, the multiobjective genetic algorithm is an effective means of inverting spectroscopic data.</annotationART></s> <s sid="285"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">When spectra have well-resolved vibronic progressions, the inversion is nearly quantitative though the algorithm is computationally less efficient than its human counterpart.</annotationART></s> <s sid="286"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">As the spectra are smeared out by inhomogeneous broadening or large molecular reorganization energies, information is lost and multiple solutions provide good fits to the data.</annotationART></s> <s sid="287"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">When a unique solution cannot be determined, a range of suitable parameters can be extracted from the set of nondominated chromosomes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="288"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">This intrinsic determination of error bounds is unique to the genetic algorithm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="289"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In those cases where no acceptable fit can be achieved, either experimental noise or physical effects not included in our model are at play.</annotationART></s> <s sid="290"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The greatest success of the genetic algorithm over the intelligently guided random search is the ability to objectively decide when additional parameters are required to describe the data.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
