<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b402623c" hasDoc="yes" version="1168" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Physicochemical properties of Pt-SO<SB>4</SB>/Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> alkane oxidation catalysts</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">A series of sulfated alumina catalysts were synthesised by wet impregnation with sulfate-containing solutions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The degree of surface sulfation and corresponding surface acidity could be readily tuned by varying the molarity of impregnating solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Strong acid treatments (&gt;0.1 M) induced aluminium-sulfate crystallisation with a concomitant decrease in porosity and surface acidity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Platinum-doped sulfated aluminas showed enhanced activity towards methane, ethane and propane combustion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Activity scaled with the degree of accessible surface sulfate and platinum loading, however C–H bond scission appeared rate-limiting over both pure and presulfated aluminas.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The magnitude of sulfate-promoted propane oxidation was greatest under heavily oxidising conditions (C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>6</SB>∶O<SB>2</SB> &gt; 1∶20) but independent of Pt loading, confirming that support-mediated alkane activation is the dominant factor in the promotional mechanism.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The importance of heterogeneously catalysed hydrocarbon chemistry can hardly be overestimated, ranging from processes such as petroleum reforming<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2">1,2</REF> to fine chemicals synthesis and pollution control.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Despite these successes C–H activation of saturated hydrocarbons remains a challenge both for their utilisation as an alternative feedstock, and their combustion for power generation and the regulation of environmental emissions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit5">4,5</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Low-temperature activation of short chain alkanes for chemical synthesis is conventionally achieved <IT>via</IT> strong solid acids, which are able to protolyse the C–H or C–C bond.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Sulfated metal-oxides represent one of the most versatile classes of solid acid, possessing high activity, good hydrothermal stability and tuneable surface acidity and porosity.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7 cit8 cit9">7–9</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">The latter is important in their application to large organic substrates wherein mass-transport diffusion limitations hinder microporous zeolitic materials.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">Sulfated metal-oxides find application in a range of gas phase reactions including alkane isomerisation and cracking<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF> and more recently liquid phase alkylation and acylation chemistry.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12 cit13">12,13</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">Their catalytic properties can be further tuned by metal doping which can enhance both catalyst activity and stability, <IT>e.g.</IT> in butane isomerisation, with C–H activation observed at temperatures as low as 60 °C.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12 cit14">12,14</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Sulfated zirconia is probably the most widely studied system, in which the interaction of sulfate ions with the zirconia surface can generate superacidic sites.</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">These materials exhibit both Lewis and Brønsted acidity dependent on the degree of surface hydration.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have recently demonstrated that wet impregnation of zirconia by dilute H<SB>2</SB>SO<SB>4</SB> affords a simple means to regulate the surface acidity and catalytic performance of mesoporous sulfated zirconia.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast the physical properties and catalytic applications of sulfated aluminas have been scarcely explored;<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9 cit16 cit17">9,16,17</REF> this despite alumina being the most widely used catalyst support material.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Gas phase sulfation of alumina is known to enhance the Pt catalysed combustion of propane for automotive emission control.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18 cit19">18,19</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Enhanced C–H activation may occur <IT>via</IT> support-mediated propane adsorption over sulfated alumina, and subsequent spillover of alkylsulfate intermediates formed at the Pt-support interface.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20 cit21">20,21</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot3" novelty="None" advantage="None">However the nature and strength of acid sites in SO<SB>4</SB>/Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> is poorly understood, while the interaction with transition-metal dopants has been hardly touched upon.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22 cit23 cit24">22–24</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Surprisingly sulfated aluminas have not been exploited to promote low-temperature C–H activation in other catalytic applications.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Here we report the preparation and characterisation of well-defined SO<SB>4</SB>/Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> and their applications as support materials in Pt-SO<SB>4</SB>/Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> catalysts for light alkane combustion.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Experimental</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Catalyst preparation</HEADER><P><s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Sulfated aluminas were prepared by incipient wetness impregnation of 1 g of γ-Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> (Degussa aluminium oxide C) with a 10 cm<SP>3</SP> solution of 0.01–2.5 M H<SB>2</SB>SO<SB>4</SB> (Fisher 98%).</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The resultant slurry was dried at 80 °C in air for 12 h and then calcined in flowing O<SB>2</SB> at 550 °C for 3 h.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Reference materials were also prepared by the same procedure using 0.1 M solutions of (NH<SB>4</SB>)<SB>2</SB>SO<SB>4</SB> (Aldrich 99%) or Al<SB>2</SB>(SO<SB>4</SB>)<SB>3</SB> (Aldrich 99.99%).</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Samples were subsequently stored in air.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Platinum was added <IT>via</IT> the incipient wetness technique using 1 cm<SP>3</SP> of (NH<SB>4</SB>)<SB>4</SB>PtCl<SB>2</SB> (Johnson Matthey, 55.24 wt% Pt assay) as an aqueous solution per gram of support.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The resultant paste was air-dried at 80 °C for 12 h and then calcined in flowing O<SB>2</SB> at 500 °C for 2 h followed by a 2 h reduction in flowing H<SB>2</SB> at 400 °C.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Gas-phase sulfation was performed either prior to reaction, using a flow of 0.1 vol% SO<SB>2</SB>∶1 vol% O<SB>2</SB> in He mix (10 cm<SP>−3</SP>) at 400 °C for 2 h followed by cooling under He, or <IT>via</IT> introduction of 0.1 vol% SO<SB>2</SB>/He (1 cm<SP>3</SP> min<SP>−1</SP>) along with the reactant stream.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Catalyst characterisation</HEADER><P><s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Porosity and surface area measurements were performed <IT>via</IT> N<SB>2</SB> adsorption on a Micromeritics ASAP 2010 instrument.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Surface areas were calculated using the BET equation over the pressure range <IT>P</IT>/<IT>P</IT><SB>0</SB> = 0.02–0.2, where a linear relationship was maintained.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The final sulfur content was determined by elemental analysis using a Carlo Erba 1108 CHN/S instrument (quoted percentages refer to total S levels).</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Pt loadings were measured using a Perkin–Elmer P40 emission ICP-MS instrument.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">XRD patterns were acquired using a Siemens D5000 diffractometer and Cu Kα radiation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">S 2p and Pt 4d XP spectra were also measured at 40 eV pass energy using a Kratos AXIS HSi instrument, equipped with charge neutraliser and Mg Kα X-ray source.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Two-point energy referencing was employed using adventitious carbon at 285 eV and the valence band, and in all instances only SO<SB>4</SB> groups were observed with a characteristic binding energy of 170 eV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thermogravimetric analysis (TGA) was performed in a Stanton–Redcroft STA-750 system using 50 mg sample in an alumina crucible under flowing nitrogen and a ramp of 10 °C min<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Temperature-programmed reduction (TPR) was carried out in a quartz tube using 50 mg sample under a 5% H<SB>2</SB>/Ar flow (E&amp;W 99%) with a ramp of 11 °C min<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp9" novelty="None" advantage="None">DRIFTS spectra were obtained using a Bruker Equinox FTIR spectrometer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Samples were diluted with KBr powder (10 wt% in KBr), then loaded into an environmental cell and subjected to additional drying under vacuum at 110 °C for 10 min prior to measurements to remove moisture physisorbed during air exposure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp10" novelty="None" advantage="None"><IT>Ex situ</IT> pyridine adsorption was performed by incipient wetness impregnation, with excess pyridine evaporated prior to sample loading and evacuation as described above.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Acidity was determined by Hammett indicators; ∼25 mg of sample was shaken with 1 cm<SP>3</SP> of a solution of Hammett indicator diluted in 10 cm<SP>3</SP> cyclohexane and left to equilibrate for 2 h.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Catalyst testing</HEADER><P><s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Catalyst testing was performed in a fixed-bed quartz reactor using 100 mg catalyst.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The total gas flow rate was 21 cm<SP>3</SP> min<SP>−1</SP> and stoichiometric mixtures were employed using 1 cm<SP>3</SP> min<SP>−1</SP> of alkane together with the appropriate oxygen flow with helium added as an inert diluent.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp12" novelty="None" advantage="None">This equated to gas mixes of 5 vol% HC and 10–25 vol% O<SB>2</SB> in He.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Gases used were CH<SB>4</SB> (E&amp;W 99.995%), C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>6</SB> (E&amp;W 99.5%) and C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>8</SB> (E&amp;W 99.9%).</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Light-off measurements were performed with a ramp rate of 15 °C min<SP>−1</SP> with the catalyst bed temperature measured with a coaxial thermocouple.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Reaction was monitored <IT>via</IT> on-line mass spectrometry (VG 200 amu QMS).</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The sole reaction products were CO<SB>2</SB> and H<SB>2</SB>O.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The overall error in conversion was ±4%.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Blank runs showed negligible gas-phase contributions to alkane combustion below 700 °C.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Results and discussion</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Sulfated aluminas</HEADER><P><s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to elucidate the respective roles of metal and support effects in sulfate-promoted alkane activation, the physico-chemical properties of a series of sulfated alumina support materials were characterised prior to platinum doping.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 1 shows the total and surface sulfur content as a function of molarity of impregnating solution.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is evident that the surface sulfur loading increased rapidly for low sulfuric acid concentrations demonstrating efficient S adsorption.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Quantification was achieved from the integrated S 2p XP intensity and overall surface composition, incorporating appropriate elemental response factors (RF) according to the equation below:The surface loading roughly mirrored the total sulfur content for all samples, although a slight plateau in the former is apparent around 0.1 M. The surface loading rose again above &gt;1 M H<SB>2</SB>SO<SB>4</SB> to give a common surface and total S loading of ∼14 wt% S for the 2.5 M impregnated sample.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is equivalent to the S content in Al<SB>2</SB>(SO<SB>4</SB>)<SB>3</SB>·18H<SB>2</SB>O.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Complete surface sulfation thus required bulk sulfur loadings in excess of 1.7 wt%.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Surface areas of impregnated aluminas were a strong function of sulfur loading as shown in Fig. 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">For sulfate concentrations below 0.1 M the surface area was close to that of untreated γ-alumina at around 140 m<SP>2</SP> g<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">This fell dramatically for higher concentrations reaching only 10 m<SP>2</SP> g<SP>−1</SP> following impregnation by 2.5 M H<SB>2</SB>SO<SB>4</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">These changes are likely associated with crystallization and pore collapse upon formation of bulk Al<SB>2</SB>(SO<SB>4</SB>)<SB>3</SB>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Formation of crystalline sulfated alumina was investigated by powder X-ray diffraction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 3 shows the uncalcined alumina precursor contained several weak reflections in the range 2<IT>θ</IT> = 32–38°, with two stronger reflections at 46 and 67.4° characteristic of γ-alumina.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Sulfation sharpened the weaker alumina features which resolved into peaks at 33, 34.6, 37 and 39.7°, and for concentrations ≥0.5 M H<SB>2</SB>SO<SB>4</SB> also resulted in new reflections at 25.6 and 29°.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The latter are characteristic of anhydrous aluminium sulfate with contributions from Al<SB>2</SB>(SO<SB>4</SB>)<SB>3</SB>·14H<SB>2</SB>O and the monohydrate Al<SB>2</SB>(SO<SB>4</SB>)<SB>3</SB>·H<SB>2</SB>O.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25 cit26">25,26</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Simple peak shape analysis assuming a stoichiometric, non-defective structure suggested the initial alumina phase comprised crystallites of ∼145 Å.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Sulfation was accompanied by significant crystallite growth with Al<SB>2</SB>(SO<SB>4</SB>)<SB>3</SB> particle sizes estimated from the 25.6° reflection exceeding 400 Å following impregnation by 0.5 M H<SB>2</SB>SO<SB>4</SB>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The thermal stability of impregnated sulfated aluminas was examined by TGA.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The γ-alumina precursor showed negligible weight loss at temperatures below 900 °C, Fig. 4.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Following sulfation a single high temperature weight loss was observed above 600 °C, indicative of a relatively well-defined sulfoxy species, the magnitude of this loss increased with acid molarity.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The loss profile for the 2.5 M impregnated alumina resembles that of bulk aluminium sulfate,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25">25</REF> which exhibited a similar high-temperature drop above 600 °C attributable to SO<SB>2</SB> desorption.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">A small low temperature loss was also observed between 100 and 300 °C from the Al<SB>2</SB>(SO<SB>4</SB>) standard, associated with loss of physisorbed water and surface dehydroxylation.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25">25</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Corresponding TPR measurements shown in Fig. 5 revealed a similar trend.</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Low sulfate loadings gave rise to a broad, high temperature reduction peak centred around 500 °C.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">As the sulfate content rose this peak shifted to higher temperature, reaching 600 °C for 2.5 M H<SB>2</SB>SO<SB>4</SB>, while a second minor state emerged at 420 °C.</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hence increased thermal stability is accompanied by a decrease in the homogeneity of sulfoxy environments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The total reduction signal scaled with sulfur loading, approaching that of pure Al<SB>2</SB>(SO<SB>4</SB>)<SB>3</SB> for the highest molarity sample.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">γ-Alumina was unreduced below 800 °C, hence all the features in Fig. 5 must be associated with sulfate reduction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Al<SB>2</SB>(SO<SB>4</SB>)<SB>3</SB> also exhibited two principal reduction states: one at 600 °C matching that from the 2.5 M H<SB>2</SB>SO<SB>4</SB> impregnated alumina; the second at 420 °C matching that for molarities ≤0.1 M. These may correspond to bulk and surface sulfate reduction processes respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The intensity ratio of the two reduction peaks for the impregnated series is inconsistent with a dual-stage reduction process in which SO<SB>4</SB> → SO<SB><IT>x</IT></SB> followed by SO<SB><IT>x</IT></SB> → S for which a 1∶3, 2∶2 or 3∶1 low∶high temperature ratio is expected.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our observations suggest that a single SO<SB>4</SB> species predominates following impregnation with 0.1–0.5 M H<SB>2</SB>SO<SB>4</SB>, beyond which sulfur is incorporated within various subsurface environments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">This results in a progressive recrystallisation of the γ-Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> substrate, as observed by XRD, coupled with pore collapse and a loss of surface area.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Table 1 presents the acid strength of the sulfated aluminas as determined using Hammett indicators.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Such measurements use a series of neutral basic indicators which change to the colour of their conjugate acid when interacting with acid sites of a critical p<IT>K</IT><SB>a</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Quantitative acid site distributions can be determined by UV spectroscopy by titration of the suspended solid with <IT>n</IT>-butylamine, according to the Hammett–Bertolacini method.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27">27</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="No">However determination of superacidity and acid site distributions of porous solid acid catalysts by such measurements remains controversial due to solvent–support interactions<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28">28</REF> and accessibility of the probe molecule within micropores.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29">29</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">Provided the polarity of the solvent used to suspend the solid and indicator is similar to that of the reaction media, Hammett indicators therefore provide a semi-quantitative value for the maximum solid acid strength.</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Table 1 shows that pure gamma alumina displayed only weak basic characteristics.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Sulfation increased the support surface acidity, however sulfated aluminas remained only weakly acidic and did not show superacid properties.</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Maximum surface acidity was achieved following 0.5 M H<SB>2</SB>SO<SB>4</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Stronger impregnating solutions actually led to a drop in acidity associated with a transformation to bulk aluminium sulfate (the latter exhibited amphoteric properties).</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">None of these impregnated materials showed superacidity in contrast to their sulfated zirconia counterparts.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that subsequent Pt doping of these materials had no effect on their <IT>H</IT><SB>0</SB> values.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Surface functionalisation of the sulfated aluminas was further explored by DRIFTS.</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Sulfation resulted in the appearance of new features in the region 1400–900 cm<SP>−1</SP> (Fig. 6a) which fall in the range expected for vibrations of coordinated sulfate species.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30 cit31">30,31</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The generally accepted modes of SO<SB>4</SB> binding to oxide surfaces involve mono- or bidentate coordination environments, which exhibit 3 or 4 vibrational modes, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">For chelating and bridged bidentate SO<SB>4</SB> species, modes attributed to the OSO and O–S–O stretches are observed in the order <IT>ν</IT><SB>a</SB>(OSO) &gt; <IT>ν</IT><SB>s</SB>(OSO) &gt; <IT>ν</IT><SB>a</SB>(O–S–O) &gt; <IT>ν</IT><SB>s</SB>(O–S–O).</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Considering first the aluminium sulfate standard, the well defined peak at 1320 cm<SP>−1</SP> can be assigned to the asymmetric OSO stretch of bidentate surface sulfate, consistent with previous observations ∼1370 cm<SP>−1</SP>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit32">32</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The peaks at 1280, 1190 and 1125 cm<SP>−1</SP> are assigned to <IT>ν</IT><SB>s</SB>(OSO), <IT>ν</IT><SB>a</SB>(O–S–O) and <IT>ν</IT><SB>s</SB>(O–S–O) respectively in agreement with the observed frequency range observed for (NH<SB>4</SB>)<SB>2</SB>SO<SB>4</SB> and Al<SB>2</SB>(SO<SB>4</SB>)<SB>3</SB> impregnated Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit32 cit33">32,33</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Only three bands were observed for low sulfur loadings suggestive of a monodentate adsorption geometry.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Indeed the relative frequencies of these peaks at 1060 cm<SP>−1</SP>, 1160 cm<SP>−1</SP> and 1250 cm<SP>−1</SP> are in good accord with the corresponding <IT>ν</IT>(<IT>O</IT>-<IT>S</IT>O<SB>3</SB>) and <IT>ν</IT><SB>s</SB>(O-<IT>SO</IT>) and <IT>ν</IT><SB>a</SB>(O-<IT>SO</IT><SB>3</SB>) modes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">A weak feature observed at 1360 cm<SP>−1</SP> in both the alumina support and all low loading samples may arise from a weak lattice mode associated with octahedral Al<SP>3+</SP> in γ-Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit34">34</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">Higher sulfur loadings attenuated these monodentate characteristics, concomitant with the emergence of features (notably the 1320 cm<SP>−1</SP> band) associated with bidentate SO<SB>4</SB> species.</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">The spectrum from alumina impregnated with 2.5 M<SB>3</SB> H<SB>2</SB>SO<SB>4</SB> bears a striking resemblance to that of pure Al<SB>2</SB>(SO<SB>4</SB>)<SB>3</SB>, demonstrating crystallisation extends throughout the selvedge.</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is important to note the precise frequencies of surface SO<SB>4</SB> vibrational modes are sensitive to the degree of surface hydration, accounting for a wide variance in literature values.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Pyridine adsorption was subsequently employed to titrate Brønsted and Lewis acid sites.</annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">As anticipated from our Hammett measurements the alumina precursor showed no detectable surface acidity, whereas all sulfated aluminas exhibited sharp peaks at 1485, 1533, 1604 cm<SP>−1</SP> and 1633 cm<SP>−1</SP> characteristic of predominantly Brønsted acid sites (Fig. 6b (inset)).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit35">35</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">A small contribution from Lewis acid sites at 1485 and 1604 cm<SP>−1</SP> cannot be discounted, however the absence of any characteristic Lewis band at ∼1450 cm<SP>−1</SP> suggests the Lewis contribution is negligible.</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">A high ratio of Brønsted <IT>versus</IT> Lewis sites is to be expected as a result of moisture adsorption during storage in air.</annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The strength of the principal pyridinium-ion vibration at 1533 cm<SP>−1</SP> is also shown as a function of total S content in Fig. 6b for SO<SB>4</SB>/Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> and bulk Al<SB>2</SB>(SO<SB>4</SB>)<SB>3</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The acid site density increased with sulfur loading up to 0.5 M, but rapidly decreased for higher loadings following the trend in <IT>H</IT><SB>0</SB> values.</annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">These DRIFTS measurements suggest crystalline Al<SB>2</SB>(SO<SB>4</SB>)<SB>3</SB> possesses no surface acid sites.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Platinum-doped sulfated aluminas</HEADER><P><s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The potential of SO<SB>4</SB>/Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> as a support material in alkane combustion was first investigated over doped sulfated aluminas with low 0.05 wt% Pt loadings (selected to maximise possible promotional effects).</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The catalytic performance was screened in propane light-off under stoichiometric conditions (1∶5 C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>8</SB>∶O<SB>2</SB>) as shown in Fig 7.</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Pure alumina was inert below 800 °C.</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Unsulfated Pt/Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> exhibited the poorest combustion activity with light-off commencing above 350 °C and a <IT>T</IT><SB>50</SB> = 510 °C (temperature for 50% conversion).</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The light-off temperature decreased with increasing alumina sulfation reaching a minimum <IT>T</IT><SB>50</SB> = 350 °C for 0.1 M impregnated SO<SB>4</SB>/Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">Further sulfation <IT>lowered catalyst activity</IT> with the <IT>T</IT><SB>50</SB> increasing to 410 °C for the 2.5 M sample, this despite a 14-fold increase in the total S content, revealing a dramatic drop in the activity per mole S. This variation in <IT>T</IT><SB>50</SB> correlates directly with the accessible surface sulfate.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">The increased light-off temperature for heavily sulfated aluminas (&gt;0.5 M) reflects the drop in surface area and acidity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">Alumina impregnation with 0.1 M H<SB>2</SB>SO<SB>4</SB> gave the optimal promotion.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">This promotional phenomenon was independent of the nature of sulfate precursor, Fig. 8, and depended solely on the concentration of sulfate ion.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The influence of Pt loading on sulfate promoted propane combustion was subsequently studied over a 0.1 M SO<SB>4</SB>/Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> support (chosen to provide the greatest enhancement).</annotationART></s> <s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 9 shows the resulting bulk and surface Pt loadings determined by XPS and elemental analysis using the equation given below.Pt wt% = I<SP>Pt</SP> × RF<SP>Pt</SP> / [(I<SP>Pt</SP> × RF<SP>Pt</SP>) + (I<SP>S</SP> × RF<SP>S</SP>) + (I<SP>O</SP> × RF<SP>O</SP>) + (I<SP>C</SP> × RF<SP>C</SP>)]The surface Pt coverage initially rose rapidly over both pure and sulfated aluminas as the total Pt content increased.</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">However the fraction of exposed Pt (<IT>i.e</IT>. metal dispersion) fell dramatically for total loadings above 1 wt% as shown in Fig. 9 (inset).</annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">In all cases the Pt dispersion was lower over sulfated alumina consistent with the formation of large Pt crystallites.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit36">36</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The structural evolution of Pt clusters was also explored <IT>via</IT> XPS.</annotationART></s> <s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 10 shows the growth of the Pt 4d<SB>3/2,5/2</SB> doublet (spin–orbit splitting = 16.7 eV) with increasing total platinum loading over pure alumina.</annotationART></s> <s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The binding energy decreased significantly from 332.0 to 330.6 eV as the loading rose from 0.05 to 25 wt% Pt (Fig. 10, inset).</annotationART></s> <s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The same components and peak shifts were observed over a 0.1 M SO<SB>4</SB>/Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>4</SB> support.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">This shift has two possible origins.</annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Core-level binding energies are often observed to decrease with increasing metal particle size, characteristic of a cluster → bulk transition and associated improved final-state relaxation and core-hole screening.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit37 cit38">37,38</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">However such behaviour is only expected for Pt clusters on weakly-interacting supports such as carbon and silica.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit39">39</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Over substrates possessing localised orbitals with binding energies that overlap the cluster d-orbitals metal–support interactions actually produce the opposite core-level shift.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit40">40</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" advantage="None">Further complications also arise due to cluster charging over insulating substrates,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit39 cit40">39,40</REF> hence the present shift cannot be simply attributed to electronic effects.</annotationART></s> <s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">An alternative explanation is suggested by our recent EXAFS measurements, which have demonstrated a dramatic change in Pt oxidation state with loading over alumina.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit36">36</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None">The shifts in Fig. 10 are thus fully consistent with, and attributable to, a transformation from small PtO<IT><SB>x</SB></IT> clusters to large metallic Pt crystallites.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None">The emergence of large metallic Pt clusters ≥1 wt% was confirmed by XRD as shown in Fig. 11.</annotationART></s> <s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None">No Pt reflections were observed for lower loadings, consistent with a high dispersion and particle sizes &lt;30 Å.</annotationART></s> <s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Higher Pt loadings resulted in the appearance of fingerprint fcc Pt {111} and {200} reflections at 39.9 and 46.5° respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res29" novelty="None" advantage="None">Peak fitting yields a volume averaged particle size of ∼400 Å for the 5 wt% Pt-SO<SB>4</SB>/Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>4</SB> sample.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The influence of surface platinum on the reducibility of the 0.1M sulfated alumina support was examined by TPR.</annotationART></s> <s sid="143"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 12 shows that the presence of even trace Pt influences the reduction profiles, causing a broadening and decrease in the sulfate reduction temperature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="144"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This observation likely reflects surface SO<SB>4</SB> destabilisation <IT>via</IT> platinum-mediated H<SB>2</SB> dissociation and spillover at the metal–support interface as observed for Pt-SO<SB>4</SB>/ZrO<SB>2</SB>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit41">41</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="145"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" advantage="None">For Pt loadings ≥0.25 wt% an additional low temperature reduction peak emerges around 350 °C.</annotationART></s> <s sid="146"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res30" novelty="None" advantage="None">This lies within the range of 200–400 °C typically observed for PtO<IT><SB>x</SB></IT> reduction in Pt/Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> catalysts;<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit42 cit43 cit44">42–44</REF> the absence of this state for lower loadings reflects the TPR sensitivity limit.</annotationART></s> <s sid="147"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" advantage="None">Reduction profiles for the highest Pt loadings contain a number of poorly resolved contributions arising from the direct reduction of surface aluminium sulfate, Pt-mediated reduction of interfacial sulfate and PtO<SB>2</SB> reduction.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="148"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The effect of Pt loading on propane combustion under stoichiometric conditions over bare and 0.1 M sulfated alumina is shown in Fig. 13.</annotationART></s> <s sid="149"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs19" novelty="None" advantage="None">A strong loading dependence was observed for both supports, with the highest Pt loadings (largest particles) exhibiting the lowest light-off temperature (highest activity).</annotationART></s> <s sid="150"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res32" novelty="None" advantage="None">Alumina presulfation enhanced the performance of all catalysts with the magnitude of promotion roughly independent of the Pt loading.</annotationART></s> <s sid="151"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res32" novelty="None" advantage="None">This observation is in line with our recent finding that support-effects are the dominant factor in sulfate-promoted propane combustion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="152"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res33" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reaction profiles follow sigmoidal curves however kinetic analysis suggests a compensation effect operates, with activation barriers rising from 70 to 127 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> as the Pt loading falls from 5 to 0.05 wt% over bare alumina, accompanied by a 10<SP>7</SP> drop in the preexponential factor.</annotationART></s> <s sid="153"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res34" novelty="None" advantage="None">A similar trend occurred over the sulfated alumina support.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="154"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Sulfate promotion of Pt/Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> catalysts <IT>via gas-phase</IT> SO<SB>2</SB> is sensitive to oxygen concentration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="155"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to examine whether this dependence extended to <IT>presulfated aluminas</IT>, the influence of air–fuel ratio on an unsulfated 0.05 wt% Pt/Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> catalyst was first isolated (Fig. 14).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="156"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs20" novelty="None" advantage="None">Propane light-off was a strong function of reactant composition, showing a dramatic increase (<IT>i.e</IT>. reduced activity) upon switching from fuel-rich to fuel-lean mixtures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="157"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res35" novelty="None" advantage="None">This can be ascribed to competitive adsorption between oxygen and propane for Pt sites, coupled with the intrinsically low sticking probability of propane <IT>versus</IT> O<SB>2</SB>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit45">45</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="158"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs21" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 15 shows that propane combustion over Pt-SO<SB>4</SB>/Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> catalysts also exhibited a strong dependence on air–fuel ratio.</annotationART></s> <s sid="159"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res36" novelty="None" advantage="None">As for the untreated supports, optimum propane conversion required fuel-rich conditions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="160"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs22" novelty="None" advantage="None">However the magnitude of sulfate promotion is greatest under oxygen-rich conditions; the threshold temperature for propane light-off falls by 185 °C <IT>versus</IT> only 74 °C under excess hydrocarbon.</annotationART></s> <s sid="161"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res37" novelty="None" advantage="None">This demonstrates the active species (present during reaction) generated <IT>via</IT> support presulfation require an oxidising environment—consistent with surface sulfoxy/sulfate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="162"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">It also highlights the possibility that sulfate reduction may occur <IT>in-situ</IT> under reducing reaction conditions.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="163"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="Old" advantage="None">It is interesting to compare the magnitude of promoted propane combustion achievable <IT>via</IT> different sulfation methodologies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="164"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res38" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 16 reveals that enhancement was essentially independent of sulfation protocol, <IT>i.e</IT>. wet-chemical presulfation of an alumina support was as efficient as gas-phase sulfation by SO<SB>2</SB> (introduced either prior to or during propane combustion).</annotationART></s> <s sid="165"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Sadowski and Treibmann have reported a similar finding.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit46">46</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="166"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">This result also demonstrates that sulfate promotion is irreversible, and indeed all our sulfated catalysts could be stored and reused without measurable decrease in light-off performance.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Light alkane reactivity</HEADER><P><s sid="167"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs23" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 17 compares the light-off curves for methane, ethane and propane combustion over sulfated and unsulfated 0.05 wt% Pt/Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="168"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs23" novelty="None" advantage="None">The alkane light-off temperatures decreased in the order propane &lt; ethane &lt; methane over both catalysts in accord with their respective C–H bond energies of 401, 420 and 440 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>; C–H bond activation is widely accepted as rate-limiting in alkane oxidation over Pt/Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="169"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res39" novelty="None" advantage="None">Alkane combustion was sensitive to both metal dispersion and reaction conditions, and the light-off temperatures for our unsulfated catalyst are in good agreement with literature <IT>T</IT><SB>50</SB> values for propane,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF> ethane and methane<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit47">47</REF> under fuel-lean conditions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="170"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res39" novelty="None" advantage="None">Activation energies were also in line with typical literature values which range between 113–146, 80–114 and 71–104 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> for methane,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit48 cit49">48,49</REF> ethane<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit47 cit50">47,50</REF> and propane,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18 cit19">18,19</REF> respectively.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="171"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs23" novelty="None" advantage="None">Alumina presulfation reduced the light-off temperature for <IT>all light alkanes</IT>, with the magnitude of promotion increasing dramatically from methane to ethane, while ethane and propane exhibited similar enhancements of 178 and 153 °C, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="172"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although the influence of sulfoxy species on the catalytic combustion of hydrocarbons has generated significant interest, previous studies have focused on enhanced propane combustion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="173"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res40" novelty="None" advantage="None">Propane light-off is variously reported as lowered by between 50–250 °C over Pt/Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> catalysts,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18 cit19 cit51 cit52">18,19,51,52</REF> consistent with the present value.</annotationART></s> <s sid="174"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot4" novelty="None" advantage="None">However no systematic correlations between catalyst structure, reaction conditions and the degree of promotion have been previously identified.</annotationART></s> <s sid="175"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">SO<SB>2</SB>-promoted methane combustion has only been previously reported by Meeyoo <IT>et al</IT>. over a Pt/Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> cordierite monolith,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit53">53</REF> wherein a ∼30 °C improvement was observed, in accordance with Fig. 17.</annotationART></s> <s sid="176"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our recent letter<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF> and the present paper represent the first report of sulfate-promoted ethane combustion.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="177"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res41" novelty="None" advantage="None">Higher Pt loadings facilitated lower temperature light-off (Fig. 18), in line with the documented structure sensitivity of alkane combustion over Pt/Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> catalysts,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit49">49</REF> but gave the same order of alkane reactivity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="178"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res41" novelty="None" advantage="None">The former finding supports our earlier predictions that large metallic Pt clusters favour C–H bond scission,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit36">36</REF> while the latter indicates alkane activation proceeded <IT>via</IT> a common rate-limiting step over all catalysts.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="179"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs24" novelty="None" advantage="None">Alumina presulfation again facilitated low-temperature light-off; however <IT>the magnitude of the promotional effect was independent of Pt loading</IT> (Fig. 19).</annotationART></s> <s sid="180"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res42" novelty="None" advantage="None">This suggests the promotional phenomenon originates principally from sulfate-related changes in the alumina support, and not the platinum.</annotationART></s> <s sid="181"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results presented in Fig. 7, wherein the Pt loading was fixed and the surface aluminium sulfate coverage varied, confirm that support-mediated chemistry indeed plays the dominant role in promoting alkane oxidation.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="182"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res43" novelty="None" advantage="None">Catalyst sulfation did not significantly alter the apparent activation barriers to combustion, in agreement with Hubbard <IT>et al</IT>.,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19">19</REF> but did increase the associated pre-exponential factors.</annotationART></s> <s sid="183"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res43" novelty="None" advantage="None">This suggests alkane oxidation occurs <IT>via</IT> a common reaction pathway over both fresh and sulfated Pt/Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB>, with sulfation generating a vast number of new surface sites active towards low temperature C–H activation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="184"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The nature of these sites remains speculative, however our model studies have shown that sulfate enhances the dissociative sticking probability of propane over Pt{111}/Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> single-crystal surfaces.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit54">54</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="185"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This enhancement directly correlated with interfacial sulfate formation, and may involve spillover of a propylsulfate intermediate, formed at the periphery of Pt clusters, onto bare metal sites for subsequent oxidation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="186"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Such alkylsulfate intermediates may provide an alternative low energy pathway to C–H bond activation.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit55">55</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="187"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fast XPS measurements recently provided direct evidence for alkylsulfate formation during the reaction of alkenes over model SO<SB>4</SB>/Pt{111} surfaces.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit56">56</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="188"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">This hypothesis is supported by the observation that SO<SB>2</SB> does not enhance combustion of long chain alkanes (<IT>e.g.</IT> cyclohexane) which have intrinsically higher sticking probabilities.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit46">46</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="189"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Sulfate-enhanced propene activation was also recently reported over a full single-crystal model Pt/γ-Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB>/NiAl{110} catalyst,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit57">57</REF> demonstrating this phenomenon extends across both the pressure and structure gaps.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="190"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">It should be noted that direct activation of propane over SO<SB>4</SB>/Pt{111} surfaces is possible under vacuum conditions, <IT>even in the absence of alumina.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit45">45</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="191"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">However the low saturation coverage (<IT>θ</IT><SB>SO<SB>4</SB></SB> = 0.25 ML) and thermal stability (&lt;200 °C) of surface SO<SB>4</SB> achievable over Pt sites alone,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit56">56</REF> suggests this is a minor pathway in the present systems.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Conclusions</HEADER><P><s sid="192"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Sulfated aluminas possessing well-defined surface sulfate species and tuneable acid properties can be prepared by simple direct impregnation by aqueous sulfate-ion solutions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="193"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Low molarity solutions (&lt;0.1 M SO<SB>4</SB><SP>2−</SP>) only modify the surface of γ-alumina while higher concentrations induce the crystallisation of non-acidic bulk Al<SB>2</SB>(SO<SB>4</SB>)<SB>3</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="194"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thermally stable surface sulfate groups promote the adsorption of light alkanes and subsequent low temperature C–H activation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="195"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Pt-promoted SO<SB>4</SB>/Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> catalysts exhibit enhanced C<SB>1</SB>–C<SB>3</SB> alkane combustion over their Pt/Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> counterparts, and activity scales with both surface aluminium sulfate coverage and metal loading.</annotationART></s> <s sid="196"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Alkane reactivity increases with chain length in all cases suggesting C–H bond scission remains rate-limiting over sulfated catalysts.</annotationART></s> <s sid="197"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The magnitude of sulfate-promotion was independent of Pt loading and greatest under fuel-lean conditions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="198"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Support-mediated alkane activation over SO<SB>4</SB>/Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> and subsequent spillover of alkyl moieties onto Pt sites is the principal origin of this enhanced catalytic combustion.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
