<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b404880f" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Roesky’s ketone: a spectroscopic study</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">We present a joint experimental-theoretical spectroscopic study of 5-oxo-1,3,2,4-dithiadiazole, also known as Roesky’s ketone.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The theoretical results of a vibrational analysis, calculated at the DFT/B3LYP/6-311+G* level of theory, of the title compound have been compared with experimental data, consisting of Raman and IR frequencies in different phases, and the bands have been assigned to the normal vibrations of the molecule.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Additionally, an analysis of the origin of the high intensity of the band assigned to the CO stretching mode was performed based on calculated stockholder charges and atomic dipoles.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results of theoretical calculations of the <SP>13</SP>C and <SP>14</SP>N NMR chemical shifts are compared to experimentally obtained shifts.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="1.">Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Compounds containing an –NSN–S– fragment are relatively new and their molecular properties, most importantly reactivity and opto-electronic features, differ substantially from those of the corresponding hydrocarbons.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This makes these compounds very interesting for further experimental and theoretical studies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">During the past few years a considerable body of work has been performed on these kinds of compounds, in the context of a multidisciplinary study in the framework of the search for new materials and their possible applications (see <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2 cit3 cit4 cit5 cit6">ref. 1–6</REF>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">Within this collection of new compounds, ring structures in which the –NSN–S– fragment is closed into a cyclic system by one or more atoms have assumed a prominent role since issues like delocalisation of π-electrons, ring currents and aromaticity become highly interesting subjects of study, both from a theoretical and an experimental point of view.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In recent years we have been focussing on five- and six-membered rings such as 1,3<IT>λ</IT><SP>4</SP><IT>δ</IT><SP>2</SP>,2,4-benzodithiadiazine and its fluorinated derivates<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7 cit8">7,8</REF> and the title compound, Roesky’s ketone or 5-oxo-1,3,2,4-dithiadiazole.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">We are currently performing a similar study on an organometallic (SN)<SB>2</SB> compound containing a cobalt atom.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">We recently subjected Roesky’s ketone to an intensive computational study to gain a deeper insight in the appropriate methods and basis sets for the most reliable description of the compound’s properties, in particular its geometry.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9 cit10">9,10</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Additionally, a detailed analysis of the bonding and structure of the ketone was performed with the emphasis on orbital topologies, atomic charges, atomic and molecular dipoles, aromaticity parameters and Fukui functions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the current paper we present a joint theoretical and experimental study on the spectroscopic properties of Roesky’s ketone: the infrared (IR), Raman and nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) spectra are discussed and a detailed analysis of the origin of the high intensity of the band assigned to the CO stretching mode was performed based on calculated stockholder charges and atomic dipoles.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.">Experimental</HEADER><P><s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Roesky’s ketone was synthesised as previously reported.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF></annotationART></s></P><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.1.">Vibrational spectroscopy</HEADER><P><s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The IR spectra of the compound, dispersed in KBr pellets, were recorded on a Bruker IFS 66v Fourier transform spectrometer, using a Globar source in combination with a Ge/KBr beam splitter and a broadband mercury cadmium telluride (MCT) detector.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The interferograms were averaged over 200 scans, Happ-Genzel apodized and Fourier transformed using a zero filling factor of 4 to yield spectra at a resolution of 2 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">FT-Raman spectra of the compound were recorded on a Bruker IFS 66v interferometer equipped with a FT-Raman FRA 106 module.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The sample was excited by the 1064 nm line of a Nd/YAG laser operating at 150 mW.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">For each spectrum, 2000 scans, using a resolution of 4 cm<SP>−1</SP>, were averaged and Fourier-transformed with a zero filling factor of 4.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.2.">NMR spectroscopy</HEADER><P><s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None"><SP>13</SP>C NMR and <SP>14</SP>N NMR spectra were recorded on a Jeol DELTA GSX270 spectrometer in CDCl<SB>3</SB> and C<SB>6</SB>D<SB>6</SB> with the chemical shift <IT>δ</IT> of the carbon atom referenced to external tetramethylsilane (TMS) and that of the nitrogen atoms to nitromethane.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">All measurements were performed at 25 °C.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.3.">Computational methods</HEADER><P><s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="New" advantage="None">All calculations were performed on isolated molecules in <IT>C</IT><SB><IT>s</IT></SB> symmetry (see <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">ref. 9</REF> for further details) using the Gaussian 98<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF> and BRABO<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF> packages, at the DFT/B3LYP<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF> and the Hartree–Fock (HF)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF> levels of theory with the 6-311+G* <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15 cit16">15,16</REF> and Dunning’s cc-pVTZ<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17 cit18">17,18</REF> basis sets.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="New" advantage="None">Geometry optimisations were performed as previously reported.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="New" advantage="None">Spectroscopic properties were calculated starting from optimised geometries with the same method/basis set combination as the one used for the corresponding geometry optimisation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="New" advantage="None">Harmonic force field calculations were performed at the DFT/B3LYP/6-311+G* level of theory, yielding the frequencies used in the vibrational analysis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="New" advantage="None">No attempts were made to scale the force field.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Cartesian force field was transformed into one described in a set of pseudosymmetry coordinates<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19 cit20">19,20</REF> to construct the potential energy distribution (PED), which was subsequently used to derive approximate descriptions of the normal modes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Stockholder charges <IT>q</IT><SB>A</SB> were calculated as previously reported,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF> based on the Hirshfeld partitioning of space.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Components of the atomic dipole moments <IT>μ</IT><SB>A</SB> were calculated according to <IT>μ</IT><SB>A,<IT>n</IT></SB> = −∫<IT>r</IT><SB><IT>n</IT></SB>Δ<IT>ρ</IT><SB>A</SB>(<IT>r⃑</IT>)d<IT>r⃑</IT>, with <IT>n</IT> = <IT>x</IT>,<IT>y</IT>,<IT>z</IT>, <IT>r⃑</IT> the position vector of the atom and Δ<IT>ρ</IT> the deformation density as usually defined.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">Chemical shielding factors were calculated at all atomic positions at the HF/6-311+G*, the DFT/B3LYP/6-311+G* and the DFT/B3LYP/cc-pVTZ levels of theory, at the corresponding geometries, using the GIAO method<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24 cit25 cit26 cit27 cit28">24–28</REF> implemented in Gaussian 98.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="New" advantage="None">The chemical shift for the carbon atom was obtained by subtracting the chemical shielding value of this atom from the one calculated for tetramethylsilane (TMS) which is 195.8637 ppm at the HF/6-311+G* level, 184.0193 ppm at the B3LYP/6-311+G* level and 184.4807 ppm at the B3LYP/cc-pVTZ level, based on the corresponding geometries.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="New" advantage="None">Chemical shifts for the nitrogen atoms were obtained by subtracting the chemical shielding values of the two atoms from that calculated for nitromethane (CH<SB>3</SB>NO<SB>2</SB>) which is −184.7452 ppm at the HF/6-311+G* level, −152.4366 ppm at the B3LYP/6-311+G* level and −147.6395 ppm at the B3LYP/cc-pVTZ level, based on the corresponding geometries.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The molecular framework and atomic numbering are shown in Fig. 1.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.">Results and discussion</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.1.">Vibrational spectroscopy</HEADER><P><s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Table 1 compares the theoretical vibrational frequencies, calculated at the B3LYP/6-311+G* level, with the experimental ones found in the gas-phase IR spectrum,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29">29</REF> the Nujol IR spectrum,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30">30</REF> the Raman spectrum in dichloromethane<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30">30</REF> and with new solid-state IR and Raman data.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">They have been ordered according to the Herzberg numbering scheme for the normal modes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The experimental values can be easily assigned based on the accordance between the frequencies and, in the case of the Nujol and the KBr spectra, also the intensities.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="New" advantage="None">The assignments have been derived from the PEDs of the normal modes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The molecule has twelve normal coordinates, which can be subdivided into six stretching modes <IT>ν</IT>, along each of the six bonds, an in-plane CO bending mode <IT>β</IT>, an out-of-plane CO bending mode <IT>γ</IT>, two in-plane ring deformation modes <IT>Δ</IT> and two out-of-plane ring torsion modes <IT>Γ</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is interesting to note that the seven bands at the low-wavenumber end of the spectrum (<IT>ν</IT><SB>6</SB>–<IT>ν</IT><SB>12</SB>) and the CO stretching mode (<IT>ν</IT><SB>1</SB>) correspond to very pure normal modes according to the calculations: contributions from other symmetry coordinates than the principal one are limited to 18%.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the four stretching modes at higher wavenumbers (<IT>ν</IT><SB>2</SB>–<IT>ν</IT><SB>5</SB>) considerable mixing with other symmetry coordinates such as the ring bending modes <IT>Δ</IT> and other stretching modes, is observed, as is to be expected in ring systems.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Nevertheless, there is always one major contribution and this has been listed in Table 1.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The only bands that can be clearly distinguished in the spectra are the ones with a considerable calculated intensity, and the most intense band in the IR spectra is <IT>ν</IT>CO (<IT>ν</IT><SB>1</SB>), as expected.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Some of the frequencies appear in all of the spectra and correlate very well with the calculated spectrum, whereas some of the calculated frequencies are obviously lacking in the experimental spectra.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">As can be seen, the bands at 874 and 515 cm<SP>−1</SP> can not be found in any of the experimental spectra.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">These bands may be too weak to be observed or, in the case of the band at 515 cm<SP>−1</SP>, accidentally degenate with the one predicted at 522 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">As expected, the calculations overestimate the higher wavenumber for the <IT>ν</IT><SB>CO</SB> band considerably, but under about 1000 cm<SP>−1</SP>, the correlation is quite acceptable and the differences remain small.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The poor correlation between the experimental and theoretical values of the calculated band at 307 cm<SP>−1</SP> needs to be commented on, since the correlation between experiment and theory is generally better for lower wavenumbers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Previously, we discussed the poor correlation between the CS bond length calculated at the B3LYP/6-311+G* level, and the corresponding interatomic distance found in the crystal by low-temperature XRD:<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF> the calculations [1.9410 Å] grossly overestimate the bond length found in the solid state [1.8305(17) Å].</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The expression of this inconsistency in the vibrational spectrum is then straightforward: an overestimated bond length means an underestimated force constant for the corresponding stretching mode, which means that the frequency will be likewise underestimated, as can be seen in Table 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Nevertheless, the Raman frequencies observed at 377 cm<SP>−1</SP> in the liquid and at 390 cm<SP>−1</SP> in the solid can only be assigned to the calculated value of 307 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.2.">The intensity of the CO stretching mode</HEADER><P><s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The intensity of an IR band is proportional to the square of the change of the dipole moment <IT>μ</IT> with the normal coordinate <IT>Q</IT> describing the vibrational mode,The stockholder partitioning scheme<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21 cit22">21,22</REF> allows the interpretation of the dipole moment in terms of atomic charges and atomic dipole moments.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23 cit31">23,31</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The <IT>n</IT>th component of the molecular dipole, <IT>μ</IT><SB><IT>n</IT></SB> with <IT>n</IT> = <IT>x</IT>, <IT>y</IT>, <IT>z</IT>, can be written aswhich is the sum of the contributions of charge transfer (first term, with <IT>q</IT><SB>A</SB> the stockholder charge and <IT>R</IT><SB>A,<IT>n</IT></SB> the coordinate of atom A) and of the intra-atomic charge polarization, calculated by the atomic dipole moment components <IT>μ</IT><SB>A,<IT>n</IT></SB> (second term).</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">By doing this for different values of <IT>Q</IT> an interpretation of the <IT>change</IT> of the dipole moment with the normal coordinate in terms of changes of atomic dipoles and charges becomes possible, and the origin of d<IT>μ</IT>/d<IT>Q</IT> can be studied.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">The high purity of the CO stretching mode (<IT>ν</IT><SB>1</SB>), henceforth abbreviated <IT>Q</IT><SB>CO</SB>, and the high intensity of the corresponding band in the experimental IR spectrum, makes this the ideal candidate for such an analysis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The relevant data has been graphically presented in Figs. 2 and 3.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The CO stretching vibration was simulated in seven discrete steps (Δ<IT>r</IT><SB>CO</SB> = 0.1 Å) and these are represented in the horizontal axes in Figs. 2 and 3, going from the shortest (point 1) CO distance to the longest (point 7) <IT>via</IT> the equilibrium position in point 4.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 2a displays the variation of the total molecular dipole moment and of its components, which were calculated using eqn. (1); the values are given in Debye (D) and were recalculated from the corresponding values in atomic units (au) using 1 D = 0.393 426 58 au.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The separate atomic contributions to the total molecular dipole, as defined in eqn. (1), can now be discussed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 2b shows the changes in the atomic positions with the CO stretching coordinate: the two atoms comprising the CO bond show the largest displacements while the other remain virtually stationary – this confirms the purity of the normal mode.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">A closer look at the changes of the atomic charges for each of the positions of the vibration, which are given in Fig. 2c, reveals that there are large variations in the charges on all six atoms, but that the largest changes in stockholder charge can be found on the oxygen atom, O(5), followed by C(5) and S(1); the charges on the two nitrogen atoms and S(3) undergo the smallest variation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Upon stretching the CO bond the oxygen and carbon atoms both gain negative charge (0.322 and 0.156 |<IT>e</IT>|, respectively) while the four other atoms gain positive charge: the largest increase is found for S(1) (0.232 |<IT>e</IT>|).</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, the negative charge which is added to O(5) during stretching seems to come primarily from S(1).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 2d shows that there are large fluctuations in the atomic dipole moments, |<IT></IT><SB>A</SB>|, for all the atoms during the stretching of the CO bond.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The variations in the two components of this property in the molecular plane, <IT>μ</IT><SB>A,<IT>x</IT></SB> and <IT>μ</IT><SB>A,<IT>y</IT></SB>, have been presented in Figs. 3a and 3b, respectively, and the figures show some interesting trends.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The value of the total atomic dipole on N(2) remains virtually constant during the stretching, as do its components, at least around the equilibrium point.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast, the value of the atomic dipole on N(4) decreases substantially, as do its components (especially <IT>μ</IT><SB>A,<IT>x</IT></SB>) indicating that the atomic dipole on this atom rotates in the plane of the molecule.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">In comparison, the atomic dipoles on S(1), S(3) and C(5) are small and again their fluctuations are related to the changes in the two components.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The atomic dipole of O(5) becomes very small in point 2, <IT>i.e.</IT> for a situation where the CO bond is shortened and, as can been seen from Fig. 2a, at the exact point where d<IT>μ</IT>/d<IT>Q</IT> changes its sign (<IT>vide infra</IT>).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">At the equilibrium position (point 4) d<IT>μ</IT>/d<IT>Q</IT> has a positive sign.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">When the CO bond is shortened, the molecular dipole becomes very small and for further reduction of the bond length, d<IT>μ</IT>/d<IT>Q</IT> has a negative sign.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The most important contribution to the total dipole in this region comes from <IT>μ</IT><SB><IT>y</IT></SB> because <IT>μ</IT><SB><IT>x</IT></SB> is very small.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fact that the contribution of the <IT>y</IT>-component is the most important can easily be interpreted because the CO bond lies virtually parallel to the <IT>y</IT> axis (see Fig. 1); consequently, when the bond is stretched, <IT>μ</IT><SB><IT>y</IT></SB> becomes larger.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">To explain what the specific contribution of <IT>μ</IT><SB><IT>y</IT></SB> is caused by, the graphs in Figs. 3c and 3d need to be analysed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">From equation 1 it is known that <IT>μ</IT><SB><IT>n</IT></SB> is the sum over all the atoms of the terms <IT>μ</IT><SB>A,<IT>n</IT></SB> and <IT>q</IT><SB>A·</SB><IT>R</IT><SB>A,<IT>n</IT></SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The combination of Figs. 3a and 3c on the one hand and Figs. 3b and 3d on the other indicates that the contributions to <IT>q</IT><SB>A·</SB><IT>x</IT><SB>A</SB> + <IT>μ</IT><SB>A·<IT>x</IT></SB> and <IT>q</IT><SB>A·</SB><IT>y</IT><SB>A</SB> + <IT>μ</IT><SB>A·<IT>y</IT></SB> due to the components of the atomic dipole moments, <IT>μ</IT><SB>A·<IT>x</IT></SB> and <IT>μ</IT><SB>A·<IT>y</IT></SB>, are several times smaller than contributions due to the components of the charge transfers, <IT>q</IT><SB>A·</SB><IT>x</IT><SB>A</SB> and <IT>q</IT><SB>A·</SB><IT>y</IT><SB>A</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the latter two the most important contribution to the variation of the components of the molecular dipole with the normal coordinate <IT>Q</IT><SB>CO</SB> comes from the oxygen atom, O(5).</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The major contribution to <IT>q</IT><SB>A·</SB><IT>x</IT><SB>A</SB> + <IT>μ</IT><SB>A,<IT>x</IT></SB> and <IT>q</IT><SB>A·</SB><IT>y</IT><SB>A</SB> + <IT>μ</IT><SB>A,<IT>y</IT></SB> for O(5) must therefore come from the <IT>q</IT><SB>A·</SB><IT>x</IT><SB>A</SB> and <IT>q</IT><SB>A·</SB><IT>y</IT><SB>A</SB> terms of O(5), or indirectly the variation of the stockholder charge on the oxygen atom.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The latter is then the cause of the high intensity of the band of the CO stretching mode (<IT>ν</IT><SB>1</SB>) in the vibrational spectrum.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.3.">NMR spectroscopy</HEADER><P><s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The experimental NMR data of Roesky’s ketone, in particular <SP>13</SP>C and <SP>14</SP>N chemical shifts, have been compiled in Table 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Regarding the <SP>13</SP>C NMR data, only one singlet can be found in the spectrum at 189.91 ppm in CDCl<SB>3</SB> and at 188.90 ppm in C<SB>6</SB>D<SB>6</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The calculated NMR shift values correlate well with the experimental values.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Regarding the <SP>14</SP>N NMR data, two singlets are found in the spectrum which means that the spins do not couple with any other nuclei, and this makes the experimental assignment difficult, even though it is known that N(2) is generally deshielded with respect to N(4) for these types of compounds.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The theoretical calculations confirm this general trend in the case of Roesky’s ketone.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">As can be seen, the correlation of the absolute values between theory and experiment is far less satisfactory than for the carbon spectrum.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The difference between the calculated and experimental values for N(2) amounts to more than 300 ppm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">For N(4) the calculations predict a strongly shielded nitrogen atom with respect to the one in the reference compound, in contrast to the experimental value.</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">When these data are compared with previous studies on substituted 1,3<IT>λ</IT><SP>4</SP><IT>δ</IT><SP>2</SP>,2,4-benzodithiazines,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF> it is clear that the unsatisfactory numerical agreement obtained here is not unusual and this confirms the complicated nature of calculated nitrogen chemical shifts and their comparison with experimental data.</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, our findings for Roesky’s ketone indicate that the values are quite dependent on the basis set used.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.">Conclusions</HEADER><P><s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to perform an in-depth spectroscopic study of Roesky’s ketone, new <SP>13</SP>C and <SP>14</SP>N NMR spectra were recorded, as well as solid-state Raman and infrared spectra.</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The newly recorded vibrational spectra together with the data already present in the literature, comprising IR and Raman spectra in different phases, have been assigned based on the results of force field calculations at the DFT/B3LYP/6-311+G* level.</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The analysis of the vibrationally induced changes of the molecular dipole moment due to the CO stretching mode reveals that the charge transfer of the oxygen atom contributes most to the change of the dipole moment during the vibration, causing the high intensity of the IR band.</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Observed trends in NMR parameters of the title compound can be theoretically predicted based on calculated NMR shielding constants.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
