<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b406795a" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The jasmonate-free rice mutant <IT>hebiba</IT> is affected in the response of phyA′/phyA″ pools and protochlorophyllide biosynthesis to far-red light</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Phytochrome (phy) A in its two native isoforms (phyA′ and phyA″) and the active (Pchlide<SP>655</SP>) and inactive (Pchlide<SP>633</SP>) protochlorophyllides were investigated by low-temperature fluorescence spectroscopy in the tips of rice (<IT>Oryza sativa</IT> L. <IT>Japonica</IT> cv Nihonmasari) coleoptiles from wild type (WT) and the jasmonate-deficient mutant <IT>hebiba</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The seedlings were either grown in the dark or under pulsed (FRp) or continuous (FRc) far-red light (<IT>λ</IT><SB>a</SB> ≥ 720 nm) of equal fluences.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the dark, the mutant had a long mesocotyl and a short coleoptile, whereas the situation was reversed under FR: short mesocotyl and long coleoptile, suggesting that the effect is mediated by phyA.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Under these conditions the WT displayed a short coleoptile and emergence of the first leaf.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the dark, the spectroscopic and photochemical properties of phyA, its content and the proportion of its two pools, phyA′ and phyA″, were virtually identical between WT and <IT>hebiba</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the total content of protochlorophyllides was higher in the mutant.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Upon illumination with FRc, [phyA] declined in the WT and the ratio between phyA′ and phyA″ shifted towards phyA″.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In <IT>hebiba</IT>, the light-induced decline of [phyA] was less pronounced and the ratio between phyA′ and phyA″ did not shift.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Moreover, in the WT, FRp stimulated the biosynthesis of Pchlide<SP>655</SP>, whereas FRc was inhibiting.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast, in the mutant, both FRp and FRc stimulated the synthesis of Pchlide<SP>655</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">This means that FRc caused the opposite effect in <IT>hebiba</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">This difference correlates with a slower photodestruction of primarily the light-labile phyA′ pool in <IT>hebiba</IT>.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">One of the dominating themes in current phytochrome (phy) research is the structural and functional heterogeneity of the phys.</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">A number of phys, products of different <IT>PHY</IT> genes, were discovered, with phyA and phyB as major members of the family.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">PhyB, the ‘classical’ phy, mediates the red light (R)-induced/far-red light (FR) reversible photoresponses in the low fluence response (LFR) range, whereas phyA accounts for the very-low fluence (VLFR) and high-irradiance (HIR) responses that are most efficiently triggered by FR.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">2</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both phys are active throughout the whole plant life cycle, but their function is often complementary and sometimes even antagonistic.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">PhyA, in particular, participates in promotion and inhibition of seed germination, FR-induced de-etiolation, promotion of flowering and resetting of the circadian clock.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">It modifies gravitropic and phototropic sensitivity and also modulates the activity of phyB and other minor phys.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is generally believed that the complex functions of phyA are accomplished by one and the same homogeneous pigment species, whereby different regions of the molecule are responsible for the different modes of the photoresponses, VLFR and HIR.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, a mounting body of evidence suggests that phyA itself is heterogeneous and that this heterogeneity may account, at least partially, for the complexity of its action.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Two post-translationally modified phyA populations were discovered in monocots and dicots and termed phyA′ and phyA″.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">These populations differ in photochemical and spectroscopic properties, in content and distribution between different organs and tissues, and in their light stability.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The exact structural differences between these two phyA species are not completely understood.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Experiments on transgenic plants over-expressing full-length oat phyA or mutant phyA with deletions at the N-terminus suggest that a stretch between amino-acid residues 6 and 69 could be involved in the modification.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The two phyA pools probably differ in this yet unknown post-translational modification and/or in the intracellular distribution of the pigment: phyA′ appears to be soluble, whereas phyA″ is either bound to membranes or to a protein lattice.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">From correlations between changes of phyA′ <IT>versus</IT> phyA″ content and the phenotype of <IT>phyA</IT> mutants and transgenic plants it can be inferred that the light-labile phyA′ pool is probably responsible for de-etiolation whereas the relatively light-stable phyA″ pool might function throughout the entire life cycle of the plant.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, phyA″ might also modify (suppress) the action of phyA′.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">It has been proposed that the balance between both phyA pools could provide a mechanism for the fine-tuning of phyA-action (see <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">ref. 4</REF> for review).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The physiological responses to phyA are likely to involve changes in the hormonal status of the plant.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hormones might affect the state and functions of the pigment, a possibility that so far has been mostly neglected.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">Mutants deficient in hormone synthesis, signaling or responses are valuable tools to address this issue.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">For instance, the rice mutant <IT>hebiba</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF> is deficient in jasmonic acid and shows a sign reversal in the light response of growth.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Whereas coleoptile growth is elevated in the dark and efficiently inhibited by R (where phyB dominates the responses <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">2</REF>), mutant coleoptiles are arrested in growth as long as they remain in the dark, but expand rapidly upon illumination.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Here we report that the inversion of the light response in <IT>hebiba</IT> is also induced by irradiation with FR (expected to act predominantly through phyA<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2 cit4">2,4</REF>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In connection with this response we find that both pools of phyA (phyA′ and phyA″) behave normally in <IT>hebiba</IT> as long as the coleoptiles are kept in the dark but not upon exposure to FR.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the WT, total phyA content (P<SB>tot</SB>) declines accompanied by a considerable shift in the equilibrium towards phyA″, whereas in the mutant this decline was much less pronounced and the phyA′/phyA″ ratio remained constant.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">We also observed an altered response of active protochlorophyllide (Pchlide<SP>655</SP>) to continuous FR as Pchlide<SP>655</SP> decreased in the WT mutant and increased in the mutant.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">This sign-reversal of the protochlorophyllide response is discussed in the context of the altered light-response of the two pools of native phyA.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Materials and methods</HEADER><P><s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">WT rice (<IT>Oryza sativa</IT> L. <IT>Japonica</IT> cv Nihonmasari) and the jasmonate-deficient <IT>hebiba</IT> mutant<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF> isolated from the same background were used in the experiments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The seedlings were raised for 5 days at 27 °C on floating meshes on tap water in complete darkness (D) or under FR (<IT>λ</IT><SB>a</SB> ≥ 720 nm).</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The light source was a 100 W tungsten lamp in combination with filters KS-19 + FS-7 (thickness 3 mm, Optical Glass Plant, Krasnogorsk, Russia) and provided a fluence rate of approx.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">0.1 W m<SP>−2</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">There were two illumination regimes at equal total fluence: (1) 7 min pulsed light and 53 min D (FRp) and (2) continuous FR (FRc).</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since homozygous mutants are male-sterile,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF> seed material from heterozygous plants was used, which segregated into approximately 75% of seedlings with a WT phenotype and 25% exhibiting the mutant phenotype (see below).</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Coleoptile tips (the apical 3 mm) were harvested for the measurement.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">From 3 to 6 tips were attached to a Plexiglas sample holder using a water–glycerol mixture (50 ∶ 50%) and frozen at 85 K in a cryostat in a transparent Duwar flask.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">All the manipulations were carried out under green safelight.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Low-temperature (85 K) fluorescence emission spectra of phy (<IT>λ</IT><SB>e</SB> = 633 nm) and protochlorophyllide (<IT>λ</IT><SB>e</SB> = 450 nm) were measured in the coleoptile tissue as described previously<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6 cit7">6,7</REF> using a custom-built spectrofluorimeter based on two double-grating monochromators of the DFS-12 and DFS-24 types (LOMO, Leningrad, USSR).</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Briefly, the spectrum was initially recorded from the sample frozen in D when phy is in its R-absorbing form, Pr, (state 0) using a very weak measuring beam at 633 nm favorable for phy measurements.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The source of the excitation light was a He–Ne laser, 1 mW, in combination with a monochromator MDR-2 to cut-off the pumping light, and the intensity was reduced by about 50-fold with neutral filters, such that the excitation light did not induce photochemical changes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Subsequently, the sample was illuminated at 85 K with the full light of the laser to convert Pr into lumi-R, the first photoproduct that is stable at low temperatures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The second spectrum of the sample was recorded for this state 1 when Pr is in the photoequilibrium with lumi-R.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">A third spectrum was recorded from the same sample upon monochromatic excitation at 450 nm to measure active (Pchlide<SP>655</SP>) and inactive (Pchlide<SP>633</SP>) protochlorophyllides.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">The raw spectra were corrected for background fluorescence to obtain the real spectra of phy and protochlorophyllide.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">As reference spectra for background fluorescence, spectra obtained from the base of the primary root were used because this tissue is virtually free of phy and protochlorophyllide.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">These reference spectra were recorded at 85 K upon excitation at 633 nm (for phy) and 450 nm (for protochlorophyllide) and subtracted from the respective raw spectra.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">It was shown earlier with the use <IT>phyA phyB</IT> mutants of <IT>Arabidopsis</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF> and pea<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF> that the spectra of old roots at their base (or of old shoots at their base), after saturating R converting Pr into Pfr, were very close to the emission spectra of etiolated stems of the double mutants.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">These spectra did not reveal emission bands belonging to phy, suggesting that the emission in the spectra of respective WT belonged to phyA and phyB and that the input of the minor phys (phyC–phyE) in the total phy fluorescence is negligible and can be ignored.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">The corrected (difference) phy spectra provided information on the spectroscopic and photochemical properties of the pigment, in particular, position of the peak, <IT>λ</IT><SB>max</SB>, half-band width, Δ<IT>λ</IT>, of the spectrum, and extent of the Pr → lumi-R conversion to reach a photoequilibrium at 85 K, <IT>γ</IT><SB>1</SB> = (<IT>F</IT><SB>0</SB> − <IT>F</IT><SB>1</SB>)/<IT>F</IT><SB>0</SB>, where <IT>F</IT><SB>0</SB> and <IT>F</IT><SB>1</SB> are the intensities of the Pr emission in the maximum in state 0 and state 1, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">The fluorescence intensity in the Pr maximum in state 0, related to the intensity of the background fluorescence at 660 nm where the input of the Pr fluorescence is negligible, were used as measure of total phy content, [P<SB>tot</SB>], in relative units.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">The experimental parameter <IT>γ</IT><SB>1</SB> provided information on the relative content of the two phenomenological phy types: Pr′ which comprises phyA′ (Pr′ = phyA′) and Pr″ which consists of phyA″ and phyB (Pr″ = phyA″ + phyB) (see <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">ref. 4</REF>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Phenomenologically, the two Pr species in rice are characterized by the individual <IT>γ</IT><SB>1</SB> values of approx.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">0.49 ± 0.03 for Pr′ and 0 for Pr″.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">Both [P<SB>tot</SB>] and the Pr′/Pr″ ratio allow to estimate the content of phyA′ and phyA″ in a given sample in relative units.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">These estimates are possible, when the input of phyB is ignored—it contributes to less than 10% of [P<SB>tot</SB>] and by Western analysis we do not observe differences between WT and <IT>hebiba</IT> mutant in terms of phyB levels.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="New" advantage="None">The content of Pchlide<SP>655</SP> and Pchlide<SP>633</SP> was determined proceeding from the intensities in their respective emission maxima after the spectra deconvolution as described in .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">ref. 11</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">From 4 to 7 independent samples were used to determine the parameters listed above and the standard error (±SE) usually did not exceed ≈10%.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">The spectra were not corrected for the spectral sensitivity of the fluorimeter.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">The noise of the spectra registration was below 3–5%.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">The spectra were interpolated manually.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Results</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Growth responses</HEADER><P><s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">To assess the physiological effect of our lighting regime, we checked the morphology of the seedlings (Fig. 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None"><IT>In the dark</IT>, the mutant seedlings had a long mesocotyl, and a short curved coleoptile, quite reverse to the situation in the WT, where the mesocotyl was short and the coleoptile long.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None"><IT>Pulsed FR illumination (FRp)</IT> induced emergence of the first leaf in approximately half of the WT plants.</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Under the same conditions, the mutant displayed a relative decrease of the mesocotyl length, whereas the coleoptile was still very similar to that of dark-grown <IT>hebiba</IT> seedlings.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Finally, under <IT>continuous FR illumination (FRc)</IT>, all the WT seedlings had the first leaf released from the coleoptile, whereas in <IT>hebiba</IT> the coleoptiles were closed and elongated, thus resembling dark-grown seedlings of the WT.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Phytochrome</HEADER><P><s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None"><IT>In dark grown seedlings</IT>, practically no difference in the spectroscopic and photochemical characteristics of phy in the WT and the mutant was detected (Fig. 2a).</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Position (<IT>λ</IT><SB>max</SB> = 685 nm) and half-band width (Δ<IT>λ</IT> = 24 nm) were the same in both lines, as well as the extent of the Pr → lumi-R photoconversion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The total phy content, the proportion of phyA′ and phyA″ and their concentration in the mutant were virtually the same as in the WT (Fig. 3).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None"><IT>In seedlings grown under FRp</IT>, the parameters of phy differed between the WT and the mutant.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although phy was spectroscopically very similar (<IT>λ</IT><SB>max</SB> = 685 nm and Δ<IT>λ</IT> = 24 nm) (Fig. 2b), <IT>γ</IT><SB>1</SB> was lower in the WT as compared to the mutant (Fig. 3).</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Pronounced differences were observed also in the content of total phyA and of its species: in <IT>hebiba</IT>, [P<SB>tot</SB>], [phyA′] and [phyA″] were significantly higher than in WT.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In general, upon FRp illumination a considerable decline in the total phy content and a shift in the phyA′/phyA″ equilibrium towards phyA″ was found in the WT, whereas <IT>hebiba</IT> showed almost no changes in [P<SB>tot</SB>] and in the proportion of the two phyA species (Fig. 3).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Even more pronounced changes in the phy state were found in <IT>seedlings grown under FRc</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The position and the shape of the spectra of phyA in the Pr form in the WT and the mutant were essentially similar (<IT>λ</IT><SB>max</SB> = 685 nm and Δ<IT>λ</IT> = 26 nm) (Fig. 2c).</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the extent of the Pr → lumi-R conversion (<IT>γ</IT><SB>1</SB>) dropped further down in the WT whereas in <IT>hebiba</IT> it remained practically unchanged as compared with dark-grown seedlings (Fig. 3).</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Seedlings of both lines revealed a considerable decline in [P<SB>tot</SB>] upon FRc, although it was more pronounced in the WT.</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">This decline was followed by further lowering of the phyA′/phyA″ proportion in the WT whereas in the mutant it remained essentially unchanged (Fig. 3).</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Protochlorophyllide</HEADER><P><s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None"><IT>In the dark</IT>, <IT>hebiba</IT> accumulates much higher protochlorophyllide both in the active and inactive forms than the WT, but the ratio [Pchlide<SP>655</SP>]/[Pchlide<SP>633</SP>] remains unaffected (Figs. 4 and 5).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None"><IT>Upon FRp</IT> we observed a stimulation of the synthesis for both Pchlide<SP>655</SP> and Pchlide<SP>633</SP> by approximately 1.5-fold in the WT whereas in the mutant it remained practically unchanged.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">A quite different picture was observed in <IT>seedlings grown under FRc</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the WT, a 3-fold inhibition of the synthesis of the active protochlorophyllide, Pchlide<SP>655</SP>, was detected, whereas a considerable activation of the synthesis (1.6-fold) was observed in <IT>hebiba</IT> (Fig. 5a).</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">A somewhat different situation was found with regard to the content of inactive Pchlide<SP>633</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the WT, it remained similar to the levels observed in the dark, whereas in <IT>hebiba</IT> it grew approx.</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">1.4-fold (Fig. 5b).</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Discussion</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Dark-grown seedlings</HEADER><P><s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The phenotype of the mutant seedlings was different of that of the WT (Fig. 1) in agreement with earlier observations.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the fluorescence and photochemical parameters of phyA in etiolated seedlings of both the WT and <IT>hebiba</IT> lines were found to be identical (Fig. 2) as well as its total content and proportion of the phyA subpopulations (Fig. 3).</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fact that the balance between phyA′ and phyA″ does not change in the mutant indicates that the post-translational modification of phyA (possibly a phosphorylation) supposed to be responsible for the difference between phyA′ and phyA″<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF> is not affected in <IT>hebiba</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The level of protochlorophyllide was, however, considerably higher in the mutant (Fig. 4 and 5).</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the mutant is deficient in jasmonate,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF> these findings would be consistent with a role of jasmonate in the synthesis of protochlorophyllide whereas it does not considerably affect the state of phyA in the dark.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Seedlings grown under FRp</HEADER><P><s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Upon FR illumination, the difference between mutant and WT became manifest not only in the phenotype (Fig. 1) and in the protochlorphyllide content (Fig. 5) but also in the status of phyA (Fig. 2 and 3).</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the direction and extent of the changes depend on the mode of illumination: FRp or FRc.</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">FRp brought about a small shift in the phyA′/phyA″ balance towards the latter in the WT, with no considerable changes in the mutant.</annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The relatively weak changes in the phyA state under FRp (which is expected to trigger VLFR<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF>) indicate that the photodestruction of phyA and the regulation of phyA synthesis are unlikely to follow the VLFR response mode.</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, FRp treatment proves to be inductive both for Pchlide<SP>655</SP> and Pchlide<SP>633</SP> biosynthesis in the WT, whereas in the mutant the active form of protochlorophyllide did not respond.</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, protochlorophyllide falls under the most sensitive targets for the VLFR but seems to be not completely triggered in the mutant.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Seedlings grown under FRc</HEADER><P><s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the same total fluence, FRc proves to be much more effective than FRp and reveals profound differences between the WT and the mutant (Fig. 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although spectroscopically phyA in the mutant was very close to that in the WT (Fig. 2) phyA seems to be much more stable in the mutant (Fig. 3).</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the WT, this decline is accompanied by a shift in the phyA′/phyA″ ratio in favor of phyA″.</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast, there is practically no change in these parameters for the mutant.</annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In agreement with <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">ref. 14</REF>, these differences are interpreted to result from the interaction of two processes: (i) autoregulation of phyA synthesis by phyA itself, which should proceed without changes in the phyA′/phyA″ ratio, and (ii) light-induced destruction of phyA primarily in the phyA′ form.</annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the mutant, photodestruction is slowed down primarily, whereas in the WT, autoregulation and photodestruction contribute roughly to the same extent to the light-induced disappearance of phyA.</annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">FRc is more efficiently triggering changes of [phyA′] as compared to FRp although the total fluence is kept constant.</annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">This suggests that the HIR rather than VLFR mode of phyA action is responsible for the changes of [phyA′].</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">FRc drastically reduces the content of active protochlorophyllide in the WT (Fig. 5), in line with the effect found in <IT>Arabidopsis</IT>, tomato and barley.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15 cit16 cit17">15–17</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The content of the inactive form was, however, practically unaffected.</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">A quite different situation is observed in the <IT>hebiba</IT> mutant: instead of inhibition, FRc induced the synthesis of both protochlorophyllides.</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The sign of the FR effect on the biosynthesis of active protochlorphyllide had been shown to depend on plant species and plant tissues and to be mediated by phyA′.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Here we show that it also depends on the genotype (WT <IT>versus</IT> a mutant).</annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Interestingly, not only protochlorophyllide synthesis, but also growth responds inversely to FR in the mutant (see above and Fig. 1).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The sign of the active protochlorophyllide regulation was found to depend on the irradiation protocol.</annotationART></s> <s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">FRp stimulated the synthesis both in WT and mutant.</annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">FRc inhibited the synthesis of the active form in the WT and stimulated it in the mutant.</annotationART></s> <s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The same tendency of the FRp and FRc effects was followed by inactive protochlorophyllide, Pchlide<SP>633</SP> (Fig. 5).</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">As far as we know, the dependence of the sign of the effect on the mode of action of the FR (VLFR or HIR) on the protochlorophyllide biosynthesis was demonstrated for the first time.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The <IT>hebiba</IT> mutant is deficient in jasmonate.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">This deficiency is already present in the dark, but becomes especially manifest in response to continuous light (both R and FR), when jasmonate synthesis is strongly induced in the WT.</annotationART></s> <s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">This strongly suggests that the light effects mediated by phyA depend on the hormonal status of the plant.</annotationART></s> <s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">It remains to be elucidated whether the changes in the relative content of the two native pools of phyA can account not only for the extent but also for the alterations in the sign of the light reactions in <IT>hebiba</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Future work will be directed to understand the role of jasmonate in the photodestruction of the highly photolabile pool of phyA′.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
