<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b407082h" hasDoc="yes" version="1168" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Elastic polarizable environment cluster embedding approach for water adsorption on the α-Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB>(0001) surface. A density functional study<XREF TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" /></annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Low coverage water adsorption on the α-Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB>(0001) surface has been studied with a generalized-gradient density functional approach using embedded cluster and periodic slab methodologies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">An advanced cluster embedding method in an elastic polarizable environment (EPE), which enables an accurate description of the adsorption-induced substrate relaxation, has been applied systematically at various density functional levels: PW91, BP, and PBEN.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, periodic slab model calculations based on the PW91 functional were carried out for varying surface supercell sizes, (2 × 2) and (3 × 3), which compare very well with the corresponding embedded-cluster results.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In agreement with two recent studies employing integrated MO + MO (IMOMO) embedded cluster and periodic Car–Parrinello BLYP methodologies, our calculations predict the 1,2-dissociative adsorption to be about 10 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> more favorable than molecular adsorption; however, at variance with the latter study, we predict 1,4-dissociative adsorption to be least favorable.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Analysis of adsorbate-induced relaxation renders the interaction energy with the unrelaxed substrate in the 1,4-dissociative case negative (unbound complex), thus rationalizing the smallest (by absolute value) interaction energy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our best estimates for binding energies, at the PBEN level, for molecular, 1,2-dissociative, and 1,4-dissociative adsorption are −22.5, −31.2, and −17.2 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>, respectively.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Aluminum oxide (alumina) is a material studied extensively experimentally as well as theoretically.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This interest derives from many industrial applications of alumina, most importantly, as a catalyst and catalyst support,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF> and as substrate for microelectronic applications.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">2</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Alumina is also important for its role in the environment as one of the major earth mineral components.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In both respects, the surface chemistry of aluminum oxide, <IT>i.e.</IT> the adsorption/desorption phenomena on a microscopic scale, is of special interest.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Under natural conditions, mineral surfaces are most probably hydroxylated.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3 cit4">3,4</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, adsorption of water and the resultant modification of the surface should be addressed prior to studying adsorption of any other chemical onto the hydroxylated alumina surface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Yet, while the interest in the surface hydroxylation of alumina is quite wide spread, its exact mechanisms, the influence of sample preparation, and its possible effect on measured properties are still not fully understood.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6">5,6</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Structure and reactivity of a clean α-Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB>(0001) surface, prepared under ultrahigh-vacuum (UHV) conditions, differ markedly from the corresponding properties of a surface prepared in the presence of water.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">While the clean α-Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB>(0001) surface is terminated by a single Al layer,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit9 cit10">8–10</REF> the hydroxylated surface is best described as O-terminated with a double Al layer directly following the surface O layer.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6 cit11">6,11</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This finding suggests that the reaction of a clean single Al-terminated surface with water should be a complex multistage process, ultimately resulting in a surface transformation into a gibbsite-like structure, which can be formally viewed as substitution of the each surface Al by three H atoms.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Various intermediate states of surface hydroxylation are also possible, depending on the sample history, as well as on the presence of defects, steps, and other irregularities, all of which render understanding the chemistry at the surface a difficult task.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Several experimental and theoretical studies<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit7 cit12 cit13 cit14 cit15 cit16">5,7,12–16</REF> demonstrated that the clean α-Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB>(0001) surface readily reacts with water.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In single-crystal desorption measurements,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF> adsorption energies of water were found to lie in the range 23–41 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Given the complexity of the hydroxylation of the α-Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB>(0001) surface, we focus in the following on the incipient stage of this process.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Water adsorption on α-Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB>(0001) has been previously studied by cluster,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13 cit14">13,14</REF> embedded cluster,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14 cit15">14,15</REF> and supercell periodic<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF> models.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Most studies clearly indicated a preference for dissociative adsorption over molecular adsorption and extensive changes in chemical bonding.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">A recent embedded cluster IMOMO (“integrated molecular orbital + molecular orbital”)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF> study<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF> agreed well with Car–Parrinello molecular dynamics (CPMD) calculations<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF> regarding the calculated binding energies for molecular adsorption and one of the dissociative adsorption modes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">Whereas large unit cells are required in supercell periodic calculations, embedded cluster models should be well suited to modeling water adsorption in the low coverage regime.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">Water adsorption on the α-Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB>(0001) surface can serve as a good example to assess cluster embedding by our new “elastic polarizable environment” (EPE) method<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF><IT>via</IT> a comparison with methods based on periodic slab models.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The goal of the current investigation is twofold: (i) to study single water molecule adsorption on the α-alumina (0001) surface with methods based on density functional theory (DFT), and (ii) to compare two modeling approaches, namely our new cluster-embedding technique and a conventional periodic slab (band structure) approach.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this way, we intend to prepare for the computational investigation of more complex systems relevant to environmental chemistry.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">We will show that the embedded cluster method gives reliable energies and structures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of 1,4-dissociative water adsorption, we obtained binding energies and structures at variance with the results of a recent CPMD study,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF> but we will demonstrate that the current results are not artifacts of the EPE cluster model, because we were able to reproduce them in periodic calculations using the same exchange–correlation functional.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Computational methods</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Periodic <IT>versus</IT> cluster models</HEADER><P><s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Surfaces of solids and chemical reactions on them present a greater challenge to computational chemistry, compared to molecular systems, because an infinite number of atoms has to be treated in principle.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Two basic approaches are commonly used in electronic structure investigations of surface systems: cluster<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19 cit20">19,20</REF> and periodic slab (“supercell”) models.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21 cit22">21,22</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">Whereas the latter are preferred for (though not limited to) modeling of ordered materials, the former are more suitable for describing spatially isolated complexes on a particular segment of a surface, where a chemically interesting phenomenon (adsorption or defect) takes place, ideally when no interaction with other adsorbates or defects besides those under direct study has to be taken into account.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">These two approaches tackle the problem from different perspectives, and, to some extent, can be considered as complementary.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both modeling strategies have advantages and limitations.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23 cit24">23,24</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">The supercell approach is formally correct because it treats the solid as a laterally infinite system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">Model artifacts can be avoided by using (i) a sufficiently large surface unit cell (to eliminate undesired lateral interactions between adsorption complexes), (ii) a sufficiently thick slab model (to avoid undesirable effects of the unphysical second surface of the slab), and (iii) a sufficiently wide vacuum gap between repeated slabs (again to avoid unphysical interactions).</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="No">As a consequence of such highly accurate modeling, supercell methods can become computationally rather demanding, in particular in the limit of low coverage, because more atoms have to be included in a unit cell and, in many currently available programs, a very large number of plane-wave basis functions has to be used.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">Cluster model approaches are more flexible and convenient in that periodicity is not required and one can cut a model cluster from a surface according to the specific properties of the chemically interesting site; in addition, all conventional quantum-chemical techniques used for molecules can be straightforwardly applied.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25">25</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="No">These models, however, suffer from boundary effects, <IT>i.e.</IT> errors arising from the artificial and arbitrary termination of the infinite substrate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="No">Also, the cluster size often has a significant impact on the reliability of the calculation, whereas finite computational resources in many cases limit calculations to medium size clusters.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19">19</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Various schemes have been developed to reduce boundary effects in cluster models, typically by using embedding procedures,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18 cit26 cit27 cit28 cit29 cit30 cit31 cit32">18,26–32</REF> which incorporate at various levels corrections for otherwise neglected interactions with the remaining infinite solid.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">A good embedding strategy (as will be demonstrated in this paper) can be a promising alternative to periodic supercell strategies, at least for systems with strongly ionic substrates.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="No">(On the other hand, cluster embedding for metals is not of comparable practical importance because it poses rather challenging formal problems.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit33">33</REF>)</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In general, models for ionic solids are hybrids of a cluster treated quantum-mechanically (QM) and its environment represented classically.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Most cluster embedding studies to date used the simplest way of cluster embedding in rigid arrays of point charges and pseudopotential ions.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>The EPE embedded cluster method</HEADER><P><s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Recently, we suggested and implemented an advanced tool for cluster embedding in an elastic polarizable environment (EPE), suitable for modeling strongly ionic substrates.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">We also presented an extension of this strategy for solids with covalent polar bonding (covEPE), <IT>e.g.</IT> zeolites.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit32">32</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the EPE method, the surface site under investigation (<IT>i.e.</IT> an adsorption complex) is described by a quantum mechanical (QM) cluster embedded in a crystalline substrate, which in turn is described by a classical force field as an elastic polarizable environment, represented by a slab model.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">The EPE approach affords a variational, mutually self-consistent description of the interaction of the QM cluster and its environment.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The environment is allowed to act on the QM cluster <IT>via</IT> short-range forces at the cluster boundary and the long-range electrostatic (Madelung) field.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">QM cluster and its environment are allowed to polarize each other.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both can undergo a relaxation due to an adsorbate, and the structure of the entire system is determined through an iterative minimization of the total energy given by<IT>E</IT><SB>tot</SB> = <IT>E</IT><SB>cl</SB> + <IT>E</IT><SB>int</SB> + <IT>E</IT><SB>lat</SB>where <IT>E</IT><SB>cl</SB>, <IT>E</IT><SB>int</SB>, and <IT>E</IT><SB>lat</SB> are the energies of intracluster interactions, the coupling of the QM cluster and the environment, and the intralattice (environment) interactions, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The coupling energy <IT>E</IT><SB>int</SB> is defined in such a way that the cluster environment will not undergo any relaxation in the absence of an adsorbate; thus, an artificial distortion of the environment at the QM cluster boundary is avoided.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Details of the EPE cluster-embedding method have been described elsewhere.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">For touchstone complexes of metal atoms on MgO(001)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18 cit34">18,34</REF> and α-Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB>(0001)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit35 cit36">35,36</REF> and CO adsorption on α-Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB>(0001),<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit37">37</REF> the results of our EPE-embedded cluster model and those of periodic calculations agreed well.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">A particular advantage of this advanced embedding scheme is its ability to model adsorption on strongly relaxed metal-oxide surfaces, such as α-Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB>(0001).</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Embedding studies using methodologies of similar spirit have recently been carried out to model MgO<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit31 cit38">31,38</REF> and ZnO<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit39 cit40">39,40</REF> surfaces.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>EPE embedded cluster calculations</HEADER><P><s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The QM cluster model employed in this work (Fig. 1) consists of a core part (the chemically important region) built of 8 Al and 12 O all-electron atoms and a boundary region given by bare ion pseudopotentials<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit41">41</REF> Al<SP>3+</SP> without any basis functions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Termination of a QM cluster by bare cation pseudopotentials avoids an artificial polarization of the cluster electron density by leakage into the outer region which otherwise would occur due to interaction with point charges representing cations of the surrounding.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit42">42</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The environment was treated classically by a force field using a shell-model description combined with the Mott–Littleton approach.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit43 cit44">43,44</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The external electrostatic field of the regular slab was represented by about 500 point charges at lattice positions around the QM cluster (the closest 240 of which were allowed to relax), whereas the total Madelung field of the remaining crystal was described <IT>via</IT> a surface charge representation of the external embedding potential.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30">30</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Following our previous strategy for modeling an α-Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB>(0001) substrate,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit37">37</REF> we first optimized the surface slab model at the classical atomistic level using empirical parameters.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit45">45</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">We employed a nine-layer slab model terminated on either side by a single Al layer.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit37">37</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">During this optimization, the lateral unit cell parameters were kept fixed at the calculated bulk values.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Then, an embedded cluster calculation of the unperturbed surface (<IT>i.e.</IT> without any adsorbate) was carried out.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">At this step, only the QM cluster was relaxed, while the environment was kept fixed at the lattice positions determined in the preceding step.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Subsequently, the energy of the resulting structure served as reference of a clean surface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Finally, we carried out QM/EPE calculations on the active region modified by the presence of the adsorbate.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The quantum-chemical part of the calculation was accomplished using the linear combination of Gaussian-type orbitals fitting-functions density functional method<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit46">46</REF> (LCGTO-FF-DF) as implemented in the parallel code ParaGauss.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit47 cit48">47,48</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">We used three gradient-corrected exchange–correlation density functionals (GGA): BP,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit49 cit50">49,50</REF> PW91,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit51">51</REF> and PBEN.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit52">52</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Kohn–Sham orbitals were represented by flexible Gaussian-type basis sets, contracted in generalized fashion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">O and H atoms of water were described by standard contracted basis sets, (9s,5p,1d)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit53 cit54">53,54</REF> → [5s,4p,1d] and (6s,1p)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit55">55</REF> → [4s,p], with the polarization p or d exponents of H and O set to 1.00 and 1.15, respectively; for the substrate we used the contracted basis sets O (9s,5p,1d) → [4s,3p,1d] and Al (12s,9p,2d)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit56">56</REF> → [6s,4p,2d].</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the LCGTO-FF-DF approach, the classical Coulomb contribution to the electron-electron interaction is evaluated by representing the electron density with the help of an auxiliary Gaussian-type basis set.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit46">46</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">For every atom, the auxiliary basis was constructed as follows: the exponents of s and <IT>r</IT><SP>2</SP> type fitting functions were generated by scaling (all or selected) s and p orbital exponents, respectively, using a standard procedure;<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit46">46</REF> “polarization exponents” were chosen as geometric series with factors 2.5, starting with 0.1 for p and 0.2 for d exponents.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The resulting auxiliary basis sets were of the type (12s,9<IT>r</IT><SP>2</SP>,5p,5d) for Al atoms, (9s,5<IT>r</IT><SP>2</SP>,5p) for O atoms of the surface, (9s,5<IT>r</IT><SP>2</SP>,5p,5d) for O atoms of water, and (6s,1<IT>r</IT><SP>2</SP>,5p) for H atoms.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>First-principle periodic calculations</HEADER><P><s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">First principle periodic calculations were carried out with the plane-wave based Vienna <IT>ab initio</IT> simulation package (VASP)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit57">57</REF> using the GGA PW91 exchange–correlation density functional.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit51">51</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The interaction between atomic cores and electrons was described by the projector augmentation wave (PAW) method.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit58 cit59">58,59</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Brillouin-zone integrations were carried out with the help of a single <B><IT>k</IT></B>-vector (<B><IT>Γ</IT></B> point) using a generalized Gaussian smearing method<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit60">60</REF> with the standard smearing width of 0.01 eV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">An energy cut-off of 400 eV was adopted throughout.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> substrate was modeled using an Al-layer terminated slab of nine layers, Al–O–Al–Al–O–Al–Al–O–Al, the same model as used in the EPE calculations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The (2 × 2) or (3 × 3) unit cells contained 24 Al and 36 O or 54 Al and 81 O centers, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The slabs were repeated periodically, with a vacuum spacing of 9 Å.</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The slab surfaces were first relaxed without adsorbates.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In case of the clean surface as well as under perturbation by a H<SB>2</SB>O adsorbate, the “top” four layers of the substrate were allowed to relax fully while the rest of the slab was kept fixed at the bulk-terminated geometry obtained from a periodic PW91 optimization.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Pertinent parameters of the optimized rhombohedral primitive unit cell of the bulk structure (space group <IT>R</IT>3̄<IT>c</IT>) were <IT>a</IT> = <IT>b</IT> = 4.80 Å and <IT>c</IT> = 13.09 Å; the spacing between Al and O layers was 0.84 Å and that between adjacent Al layers 0.49 Å.</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The geometry relaxation was stopped when the total energy difference between two ionic relaxations was less than 10<SP>−3</SP> eV and the force on each unconstrained atom was less than 0.01 eV Å<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">For comparison, we mention that the CPMD study<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF> was carried out for slab models of 9 layers, separated by a vacuum gap 14 Å, a 3 × 3 surface unit cell, and an energy cut-off of 952 eV.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Results and discussion</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>The clean α-Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> (0001) surface</HEADER><P><s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">The (0001) surface of α-Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> is well characterized and therefore often serves as a benchmark for developing theoretical models.</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The termination by a single layer of Al<SP>3+</SP> cations has been predicted to be most stable in several atomistic<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit61 cit62">61,62</REF>, and first-principles<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit63 cit64">63,64</REF> calculations and also confirmed experimentally.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit9 cit10">8–10</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Relaxation was shown to be crucial for the formation of this most stable surface of α-Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both experiment<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit9">8,9</REF> and calculations<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13 cit64 cit65 cit66 cit67 cit68 cit69 cit70 cit71">13,64–71</REF> demonstrated strong relaxation, by 50–90%, of the distance between the topmost aluminum and oxygen layers.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In both computational strategies, periodic slab and embedded cluster (EPE) modeling, we started by relaxing a clean surface terminated with a single Al-layer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In the EPE model, this was done by optimizing a periodic slab model with a shell model (atomistic) force field.</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In agreement with previous studies,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13 cit68 cit69 cit70 cit71">13,68–71</REF>, a significant relaxation of the surface layers was obtained (Table 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Recent pseudopotential as well as all-electron slab calculations<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit68 cit69 cit70 cit71">68–71</REF> on slabs with 12–15 atomic layers, using a variety of exchange–correlation approximations (including hybrid functionals), predicted a surface relaxation behavior that is especially large for the outermost Al layer, but comprises several subsurface layers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The interlayer distance between the first Al layer and the next O layer, Al1–O1, is substantially reduced compared to the bulk-terminated value, 0.84 Å.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit72">72</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our result from atomistic calculations, 0.29 Å, compares favorably with experimental estimates of 0.3 ± 0.1 Å<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF> and 0.41 ± 0.05 Å.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our force-field based value is also close to results of other cluster or embedded cluster calculations,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14 cit15">14,15</REF> which yielded 0.25 Å.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our PW91-slab calculations either with (2 × 2) or (3 × 3) supercell, similarly to the periodic CPMD study<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF> where the BLYP<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit49 cit73">49,73</REF> functional had been used, predicted an even stronger decrease of the Al1–O1 interlayer distance to 0.15 Å.</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Typical relaxation magnitudes obtained from periodic DFT-based calculations reported in the literature range from −79 to −94% (Table 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The CPMD-BLYP result<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF> of −82% agrees quantitatively with our PW91-slab results.</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Periodic DFT-based methods significantly overestimate the experimentally determined relaxation (Table 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, there is much uncertainty about these experimental values associated with difficulties in the preparation of a clean surface.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">After the QM cluster was embedded and optimized in the next step of the EPE procedure, its equilibrium geometry changed somewhat compared to that optimized in periodic atomistic calculations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is a consequence of the fact that the force-field and the QM descriptions do not match quite well enough.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18 cit37">18,37</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Table 2 summarizes optimized interatomic distances from atomistic calculations, EPE embedded cluster model (which employed the PW91 DF for its QM part) and those from periodic slab calculations (also based on the PW91 DF).</annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Not unexpectedly, the geometrical parameters of the QM cluster are closer to those rendered by PW91-slab calculations than to the geometry from atomistic calculations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The average Al1–O distance (1.72 Å) in our cluster model is 0.04 Å larger than that in the relaxed PW91-slab structure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The interlayer spacing of the “top” Al layer to the O layer underneath, 0.23 Å, lies in between the values from periodic atomistic and DFT-based calculations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">This result corresponds to a smaller degree of surface relaxation, <IT>i.e.</IT> −72%, and is very close to other cluster model values (−70%)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14 cit15">14,15</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Water adsorption on α-Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB>(0001)</HEADER><P><s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Adsorption of a single water molecule onto the α-Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB>(0001) surface has previously been studied with several computational approaches.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13 cit14 cit15">13–15</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Wittbrodt <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF>. carried out HF and hybrid-DF (B3LYP) calculations on medium size cluster models; they used a 6-31+G(d) basis set in the central region of the cluster and a rather small 3-21G basis in the boundary region.</annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="Old" advantage="None">These authors applied simple embedding in a field of rigid point charges to selected structures, mainly to examine the resulting changes in the energetics, which they found to be small.</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">They concluded that the interaction energies for molecular and “1,2-dissociative” water adsorption should roughly be the same, whereas the interaction energy for “1,4-dissociative” adsorption was calculated 3–4 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> smaller.</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The notations “1,2-” and “1,4-” refer to different proton acceptor positions O<SB>s</SB> relative to the Al1 atom, which accepts the OH<SP>−</SP> moiety; see Fig. 1.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Subsequently, this conclusion was dismissed in periodic CPMD-BLYP calculations of Hass <IT>et al</IT>.,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF> who found dissociative adsorption to be favored by 10 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The authors of the latter supercell study attributed the discrepancy to deficiencies of the cluster approach.</annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">To cast aside the differences in methods and basis sets, they repeated the non-embedded cluster calculations of <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">ref. 14</REF> at their CPMD-BLYP level and found 1,2-dissociative adsorption to be only 3 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> more favorable.</annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">They also pointed to significant adsorption-induced long-range restructuring of the surface, which is not accounted for in small cluster models.</annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Indeed, most atoms in those cluster models had been constrained to their bulk positions to avoid unphysical relaxation at the cluster boundaries.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The more recent cluster study of Shapovalov and Truong<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF> employed the same Al<SB>8</SB>O<SB>12</SB> model as Wittbrodt <IT>et al</IT>.,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF> but at a higher level of theory, namely a two-layer IMOMO methodology.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The “model system” treated at the coupled-cluster singles and doubles (CCSD) level was a non-embedded Al<SB>4</SB>O<SB>6</SB> cluster with the adsorbate, whereas the “real system” treated at the MP2 level consisted of an Al<SB>8</SB>O<SB>12</SB> cluster, surrounded by full ion pseudopotentials (without orbital basis functions) and embedded in an array of point charges.</annotationART></s> <s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">A basis set of double-<IT>ζ</IT> quality with effective core potentials on Al was employed for both “real” and “model” systems.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Also, a more elaborated embedding scheme, compared to the earlier cluster study,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF> was used, still with a rigid cluster environment.</annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">This improved model rendered binding energies for molecular and 1,2-dissociative adsorption in good agreement with those of the periodic CPMD study.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="No">Shapovalov and Truong did not consider the 1,4-geometry,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF> although it constitutes the most interesting and controversial issue, in view of the discrepancy between the results of the cluster and the slab model, which have been attributed to long-range surface modifications not reflected by medium-size cluster models.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the present work, a somewhat different cluster model of the same size Al<SB>8</SB>O<SB>12</SB> was chosen (Fig. 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This cluster allowed us to consider both 1,2-and 1,4-dissociative water adsorption using the same model.</annotationART></s> <s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="Old" advantage="No">The above mentioned cluster model of Wittbrodt <IT>et al</IT>. was criticized in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">ref. 13</REF> especially in reference to the 1,4-dissociative path, due to limitations of the model size, <IT>i.e.</IT> under-coordination of the proton acceptor (labeled as O<SB>s4</SB> in Fig. 2) and lack of surface Al centers neighboring the O<SB>s4</SB> center, which suggests edge artifacts.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">Our cluster model overcomes these drawbacks and takes into account long-range electrostatic effects in a consistent manner.</annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">In addition, all degrees of freedom were allowed to relax in our model, whereas in the work of Shapovalov and Truong<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF> only the position of the central Al atom of the substrate and the adsorbate were optimized and the rest of the QM cluster as well as its environment were kept frozen at the substrate geometry.</annotationART></s> <s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">As we will discuss below, energies for molecular and 1,2-dissociative adsorption obtained in both calculations are nevertheless in close agreement.</annotationART></s></P><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>Structural aspects</HEADER><P><s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">In their periodic CPMD-BLYP study, Hass <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF>. considered molecular as well as 1,2-, 1,4-, and 1,6-dissociative adsorption of water.</annotationART></s> <s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The 1,2-and 1,4-dissociative pathways were found to be most important; therefore, only these and molecular adsorption were considered in the present work.<SUP TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" /></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Water adsorption noticeably affects the substrate geometry (Table 2).</annotationART></s> <s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">As a result of adsorption, the distance between the Al1 and O1 planes increased in the EPE calculation, as was also observed in previous theoretical studies.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13 cit14 cit15">13–15</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The relaxation of the Al1–O1 interplanar distance relative to bulk geometry decreases from −69% for the bare cluster to −49% for molecular adsorption, to −15 to −26% for dissociative adsorption.</annotationART></s> <s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Table 3 summarizes the corresponding relaxation (in percent) from the present as well as other periodic and cluster calculations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The relative upward displacement of the OH accepting Al atom is very similarly predicted by periodic as well as cluster methods.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the bare surface, all periodic DFT-based calculations predict too large a relaxation compared to experiment.</annotationART></s> <s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Embedded cluster models generally give a smaller relaxation of the outermost layer spacing; the percentage values range from 70 to 72%.</annotationART></s> <s sid="143"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">For molecular adsorption, the calculated relaxation from periodic slab and embedded cluster models is −48 to −54%.</annotationART></s> <s sid="144"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">For 1,2-dissociation, the cluster-model values scatter over a wider range, from −11 to −20%, than those from periodic calculations, from −13 to −15%, but all methods clearly predict a significant recovery of the Al1-O1 layer spacing in the direction of the bulk value.</annotationART></s> <s sid="145"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Of course, such comparisons of relaxation percentages have to be done with due caution, because the quoted value depends on the range around the “perturbation site” over which the interlayer spacing is averaged.</annotationART></s> <s sid="146"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Still, because the calculated relaxation of the O1-layer was found small (when considered), at least a qualitative comparison can be made.</annotationART></s> <s sid="147"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The present periodic and embedded cluster results yielded larger contraction values for 1,4-dissociative adsorption than for 1,2-dissociation, from −24 to −28%, whereas the periodic CPMD study<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF> gave almost the same values for both dissociative modes (Table 3).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="148"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">A closer look at the structures (compared in Table 2) reveals that 1,4-dissociation is indeed the only case, where the present work and the periodic CPMD study disagree notably;<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF> below, we will discuss this disagreement in more detail.</annotationART></s> <s sid="149"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">In Table 2, the optimized geometric parameters at the adsorption site are compared for the EPE-embedded cluster PW91 and periodic PW91 approaches employed in our study; the corresponding structures are shown in Fig. 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="150"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The optimized geometries within these two very different computational methodologies, cluster and slab models, agree very well; slab model geometries for (2 × 2) and (3 × 3) supercells agree within 0.01 Å.</annotationART></s> <s sid="151"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the EPE model, Al–O<SB>s</SB> bond lengths are predicted either 0.01–0.02 Å shorter or 0.01–0.04 Å longer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="152"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">For molecular, 1,2-, and 1,4-dissociative adsorption, the Al–O<SB>ads</SB> bond lengths differ by 0.01, 0.02 and 0.04 Å, respectively.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="153"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Molecular adsorption results in slightly elongated Al–O distances only at the adsorption site, 1.71–1.77 Å; these distances are 0.02–0.03 Å longer than in the relaxed bare QM cluster.</annotationART></s> <s sid="154"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The periodic PW91 calculations gave significantly larger changes, from 1.68 Å for the relaxed surface to 1.73 Å in the chemisorbed complex.</annotationART></s> <s sid="155"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Al–O<SB>ads</SB> distance (Fig. 2) is 1.98 and 1.96 Å in cluster and slab calculations, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="156"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is in close agreement with the value of 1.95 Å obtained in the periodic CPMD-BLYP study.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="157"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In our embedded-cluster model for 1,2-dissociative adsorption, we did not encounter artificially elongated Al–O<SB>s2</SB> distances of 2–2.2 Å as obtained in previous cluster calculations.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14 cit15">14,15</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="158"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our cluster result, 1.91 Å, is identical to that from our periodic PW91 calculations, to be compared with the periodic CPMD value, 1.90 Å.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="159"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Overall, the EPE bond lengths for molecular and 1,2-dissociative adsorption agree quite well with the corresponding CPMD values.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="160"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The geometries from our periodic PW91 calculations are in almost quantitative agreement with that former slab model study, with the exception of 1,4-dissociative adsorption, where both our EPE and periodic models agree well, but predict a structure of the adsorption complex, which differs significantly from that of the CPMD study.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="161"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">This may be a result of the different exchange–correlation functional used, PW91 here <IT>vs.</IT> BLYP.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit74">74</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="162"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hass <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF>. found significant and far extending restructuring of the substrate, in particular, the top-layer Al<SB>3</SB> center bound to O<SB>s4</SB> descended even below the top O layer and became six-fold coordinated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="163"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">In our EPE and periodic results, we did not observe this type of restructuring, although Al<SB>3</SB> moved 0.03 Å “down” compared to the clean substrate, <IT>i.e.</IT> the Al<SB>3</SB>-O1 spacing decreased at variance with the Al1–O1 spacing.</annotationART></s> <s sid="164"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, we observed another type of restructuring: O<SB>s4</SB> is no longer bound to Al<SB>2</SB> and thus coordinated by only two Al atoms, both in the cluster and the slab model.</annotationART></s> <s sid="165"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is likely a result of “bonding competition” between surface–adsorbate and intrasurface bonding.</annotationART></s> <s sid="166"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">Breaking one of the Al–O bonds possibly accounts for the fact that we calculated the energy gain of 1,4-dissociative adsorption 12–14 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> smaller compared to 1,2-dissociative adsorption (see below).</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>Energy aspects</HEADER><P><s sid="167"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">We now turn to a discussion of the central results of our study, the interaction energies of a single water with the α-Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB>(0001) surface for three selected adsorption modes: molecular, 1,2-dissociative, and 1,4-dissociative adsorption (Fig. 2).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="168"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The periodic CPMD slab model study of Hass <IT>et al</IT>.,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF> based on the BLYP functional,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit49 cit73">49,73</REF> found 1,2-dissociative adsorption 10 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> more favorable than molecular adsorption (Table 4).</annotationART></s> <s sid="169"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">As one of the main conclusions, their work rejected simple cluster models, <IT>e.g.</IT> those of <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">ref. 14</REF>, as they failed to predict a significantly larger binding energy for dissociative than for molecular water adsorption (Table 4).</annotationART></s> <s sid="170"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">In fact, Hass <IT>et al</IT>. repeated the bare cluster model calculations of <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">ref. 14</REF> (<IT>i.e.</IT> without embedding) using their own CPMD-BLYP formalism.</annotationART></s> <s sid="171"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this way, they obtained −25.7 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> binding energy for molecular adsorption and −28.9 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> for the dissociative adsorption.</annotationART></s> <s sid="172"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, with the “free” cluster model, the preference for dissociative adsorption was notably reduced, from 10 to 3 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="173"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Similarly, without cluster embedding, close binding energies were obtained for molecular and 1,2-dissociative adsorption at the B3LYP<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF> and the CCSD levels;<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF> an MP2 cluster calculation, preferring molecular adsorption, even gave a qualitatively wrong picture.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="174"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">For both MP2 and CCSD calculations, IMOMO cluster embedding was shown to stabilize dissociative adsorption and destabilize molecular adsorption.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="175"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac20" novelty="None" advantage="None">When corrected for the basis set superposition error (BSSE) by the counterpoise method<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit75">75</REF> (by 4–5 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>), the CCSD results for the embedded cluster models on molecular and 1,2-dissociative adsorption agreed almost quantitatively with those of the earlier CPMD-BLYP slab model study.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="176"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac20" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results for molecular adsorption, obtained in CPMD-BLYP slab model and CCSD embedded cluster calculations, were −23.3 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> and −23.4 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>, respectively, and the results for 1,2-dissociative adsorption were −33.2 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> and −31.6 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="177"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac20" novelty="None" advantage="None">This rather close agreement indeed is most astonishing if one considers the markedly different procedures to account for electron correlation and the completely different approaches to account for environment effects (Table 4).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="178"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">To compare periodic slab models and embedded cluster models in a strict sense, it is certainly desirable to have results at hand that were obtained for the same electronic structure approach.</annotationART></s> <s sid="179"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac21" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus far, this has not been the case.</annotationART></s> <s sid="180"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, we applied our advanced embedding strategy (EPE) and periodic first principle calculations for the PW91 functional, to obtain such a benchmark.</annotationART></s> <s sid="181"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">To make this comparison more general, we also performed EPE embedded cluster calculations for two further gradient-corrected density functionals, BP and PBEN (see Computational Methods).</annotationART></s> <s sid="182"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="Old" advantage="None">We estimated basis set superposition errors using the counterpoise method.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit75">75</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="183"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Finally, in periodic PW91 calculations, we compared results for supercells of two sizes, (2 × 2) and (3 × 3).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="184"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">As seen from Table 4, our EPE calculations give qualitatively correct energetics in all cases: molecular adsorption is 7.6–8.7 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> less favorable than 1,2-dissociative adsorption, depending on the functional.</annotationART></s> <s sid="185"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">Also, the three functionals consistently render the interaction for 1,4-dissociative adsorption weakest, 5.2–5.6 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> less (in absolute value) than molecular adsorption.</annotationART></s> <s sid="186"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">Of all density functionals, PW91 predicts the strongest interaction; BP interaction energies are 1.6–2.3 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> smaller (in absolute value) and PBEN energies are 4.4–5.5 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> smaller (Table 4).</annotationART></s> <s sid="187"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Overall, this agreement of the interaction energies as obtained from the EPE calculations is very satisfying and the order of interaction energies follows known trends: PW91 &gt; BP &gt; PBEN (in absolute value).</annotationART></s> <s sid="188"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">Experience has shown that PBEN energetics are most reliable for metal–ligand interactions and such interaction energies are usually expected to be smaller than the corresponding PW91 results which tend to overestimate such interactions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit74 cit76">74,76</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="189"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">The interaction energies from periodic calculations with a (3 × 3) surface unit cell and the PW91 functional are also very similar, both in trend and magnitude, to the energies from the corresponding PW91 EPE embedded cluster calculations; the cluster results are 3.5–5.7 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> smaller (by absolute value) than the analogous slab model results.</annotationART></s> <s sid="190"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">In fact, the interaction energies obtained with the larger (3 × 3) and smaller (2 × 2) surface unit cells bracket the EPE cluster results (Table 4).</annotationART></s> <s sid="191"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is remarkable that the differences between the two slab model calculations with different surface unit cells are rather substantial, 5.5–7.2 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>, whereas the relative energetics of the three adsorption modes remain, nevertheless, essentially unaffected by the size of the surface unit cell.</annotationART></s> <s sid="192"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">Indeed, the EPE interaction energies are rather close to those of periodic (2 × 2) calculations, with differences amounting to only 1.5–2.0 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> (Table 4).</annotationART></s> <s sid="193"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">From this comparison it is evident that the substrate relaxation is large and extends far, as was also concluded in the CPMD-B3LYP study;<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF> therefore, even larger surface unit cells may be required to recover that part of the interaction energy which is masked by the artificial periodicity of the slab models.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="194"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Qualitatively, the contributions of the substrate relaxation to the total binding energies can be deduced from the binding energies computed by optimizing only adsorbate-related degrees of freedom, <IT>i.e.</IT> with the positions of substrate atoms “frozen” at the clean surface geometry.</annotationART></s> <s sid="195"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" advantage="None">The corresponding results, obtained for EPE embedded clusters and (2 × 2) slab models at the PW91 level, are also given in Table 4.</annotationART></s> <s sid="196"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" advantage="None">Only for molecular adsorption is this latter interaction energy close to the total binding energy from EPE cluster calculations, −21.7 <IT>vs.</IT> −28.0 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>, respectively; the corresponding energies from periodic (2 × 2) slab model calculations are very similar, −20.5 (“frozen”) and −26.5 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="197"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None">For 1,2-dissociative adsorption, the EPE binding energy at the frozen substrate is only −1.8 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>, and that for 1,4-dissociative adsorption is even positive, 28.2 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>, <IT>i.e.</IT> the complex is unbound.</annotationART></s> <s sid="198"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None">The latter, surprising value is supported by the corresponding result of periodic calculations, 29.6 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="199"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None">Unfortunately, it was not possible to converge the geometry of 1,2-dissociative adsorption with the substrate fixed at the structure without perturbation by the adsorbate; several calculations converged to the energetically favorable structure of molecular adsorption.</annotationART></s> <s sid="200"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">From these calculations one concludes that the adsorbate-induced relaxation of the substrate is largest for 1,4-dissociative adsorption, ∼50 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>, but only ∼34 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> for 1, 2-dissociative mode; for molecular adsorption it is only ∼6 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>, <IT>i.e.</IT> almost negligible in comparison with the other two adsorption modes.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="201"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res29" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our PBEN results for molecular and 1,2-dissociative adsorption from EPE-embedded cluster models agree almost quantitatively (up to 1–2 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>) with the CCSD embedded-cluster results of <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">ref. 15</REF> and the CPMD-BLYP periodic slab model results of .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">ref. 13</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="202"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res29" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, this tight agreement does not extend to 1,4-dissociative adsorption.</annotationART></s> <s sid="203"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">Recall that, for the PW91 functional, the current EPE and periodic slab model results for 1,4-dissociative adsorption agree equally well with each other, as do the results for the other two types of adsorption complexes, molecular adsorption and 1,2-adsorption (Table 4).</annotationART></s> <s sid="204"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, one cannot dismiss the large discrepancy between the PBEN EPE adsorption energy for 1,4-dissociative adsorption, −17.2 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>, and the corresponding CPMD-BLYP slab model results, −32.5 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>, as a cluster artifact (Table 4).</annotationART></s> <s sid="205"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Unfortunately, the structure of the latter adsorption complex was not available to us to crosscheck the energy for our two computational approaches.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="206"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">Finally, we return to the IMOMO cluster calculations,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF> which are the cluster models that allow treatment by high-level post-HF correlation methods.</annotationART></s> <s sid="207"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">In that sense, these IMOMO cluster results can also be taken as a set of benchmark data.</annotationART></s> <s sid="208"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In fact, they agree best of all with our PBEN energetics, corroborating the claimed higher quality of this density functional for the determination of binding energies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="209"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fact that two rather diverse cluster-embedding strategies gave quite similar results, with energy differences of only 0.9 and 0.4 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> (Table 4), supports the reliability of these modeling approaches.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Conclusions</HEADER><P><s sid="210"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This work demonstrated the performance of our new cluster embedding technique in an elastic polarizable environment (EPE), using low coverage water adsorption on the α-alumina (0001) surface as test system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="211"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">We compared embedded cluster results to periodic supercell calculations of this work and to literature data.</annotationART></s> <s sid="212"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">To render the conclusions of this study more general, we employed three density functionals, PW91, PBEN, and BP, and we also examined the convergence of the periodic slab results with respect to the size of the surface unit cell of periodic calculations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="213"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">We found the current PW91 embedded cluster results to agree well with those of periodic PW91 calculation, in terms of both structure and energetics.</annotationART></s> <s sid="214"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="No">Slab models suffer from artificially imposed periodicity (as was demonstrated by comparison of 2 × 2 and 3 × 3 models), which can only be overcome by using rather large surface unit cells.</annotationART></s> <s sid="215"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">Thus, the variational EPE cluster embedding method can serve as an economic alternative to periodic slab models, which should be particularly important for disordered surfaces and charged defect sites, common in oxide systems.</annotationART></s> <s sid="216"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Still, there is room for improvement of the current embedding model by refining the force field; the present work adopted a shell model force field from the literature.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit45">45</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="217"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Despite the scatter in magnitudes of calculated interaction energies by up to 5 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>, the relative energetics of different water adsorption complexes were predicted uniformly by all three density functionals employed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="218"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">We consider the PBEN functional to yield the most accurate adsorption energies: −22.5, −31.2, and −17.2 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> for molecular, 1,2-dissociative and 1,4-dissociative adsorption, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="219"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The almost quantitative agreement of the present DF results with those of a high-level post-HF correlation method, IMOMO CCSD-MP2,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF> confirms their reliability for the evaluation of adsorption energies on oxide surfaces.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="220"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Finally, comparison of the current results with an earlier periodic CPMD study,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF> raises new questions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="221"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">For molecular and 1,2-dissociative adsorption, the CPMD study, based on the BLYP functional, reported binding energies very similar to ours, −23.3 and −33.2 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>; however, we were not able to reproduce the rather large binding energy, −32.5 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>, found in that study for 1,4-dissociative adsorption.</annotationART></s> <s sid="222"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">We demonstrated by comparison with our own periodic slab calculations that this discrepancy is not an artifact of a cluster model.</annotationART></s> <s sid="223"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our results therefore do not support the earlier conclusion<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF> about preferred dissociation into 1,4-mode, but rather suggest the 1,2-dissociative pathway.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="224"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Having presented this model study, we wish to emphasize its idealized nature, as a water reaction with a <IT>partially hydroxylated</IT> alumina surface would be of truly practical interest.</annotationART></s> <s sid="225"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac22" novelty="None" advantage="None">This more complex case has only once been addressed theoretically,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF> but clearly more work is needed to gain full insight into this interesting chemical problem.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
