<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b407371c" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Simulation of the growth and differentiation of stem cells on a heterogeneous scaffold</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">We present Monte Carlo simulations illustrating that scaffolds with specially designed heterogeneities can be used as a tool for governing the growth and differentiation of stem cells.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This tool is predicted to be efficient provided that the size of the heterogeneities exceeds (but not appreciably) the cellular size and the rate of cell diffusion is relatively fast compared to that of cell division.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="1.">Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Depending on the source, stem cells have the potential to form one, many or all cell types of an organism (the diversity and abilities to evolve in different directions decrease from embryonic stem cells to “adult” stem cells) and accordingly can in principle be employed to build blocks for every tissue we comprise.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Using this potential and bringing stem-cell therapies to the clinic demand a better understanding of the factors that maintain cells in a multipotent state or drive them to create differentiated cells.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2">1,2</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Specifically, there is a need to improve the control of differentiation of cells and to promote desirable division <IT>via</IT> external signals, in order to reach suitable spatial cellular arrangements.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2 cit3 cit4">2–4</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">An additional challenge is to extend and sophisticate the tools which can be employed to govern the tissue evolution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">One of the opportunities here is to use specially designed heterogeneous scaffolds, on which the original cell culture(s) are deposited and eventually develop into a tissue<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF> (for other strategies, see, <IT>e.g.</IT>, <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">ref. 6</REF>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">To illustrate this concept, we present the first Monte Carlo (MC) simulations of the growth and differentiation of stem cells on a scaffold with μm-sized heterogeneities (such scaffolds can be fabricated by using, <IT>e.g.</IT>, various lithographic techniques; for recent examples of experimental studies of behaviour of cells on heterogeneous surfaces, see <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">ref. 7</REF>).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Physically, the cellular growth is complicated by cell–cell adhesion resulting usually in aggregation of similar cells and/or segregation of different cells.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Such phenomena can be treated by using a lattice approximation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">To our knowledge, the first lattice MC simulations of cell sorting were executed by Graner and Glazier.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">At present, there are various versions of lattice MC models focused primarily on the 2D cell segregation and/or growth (see, <IT>e.g.</IT>, papers <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9 cit10 cit11 cit12 cit13 cit14">refs. 9–14</REF> and references therein).</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In particular, the proliferation and differentiation of stem cells on an uniform surface was analysed in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13 cit14">refs. 13 and 14</REF>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our aim here is to simulate the evolution from a single stem cell into various cell types, on a heterogeneous surface, where the cell division/differentiation occurring according to certain rules is influenced by the surface.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.">Model</HEADER><P><s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In our present coarse-grained lattice model, cells are located on a 2D <IT>L</IT> × <IT>L</IT> square lattice.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">(Alternatively, one could use, <IT>e.g.</IT>, a triangular lattice.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">It would not change the conclusions, because the segregation and/or island-growth kinetics are not too sensitive to the type of a lattice.) Each lattice site is either vacant or occupied by one cell (for the multi-site models making it possible to mimic changes of the cell shape, see <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit11">refs. 8 and 11</REF>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The symbol <IT>i</IT> (or <IT>j</IT>) indicating a cell type runs from 1 to 3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Cells of type 1 are assumed to be totipotent (in our context, the terms “totipotent” and “pluripotent” are used interchangeably), <IT>i.e.</IT>, they are able to give rise to all cell types.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Cells of types 2 and 3 represent differentiated cells.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Specifically, the latter cells are considered to be able to produce only cells of its own kind (<IT>e.g.</IT>, the division of a cell of type 2 results in the formation of two cells of this type).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The cell size is assumed to be slightly larger than the site size but smaller than the distance between the next-nearest-neighbour (nnn) sites.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">With this prescription, the interactions between nearest-neighbour (nn) and nnn cells, <IT>ε</IT><SB><IT>ij</IT></SB><SP>nn</SP> and <IT>ε</IT><SB><IT>ij</IT></SB><SP>nnn</SP>, should be repulsive and attractive due to deformation and adhesion, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">These interactions, introduced to take into account softness, deformation, and adhesion of cells, are of course “effective”.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">(In reality, the cell adhesion may be related, <IT>e.g.</IT>, to interactions <IT>via</IT> membrane proteins.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Explicit inclusion of such details is beyond our coarse-grained description.)</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Cell diffusion is a complex process including deformation of the cell shape.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In our coarse-grained treatment, we skip the details and realize this process <IT>via</IT> cell jumps to vacant nn sites.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">A jump is allowed provided that in the final state (after the jump) the cell has at least one contact with other cells, <IT>i.e.</IT>, after a jump at least one of the nn or nnn sites should be occupied (this condition is introduced in order to suppress rare events of escape of single cells from the central area where they are located; its role in the simulations is minor, because the probability of such events is low anyway).</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The normalized jump probability is defined by the standard Metropolis rule.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case under consideration, the Metropolis algorithm is appropriate, because it correctly describes the tendency of cells to increase the number of adhesive contacts.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">One should however bear in mind that in our context the thermal energy, <IT>k</IT><SB>B</SB><IT>T</IT>, used in the Metropolis rule, is effective as well as the cell–cell interactions (for this aspect of the simulations, see <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">ref. 10</REF>).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The mechanism of cell division is governed by the spatial constraints and cell–cell signaling<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF> including messenger transport between cells, signal transmission <IT>via</IT> the cell membrane, gene regulation, <IT>etc</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In our model, this complex process is mimicked by introducing prescribed probabilities of cell division, which are different for different arrangements of cells and depend on the underlying surface to which the cells are attached.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In particular, the division of a given cell is allowed provided that (i) all the nn sites are vacant (the cells located in nn sites are deformed and accordingly the probability of their division is assumed to be negligibly small) and (ii) the newly-born cell has at least one nn vacant site.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The signaling may occur <IT>via</IT> ligand diffusion between cells<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF> or <IT>via</IT> the so-called gap–junction communication.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19">19</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the former case, the cells may be far from each other and the ligand concentration is usually fairly low.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the latter case, the cells should be in close contact.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In open systems (<IT>e.g.</IT>, on surfaces), ligand diffusion away from cells may easily result in decrease of the ligand concentration and accordingly the role of the long-range signaling may be less significant.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In our present simulations, we take into account only short-range signaling in order to keep the model as simple as possible (in principle, the long-range signaling can be incorporated as well as described in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">ref. 14</REF>, but this is beyond our present goals).</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In particular, the range of cell–cell signaling is considered to be limited to next-nearest neighbours.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, the division probability may depend on the occupation of nnn sites (nn sites are empty; see above).</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">This approximation is reasonable at the initial stages of cellular growth when the number of cells is not too large (at the later stages, the growth may be influenced by long-range inhibitory interactions among the cells<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF> and/or limitations in the supply of oxygen and nutrients<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Specifically, we use the simplest rules including spontaneous division of stem and differentiated cells and induced division of stem cells.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Spontaneous division of a cell of type <IT>i</IT>, occurring with probability <IT>p</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB><SP>sp</SP>, is considered to result in the formation of two cells of type <IT>i</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rules for induced division of a stem cell, due to communication with adjacent cells, may be rather complex.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">To be specific, we assume that division of a stem cell, related to communication with a nnn cell of type <IT>i</IT>, results in generation of an additional cell of type <IT>i</IT> + 1 with probability <IT>p</IT><SB><IT>i</IT>+1</SB><SP>ind</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">For example, a stem (type-1) cell communicating with a type-2 cell can give rise to a type-3 cell.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">(To validate this rule, we may refer, <IT>e.g.</IT>, to differentiation of neural stem cells.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">In reality, the probabilities <IT>p</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB><SP>sp</SP> and <IT>p</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB><SP>ind</SP> depend not only on the cell type but also on the growth factors added into the nutrition solution for the cell culture.) During trials of the induced division of stem cells, one of the nnn site is chosen at random and then the process is performed with the prescribed probability depending on the occupation of this site.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">The scaffold surface may be fabricated of “conventional” materials with heterogeneities fabricated on the μm scale.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Another promising approach is based on the use of selectively-functionalized supported lipid bilayers, offering efficient reduction of nonspecific cell and protein binding, in combination with appropriate attachment sites.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">To mimic such situations, the lattice sites representing the scaffold surface are assumed to form patches.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Specifically, the patches of type 1, 2 and 3 are considered to interact more strongly with cells of type 1, 2 and 3, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The cells are allowed to diffuse on all the patches, but as soon as a cell of type <IT>i</IT> reaches the patch formed of material <IT>i</IT>, its movement becomes limited by this patch, <IT>i.e.</IT>, jumps back to the other patches are no longer possible (this is a prerequisite for efficient cell segregation).</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">To reduce the number of the model parameters, the rates of diffusion of different cells on different patches are set equal (this rule is sufficient for our present goals but if necessary it can easily be relaxed).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">To characterize the relative rates of cell division/differentiation and diffusion, we use the dimensionless parameter <IT>p</IT><SB>div</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rates of these processes are considered to be proportional to <IT>p</IT><SB>div</SB> and 1 − <IT>p</IT><SB>div</SB>, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">With this specification, our MC algorithm consists of sequential trials to realize diffusion or division events.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">A site is chosen at random.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">If the site is vacant, the trial ends.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">Otherwise, a cell located in the site tries to diffuse if <IT>ρ</IT> &gt; <IT>p</IT><SB>div</SB> or to divide if <IT>ρ</IT> &lt; <IT>p</IT><SB>div</SB>, where <IT>ρ</IT> (0 ≤ <IT>ρ</IT> ≤ 1) is a random number.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">In both case, one of the nn site is selected at random and if the latter site is vacant the processes are performed with the prescribed probabilities by using the rules described above.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">All the MC runs were started with a single stem cell located in the center of the clean lattice (with <IT>L</IT> = 150) at the patch formed of material 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">During the simulations, we used the reflective (no-flux) boundary conditions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">Time was measured in MC steps (MCS).</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">One MCS is defined as <IT>L</IT> × <IT>L</IT> MC trials.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">The duration of the runs was selected so that in the end there were about 3000 cells.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.">Results of simulations</HEADER><P><s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">In reality, the typical cell cycle time varies from an hour in an early embryo to about 20 h in adult stem cells.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rate of diffusion strongly depends on the cell-substrate interaction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, the ratio of the rates of these processes is expected to be in a wide range.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot3" novelty="None" advantage="None">At present, quantitative data on this subject are however scarce.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">To get a realistic value of <IT>p</IT><SB>div</SB>, we scrutinized diffusion, proliferation and differentiation of mouse neural stem cells on various substrate-coated plates<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF> (these observations were possible as a by-product of experimental studies of neural stem cells in our laboratory).</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Diffusion was observed to be relatively fast compared to division.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Specifically, it appears to be reasonable to put <IT>p</IT><SB>div</SB> = 0.01 or somewhat lower.</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In our present simulations, cell division is chosen to be two or three orders of magnitude slower compared to diffusion, <IT>i.e.</IT>, we employ <IT>p</IT><SB>div</SB> = 0.01 or 0.001.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The energetic parameters are selected so that cells of different types tend to segregate and so that this process is not too slow.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Practically, this means that the ratio of the effective cell–cell interactions and <IT>k</IT><SB>B</SB><IT>T</IT> should not be too large.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">In particular, we use <IT>ε</IT><SB><IT>ij</IT></SB><SP>nn</SP>/<IT>k</IT><SB>B</SB><IT>T</IT> = 1, <IT>ε</IT><SB>11</SB><SP>nnn</SP>/<IT>k</IT><SB>B</SB><IT>T</IT> = −1, <IT>ε</IT><SB><IT>ii</IT></SB><SP>nnn</SP>/<IT>k</IT><SB>B</SB><IT>T</IT> = −2 for <IT>i</IT> ≥ 2, and <IT>ε</IT><SB><IT>ij</IT></SB><SP>nnn</SP>/<IT>k</IT><SB>B</SB><IT>T</IT> = −1 for <IT>i</IT> ≠ <IT>j</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">For spontaneous and induced division of cells, we employ <IT>p</IT><SB>1</SB><SP>sp</SP> = 0.1, <IT>p</IT><SB>2</SB><SP>sp</SP> = <IT>p</IT><SB>3</SB><SP>sp</SP> = 1, <IT>p</IT><SB>2</SB><SP>ind</SP> = <IT>p</IT><SB>3</SB><SP>ind</SP> = 0.1, and <IT>p</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB><SP>ind</SP> = 0 for <IT>i</IT> ≥ 4.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">As a reference case, we have calculated [Figs. 1(a) and 2(a)] the cellular growth with <IT>p</IT><SB>div</SB> = 0.01 on the uniform surface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this case, the growth of cells of type 2 is rather rapid.</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the very beginning, the birth of these cells is preferable compared to that of type-3 cells due to cell–cell communication between the stem cells.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Later on, the type-2 cells surround stem cells and effectively suppress generation of cells of type 3 due to the spatial constraints (usually there are no or only a few cells of the latter type).</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Introducing heterogeneities does not change qualitatively the growth kinetics and lattice patterns [see, <IT>e.g.</IT>, the results shown in Figs. 1(b) and 2(b) for a three-strip scaffold with a narrow (two-side) central strip].</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Physically, this growth mode seems to be connected with insufficiently high rate of diffusion of cells (note that this process is partly suppressed due to attractive cell–cell interactions and spatial constraints).</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Specifically, diffusion is able to maintain a cell arrangement which is locally close to equilibrium but not able to result in global redistribution of cells.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">To increase the relative rate of cell diffusion, we have reduced <IT>p</IT><SB>div</SB> down to 0.001.</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the uniform surface or in the case of relatively wide heterogeneities [<IT>e.g.</IT>, for a three-strip scaffold with a six-site (or wider) width of the central strip], this modification has not changed the growth mode.</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In particular, as a rule, the cells of type 2 again dominate [Figs. 3(a) and 4(a)].</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the scaffolds with narrow heterogeneities [Figs. 3(b–d) and 4(b–d)], the growth kinetics and lattice patterns are however found to be qualitatively different compared to those presented earlier.</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Specifically, the increase of the relative rate of cell diffusion has resulted in effective segregation of the cells.</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Under such circumstances, the birth of cells of type 3 by cells of type 1 is not suppressed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">For this reason, the population of cells of type 3 is appreciable (the numbers of cells of types 2 and 3 are comparable).</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">For <IT>p</IT><SB>div</SB> = 0.001 this effect holds (not shown) with decreasing <IT>k</IT><SB>B</SB><IT>T</IT> and/or increasing the absolute values of the energetic parameters (if, <IT>e.g.</IT>, <IT>ε</IT><SB><IT>ij</IT></SB><SP>nnn</SP>/<IT>k</IT><SB>B</SB><IT>T</IT> = −3 for <IT>i</IT> ≥ 2).</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">With increasing <IT>k</IT><SB>B</SB><IT>T</IT> (if, <IT>e.g.</IT>, <IT>ε</IT><SB><IT>ii</IT></SB><SP>nnn</SP>/<IT>k</IT><SB>B</SB><IT>T</IT> = −1 for <IT>i</IT> ≥ 2), the cell motility increases, the rate of cell division increases as well (primarily for cells of type 2), but the driving force for segregation obviously decreases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The former two factors do not compensate the latter one, and the cells of type 2 dominate both for <IT>p</IT><SB>div</SB> = 0.01 and 0.001 (not shown), because as a rule the cells of type 1 are surrounded by cells of type 2 and the birth of cells of type 3 by cells is suppressed.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.">Conclusion</HEADER><P><s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In summary, we have illustrated that scaffolds with specially designed heterogeneities can be used as a tool for governing the growth and differentiation of stem cells.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This tool is predicted to be effective provided that the size of the heterogeneities exceeds (but not appreciably) the cellular size and the rate of cell diffusion is relatively fast compared to that of cell division.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
