<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b407174c" hasDoc="yes" version="1168" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Structure of the tripeptide model Ac–Val–Tyr(Me)–NHMe and its cluster with water investigated by IR/UV double resonance spectroscopy</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">In this paper the structures of the isolated tripeptide model Ac–Val–Tyr(Me)–NHMe (Val = valine, Tyr = tyrosine) and its cluster with water are investigated by mass-, isomer- and state-selective IR/UV double resonance spectroscopy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">From the IR spectra both in the region of the NH and CO stretching vibrations and in combination with force field and <IT>ab initio</IT> calculations it can unambiguously be derived that the peptide contains a stretched, β-sheet related structure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus the peptide serves as an ideal candidate for β-sheet model systems.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">By adding one water molecule to the peptide the β-sheet related structure seems to be preserved with a water molecule being attached to the NHMe group.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="I.">Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The conformational preferences of isolated protein building blocks, amino acids and peptides, have been subject of great interest in recent years.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Due to their flexibility peptides can occur in many different conformers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to learn something about the driving forces to form a conformer, investigations can start by applying molecular beam experiments on isolated amino acids and peptides.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The experimental discrimination between different conformers requires the use of mass-, isomer- and state-selective methods.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">If the investigated species contains an aromatic chromophore (like the common amino acids phenylalanine, tyrosine or tryptophan) R2PI (resonant 2-photon ionization) spectroscopy can be used.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">This was first done by Levy and coworkers<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2 cit3">1–3</REF> who recorded R2PI spectra of the free amino acids phenylalanine (Phe), tyrosine (Tyr) and tryptophan (Trp) as well as some di- and tripeptides.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to get information on the structure of the amino acids in the electronic grounds states (S<SB>0</SB>) vibrational frequencies of the important functional groups have to be recorded.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">IR/UV double resonance spectroscopy (IR/R2PI; see <IT>e.g</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit5 cit6 cit7 cit8 cit9 cit10 cit11 cit12 cit13">ref. 4–13</REF>). turns out to be an excellent method to investigate the IR spectra of different neutral species in their S<SB>0</SB> states.</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In combination with force field, <IT>ab initio</IT>, and density functional theory (DFT) calculations structural assignments can be derived.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The first applications of the IR/R2PI technique to the amino acids phenylalanine<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF> and tryptophan <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF> have been performed by Simons and coworkers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The IR spectra have been recorded in the region of the NH and OH stretching vibrations and several isomers have been deduced from the IR spectra containing intramolecular hydrogen bonds between the COOH and NH<SB>2</SB> group.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In a recent publication Bakker <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF>. investigated the spectral fingerprint region of tryptophan from 330 to 1500 cm<SP>−1</SP> by using a free electron laser as IR light source.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In our group the protected amino acids Ac–Phe–OMe (Ac = acetyl, Me = methyl)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11 cit12">11,12</REF> and Ac–Phe–NHMe<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF> have been investigated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In these studies not only the NH stretch region but also the region of the CO stretching and NH bending vibrations (about 1500–1800 cm<SP>−1</SP>) has been investigated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In most cases information on the CO stretching vibrations are necessary to yield an unambiguous assignment of a structural arrangement.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to open the new spectral window in the region of 1700 cm<SP>−1</SP> for the IR/R2PI spectroscopy of CO stretching vibrations a new laser system has been constructed.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12 cit15">12,15</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Zwier and coworkers investigated the protected amino acids Ac–Trp–NH<SB>2</SB> and Ac–Trp–NHMe in the region of the NH stretching vibrations by applying IR/laser induced fluorescence (LIF) spectroscopy.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Three (two) isomers of Ac–Trp–NHMe (Ac–Trp–NH<SB>2</SB>) have been observed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In order to discuss the conformational dynamics of Ac–Trp–NHMe after vibrational excitation the new hole-filling spectroscopy has been applied.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The backbones of (protected) amino acids and peptides are characterized by a set of torsional angles <IT>ϕ</IT> and <IT>ψ</IT> for each amino acid (Ramachandran plot).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18 cit19">18,19</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, the side-chain configurations are characterized by the dihedral angles <IT>χ</IT><SB>1</SB> and <IT>χ</IT><SB>2</SB>, <IT>cf.</IT> Fig. 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of a β-sheet related structure (β<SB>L</SB>) the angles <IT>ϕ</IT> and <IT>ψ</IT> fall into the region of about −180° &lt; <IT>ϕ</IT> &lt; −120° or 120° &lt; <IT>ϕ</IT> &lt; 180° and −180° &lt; <IT>ψ</IT> &lt; −120° or 120° &lt; <IT>ψ</IT> &lt; 180°, <IT>i.e.</IT> NH and CO groups of an amino acid are nearly parallel to each other.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Structures forming an intramolecular hydrogen bond between a NH and a CO group can form <IT>γ</IT><SB>L</SB> arrangements with angles <IT>ϕ</IT> and <IT>ψ</IT> of the backbone lying between: −120° &lt; <IT>ϕ</IT> &lt; 0°; 0° &lt; <IT>ψ</IT> &lt; 120°.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">A detailed description of the nomenclature with respect to the angles <IT>ϕ</IT>, <IT>ψ</IT>, <IT>χ</IT><SB>1</SB> and <IT>χ</IT><SB>2</SB> is given in .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11 cit19">refs. 11,19</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast to the unprotected amino acids the protected species (at N and C terminus) cannot form intramolecular hydrogen bonds between the polar acid (COOH) and basic (NH<SB>2</SB>) groups leading to a higher selectivity of the structures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of Ac–Phe–OMe<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11 cit12">11,12</REF> only a β-sheet related (β<SB>L</SB>) conformer has been observed as prominent isomer, whereas for Ac–Phe–NHMe<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF> four isomers are obtained with a β<SB>L</SB> structure being the most stable one.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">These protected amino acids serve both as most simple model systems to describe β-sheet related structures as well as β-sheet models.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">β-sheet models contain peptides or protected amino acids that undergo intermolecular hydrogen bonds like two amino acids in a β-sheet secondary structure.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11 cit12 cit14 cit20">11,12,14,20</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The conformational properties of amino acids depend on many different influences.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The interaction with water plays an important role in directing an amino acid or peptide into a certain conformer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to investigate the process of microsolvation the following questions have to be answered: What will happen if water is added to an isolated peptide?</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot4" novelty="None" advantage="None">What is the preferred hydrogen bonding site?</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot4" novelty="None" advantage="None">How many water molecules have to be attached to cause a conformational change?</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Clusters of amides and amino acids with water have been investigated by different molecular beam experiments,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21 cit22 cit23 cit24 cit25 cit26 cit27 cit28">21–28</REF> but no hydrated peptides have been investigated up to now.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Snoek <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25">25</REF>. have been the first to examine the hydrated clusters of a free amino acid, tryptophan, with up to three water molecules by applying IR/R2PI spectroscopy and UV/UV hole-burning spectroscopy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of the investigated unprotected amino acid the water molecules are attached to the polar end groups.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">There are some experimental studies on larger neutral peptides, like dipeptides or tripeptides.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The first IR/R2PI spectrum on a dipeptide has been published by our group choosing the Ac–Val–Phe–OMe (Val = valine) system.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29">29</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The IR spectra have been recorded both in the region of the CH and NH as well as the CO stretching modes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">In very recent publications other groups also extended their applications of IR/R2PI spectroscopy to peptides containing tryptophan and glycine<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30">30</REF> or phenylalanine and proline.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit31">31</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">It should be mentioned that UV/UV hole burning spectroscopy<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit32">32</REF> has also been applied to some dipeptides.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit33 cit34">33,34</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">These method yields no direct information on the structure of the electronic ground state, but the UV/UV-hole burning spectroscopy is an ideal tool to distinguish between different isomers especially in the case of congested R2PI spectra.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">An overview on newest developments in the field of biological molecules in the gas phase is given in .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit35">ref. 35</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">In this paper we extend our investigations on the model tripeptide Ac–Val–Tyr(Me)–NHMe (<IT>cf.</IT> Fig. 1) and its cluster with one water molecule.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Tyr(Me) represents the amino acid tyrosine with a methylated OH group in the side-chain.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">This modification is important to avoid any hydrogen bonds <IT>via</IT> a polar side-chain.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">Due to the use of a NHMe instead of an OMe protecting group, Ac–Val–Tyr(Me)–NHMe contains three amid groups and serves as model for a tripeptide.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">Since Val and Tyr contain bulky side-chains both amino acids are ideal candidates to form β-sheet related structures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The existence of β-sheet related structures is important to build up an extended β-sheet model.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="No">On the other hand the molecule gets more flexible compared to Ac–Val–Phe–OMe, <IT>i.e.</IT> the additional NH group may lead to intramolecular hydrogen-bonded (<IT>γ</IT><SB>L</SB>) structures similar to the one observed for isomers of Ac–Phe–NHMe,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF> Ac–Trp–NH<SB>2</SB>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF> and Ac–Trp–NHMe.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">In contrast to unprotected amino acids the polar NH and CO groups of Ac–Val–Tyr(Me)–NHMe are located in the backbone and not at the end of the molecule, <IT>i.e.</IT> water will be attached to the backbone of the peptide.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">In this paper we will report on the influence of the first water molecule attached to the model tripeptide Ac–Val–Tyr(Me)–NHMe.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="II.">Experimental</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>(a) Synthesis of Ac–Val–Tyr(Me)–NHMe</HEADER><P><s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">295 mg (1.00 mmol, 1.00 eq) <IT>N-tert</IT>-butyloxycarbonyl-<IT>O</IT>-methyl-(<IT>S</IT>)-tyrosine were dissolved in 5 ml of dry dichloromethane under argon and cooled to −10 °C.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">To this solution 162 mg (1.00 mmol, 1.00 eq) of <IT>N,N</IT>′-carbonyldiimidazole were added and the reaction mixture was stirred for another 2 h at −10 °C.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Subsequently, 500 μl (1.10 mmol, 1.10 eq) of a 2 M solution of methylamine in tetrahydrofuran were added.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The mixture was warmed to 0 °C and stirred for 15 min.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The excess of methylamine was removed by passing an argon gas stream through the reaction vessel for 15 min.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The organic phase was then washed three times with 3% aqueous citric acid, three times with sodium carbonate/sodium bicarbonate buffer (pH 10) and once with water, and finally dried over magnesium sulfate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">After evaporation of the solvent (membrane pump) 250 mg (810 μmol, 81%) of a colorless solid (<IT>N</IT>-<IT>tert</IT>-butyloxycarbonyl-<IT>O</IT>-methyl-(<IT>S</IT>)-tyrosine methyl amide, <IT>cf.</IT> Fig. 2a) were obtained.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">230 mg (746 μmol, 1.00 eq) <IT>N</IT>-<IT>tert</IT>-butyloxycarbonyl-<IT>O</IT>-methyl-(<IT>S</IT>)-tyrosine methyl amide (<IT>cf.</IT> Fig. 2a) were stirred in a mixture of 5 ml trifluoroacetic acid and 20 ml of dichloromethane for 2.5 h with ice cooling.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The solvent was removed in vacuum with toluene as azeotropic mixture.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">After vacuum-drying the product <IT>O</IT>-methyl-(<IT>S</IT>)-tyrosine methyl amide trifluoracetate (<IT>cf.</IT> Fig. 2b) could be isolated in quantitative yield as a ductile colorless oil.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">190 mg (1.20 mmol, 1.20 eq) of <IT>N</IT>-acetyl-(<IT>S</IT>)-valine, 494 mg (1.30 mmol, 1.30 eq) of the coupling reagent HATU, and 408 mg (3.00 mmol, 3.00 eq) of the coupling reagent HOAt, as well as 350 μl (3.00 mmol, 3.00 eq) of lutidine were dissolved under argon in a solvent mixture of dry dichloromethane/DMF (5:1) and stirred for 10 min at 0 °C.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Subsequently, a mixture of 322 mg (1.00 mmol, 1.00 eq) <IT>O</IT>-methyl-(<IT>S</IT>)-tyrosine methyl amide trifluoroacetate (<IT>cf.</IT> Fig. 2b) and 107 μl (1.00 mmol, 1.00 eq) of lutidine in little dichloromethane/DMF (5:1) were added.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reaction mixture was initially stirred with ice-cooling for 2 h.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The organic layer was extracted three times with 1 M aqueous KHSO<SB>4</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The precipitating solid was filtered off and treated separately.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The organic layer was subsequently washed three times with saturated sodiumbicarbonate and once with water and with saturated sodium chloride solution, as well as the solid.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The organic layer was dried over sodium sulfate and the solvent was completely removed at the rotatory evaporator.</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The resulting solid was combined with the previously filtered and thoroughly washed solid; the combined solids were vacuum dried, affording 158 mg (453 μmol, 45%) of the colorless solid Ac–Val–Tyr(Me)–NHMe (<IT>cf.</IT> Fig. 1).</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>(b) Experimental set-up</HEADER><P><s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The experimental set-up has been described elsewhere (<IT>cf</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11 cit12 cit36">refs. 11,12,36</REF>)..</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus only a short description is given: The R2PI and IR/R2PI spectra were measured in a vacuum system consisting of a differentially pumped linear time-of-flight mass spectrometer and a pulsed valve (General Valve Iota One, 500 μm orifice) for skimmed jet expansion (<IT>X</IT>/<IT>D</IT> = 130).</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">A frequency-doubled dye laser (Lumonics HD 300), pumped by a Nd:YAG laser (Lumonics HY 400), was used for excitation to the S<SB>1</SB> state and for ionization.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The IR light in the region of 2.63–3.08 μm (3250–3800 cm<SP>−1</SP>) was generated with a LiNbO<SB>3</SB> crystal by difference frequency mixing of the fundamental (1064 nm) of a seeded Nd:YAG laser (Spectra-Physics PRO-230) and the output of a dye laser (Sirah, Precision Scan) pumped by the second harmonic (532 nm) of the same Nd:YAG laser.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The IR output is amplified by an optical parametric amplification (in a LiNbO<SB>3</SB> crystal) of the output of the IR laser (2.63–3.08 μm) and the fundamental of the Nd:YAG laser.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit36">36</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">IR light in the region of 6 μm is generated by a third nonlinear process<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12 cit15">12,15</REF> The signal (1.79–1.82 μm, 5500–5600 cm<SP>−1</SP>) and idler (2.56–2.63 μm, 3800–3900 cm<SP>−1</SP>) of the OPA process are the inputs to a difference frequency mixing process in an AgGaSe<SB>2</SB> crystal leading to the IR light of 1600–1800 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the time delay chosen for the two lasers is not longer than 100 ns, all lasers have been spatially overlapped.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to obtain IR/R2PI spectra the IR laser is fired 60 ns prior to the UV laser.</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The substance (Ac–Val–Tyr(Me)–NHMe) and the valve are heated to 150 °C.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Helium was used as carrier gas (2000 mbar).</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="III.">Results and discussion</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>(a) Structure of Ac–Val–Tyr(Me)–NHMe</HEADER><P><s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The IR/R2PI spectrum of Ac–Val–Tyr(Me)–NHMe in the range of 1600–1800 and 3300–3600 cm<SP>−1</SP> is depicted in Fig. 3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The spectrum has been recorded <IT>via</IT> the electronic origin of the S<SB>1</SB> ← S<SB>0</SB> transition at 35 434 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">No further prominent transitions can be observed in the R2PI spectrum from 35 200 to 35 900 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the region of the NH stretching modes of the IR/R2PI spectrum three vibrational transitions are observed at 3411, 3440 and 3477 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">All vibrations are located above 3400 cm<SP>−1</SP> which strongly indicates that a linear β-sheet related structure and no intramolecular hydrogen bonds are formed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The frequencies of hydrogen-bonded NH stretching modes are typically located below 3400 cm<SP>−1</SP>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11 cit14 cit16">11,14,16</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The NH stretching frequency at 3440 cm<SP>−1</SP> is very close to the value of the NH stretching mode of Val at 3441 cm<SP>−1</SP> in the spectrum of Ac–Val–Phe–OMe<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29">29</REF> and can therefore be assigned to the NH stretching mode of the valine moiety.</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The identity of the observed frequencies is not surprising, since the structural arrangements in the linear conformers of Ac–Val–Phe–OMe and Ac–Val–Tyr(Me)–NHMe should be nearly identical.</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">According to the results on Ac–Phe–NHMe<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF> and Ac–Trp–NHMe<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF> it is known that the NH stretching vibration of the NHMe protecting group is located around 3470 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore the transition at 3477 cm<SP>−1</SP> is assigned to the N<SB>3</SB>–H<SB>3</SB> (<IT>cf.</IT> Fig. 1) vibration of Ac–Val–Tyr(Me)–NHMe.</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus the remaining transition at 3411 cm<SP>−1</SP> has to be correlated with the N–H vibration of the tyrosine moiety.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Unfortunately the protected amino acid Ac–Tyr(Me)–NHMe has not been investigated up to now.</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus a direct comparison of the NH stretching frequency of the tyrosine moiety in Ac–Val–Tyr(Me)–NHMe with the one in Ac–Tyr(Me)–NHMe is not possible but the observations obtained from other protected amino acids and peptides explain the relative low frequency of 3411 cm<SP>−1</SP> (compared to the value of 3451 cm<SP>−1</SP> of the Phe residue in Ac–Val–Phe–OMe<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29">29</REF>): By comparing the IR spectra of the protected amino acids Ac–Phe–OMe<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF> and Ac–Phe–NHMe<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF> as well as Ac–Trp–OMe<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit37">37</REF> and Ac–Trp–NHMe<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF> strong red-shifts (20 and 25 cm<SP>−1</SP>) of the NH stretching frequency of the Phe and Trp residues are observed resulting from the change of the OMe to NHMe protecting groups.</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">By going from the protected amino acid Ac–Phe–OMe to the protected dipeptide Ac–Val–Phe–OMe an additional small red shift (7 cm<SP>−1</SP>) of the (Phe) NH stretching mode is observed, <IT>i.e.</IT> both the choice of a NHMe protecting group and the extension of the backbone (from a protected amino acid to a tripeptide model) leads to a red-shift of the NH stretching frequency of the tyrosine residue.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The assignment to a linear β-sheet related structure is further supported by vibrational frequencies obtained for the CO groups of Ac–Val–Tyr(Me)–NHMe.</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The IR/R2PI spectrum exhibits three transitions at 1694, 1700, and 1715 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The transition at 1715 cm<SP>−1</SP> is in good agreement with frequencies of the C<SB>1</SB>O<SB>1</SB> (acetyl) group (<IT>cf.</IT> Fig. 1) observed for Ac–Val–Phe–OMe (1711 cm<SP>−1</SP>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29">29</REF>)</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, the value of 1694 cm<SP>−1</SP> is nearly identical to the frequency observed for the corresponding valine residue of Ac–Val–Phe–OMe (1696 cm<SP>−1</SP>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29">29</REF>)</annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus the vibration at 1694 cm<SP>−1</SP> can easily be assigned to the stretching vibration of the C<SB>2</SB>O<SB>2</SB> group of Ac–Val–Tyr(Me)–NHMe.</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Finally the remaining transition at 1700 cm<SP>−1</SP> has to be correlated with the C<SB>3</SB>O<SB>3</SB> stretching mode (<IT>cf.</IT> Fig. 1) of the Tyr residue.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In order to support the vibrational assignments force field, <IT>ab initio</IT> (Hartree–Fock, HF) and DFT (B3LYP functional) calculations have been performed using the Discover<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit38">38</REF> and Gaussian 98<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit39">39</REF> programs.</annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">To generate starting geometries for <IT>ab initio</IT> calculations, a preselection <IT>via</IT> molecular dynamics using the CFF force field<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit38 cit40 cit41 cit42 cit43">38,40–43</REF> has been done.</annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Molecular dynamics have been performed at a temperature of 750 K and with a time step of 1 fs.</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">After 1000 steps the structure has been minimized.</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">This structure has been used to continue the dynamics in the same manner.</annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The following minimized structure has been compared to the first <IT>via</IT> its relative energy to discriminate between different minima.</annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">With this technique 30,000 structures have been minimized and compared to each other.</annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The dynamics have been repeated several times to explore the PES.</annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The preselection using the CFF force field shows that β-sheet related structures turn out to be the most stable conformers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is in agreement with the analysis of the IR spectra indicating to β-sheet related structures, which can differ in their side-chain arrangements.</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">In a general overview on several peptides and clusters<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit44">44</REF> we will show that the class II force field CFF can be taken for the interpretation of “high resolution” IR spectra of isolated species.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Due to the size of the system and in order to compare the results with earlier studies, we have chosen the 3-21G(d) basis set for the subsequent HF calculations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">All structures with β-sheet related backbone arrangements have been fully optimized and the relative energies have been corrected by the zero point energies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The calculated frequencies have been scaled with factors derived from our investigations on Ac–Phe–OMe (0.9076 for the NH vibrations and 0.9140 for the CO stretching modes.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF>)</annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The most stable isomer has a β<SP>V</SP>(g−)–β<SP>T</SP>(a) (superscripts: V = valine, T = tyrosine) arrangement (<IT>cf.</IT> Fig. 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The torsional angles characterizing the backbone and side-chain conformations have the following values: <IT>ϕ</IT><SP>V</SP>(C<SB>1</SB>–N<SB>1</SB>–CVα–C<SB>2</SB>) = −140°, <IT>ψ</IT><SP>V</SP>(N<SB>1</SB>–CVα–C<SB>2</SB>–N<SB>2</SB>) = 164°, <IT>χ</IT>V1(N<SB>1</SB>–CVα–CVβ–CVγ) = −68°, <IT>ϕ</IT><SP>T</SP>(C<SB>2</SB>–N<SB>2</SB>–CTα–C<SB>3</SB>) = −166°, <IT>ψ</IT><SP>T</SP>(N<SB>2</SB>–CTα–C<SB>3</SB>–N<SB>3</SB>) = 173°, <IT>χ</IT>T1(N<SB>2</SB>–CTα–CTβ–CTγ) = −147°.</annotationART></s> <s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">It has to be mentioned that two structures of all β<SP>V</SP>–β<SP>T</SP> conformers have to be discussed which only differ by the orientation of the OMe group in the tyrosine side-chain.</annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">If the angle <IT>χ</IT>T2 (<IT>cf.</IT> Fig. 1) has a positive (negative) value the structure is characterized by a+(−) sign.</annotationART></s> <s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">All ± structures of a given conformer have nearly identical energies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The structure shown in Fig. 1 is a β<SP>V</SP>(g−)–β<SP>T</SP>(a)<SP>+</SP> arrangement with a torsional angle of <IT>χ</IT>T2 (<IT>C</IT>Tα–CTβ–CTγ–CTδ) = 68°.</annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac20" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the β<SP>V</SP>(g−)–β<SP>T</SP>(a)<SP>−</SP> structure the OMe group would be rotated about the C–O axis by 180°.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The values <IT>ϕ</IT> and <IT>ψ</IT> of the β<SP>V</SP>(g−)–β<SP>T</SP>(a)<SP>±</SP> structures deviate not more than 7° from the values obtained for the minimum energy structure of Ac–Val–Phe–OMe.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29">29</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">There are two different structural arrangements (β<SP>V</SP>(g+)–β<SP>T</SP>(a)<SP>±</SP>; β<SP>V</SP>(a)–β<SP>T</SP>(a)<SP>±</SP>) which are close in energy to the most stable structure of Ac–Val–Tyr(Me)–NHMe, <IT>i.e.</IT> the energy difference between the structures is about 100 cm<SP>−1</SP> including zero point energy corrections.</annotationART></s> <s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The calculation of relative energies cannot be satisfactory at the HF/3-21G(d) level of theory and more sophisticated theoretical applications have to be performed in order to define the global minimum energy structure of Ac–Val–Tyr(Me)–NHMe.</annotationART></s> <s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">In contrast to the relative energies the scaled frequencies obtained from calculations at the HF/3-21G(d) level of theory are often in good agreement with the experimental values which is a result of a cancellation of errors.</annotationART></s> <s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The vibrational frequencies obtained for the β<SP>V</SP>(g−)–β<SP>T</SP>(a)<SP>+</SP> structure are listed in Table 1 yielding a reasonable agreement to the experimentally observed frequencies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Additionally HF calculations using the 6-31G(d,p) basis and DFT calculations (B3LYP functional, 6-31+G(d) basis set) have been performed for the β<SP>V</SP>(g−)–β<SP>T</SP>(a)<SP>+</SP> structure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The following dihedral angles of the backbone structure are obtained from the HF/6-31G(d,p) (B3LYP/6-31+G(d)) calculations: <IT>ϕ</IT><SP>V</SP> = −129° (−130°), <IT>ψ</IT><SP>V</SP> = 160° (161°), <IT>χ</IT>V1 = −63° (−62°), <IT>ϕ</IT><SP>T</SP> = −157° (−157°), <IT>ψ</IT><SP>T</SP> = 172° (160°), <IT>χ</IT>T1 = −169° (−167°), <IT>χ</IT>T2 = 74° (70°).</annotationART></s> <s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The resulting vibrational frequencies are also listed in Table 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The frequencies obtained from the DFT calculations strongly support our vibrational assignments.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>(b) Structure of Ac–Val–Tyr(Me)–NHMe(H<SB>2</SB>O)<SB>1</SB></HEADER><P><s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The IR/R2PI spectrum of Ac–Val–Tyr(Me)–NHMe(H<SB>2</SB>O)<SB>1</SB> in the spectral region from 3250 to 3800 cm<SP>−1</SP> is shown in Fig. 4.</annotationART></s> <s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The spectrum has been recorded <IT>via</IT> the electronic origin of the S<SB>1</SB> ← S<SB>0</SB> transition at 35636 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In order to get an interpretation of the spectrum the experimentally observed NH stretching frequencies are compared with the one of the Ac–Val–Tyr(Me)–NHMe monomer; in addition the OH stretching frequencies of the water moiety have to be discussed.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">A water molecule can be attached as hydrogen acceptor (by forming an N–H⋯O bond) or as hydrogen donor (by forming an CO⋯H bond).</annotationART></s> <s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">These arrangements lead to significantly different OH stretching frequencies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac21" novelty="None" advantage="None">In case of a CO⋯H hydrogen donor bond an OH donor stretching frequency in the region of about 3450–3600 cm<SP>−1</SP> would be expected, <IT>e.g.</IT> in <IT>trans</IT>-<IT>N</IT>-phenylformamide(H<SB>2</SB>O)<SB>1</SB><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF> or <IT>trans</IT>-<IT>N</IT>-benzylformamide<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF> the vibrations are located at 3536 and 3525 cm<SP>−1</SP>, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac22" novelty="None" advantage="None">Similar results are obtained in investigations on other hydrated clusters with aromatic chromophores<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit45">45</REF> or in our investigations on Ac–Phe–OMe(H<SB>2</SB>O)<SB>1</SB>, a hydrated cluster of a protected amino acid with water.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit46">46</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="143"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac22" novelty="None" advantage="None">In Ac–Phe–OMe(H<SB>2</SB>O)<SB>1</SB> two isomers are discussed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="144"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac22" novelty="None" advantage="None">The first one contains a CO⋯H donor bond and in the second one a water molecule forms a bridge between a N–H (hydrogen bond acceptor) and a CO group (hydrogen bond donor).</annotationART></s> <s sid="145"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac22" novelty="None" advantage="None">Also for the second isomer containing a combined donor/acceptor binding motif the OH stretching frequency is significantly below 3600 cm<SP>−1</SP> (at 3575 cm<SP>−1</SP>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit46">46</REF>)</annotationART></s> <s sid="146"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">If water acts as proton donor the remaining free OH stretching mode would be expected around 3720 cm<SP>−1</SP> (<IT>cf. e.g</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6 cit8 cit45 cit47">refs. 6,8,45,47</REF>)..</annotationART></s> <s sid="147"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The experimental spectrum shows two transitions in the OH stretching region at 3635 and 3718 cm<SP>−1</SP> (<IT>cf.</IT> Fig. 4).</annotationART></s> <s sid="148"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The value observed for the free OH stretching mode is in very good agreement with the value expected for a donor bonded H<SB>2</SB>O molecule but no transition can be observed between 3450 and 3600 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="149"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus no OH stretching donor vibration can be assigned.</annotationART></s> <s sid="150"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the other hand the transition at 3635 cm<SP>−1</SP> is only shifted by −22 cm<SP>−1</SP> with respect to the free symmetric vibration of isolated water<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit48 cit49">48,49</REF> strongly indicating that water cannot act as a donor.</annotationART></s> <s sid="151"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac23" novelty="None" advantage="None">If the water molecules acts as proton acceptor like in indole(H<SB>2</SB>O)<SB>1</SB>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit50">50</REF> phenol(H<SB>2</SB>O)<SB>1</SB><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF> or <IT>N</IT>-phenylformamide(H<SB>2</SB>O)<SB>1</SB><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF> a frequency of about 3650 cm<SP>−1</SP> is obtained for the symmetric OH stretching mode.</annotationART></s> <s sid="152"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac23" novelty="None" advantage="None">In some cases this value can also shift to frequencies of about 3635 cm<SP>−1</SP>, <IT>e.g.</IT> in the π-bonded fluorene(H<SB>2</SB>O)<SB>1</SB> cluster (3632 cm<SP>−1</SP>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit51">51</REF>)</annotationART></s> <s sid="153"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is interesting to note that a π-interaction can also be discussed for the Ac–Val–Tyr(Me)–NHMe(H<SB>2</SB>O)<SB>1</SB> cluster (see below).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="154"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac24" novelty="None" advantage="None">Concerning the asymmetric OH stretching vibration its frequency is often located at about 3745 cm<SP>−1</SP>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6 cit8 cit50">6,8,50</REF><IT>i.e.</IT> a few wavenumbers lower than the corresponding frequency of the free water molecule at 3756 cm<SP>−1</SP>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit48 cit49">48,49</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="155"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac25" novelty="None" advantage="None">But there are also some acceptor bound species which show a much stronger shift down to about 3710 cm<SP>−1</SP>, <IT>cf. e.g.</IT> 2-naphthyl-1-ethanol(H<SB>2</SB>O)<SB>2</SB> with an asymmetric OH stretching vibration of the acceptor water at 3708 cm<SP>−1</SP>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit52">52</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="156"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac25" novelty="None" advantage="None">This water molecule also undergoes a π-interaction with the aromatic chromophore.</annotationART></s> <s sid="157"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac26" novelty="None" advantage="None">Additionally the π-bonded fluorene(H<SB>2</SB>O)<SB>1</SB><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit51">51</REF> is an example which shows a shift of the asymmetric OH stretching mode to 3719 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="158"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, it is interesting that the splitting of symmetric (<IT>ν</IT><SB>1</SB>) and asymmetric (<IT>ν</IT><SB>3</SB>) OH stretching mode in Ac–Val–Tyr(Me)–NHMe(H<SB>2</SB>O)<SB>1</SB> is only 83 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="159"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">This value is lower than the corresponding difference of an isolated water molecule (99 cm<SP>−1</SP><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit48 cit49">48,49</REF>) or other acceptor bound clusters<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6 cit8 cit45 cit50">6,8,45,50</REF>, but a similar low splitting has also been observed for the water dimer (about 85 cm<SP>−1</SP><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit53">53</REF>) and for the fluorene(H<SB>2</SB>O)<SB>1</SB> cluster (87 cm<SP>−1</SP>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit51">51</REF>)</annotationART></s> <s sid="160"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">It should be noted that our <IT>ab initio</IT> calculations performed at the HF/6-31G(d,p) level of theory (see below) predict a splitting of 87 cm<SP>−1</SP>, if the difference is scaled to the corresponding value obtained for the free water molecule calculated at the same level of theory, <IT>i.e.</IT> the <IT>ν</IT><SB>1</SB>/<IT>ν</IT><SB>3</SB> splitting is significantly reduced in the complex of Ac–Val–Tyr(Me)–NHMe with water.</annotationART></s> <s sid="161"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is in agreement with the experimental result.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="162"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">According to the discussion of the OH stretching vibrations it can be assumed that the water molecule undergoes a hydrogen acceptor bond, <IT>i.e.</IT> water is attached to one of the three NH groups and forms a N–H⋯O hydrogen bond.</annotationART></s> <s sid="163"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In order to find out which NH group is hydrogen-bonded the remaining transitions at 3393, 3418 and 3435 cm<SP>−1</SP> (<IT>cf.</IT> Fig. 4) are compared with the NH stretching frequencies of the Ac–Val–Tyr(Me)–NHMe monomer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="164"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is obvious that the bands at 3435 and 3418 cm<SP>−1</SP> show only small shifts (−5 and +7 cm<SP>−1</SP>) with respect to the corresponding transitions of the monomer (3440 and 3411 cm<SP>−1</SP>) and are therefore assigned to free NH stretching modes of the valine and tyrosine residues.</annotationART></s> <s sid="165"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since no transition is observed in the region from 3435 to 3635 cm<SP>−1</SP>, the free NH stretching vibration of the N<SB>3</SB>–H<SB>3</SB> group (located at 3477 cm<SP>−1</SP> in the monomer) can definitely not be observed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="166"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This leads to the conclusion that the water molecule is hydrogen-bonded to the N<SB>3</SB>–H<SB>3</SB> group of the NHMe protecting group (<IT>cf.</IT> Fig. 1), yielding a broader N–H stretching transition at 3393 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="167"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The experimentally observed shift (84 cm<SP>−1</SP>) of the N<SB>3</SB>–H<SB>3</SB> stretching vibration between monomer and cluster is in agreement with the value obtained for the <IT>N</IT>-phenylformamide cluster.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="168"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">It can be concluded that the IR/R2PI spectrum of Ac–Val–Tyr(Me)–NHMe(H<SB>2</SB>O)<SB>1</SB> can be interpreted by predicting a structure which contains a water molecule undergoing a N<SB>3</SB>–H<SB>3</SB>⋯O acceptor bond.</annotationART></s> <s sid="169"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">As mentioned above the NH stretching frequencies of the Val and Tyr residues are very close to their corresponding values in the monomer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="170"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus it is very likely to assume that the conformation of the backbone has not changed significantly.</annotationART></s> <s sid="171"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None"><IT>Ab initio</IT> calculations at the HF level of theory are performed using the same basis sets (3-21G(d) and 6-31G(d,p)) as for the monomer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="172"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">According to the experimental results a β-sheet related structure with water attached to the N<SB>3</SB>–H<SB>3</SB> group has been used as starting geometry.</annotationART></s> <s sid="173"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Subsequently, structures including all possible side-chain configurations have been optimized at the HF/3-21G(d) level of theory.</annotationART></s> <s sid="174"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">As in the monomer a β<SP>V</SP>(g−)–β<SP>T</SP>(a) conformer turns out to be the most stable structure (<IT>cf.</IT> Fig. 5).</annotationART></s> <s sid="175"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus this β<SP>V</SP>(g−)–β<SP>T</SP>(a) structure has been further optimized at the HF/6-31G(d,p) level yielding a complex with an almost linear intermolecular hydrogen bond, <IT>i.e.</IT> the angle between N<SB>3</SB>, H<SB>3</SB> (<IT>cf.</IT> Fig. 1) and the oxygen atom of the water molecule is 174°, the N<SB>3</SB>–H<SB>3</SB>⋯OH<SB>2</SB> bond length is 2.04 Å.</annotationART></s> <s sid="176"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">One hydrogen atom of the water molecule lies above the center of the aromatic ring (Tyr residue, <IT>cf.</IT> Fig. 5).</annotationART></s> <s sid="177"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">This π-interaction may lead to an additional stabilization of this structure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="178"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The torsional angles of backbone and side-chain of the Val moiety have identical values with respect to the monomer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="179"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Due to the influence of the attached water at the NHMe group, the torsional angles of the Tyr residue show a small shift (2° for <IT>ϕ</IT><SP>T</SP>, 16° for <IT>ψ</IT><SP>T</SP> and 0° for <IT>χ</IT>T1), but the β<SB>L</SB>-arrangement is still conserved.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="180"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The frequencies calculated for the NH stretching vibrations of the N<SB>3</SB>–H<SB>3</SB> group as well as the Tyr and Val moieties (3400, 3440 and 3441 cm<SP>−1</SP>) are in agreement with the experimental frequencies (3393, 3418 and 3435 cm<SP>−1</SP>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="181"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The calculated frequencies have been scaled with the same factor as the one obtained for the monomer at the same level of theory.</annotationART></s> <s sid="182"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, a stabilization energy of 1288 cm<SP>−1</SP> (15.4 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>) is obtained for the cluster at the HF/6-31G(d,p) level including BSSE corrections<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit54">54</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="IV.">Conclusion</HEADER><P><s sid="183"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">The tripeptide model Ac–Val–Tyr(Me)–NHMe is an extended molecule that is flexible enough to form several structural conformers, both stretched (β-sheet related) and intramolecular hydrogen-bonded arrangements.</annotationART></s> <s sid="184"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">From our spectroscopic investigations a β-sheet related arrangement can be derived.</annotationART></s> <s sid="185"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This result indicates a high selectivity with respect to β-sheet related structures if appropriate amino acids are chosen.</annotationART></s> <s sid="186"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">According to these results Ac–Val–Tyr(Me)–NHMe is a good candidate for β-sheet model systems, <IT>i.e.</IT> intermolecular hydrogen-bonded cluster with other peptides can be formed leading to a structural configuration similar to the one observed between peptides in an extended β-sheet.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="187"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is interesting to note that the monomer seems only slightly influenced by the addition of one water molecule.</annotationART></s> <s sid="188"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Water forms an almost linear hydrogen bond to the NH group of NHMe which is the strongest donor of the molecule.</annotationART></s> <s sid="189"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">It will be a further question, whether the addition of more water molecules will change the backbone configuration of the peptide.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
