<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b409840d" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Resolution of ultrafast excited state kinetics of bilirubin in chloroform and bound to human serum albumin</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The <IT>Z</IT>–<IT>E</IT>-isomerisation of bilirubin upon excitation with visible light is a fundamental step in phototherapy of newborns with neonatal jaundice.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Here we report results of an ultrafast optical spectroscopy study of bilirubin in CHCl<SB>3</SB> as well as bound to human serum albumin.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The data show that the initially excited singlet state has sub-ps decay times with major amplitude.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Transient absorption measurements reveal that the ultrafast decay of the emission is accompanied by the formation of a transient intermediate which decays on the 15–20 ps timescale.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The initial photoprocesses are thus considerably faster than the previously reported fastest lifetimes for bilirubin and this is, to our knowledge, the first time that the earliest processes in excited bilirubin have been resolved.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER /><P><s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Bilirubin-IXα (BR, see Fig. 1 for the structure) is a yellow-orange, neurotoxic substance formed in mammals by the catabolism of haem.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is an open-chain tetrapyrrole consisting of two nearly identical dipyrrinone chromophores with propionic acid side-chains located at C-8 and C-.12<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The publication of the crystallographic structure in 1976 confirmed previous predictions that 4<IT>Z</IT>,15<IT>Z</IT>-BR adopts a three-dimensional ridge-tile shape stabilised by a network of six intramolecular hydrogen bonds between the carboxyl groups and the lactam and pyrrole moieties of the opposite dipyrrinone unit.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">2</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This folded conformation is retained in chloroform,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF> and even to a large extent in strongly polar solvents like DMSO and aqueous buffer.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit5">4,5</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The persistence of hydrogen bonding, internally neutralising all the polar groups, is most likely the reason why BR is essentially insoluble in water at physiological pH and therefore intrinsically unexcretable.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the normal clearance pathway, BR is transported through the bloodstream to the liver in the form of an association complex with serum albumin and excretion is facilitated through hepatic conjugation to glucuronic acid by bilirubin uridine-5′-diphosphate glucuronosyltransferase.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the levels of this enzyme are initially low in newborn infants and unconjugated BR accumulates in the blood.</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">This often leads to a characteristic yellowing of the skin and sclera of the eye, a condition known as neonatal jaundice.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the late 1960s phototherapy with white or blue light has emerged as an effective and widely used method to lower abnormally high BR levels in jaundiced infants.</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Consequently, the determination of the principal mechanism(s) responsible for its success has been the focus of numerous investigations.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6 cit7">6,7</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is currently believed that phototherapy enhances the excretion of unconjugated BR in bile and urine primarily through the formation of more polar configurational and structural photoisomers of BR.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Some photooxidation and destruction of the chromophore also occurs, but these processes are slow and do not make a major contribution.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Configurational photoisomerisation around one of the two exocyclic double bonds to give the 4<IT>E</IT>,15<IT>Z</IT> or 4<IT>Z</IT>,15<IT>E</IT> isomers is the most efficient photochemical reaction of BR in organic solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, these methanol-soluble <IT>E</IT>-isomers are relatively unstable because one set of hydrogen bonds (Fig. 1) is broken upon <IT>Z</IT> → <IT>E</IT> isomerisation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Reversion to the 4<IT>Z</IT>,15<IT>Z</IT> configuration occurs thermally or photochemically and during irradiation a photoequilibrium is rapidly reached because these three isomeric forms have extensively overlapping absorption spectra.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Upon prolonged photolysis, the formation of lumirubin, a more stable (irreversibly cyclised) structural isomer of BR, also becomes a significant process.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Interestingly, both types of photoisomerisation process are enhanced when BR is bound to the high affinity site of human serum albumin (HSA).</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Moreover, the <IT>Z</IT> → <IT>E</IT> isomerisation occurs regioselectively and 4<IT>Z</IT>,15<IT>E</IT>-BR is formed almost exclusively with blue-light excitation.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9 cit10">9,10</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">A complicating factor in the study of the photochemistry of BR is the unusual wavelength dependence of the reactions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The quantum yield of the 4<IT>Z</IT>,15<IT>E</IT> isomer of BR bound to HSA decreases from 0.11 at 457.9 nm to 0.054 at 514.5 nm.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Conversely, the quantum yield of lumirubin formation increases<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF> in an approximately inverse fashion to a maximum of 0.002 at 514.5 nm.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, the isomeric ratio 4<IT>E</IT>,15<IT>Z</IT>: 4<IT>Z</IT>,15<IT>E</IT> of HSA-bound BR increases ten-fold over the same wavelength range.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Of particular significance is the observation of a modest decline in the quantum yield of 4<IT>Z</IT>,15<IT>E</IT>-BR with increasing wavelength in ammoniacal methanol solution, suggesting the complex behaviour of BR is, at least partly, an inherent property of the molecule.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The origin of these effects has been attributed to exciton coupling of the excited singlet states of the two dipyrrinone chromophores and to the extent of localisation of the excitation energy on the lower-lying C-15 bridged dipyrrinone.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15 cit16">15,16</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">A dipole–dipole interaction energy (Δ<IT>E</IT><SB><IT>ij</IT></SB>) of <IT>ca.</IT> 1000 cm<SP>−1</SP> has been calculated from the structure, assuming point dipoles and two identical chromophores,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF> in fair agreement with the splitting energies (2Δ<IT>E</IT><SB><IT>ij</IT></SB>) used to simulate the absorption and circular dichroism spectra.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17 cit18">17,18</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Photophysical measurements of excited BR in solution at room temperature indicate that radiationless decay to the ground state is the dominant deactivation pathway, since the quantum yields of fluorescence (<IT>ϕ</IT><SB>f</SB> &lt; 0.0002),<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF> intersystem crossing to the triplet state (<IT>ϕ</IT><SB>isc</SB> ≤ 0.01),<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19">19</REF> and photoisomerisation (<IT>ϕ</IT><SB><IT>ZE</IT></SB> + <IT>ϕ</IT><SB><IT>EZ</IT></SB> ≤ 0.035)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF> are all very small.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fluorescence yield of BR is, however, enhanced on binding to HSA (<IT>ϕ</IT><SB>f</SB> = 0.003) and there is a further dramatic increase (<IT>ϕ</IT><SB>f</SB> = 0.92) upon lowering the temperature to 77 K as a result of the increased environmental rigidity.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is therefore surprising that the lifetime of the lowest excited singlet state of BR determined by picosecond transient absorption is practically the same in CHCl<SB>3</SB> (17 ± 3 ps) and bound to HSA (19 ± 3 ps) at room temperature,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF> although a somewhat longer fluorescence lifetime was reported for HSA-bound BR using photon-counting methods.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Nevertheless, the assignment of the transient absorption spectra to the singlet state appears to be supported by the 14 ± 2 ps fluorescence lifetime measured in CHCl<SB>3</SB>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF> and the 18 ± 3 ps decay time for HSA-bound BR obtained using a streak camera.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Two important conclusions that were drawn from these and other measurements are (1) that the excited singlet state decays rapidly, with near unity efficiency, to a very short-lived twisted intermediate state from which decay back to the ground state configuration is much more favourable than conversion to the photoisomer and (2) the radiative rate of BR must increase by more than an order of magnitude on binding to HSA.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">To determine if these conclusions are valid, we have reinvestigated the early photoprocesses of BR in chloroform solution and bound to HSA using femtosecond transient absorption and fluorescence techniques.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fluorescence decays were recorded with magic-angle polarisation at room temperature using the fluorescence upconversion technique and a spectrometer that has been previously described.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22 cit23">22,23</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Bilirubin (for biochemistry, Merck) and HSA (essentially fatty acid and globulin free, Fluka) were used as received and stock solutions were prepared fresh in dim light conditions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The solutions were held in a rotating cell with a 0.5 mm path length and were changed regularly, because prolonged irradiation led to broadening in the absorption spectrum, photodegradation, and formation of biliverdin (in CHCl<SB>3</SB>).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, the energy of the excitation pulses were intentionally kept low (∼0.1 nJ) and the initial and final scans were checked to ensure that the kinetics had remained constant.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The normalised steady state absorption and fluorescence spectra of BR in CHCl<SB>3</SB> and bound to HSA in a 1∶1 stoichiometry are shown in Fig. 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The absorption spectrum of HSA-bound BR is noticeably broader than in CHCl<SB>3</SB>, but the maximum is shifted only 1–2 nm to the red.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Consequently, an excitation wavelength of 454 nm, corresponding to the absorption maximum of BR in CHCl<SB>3</SB>, was chosen for the measurements.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">There is a larger red shift of <IT>ca.</IT> 10 nm in the fluorescence maximum of HSA-bound BR (520 nm).</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fluorescence decay kinetics recorded at 525 nm with variable time steps (from 10 fs up to 1 ps), to enable improved coverage of the different time ranges, are presented in Fig. 3.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The decay of the BR fluorescence is clearly very fast and it is not single-exponential.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The intensity of the emission from HSA-bound BR falls to half the maximum value in approximately one picosecond and it decays considerably faster in CHCl<SB>3</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">No difference in the fluorescence decay could be detected using a sample of chloroform treated with KOH, compared to the untreated solvent.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Lifetimes obtained by multiexponential least squares fitting, using a response function of 150–170 fs, are given in Table 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Four or five reasonably well-separated lifetime components were required to obtain good agreement between the fitted and measured data.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The lifetimes and amplitudes of the major components (those with &gt;10% amplitude) are believed to be accurate within 15%, as judged by comparing results from independent measurements, as well as the quality of fits after fixing one of the major lifetime components at different values.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The two sub-picosecond lifetime components account for the major part of the amplitude in both cases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Evidently, the decay of the BR fluorescence is more complex and occurs on a substantially faster timescale than previously reported using the time-correlated single-photon counting technique.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">A short singlet state lifetime is in fact expected from the extremely low quantum yield of fluorescence in chloroform (<IT>ϕ</IT><SB>f</SB> &lt; 0.0002).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The oscillator strength determined by integrating the visible absorption spectrum of BR and using the manufacturer’s absorption coefficient of <IT>ε</IT><SB>max</SB> = 60 200 M<SP>−1</SP> cm<SP>−1</SP>, is <IT>ca.</IT> 1.1 and the calculated<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25">25</REF> radiative lifetime is <IT>τ</IT><SB>0</SB> ≈ 1.4 ns.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, the singlet state lifetime of BR is estimated to be &lt;280 fs.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This calculation does not take into account that there are two dipyrrinone chromophores contributing to the absorption transition.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, even a doubling of the estimated lifetime does not reconcile this sub-picosecond lifetime with those lifetimes reported earlier.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15 cit20 cit21">15,20,21</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The calculated value is, however, in reasonable agreement with the weighted average of the two shortest lifetimes reported here.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The notably slower overall decay observed for BR bound to HSA is consistent with the more than ten-times enhancement in the fluorescence quantum yield of HSA-bound BR (<IT>ϕ</IT><SB>f</SB> = 0.003), compared to chloroform solution (<IT>ϕ</IT><SB>f</SB> &lt; 0.0002),<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF> and thus it is not necessary to invoke a dramatically different radiative rate in HSA.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">From the inset of Fig. 3, showing the normalised fluorescence decay on a longer time scale, it is apparent that the (smaller amplitude) medium and longer lifetime components are the major contributors to the steady state fluorescence of BR bound to HSA.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The situation is reversed in CHCl<SB>3</SB>, where the major part of the area under the decay curve is located within the first few picoseconds after excitation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The slowing of the decay kinetics upon binding to HSA is attributed to steric hindrance, but there can be no major barrier to twisting, as the fluorescence quantum yield remains low and photoisomerisation is more efficient than in organic solvents.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Further evidence that the initial excited state processes of bilirubin occur on an ultrafast timescale is provided by femtosecond transient absorption experiments, which were performed using a 5 kHz Ti∶sapphire regenerative amplifier and optical parametric amplifier (Spectra Physics).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">BR in CHCl<SB>3</SB> was circulated continuously through a 1 mm pathlength flow cell, at a flow rate sufficient to ensure a stable signal intensity, by means of a peristaltic pump.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The polarisation of the pump beam was set at the magic angle with respect to the probe beam and the response function was <IT>ca.</IT> 200 fs.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 4 shows time-resolved absorption difference spectra of BR in CHCl<SB>3</SB> at different times ranging from <IT>ca.</IT> 50 fs to 25 ps after 454 nm excitation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Immediately after excitation a negative signal (<IT>i.e.</IT> a decrease in absorption) appears at wavelengths shorter than 490 nm (marked (a) in Fig. 4).</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the ground state of BR absorbs in this region (see Fig. 2), this signal can be assigned to ground state bleaching.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">A second negative absorption signal is also apparent between <IT>ca.</IT> 525 and 625 nm at ∼50 and 250 fs after excitation and this signal (marked (b) in Fig. 4) is attributed to stimulated emission.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although this signal occurs in the same region as the steady state emission of BR (Fig. 2), the negative signal at 50 fs has a maximum at a longer wavelength and, moreover, it moves further to the red by 250 fs.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Overlapping the stimulated emission is an excited state absorption, which is apparent as a positive signal between <IT>ca.</IT> 490 and 520 nm in the ∼50 fs spectrum.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">By 450 fs the positive absorption signal (marked (c) in Fig. 4) extends beyond 650 nm and, concommitant with the disappearance of the stimulated emission signal, continues to rise reaching a maximum by 2 ps, before decaying on a 15–20 ps timescale.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The time-resolved spectra that we measured at longer delay times (2 ps and longer) are in agreement with the picosecond absorption spectra of Greene <IT>et al</IT>.,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF> showing both negative absorption (bleach) at wavelengths shorter than <IT>ca.</IT> 490 nm and positive absorption at longer wavelengths.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the stimulated emission signal was not observed in this earlier pioneering work and the positive transient absorption signal was assigned to the singlet state, rather than to formation of a transient intermediate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, it is not the excited singlet state of BR that has the same lifetime bound to HSA and dissolved in chloroform, but the twisted intermediate state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">A more detailed study of the time-resolved absorption of BR both in CHCl<SB>3</SB> and complexed to HSA in buffer is in progress.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">In conclusion, ultrafast time resolved fluorescence measurements have been performed on bilirubin dissolved in chloroform and bound to human serum albumin for the first time.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The decays are complex and dominated by sub-picosecond processes, but additional significantly slower components were observed for HSA-bound BR, accounting for the larger quantum yield of fluorescence.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ultrafast disappearance of the emission was also seen in pump-probe absorption measurements of BR in CHCl<SB>3</SB>, as was the build up of a “dark state”, presumably a twisted intermediate, which decays on the 15–20 ps timescale.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
