<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b410053k" hasDoc="yes" version="1168" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Optimising the EVA descriptor for prediction of biological activity<XREF TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" /></annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">EVA is a multivariate molecular descriptor for use in QSAR studies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">It is constructed from vibrational eigenvalues derived from either a quantum theoretical or molecular mechanical treatment of molecular structure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This paper applies the method to biological-activity data using measures of the inotropic potential of a range of Calcium channel agonists.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The performance of the descriptor, as both an explanatory and a predictive tool, is analysed in relation to the way in which it is constructed using a rigorous statistical treatment.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Its capabilities are examined in relation to those of previously published methodology which used a composite descriptor.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is shown to have improved performance and several procedural advantages, such as ease of calculation and operation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">It is a 3-D structural descriptor which does not require prior co-alignment of structures for a QSAR study.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="1">Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">A Quantitative Structure-Activity Relationship (QSAR) is a statistical model relating a common property of a series of chemicals (such as their responses in an assay of a particular type of biological activity) to their molecular structure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The major goal is to use this relationship to discover new chemicals with properties optimally suited to a defined application in an area such as pharmaceuticals, agrochemicals or catalysts.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The process entails relating structurally significant features of a set of chemicals to activity measurements (responses) that are the complex result of integration of many physical, chemical and metabolic processes.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="No">The structural features are summarised numerically in a molecular descriptor, but it is often difficult to do so efficiently and effectively since these features may also be very complex.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, many studies are performed on data sets comprising limited numbers of compounds and associated responses and this restricts the number of variables that can be used to describe structure in the QSAR model.</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to maximise the value of this small number of variables, molecular descriptors that summarise efficiently a large amount of diverse chemical information are required.</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">One recent example is the theoretically-based multivariate descriptor, EVA.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2 cit3">1–3</REF></annotationART></s></P><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="1.1">The EVA (<IT>E</IT>igen<IT>VA</IT>lue) descriptor</HEADER><P><s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The premise on which the EVA approach is based is that a molecule's normal modes of vibration encode a suitable description of chemical structure, summarising the features necessary for the production of robust, predictive, QSARs.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The normal modes are readily derived, using computational techniques based on either Quantum Theoretical or Molecular Mechanical methods.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">When suitably encoded they may be used as robust structural descriptors in QSAR lead-optimisation studies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the following section, an overview of the approach is provided; for a more complete discussion, the reader is referred to reference .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">QSAR studies demand as complete a structural description of a molecule as possible, in numerical terms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Using Quantum Mechanics, the molecular wavefunction, <IT>Ψ</IT>, provides a thorough characterisation of the nuclear and electronic properties of a molecule (and in principle should also allow for the estimation of properties such as biological activity).</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="No">However, extraction of useful information for a QSAR study is difficult.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Following studies with experimentally-based Infra-red Spectra, <IT>theoretically</IT>-<IT>derived normal modes of vibration</IT> were identified as a suitable molecular descriptor encoding information on the identity of the constituent atoms, their bonding and spatial relationships (hence molecular shape and size), their vibrational modes and molecular electronic structure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Intuitively, such a descriptor should constitute a robust, predictive, structural representation.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Calculation of a molecule's normal modes is achieved using the molecular electronic potential energy function, <IT>V</IT>, which is derived from the molecular wavefunction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Normal Coordinate Analysis (NCA) is performed to characterise the molecular vibrational properties.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">This approach involves the pointwise estimation of the potential function to determine the equations of motion, yielding both normal coordinate <IT>E</IT>igen<IT>VA</IT>lues (the normal mode frequencies of vibration) and their associated eigenvectors (the atom vibration vectors).</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The EVA procedure makes use of the eigenvalues, the eigenvectors being retained for final back-transformation to the molecular structures.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="No">The normal modes for a set of molecules cannot be used directly in a multivariate statistical analysis because current methods demand that the descriptor for each molecule in the training set is comprised of the same number of well-defined components, (<IT>i.e.</IT>, the molecular descriptor must be a vector of fixed dimension).</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="No">Since the number of normal modes varies with the number of atoms N in a molecule (actually 3N-6 for a molecule without axial symmetry) each descriptor within a series will generally be of different dimension.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Data transformation is therefore required to convert, without loss of information, a varying number of vibrational eigenvalues into the descriptor EVA, which is of fixed dimension.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is done by projecting the eigenvalues (vibrational frequencies) onto a bounded frequency scale (BFS) with individual vibrations represented by points along this axis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The frequency range is chosen to be 0 cm<SP>−1</SP> to 4000 cm<SP>−1</SP> to encompass all fundamental molecular vibrations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Each of the 3N-6 vibrations is represented by an equivalent Gaussian curve, <IT>G</IT>{f(<IT>μ</IT>), <IT>σ</IT><SP>2</SP>}, in which <IT>μ</IT> is the vibrational frequency; the area under each curve is assigned as unity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Proximate or coincident Gaussian functions are permitted to overlap and the “intensity” is summed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The choice of <IT>σ</IT> for each function defines the degree to which the vibrations overlap and is typically 10 cm<SP>−1</SP> to 20 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This smoothing operation introduces, deliberately, a “fuzziness” to the spectrum of vibrations and is a key step in the definition of EVA; a value that is too small will fail to detect similarities where they exist, and one that is too large will result in overlaps that obscure significant proportions of the variation in the descriptor.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The process results in a degree of serial correlation in the descriptor that causes inevitably some redundancy in the descriptor variables.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, it also enables the significance of the presence or absence of peaks to be assessed in the subsequent analysis, together with the monitoring of changes in peak position.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Once a Gaussian smoothing function has been applied, the resultant spectrum is sampled across its whole width in fixed increments (<IT>L</IT> cm<SP>−1</SP>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The choice of increment determines the number of variables in the EVA descriptor; thus, for example, a 2 cm<SP>−1</SP> increment results in a descriptor string of 2000 variables.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Molecular vibrations are therefore depicted as “peaks” of intensity on a scale of frequency <IT>versus</IT> height.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">This produces the molecular descriptor, EVA, which retains the integrity of its constituent frequency data.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The choice of the variables <IT>σ</IT> and <IT>L</IT> can have a marked effect on the quality of the subsequently derived QSAR/QSPR model, and this is discussed below (see section 3.2).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The EVA descriptor was originally formulated at Shell Research Ltd, Sittingbourne Research Centre, and was applied successfully in a series of agrochemical lead-optimisation studies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">While much of the experimental data used in the development remain proprietary and hence are not available for publication, its utility has been demonstrated by modelling experimentally observed log<IT>P</IT> values.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The intention of the present study is to illustrate the application of the method to biological data that are within the public domain, incidentally providing a comparison of the performance of the EVA descriptor with that of other, more familiar, descriptors.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">A convenient example lies in a set of calcium ion channel agonists and their associated responses in an assay of biological activity;<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF> this represents a particularly attractive set as it has been analysed previously by Davis <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6">5,6</REF>. with another theoretically-based 3-D descriptor, GRID.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This paper compares the performance of EVA with the published results of this study.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In the previous work,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6">5,6</REF> the 3D structural descriptor, GRID,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF> was used to analyse the molecular features which account for the observed activities.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The additional inclusion of selected physicochemical descriptors, and the consequences of variable scaling, was then considered in turn to assess whether the QSAR model could be improved upon.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">All results were cited in terms of the squared correlation coefficient of the fitted PLS regression model, <IT>r</IT><SP>2</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The intention of the present studies is to conduct a parallel investigation to examine the performance of the EVA descriptor.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">A particular focus will be to examine the robustness of the predictive ability of the EVA based QSAR model.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Results will therefore be presented in terms of the squared correlation coefficients of the <IT>cross-validated</IT> equations, <IT>q</IT><SP>2</SP>, rather than the fitted regression model.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The parameter <IT>q</IT><SP>2</SP> is commonly used as a measure of the predictive ability of the regression model, but in order to facilitate comparison between the two studies the values of <IT>r</IT><SP>2</SP> will also be included as appropriate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This paper reports the results of an investigation to show how to optimise the EVA descriptor in order to increase the predictive power of a QSAR equation.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2">Experimental</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.1">The Calcium Channel Agonist data set</HEADER><P><s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Table 1 shows the structures of the compounds used by Davis <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6">5,6</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The compounds were assayed <IT>in vitro</IT> for their inotropic potency, <IT>i.e.</IT>, their ability to increase cardiac contractibility, using guinea pig atria paced at 1 Hz.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">This was expressed as the concentration of the drug that increased the tension developed in the preparation to 50% of the isoprenaline maximum (<IT>EC</IT><SB>50</SB>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Results were expressed relative to the <IT>EC</IT><SB>50</SB> of the standard calcium channel agonist Bay K 8644 (Fig. 1) and these values are given in Table 1.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Also listed in Table 1 are values of the calculated log octanol/water partition coefficient (clog<IT>P</IT>) and the calculated molar refractivity (cMR) respectively, corresponding to the various structures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">These were calculated using MedChem software v.3.54 B (1989).</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the corresponding table in the paper by Davis <IT>et al.</IT> the quoted values for these parameters are different, having been modified by in-house fitting to a few experimentally determined values.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the present paper we use the standard values in order to maintain external consistency.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.2">GRID descriptor</HEADER><P><s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">For the 3-D QSAR analysis of the data set, Davis <IT>et al.</IT> made use of the GRID descriptor.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">The technique was developed originally as a method of probing proteins for potential binding sites and has been used successfully to predict sites of binding of small ligands in proteins,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF> in addition to its more recent role as a structure descriptor.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">A detailed discussion of the derivation of the GRID descriptor can be found in reference .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF></annotationART></s></P><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.2.1">The inclusion of physicochemical descriptors</HEADER><P><s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="No">A limitation of GRID is that by generating the descriptors from the calculated interaction energy of a probe molecule, only the enthalpic component of the drug–receptor interaction can be modelled.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="No">This neglects other factors which can be, potentially, highly influential, such as the entropic changes resulting from the interaction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In recognition of this limitation, Davis <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6">5,6</REF>. included two physicochemical descriptors, clog<IT>P</IT> and cMR.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Clog<IT>P</IT> represents a particularly useful descriptor since by accounting for lipophilicity and solvation, features that are influenced heavily by hydrogen bonding, it can give information on the entropic changes associated with a molecule's coming out of solution and binding at a receptor site.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.3">EVA descriptor generation</HEADER><P><s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">EVA descriptors were generated for the 36 compounds in the calcium channel agonist set.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6">5,6</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">A typing error in the published table<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6">5,6</REF> cites incorrectly the substitution about the benzoylpyrrole backbone of compounds 8, 12, 19, 33, 35 and 36 as 2,4 rather than as .2,5<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The correct structures were used in the present study and were created using Sybyl 6.2 from Tripos Associates<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF> on a Silicon Graphics Indy R4000 platform.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In the previous studies, Davis <IT>et al.</IT> constrained the energy minimisation of the structures in an attempt to minimise noise in the GRID descriptors and hence optimise the subsequent QSAR investigations.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6">5,6</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="No">In order to perform the calculation of the normal modes of vibration required for EVA, it is a prerequisite to ensure that the potential energy of a molecular conformation is at a stationary point.</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="No">Slight deviations away from this energy minimum can lead to the introduction of rotational and translational modes during the determination of the equations of motion in the NCA.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="No">This in effect ‘contaminates’ the vibrational modes, resulting in the determination of vibrations that are not purely harmonic in nature and degrading significantly the quality of the calculated vibrational spectrum.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">A more detailed discussion of this is provided in reference .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="No">No attempt was made therefore to reproduce directly the conformational co-ordinates used by Davis <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6">5,6</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Molecular structures were optimised using the MOPAC 6.0 AM1 Hamiltonian<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF> (keywords: SCFCRT = 1.D-12 GNORM = 0.05).</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Successfully minimised structures were then used to generate the NMs (additional keyword: FORCE).</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">These were then converted into EVA descriptors in the manner described.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="No">It is acknowledged that the calculation of NMs using a semi-empirical route is less accurate than for example, by the use of Density Functional Theory methods.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">However, the use of the MOPAC AM1 Hamiltonian has previously been shown to produce qualitatively good results.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">Furthermore, EVA descriptors generated from the MOPAC AM1 Hamiltonian have been applied successfully in previously reported studies.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Consequently, it is believed that the EVA descriptors generated in this way are acceptable for the present investigation.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.4">Statistical analysis</HEADER><P><s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="Old" advantage="None">To generate useful QSARs between the activity, <IT>EC</IT><SB>50</SB>, and the EVA descriptor, the Partial Least Squares regression method (PLS) was adopted for the investigations; this is in line with the GRID-based studies of Davis <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6">5,6</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">PLS is a supervised approach that provides a reduced solution of new ‘latent’ variables that are linear combinations of the original variables and are well correlated with <IT>Y</IT>. In essence, it is a projection method that defines a hyperplane through the <IT>x</IT>-descriptor space.</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The latent variables represent the projected ‘summaries’ of the original variables onto this plane and each PLS component represents a co-ordinate dimension of the hyperplane.</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">A more complete discussion of the PLS approach can be obtained from references <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF> and .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">The PLS regression approach is an accepted technique for handling situations where over-square matrices are encountered and has some advantages over unsupervised techniques such as, for example, Principal Components analysis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">By constructing the components in a supervised fashion, it is possible to produce fewer numbers of components correlated with <IT>Y</IT>, thereby summarising the data more efficiently.</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">With matrices such as EVA and GRID this is a clear advantage.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">As has been mentioned earlier in section 1.1, by having the ability to vary the form and dimension of the EVA descriptor (<IT>i.e.</IT>, <IT>σ</IT> and <IT>L</IT>), it is possible to change the manner in which the structural information is presented.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">In effect, this can be thought of as a form of data scaling, in line with log and variance scaling methods.</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">This affects ultimately the regression analysis, particularly with respect to the co-variance with the activity data and the way in which the information is loaded onto the components.</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore an essential stage in the application of EVA is the generation of descriptors with different <IT>σ</IT> and <IT>L</IT> values and their subsequent systematic validation to identify the optimum predictive model.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Previous studies have shown that a <IT>σ</IT> value of between 10 and 20 cm<SP>−1</SP> is a reasonable starting point for such investigations.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF></annotationART></s></P><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.4.1">Model validation and significance testing</HEADER><P><s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">A key step in regression analysis is the validation to determine the correct dimensionality of the model, <IT>i.e.</IT>, the number of significant PLS components to be included.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Without this validation there is a risk of ‘over-training’, leading to apparently well-fitting models with effectively little predictive capacity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">As the intention of the present study is to assess the predictive capability of the EVA descriptor, two forms of model validation have been incorporated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In line with the study by Davis <IT>et al.</IT>, Cross-Validation (CV) has been used to test each successive PLS component for significance.</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In addition, randomisation tests have been included to establish confidence limits on whether or not random correlations are being selected in place of real relationships.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">CV represents one of the most favoured methods of testing the PLS components for significance.</annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In essence, CV randomly divides the data set into groups of compounds.</annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Each group is then omitted from the data set in turn and the remaining set used to construct a new regression model, which is then used to calculate the responses for the members of the omitted set.</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">From the predicted <IT>y</IT>-values for each of the omitted ‘test’ sets, the sum of squares of the differences from actual values can be calculated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">This yields the <IT>PRESS</IT> score (Predictive Residual Sum of Squares) and by weighting this against both the inclusion of successive components and the number of cases in the set, the standard error of cross-validation, <IT>S</IT><SB>cv</SB>, can be calculated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">This provides a good test of the significance of the inclusion of each component upon the overall regression model and has some advantages over other procedures such as, for example, the <IT>F</IT>-ratio test.</annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">By simulating how well the model predicts new data, it provides an estimate of the robustness of the model and potentially can highlight models that are influenced by data points with high leverage (<IT>e.g.</IT>, outliers).</annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">As the underlying intention of a QSAR is to make predictions, then this is useful.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Initial analysis of the EVA descriptor models was performed using Leave-One-Out Cross-Validation (LOO CV).</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="Old" advantage="None">To determine the optimum regression model, the <IT>S</IT><SB>cv</SB> scores for the first 10 PLS components were calculated and the minimum <IT>S</IT><SB>cv</SB> score identified.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Previous experience has shown that the relevant information linking the response and descriptor variables is summarised in the first few components (typically ≤ 6).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The squared correlation coefficient of the cross-validated equation, <IT>q</IT><SP>2</SP>, was then cited for the inclusion of each successive component.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">In a previous publication,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF> it was shown that the LOO CV <IT>q</IT><SP>2</SP> obtained on a training set of 135 structures, using EVA as the descriptor and log<IT>P</IT><SB>ow</SB> as the measured response, was a very good indicator of subsequent predictive power for log<IT>P</IT><SB>ow</SB> in an unrelated test set of 76 compounds.</annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="Old" advantage="No">However, work by Shao<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF> has challenged the suitability of LOO CV for testing the predictive robustness of a QSAR model and suggests that Leave-<IT>n</IT>-Out Cross-Validation, where <IT>n</IT> is greater than 1, represents a more robust alternative.</annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Consequently, in the present investigations we have compared LOO CV results with those obtained using Leave-Group-Out Cross-Validation (LGO CV) with <IT>n</IT> = 7 (see section 3.2); this is also in line with the validation approach applied by Davis <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6">5,6</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="Old" advantage="No">However, while LOO CV represents an easily reproducible test, <IT>i.e.</IT>, each run will yield the same <IT>q</IT><SP>2</SP> result, in LGO CV the cases assigned to each group to be left out are selected at random.</annotationART></s> <s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="Old" advantage="No">This means that LGO CV must be repeated a large number of times (<IT>e.g.</IT>, 1000) in order to obtain a realistic estimate of the internal predictivity and is hence more computationally demanding than LOO CV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">Our work shows that with this data set and analytical approach, LOO CV gives very similar results to LGO CV and so we have adopted the simpler procedure.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">It must be acknowledged that neither LOO CV nor LGO CV can be regarded as a sufficient indicator of model validity; in addition, some measure of the probability that the result may be a chance occurrence is needed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is particularly important in regression studies where there are a smaller number of cases than the dimensionality of the <IT>x</IT>-descriptor, <IT>i.e.</IT>, where an over-square matrix is present.</annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In such instances, there is an increased possibility of the extraction of a random correlation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Consequently, in order to address this with regard to the EVA descriptor, a randomised permutation test was performed to examine the model for chance correlations; this is in line with previous studies that have applied the EVA descriptor.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2 cit18">2,18</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The process involves:</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="Old" advantage="None">1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Randomly assigning observations to structures,</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="Old" advantage="None">2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Performing a regression analysis using EVA and then evaluating <IT>q</IT><SP>2</SP> (or <IT>r</IT><SP>2</SP>),</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="Old" advantage="None">3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Repeating steps 1 and 2 a large number of times (<IT>e.g.</IT>, 1000 times) to ensure thorough sampling,</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="Old" advantage="None">4.</annotationART></s> <s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Determining the frequency distribution of <IT>q</IT><SP>2</SP> (or <IT>r</IT><SP>2</SP>),</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="Old" advantage="None">5.</annotationART></s> <s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Determining where in this frequency distribution the <IT>q</IT><SP>2</SP> (or <IT>r</IT><SP>2</SP>) of the real assignment lies.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="Old" advantage="None">An actual result that is extreme in the upper confidence tail of the distribution is regarded as having a low probability of occurring by chance</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3">Results and discussion</HEADER><P><s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the following section, the results are reported for the QSAR investigation of a set of 36 calcium channel agonists (Table 1), using EVA as the structural descriptor and PLS regression as the statistical approach.</annotationART></s> <s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Except where stated otherwise, all results will be reported in terms of the squared correlation coefficient (<IT>q</IT><SP>2</SP>) of the Leave-One-Out Cross-Validated (LOO CV) equation.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">To facilitate comparisons, Table 2 is taken directly from the work of Davis <IT>et al.</IT>, detailing the PLS regression models reported for the full 36 compound data set.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6">5,6</REF></annotationART></s></P><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.1">Determination of optimum PLS regression model</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.1.1">Optimum EVA descriptor model</HEADER><P><s sid="143"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">Initial identification of the optimum EVA model was performed by comparing the results obtained with a series of descriptors using <IT>σ</IT> values of 10, 20, 30 and 40 cm<SP>−1</SP>, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="144"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results established a narrowed focus of attention around <IT>σ</IT> = 20 cm<SP>−1</SP> and a further series of EVA descriptors was then generated (16 ≤ <IT>σ</IT> ≤ 26 cm<SP>−1</SP>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="145"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Comparison of the predictive performance of the models identified the optimum EVA model as having <IT>σ</IT> = 24 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="146"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Throughout, the BFS start point, <IT>S</IT>, was fixed at 1 cm<SP>−1</SP> and <IT>L</IT> was defined as <IT>σ</IT>/2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="147"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This has been assumed previously<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF> to represent a reasonable sampling frequency for a given value of <IT>σ</IT> and is justified below (section 3.2).</annotationART></s> <s sid="148"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results for the full range of EVA models considered are included in Table 3.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.1.2">Model transformations and variance scaling effects</HEADER><P><s sid="149"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="Old" advantage="No">As was demonstrated earlier,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6">5,6</REF> PLS analysis can be highly sensitive to the relative scales of variance between the <IT>x</IT>-block and <IT>y</IT>-variable (this is especially significant when different <IT>x</IT>-descriptors, each with its own unit and scale, are included in the regression equation, although this situation does not apply to EVA).</annotationART></s> <s sid="150"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="Old" advantage="None">A series of transformations and scaling procedures was applied to both the activity and EVA variables, to investigate the impact on performance.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="151"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Scaling and transformation tests were conducted in two parts.</annotationART></s> <s sid="152"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In the case of the activity variable, <IT>EC</IT><SB>50</SB>, both log scaling and variable standardisation were considered, as in the study of Davis <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6">5,6</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="153"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met14" novelty="Old" advantage="None">For the EVA descriptor, two forms of variance scaling were applied, Autoscaling and Blockscaling.</annotationART></s> <s sid="154"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met14" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Autoscaling standardises each individual variable column to zero mean and unit variance, while Blockscaling scales the entire descriptor block to zero mean and unit variance.</annotationART></s> <s sid="155"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The impact of these two scaling methods is of particular interest, because differences in column variance across the descriptor are considered to contain structurally significant information.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="156"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The full results are reported in Table 4.</annotationART></s> <s sid="157"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Variance scaling with the <IT>EC</IT><SB>50</SB> variable has no impact on the PLS regression model (4<IT>c</IT> model, <IT>q</IT><SP>2</SP> = 0.498).</annotationART></s> <s sid="158"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Similarly, blockscaling the EVA descriptor does not affect the performance.</annotationART></s> <s sid="159"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, log<SB>10</SB> transformation of the activity values does result in a significant degradation of the PLS model (1<IT>c</IT> model, <IT>q</IT><SP>2</SP> = 0.194).</annotationART></s> <s sid="160"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Notably, use of the autoscaled EVA descriptor yields the worst model of all.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.2">EVA QSAR model testing and stability</HEADER><P><s sid="161"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="Old" advantage="No">As discussed above (section 2.4.1), with over-square <IT>x</IT>-matrices the PLS regression approach, potentially, can extract chance correlations with the <IT>y</IT>-variable.</annotationART></s> <s sid="162"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of the EVA descriptor, an extreme example of an over-square matrix, then the likelihood of such an occurrence may be increased.</annotationART></s> <s sid="163"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, a series of rigorous validation exercises was applied to establish confidence in the QSAR model obtained.</annotationART></s> <s sid="164"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="Old" advantage="None">These include sensitivity tests on the effects of changes in the EVA <IT>L</IT> variable, LGO CV (in line with references <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF> and <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF>) and randomised activity permutation tests.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="165"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Fundamentally, two variables, namely <IT>σ</IT> (Gaussian standard deviation) and <IT>L</IT> (the BFS sampling interval), determine the form and dimension of the EVA descriptor when derived from the normal coordinate spectrum.</annotationART></s> <s sid="166"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="No">Potentially, the value chosen for <IT>L</IT> can impact on the information content retained in the final descriptor model and an extreme illustration of this would occur if the sampling interval were so large that not all of the intensities under the Gaussian curves were to be sampled.</annotationART></s> <s sid="167"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">As outlined earlier in the initial determination of the optimum EVA model, <IT>L</IT> was defined as <IT>σ</IT>/2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="168"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">This ensures that all structural information is retained, while keeping the associated computational time within reason.</annotationART></s> <s sid="169"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met15" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Validation of this procedure was carried out by comparing the effects of using a range of sampling intervals (<IT>σ</IT>/4 ≤ <IT>L</IT> ≤ 4<IT>σ</IT>).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="170"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The full set of results is shown in Table 5 and illustrated in Fig. 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="171"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">For sampling intervals where <IT>L</IT> ≤ <IT>σ</IT>, the information content remains intrinsically stable, with no significant impact on the statistical performance of the EVA models.</annotationART></s> <s sid="172"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">However when <IT>L</IT> &gt; <IT>σ</IT>, decreasing stability in the performance in the EVA model is observed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="173"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results confirm that <IT>L</IT> = <IT>σ</IT>/2 is a reasonable rule.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="174"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="Old" advantage="None">To test rigorously the predictive performance of the optimum EVA model (EVA{24,12}), LGO CV was used and compared with the results of LOO CV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="175"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In line with the LGO CV in references <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF> and <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF>, the 36 compounds were divided randomly into 7 groups.</annotationART></s> <s sid="176"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Repeated runs of the LGO CV (1000 iterations) were carried out with different randomisations to ensure that the range of possibilities was thoroughly sampled.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="177"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results for the LGO CV study are presented in Table 5.</annotationART></s> <s sid="178"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">These show that the 4-component model occurs most frequently (560 iterations; Fig. 3a), in agreement with LOO CV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="179"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The range of <IT>q</IT><SP>2</SP> scores for the LGO CV 4 component model is approximately normal in distribution (Fig. 3b and 3c).</annotationART></s> <s sid="180"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Determination of the mean <IT>q</IT><SP>2</SP> reveals that <IT>q</IT><SP>2</SP><SB>LGO</SB> compares closely with <IT>q</IT><SP>2</SP><SB>LOO</SB> (Fig. 2c: <IT>q</IT><SP>2</SP><SB>LGO</SB> = 0.474, <IT>q</IT><SP>2</SP><SB>LOO</SB> = 0.498), which gives confidence in the use of LOO CV to test the range of EVA models.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="181"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Figs. 4 and 5 show the results of the randomised activity permutation tests on the same data set, obtained by using 1000 permutations of the response data with respect to structure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="182"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 3 shows the frequency distribution and normalised plot of <IT>q</IT><SP>2</SP>, obtained from the LOO CVs; the actual experimental result of 0.498 lies well outside the upper 95% confidence limit (&gt;99%).</annotationART></s> <s sid="183"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">A similar result is shown in Fig. 4 for the fitted <IT>r</IT><SP>2</SP> distribution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="184"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Table 6 summarises these results.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.3">Augmentation of EVA {24,12} with the physicochemical descriptors clogP and cMR</HEADER><P><s sid="185"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="No">Davis <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6">5,6</REF>. showed that the 3D molecular descriptor GRID did not by itself encode sufficient information to give a high-quality QSAR regression model of −<IT>log EC</IT><SB>50</SB> (<IT>r</IT><SP>2</SP> = 0.42).</annotationART></s> <s sid="186"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, inclusion of clog<IT>P</IT> and cMR, in linear combination with GRID, gives a significant improvement (<IT>r</IT><SP>2</SP> = 0.86).</annotationART></s> <s sid="187"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is therefore of interest to examine the influence of including clog<IT>P</IT> and cMR with EVA.</annotationART></s> <s sid="188"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results are given in Table 6 and show that inclusion of these parameters (either singly or in combination) degrades the quality of the fit (<IT>r</IT><SP>2</SP>) and also the predictive power (<IT>q</IT><SP>2</SP>).</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.4">EVA and analysis of the data of Davis <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6">5,6</REF>.</HEADER><P><s sid="189"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">QSAR methods that relate biological response to molecular structure are traditionally based on linear free energy relationships, as illustrated in the pioneering work of Hansch <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19">19</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="190"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Typically, these methods attempt to draw correlations between empirical descriptors which supposedly represent generalised forms of enthalpic and entropic effects associated with a drug molecule's transport to, and interaction with, a receptor or enzyme active site.</annotationART></s> <s sid="191"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The current research is aimed at further developing a new molecular descriptor, EVA, which encodes a large amount of diverse chemical information and can be used more effectively than the previous empirical forms.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="192"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Analysis of the predictive performance of a range of EVA PLS models (Table 3) identifies the optimum descriptor as having a Gaussian sigma; = 24 cm<SP>−1</SP> and a sampling interval <IT>L</IT> = 12 cm<SP>−1</SP>, EVA {24,12}.</annotationART></s> <s sid="193"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Cross-Validation (using both LOO CV and LGO CV methods) suggests that the first 4 components are significant, yielding a QSAR that is able to account for <IT>circa.</IT> 80% of the variation in the <IT>EC</IT><SB>50</SB> activity (fitted <IT>r</IT><SP>2</SP> = 0.801).</annotationART></s> <s sid="194"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Rigorous testing of the internal predictivity of the EVA QSAR model (Tables 3 and 5) shows that for structures outside the training set <IT>circa.</IT> 50% of the activity variation may be predicted with confidence, an experimentally useful result (4-component models, <IT>q</IT><SP>2</SP><SB>LGO</SB> = 0.474; <IT>q</IT><SP>2</SP><SB>LOO</SB> = 0.498).</annotationART></s> <s sid="195"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The close agreement between the two validation methods, illustrated in Fig. 2, gives considerable confidence in the use of LOO CV to validate the chosen EVA model and indicates that EVA is robust as a predictive QSAR tool, <IT>i.e.</IT>, the model is stable.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="196"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since Davis <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6">5,6</REF>. analysed their data with log-transformation of the <IT>EC</IT><SB>50</SB> values (<IT>i.e.</IT>, the <IT>y</IT>-variate was −log(<IT>EC</IT><SB>50</SB>), Table 1) and their original data are not available to us, an exact comparison of the two sets of results is difficult.</annotationART></s> <s sid="197"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Moreover, cross-validation tests were not reported so it is only possible to compare values of <IT>r</IT><SP>2</SP>, obtained by fitting the full-regression equation, rather than <IT>q</IT><SP>2</SP>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="198"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The best model of Davis <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6">5,6</REF>. uses a linear combination of GRID, clog<IT>P</IT> and cMR.</annotationART></s> <s sid="199"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">(GRID alone gives a 1-component model, <IT>r</IT><SP>2</SP> = 0.42, clog<IT>P</IT> alone a 1-component model, <IT>r</IT><SP>2</SP> = 0.69, and GRID in combination with clog<IT>P</IT> and cMR gives a 4-component model, <IT>r</IT><SP>2</SP> = 0.86).</annotationART></s> <s sid="200"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The values of −log(<IT>EC</IT><SB>50</SB>) predicted by this model are not quoted, but a comparison with experimentally observed values is given graphically in Fig. 5 of reference <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF>; by careful measurement, it is possible to obtain reliable estimates for the predicted −log(<IT>EC</IT><SB>50</SB>) values.</annotationART></s> <s sid="201"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Taking antilogarithms yields values for predicted <IT>EC</IT><SB>50</SB> and the regression statistics may be calculated and compared with those obtained for the EVA model.</annotationART></s> <s sid="202"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Overall, the full EVA model (<IT>r</IT><SP>2</SP> = 0.80, standard error = 4.1) gives a considerably better fit to the untransformed experimental data than does the GRID + clog<IT>P</IT> + cMR model (<IT>r</IT><SP>2</SP> = 0.42, standard error = 7.0).</annotationART></s> <s sid="203"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results are shown in Table 7 and are further illustrated in Fig. 6 which shows plots of residuals for both treatments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="204"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">For small values of <IT>EC</IT><SB>50</SB> (typically less than 4.1, the standard error of the EVA treatment) the two models (not surprisingly) cannot be distinguished; however, for higher values of <IT>EC</IT><SB>50</SB> EVA consistently outperforms the other model by an impressive margin.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="205"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">A model-validation test using randomised activity permutations establishes confidence intervals for both the predictive (Fig. 4) and fitted (Fig. 5) regression models and demonstrates that, although the EVA descriptor presents an over square <IT>x</IT>-matrix in the PLS regression model, random correlations with the activity data are highly unlikely (<IT>&gt;99%</IT> probability that the correlations have not arisen by chance).</annotationART></s> <s sid="206"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">EVA contains structurally significant features that account well for the observed biological activity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="207"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">It should also be emphasised that EVA is a robust descriptor of 3D molecular structure, which does not require prior alignment of structures in order for a QSAR study to be performed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="208"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">This is especially useful when dealing with non congeneric series, where alignment about a common skeletal feature is not feasible.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit3">1,3</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="209"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although the relevance, multicolinearity and redundancy of the EVA descriptors have not been addressed in this study, they probably provide the most likely explanation for the relatively small values obtained for the estimates of LOO <IT>q</IT><SP>2</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="210"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">These aspects will be reported in a future publication.</annotationART></s> <s sid="211"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Clearly, a model that yielded a <IT>q</IT><SP>2</SP> of &gt;50% would be even more useful.</annotationART></s> <s sid="212"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Plots of the predicted <IT>vs.</IT> actual activity for both the fitted and cross-validated regression models (Figs. 7 and 8) highlight problems with outliers, particularly those compounds with <IT>EC</IT><SB>50</SB> values which are essentially zero; these structures can only contribute noise to the analysis, and the consequences are addressed in detail in section 3.7.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.5">Data scaling</HEADER><P><s sid="213"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp9" novelty="None" advantage="None">In studies where the <IT>x</IT>-variate function is a vector consisting of a number of variables such as molecular properties with different dimensionalities and variances, careful tailoring of the variable variances is critical in extracting an optimum QSAR model.</annotationART></s> <s sid="214"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is true, for example, of the work by Davis <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6">5,6</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="215"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the present study however, Table 4 shows that blockscaling and autoscaling of the <IT>x</IT>-variate function does not improve the EVA QSAR model.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="216"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In particular, autoscaling (which scales columns independently to zero mean and unit variance), performs significantly worse.</annotationART></s> <s sid="217"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In the EVA descriptor, all variable columns are presented on the same scale with the differences in variance between them intrinsically encoding structurally relevant information.</annotationART></s> <s sid="218"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="No">Consequently, individual columns should not be standardised since this would result in giving columns with little variation and therefore little information, undue weighting.</annotationART></s> <s sid="219"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Indeed, in-house development with proprietary data sets (Shell Research Ltd., the former Sittingbourne Research Centre) has in the past demonstrated that scaling typically does not improve the performance of EVA-based QSAR models.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="220"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Log transformation of the <IT>y</IT>-variate, <IT>EC</IT><SB>50</SB>, leads to a substantially worse EVA model.</annotationART></s> <s sid="221"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">This contrasts markedly with the results of a similar transformation in the work of Davis <IT>et al.</IT>, which gave the best result.</annotationART></s> <s sid="222"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is investigated further in section 3.7, below.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.6">Inclusion of the physicochemical descriptors</HEADER><P><s sid="223"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp10" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is reasonable to ask the question as to whether or not the inclusion of the physicochemical parameters clog<IT>P</IT> and cMR would improve the EVA model.</annotationART></s> <s sid="224"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results of doing so are shown in Table 8 and provide an insight into the information content of EVA.</annotationART></s> <s sid="225"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is clear that the inclusion of either clog<IT>P</IT> or cMR, or both, does not lead to an improved QSAR model, even with scaling of the variables in this more complex <IT>x</IT>-variate vector.</annotationART></s> <s sid="226"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The implication may be that the information contained within the physicochemical parameters is already encoded intrinsically within the EVA descriptor.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="227"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to test this hypothesis, namely that EVA encodes physicochemical information, regression models were constructed for clog<IT>P</IT> and cMR, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="228"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results (Table 9) show that while EVA accounts for the variation in cMR extremely well (<IT>r</IT><SP>2</SP> = 0.983, <IT>q</IT><SP>2</SP> = 0.963), it does not do so at all well for clog<IT>P</IT> (<IT>r</IT><SP>2</SP> = 0.415, <IT>q</IT><SP>2</SP> = 0.281).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="229"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The result with clog<IT>P</IT> is surprising, since in previous work it has been shown that EVA QSAR can explain the variation in experimentally measured log<IT>P</IT> values across a wide variety of structurally-diverse, non-related compounds and be usefully predictive (135 compounds, <IT>r</IT><SP>2</SP> = 0.96, <IT>q</IT><SP>2</SP> = 0.68).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="230"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Why should the approach be less successful with the congeneric set of structures described in Table 1?</annotationART></s> <s sid="231"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The most likely reason for this anomaly is in the variance in clog<IT>P</IT>; the range of values is relatively small, <IT>i.e.</IT>, only 3 log units in comparison to 6 log units in the log<IT>P</IT> study.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.7">Investigation of outliers</HEADER><P><s sid="232"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">It was noted that eight of the structures in the data set have corresponding values of <IT>EC</IT><SB>50</SB> that were approaching zero, ranging from 0.01 to 0.09 (see Table 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="233"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Given the nature of the bioassay from which they have been derived, within experimental error, they probably may not be significantly different from zero.</annotationART></s> <s sid="234"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Inclusion of these data has the consequence of biasing the activity data set (<IT>y</IT>-variate) heavily, and introducing noise in the form of irrelevant descriptor information (<IT>x</IT>-variate).</annotationART></s> <s sid="235"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The consequence of removing these data to leave a set of 28 structures and activity scores was investigated.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="236"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Table 10 compares the regression results with those obtained for the original set of 36 structures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="237"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the untransformed <IT>EC</IT><SB>50</SB> data, there was a slight improvement in both the fit of the full regression equation and in the predictive power, albeit with the addition of a further 2 components in the regression model (6 component model, <IT>r</IT><SP>2</SP> = 0.939, <IT>q</IT><SP>2</SP> = 0.527, <IT>cf.</IT> a 4-component model, <IT>r</IT><SP>2</SP> = 0.802, <IT>q</IT><SP>2</SP> = 0.498).</annotationART></s> <s sid="238"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast, there was a highly significant change in the performance of the regression results for the −log(<IT>EC</IT><SB>50</SB>) scores, Figs. 9 and 10 (5-component model, <IT>r</IT><SP>2</SP> = 0.963, <IT>q</IT><SP>2</SP> = 0.721, <IT>cf.</IT> a 1-component model, <IT>r</IT><SP>2</SP> = 0.332, <IT>q</IT><SP>2</SP> = 0.194).</annotationART></s> <s sid="239"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">This compares favourably with the results of a similar transformation in the work of Davis <IT>et al.</IT> (4-component model, <IT>r</IT><SP>2</SP> = 0.86).</annotationART></s> <s sid="240"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">More importantly, the <IT>q</IT><SP>2</SP> result would provide significant confidence in support of the application of this model in a predictive role.</annotationART></s> <s sid="241"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, it should be recognised that chemical interpretability will be non-trivial, given the Gaussian transformation and subsequent sampling of the normal modes of vibration.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="242"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The degree of improvement in the log transformed <IT>EC</IT><SB>50</SB> was marked, however, it was not unexpected.</annotationART></s> <s sid="243"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="Old" advantage="No">As was highlighted earlier, PLS analysis can be highly sensitive to the relative scales of variance between the <IT>x</IT>-block and <IT>y</IT>-variable.</annotationART></s> <s sid="244"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Certainly, for the log-transformed <IT>y</IT>-variable set, this variance would have been significant.</annotationART></s> <s sid="245"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, given the likely experimental error in the bioassay, it is reasonable to postulate that relative differences in the log values for these compounds would have been subject to significant error.</annotationART></s> <s sid="246"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Consequently, in attempting to generate a model, these data would have had a greater bias in the log-transformed set.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="247"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">It remains interesting to speculate on whether the sensitivity in model formation was also in part a product of the choice of an essentially linear regression model.</annotationART></s> <s sid="248"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">While outside the scope of this study, it remains an appealing point for future studies to test the performance of the EVA descriptor across a series of non-linear statistical methods.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.8">Chemical similarity searching</HEADER><P><s sid="249"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The formulation of the EVA descriptor as a bit string opens up the possibility of using the encoded vibrational mode information for chemical similarity searching.</annotationART></s> <s sid="250"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">There is a substantial body of literature that describes the procedures and software available for this purpose and which points out the strengths and pitfalls of the approach.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20 cit21 cit22">20–22</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="251"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Current procedures are based principally on the use of chemical fragments represented as topological maps, atom counts and bond types.</annotationART></s> <s sid="252"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Use of EVA for similarity searches would provide useful additional information to complement and extend this structural data.</annotationART></s> <s sid="253"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Applications might include selective compound acquisition<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF> and identification of compounds with similar biological activities<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4">Conclusions</HEADER><P><s sid="254"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Within the context of the present study, EVA is well suited to the production of usefully predictive QSARs with both biological and physicochemical data.</annotationART></s> <s sid="255"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The absence of a requirement for additional descriptors demonstrates that EVA has a very high information content encompassing, intrinsically, physicochemical descriptors such as clog<IT>P</IT> and cMR.</annotationART></s> <s sid="256"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In direct comparison with a composite descriptor (GRID + clog<IT>P</IT> + cMR), EVA has been shown to have superior predictive performance.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="257"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">As a general tool for QSAR studies, EVA advantageously may be applied without the prior alignment of structures required for other 3-D descriptors such as COMFA and GRID.</annotationART></s> <s sid="258"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="No">However, optimisation of the EVA descriptor by adjusting how it is constructed can influence the predictive power of a QSAR equation.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="259"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Further studies with other sets of biological data will be necessary in order to demonstrate the robustness of these conclusions.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Abbreviations</HEADER><P><s sid="260"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">QSAR, Quantitative Structure-Activity Relationship; EVA {<IT>σ</IT>, <IT>L</IT>, <IT>S</IT>}, <IT>E</IT>igen <IT>VA</IT>lue molecular spectral descriptor model where: <IT>σ</IT> (sigma) = standard deviation of the EVA Gaussian curve, <IT>L</IT> = sampling interval of summed intensities and <IT>S</IT> = sampling interval start point on the bounded frequency scale; BFS, Bounded Frequency Scale (0 to 4000 cm<SP>−1</SP>); NCA, Normal Co-ordinate Analysis; NMs, Normal Modes (of Vibration); <IT>EC</IT><SB>50</SB>, relative force of contraction; clog<IT>P</IT>, calculated log octanol/water partition coefficient; cMR, calculated molar refractivity; PLS, Partial Least Squares regression analysis; <IT>r</IT><SP>2</SP>, squared correlation coefficient; CV, cross-validation; LOO, ‘Leave One Out’ cross-validation; LGO, ‘Leave One Group Out’ cross-validation; <IT>q</IT><SP>2</SP>, squared correlation coefficient of the cross-validation equation; <IT>PRESS</IT>, Predictive REsidual Sum of Squares; <IT>S</IT><SB>cv</SB>, cross-validated standard error, where ; <IT>n</IT>, number of compounds in data set; <IT>c</IT>, number of PLS components included in QSAR model; <IT>F</IT>-ratio, weighted ratio of r<SP>2</SP> to 1.0 − r<SP>2</SP>, where </annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
