<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b310851a" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Infrared intensities of furan, pyrrole and thiophene: beyond the double harmonic approximation</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Infrared intensities of the fundamental, overtone and combination transitions in furan, pyrrole and thiophene have been calculated using the variational normal coordinate code MULTIMODE.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">We use pure vibrational wavefunctions, and quartic force fields and cubic dipole moment vector surfaces, generated by density functional theory.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results are compared graphically with second-order perturbation calculations and with relative intensities from experiment for furan and pyrrole.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="1.">Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This paper is a continuation of our previous studies of vibrational transitions in five-membered aromatic ring compounds.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have found that both perturbative and variational approaches, based on the fourth degree Taylor expansion of the potential, yield energies of vibrational levels for fundamental and overtone transitions in excellent agreement with experimental data.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The next logical step is to expand the dipole moment vector as a Taylor series in normal coordinates and calculate anharmonic contributions to the infrared intensities.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This approach was tested recently for water and formaldehyde.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">2</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">While for small molecules there are many avenues along which to pursue infrared intensities of higher quality, for larger molecules (with more than five atoms) expansion in normal coordinates appears to be the only practical approach.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">A number of scientists are now recognising the importance of comparing theoretical spectra with observation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">For example Hirano <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF>. have recently used the Morbid program<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF> to predict and compare spectra for MgNC and MgCN.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The paper is organised as follows.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In Section 2 we discuss the potential and dipole fields, variational and perturbation approaches used to evaluate the transition dipole moments and calculation of infrared intensities from these moments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In Section 3 we present and discuss the results for furan, pyrrole and thiophene.</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In Section 4 we summarise the findings and outline future directions.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.">Methodology</HEADER><P><s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">To study molecular vibrations it is necessary to solve the Schrödinger equation for nuclear motion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">While there are many different coordinate systems in which the kinetic and potential energy operators can be expressed, for larger molecules the only expansion of the kinetic energy operator, which is not prohibitively complicated, is in terms of normal coordinates.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore it is advantageous to express the potential energy also in terms of the normal coordinates.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">If analytical second derivatives <IT>φ</IT><SB><IT>jk</IT></SB> are calculated at the equilibrium geometry and at the geometries displaced along the normal coordinates, cubic and semi-diagonal quartic force constants, <IT>φ</IT><SB><IT>ijk</IT></SB> and <IT>φ</IT><SB><IT>iijk</IT></SB>, can be obtained by numerical differentiation: If infrared intensities are desired, also dipole moment field needs to be evaluated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the dipole moment is a derivative of the energy with respect to the electric field, the equivalent of the quartic expansion of the potential is a cubic expansion of the dipole surfaces.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The second and third derivatives of dipole moment, <IT>d</IT><SB><IT>αij</IT></SB> and <IT>d</IT><SB><IT>αiij</IT></SB> (where <IT>α</IT> is a Cartesian component of the dipole moment vector <IT>d</IT><SB><IT>αj</IT></SB> referred to Eckart axes), are calculated in a manner analogous to the cubic and quartic force constants: Potential and dipole moment surfaces were calculated by the Density Functional Theory (DFT) approach using the B97-1 functional<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF> and a TZ2P basis set.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Calculations were performed using the Cadpac program package.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The step size δ<IT>Q</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB> was chosen such that it would correspond to an energy step of 1 m<IT>E</IT><SB>h</SB> on the harmonic potential surface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="None" advantage="None">A fuller discussion of the finite difference calculation, the effects of the step size, as well as values for the anharmonic constants may be found in .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">ref. 1</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The variational calculations were performed using the program MULTIMODE.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit9 cit10">8–10</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="None" advantage="None">This program performs vibrational self-consistent force field (VSCF) calculations, followed by the truncated Configuration Interaction (CI) expansion in virtual VSCF functions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">This has an advantage of explicitly treating all resonances among states included in the CI expansion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Terms coupling up to three normal coordinates were used in the VSCF Hamiltonian.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The CI expansion included all single, double, triple and quadruple VCI excited states with the sum of vibrational quantum numbers less than or equal to four.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Finally, the matrix elements <IT>R</IT><SB><IT>αij</IT></SB> were evaluated using the dipole moment surface <IT>D</IT><SB><IT>α</IT></SB>(<B><IT>Q</IT></B>) and the CI vectors <IT>Ψ</IT>(<B><IT>Q</IT></B>): <IT>R</IT><SB><IT>αij</IT></SB> = ∫<IT>Ψ</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB>(<B><IT>Q</IT></B>)<IT>D</IT><SB><IT>α</IT></SB>(<B><IT>Q</IT></B>)<IT>Ψ</IT><SB><IT>j</IT></SB>(<B><IT>Q</IT></B>)<IT>d</IT><B><IT>Q</IT></B>Second-order perturbation calculations were carried out using the program SPECTRO.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="None" advantage="None">While this program is capable of treating low-level resonances by removing the divergent terms and explicitly solving 2 × 2 CI problems (or by providing matrix elements for larger CI problems), second-order perturbation theory does not handle resonances involving states with the sum of vibrational quantum numbers being larger than 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="None" advantage="None">While there are many resonances present in the systems studied, none of the resonances are very strong.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, we decided not to include any resonances in the present perturbation calculations with SPECTRO.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">For more information about the programs MULTIMODE and SPECTRO and their use, see for example <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2">refs. 1 and 2</REF>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The infrared intensities of a <IT>v</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB> → <IT>v</IT>′<SB><IT>j</IT></SB> transitions were evaluated using the usual expression: where <IT>N</IT><SB>A</SB> is Avogadro's constant, <IT>ν</IT><SB><IT>a</IT></SB> is the wavenumber of the transition, and <IT>N</IT><SB><IT>v</IT></SB> is the fraction of molecules in the state <IT>v</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">If we assume an equilibrium distribution, then for the transitions originating from the ground vibrational state the term (<IT>N</IT><SB><IT>v</IT></SB> – <IT>N</IT><SB><IT>v</IT>′</SB>) tends to 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Evaluating the fraction and converting to practical units leads to a working formula with <IT>ν</IT><SB><IT>a</IT></SB> in cm<SP>–1</SP> and <IT>R</IT><SB><IT>αij</IT></SB> in debye.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This formula does not sum over hot and stimulated emission bands, which can all be treated explicitly.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">It also allows us to treat all kinds of transitions on an equal footing, which is especially important for variational calculations which mix transitions of various characters (<IT>e.g.</IT> fundamental, overtone, combination).</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.">Results and discussion</HEADER><P><s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The stick spectra representing vibrational transitions from the ground vibrational state, obtained by variational and perturbational calculations for furan and pyrrole, are compared with scaled experimental results of Mellouki <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF>. in Figs. 1 and 2, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since, to our knowledge, there is no consistent set of experimental infrared intensities for thiophene available, Fig. 3 compares only calculated results.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The peaks corresponding to fundamental transitions <IT>ν</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB> are labeled by <IT>i</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Transitions for which experimental intensities were not available are denoted with a star.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">It can readily be seen that the agreement between the stick spectra calculated by variational and second-order perturbation approaches is, in general, very good, especially for furan and thiophene.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">For pyrrole there are some disagreements, most notably for the states involving <IT>ν</IT><SB>16</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">As observed previously<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF> this mode shows large negative anharmonicity and is probably not adequately described by a quartic Taylor expansion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Also the density of states is higher for pyrrole, which leads to an increase in the number and strength of resonances.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">It seems that inclusion of resonances would be necessary for a proper perturbation description of intensities in pyrrole; however, this would eliminate much of the simplicity of the second-order perturbative approach, and this is one of its most attractive features.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">(A referee has observed that it is difficult to see from Figs. 2(a) and (b) that the variational treatment represents an improvement over the perturbational approach.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">We agree, but we anticipate that as the molecules become larger, as a force field becomes more complicated with more complicated resonances, the difference between the variational and perturbational spectra will become more marked.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">We underline a fact that only the variational approach can include all resonances, and therefore it must be recommended when it is possible.)</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the region above 2000 cm<SP>–1</SP> there are more states shown in the variational calculation panels than in the corresponding second-order perturbation calculation and experiment panels.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is due to the fact that MULTIMODE yields all states (as long as they are included in the CI expansion), while SPECTRO produces only states with the sum of vibrational quantum numbers less than or equal to two.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Higher excited states can be produced, but the quality of the results is not the same.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Also, only states which were properly assigned are included in the experimental panel.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">One of the consequences of the higher number of states and explicit treatment of all couplings in MULTIMODE are apparent in the lower intensities for high-frequency C–H and N–H stretches obtained from MULTIMODE, as compared with those obtained from SPECTRO.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In fact, all of these modes are strongly coupled to other modes, resulting in several modes each with lower intensity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, if a stick spectrum is replaced by gaussians with finite width, the summed intensities are comparable.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Comparison with experiment is complicated by the lack of firm experimental data.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Mellouki <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF>. published relative intensities for furan and pyrrole.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the authors caution that the data are not accurate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">For comparison with our stick spectra we have scaled the relative intensities of <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">ref. 12</REF> by factors of 22.2 for furan and 163 for pyrrole, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Despite the above mentioned uncertainties in the experimental spectrum, it can be seen that the correspondence between theoretical and experimental results is good for these two molecules.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">It can be observed that overtone and combination bands obtained from MULTIMODE are shifted towards higher wavenumbers with respect to those obtained from SPECTRO.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is due to the relatively small size of the CI.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">To calculate the wavenumbers of overtones it is necessary to include states with the sum of vibrational quantum numbers larger than four.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">A proper description of combination bands further requires the inclusion of quintuple excitations in the CI.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Nevertheless, the intensities of overtone and combination bands are in reasonable agreement with those obtained from SPECTRO and with the scaled experimental results.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.">Conclusions</HEADER><P><s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this paper we have demonstrated the success of the variational code MULTIMODE to predict integrated band intensities for molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">All one needs are quartic potential energy surfaces and cubic dipole surfaces, expanded in normal coordinates.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">An <IT>ab initio</IT> or DFT quantum chemistry code which calculates analytic second derivatives is also required.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The quality of our results is immediately apparent by comparing Fig. 1(a) (MULTIMODE) with Fig. 1(c) (experiment), for furan, and likewise Figs. 2(a) and (c) for pyrrole.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have every reason to expect that the MULTIMODE predicted spectra (Fig. 3(a)) for thiophene would be close to observation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The new feature of our science is its automatic capability of working beyond the double harmonic approximation, thus including anharmonicity, overtones and combination bands in our calculations.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Of course we have only looked at the wider detail.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our earlier studies show that frequencies determined by DFT are in error by 1%, and the calculated intensities are also only very approximate, and without fine structure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Even so, we believe that these qualitative spectra will be useful in molecular identification, at least.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">A caveat to these results is that ideally we should perform as large a CI as possible within MULTIMODE in order to ensure that the overtones and combination bands are fully converged.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The larger the molecule, the more mixing is present.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Finally, we are in the process of calculating ro-vibrational wavefunctions, from which band spectra can be obtained (for low <IT>J</IT>).</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
