<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b312115a" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">The S<SB>1</SB> neutral and D<SB>0</SB> cationic states of fluorobenzene and fluorobenzene–argon probed by ZEKE spectroscopy with partial rotational resolution</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Rotationally resolved zero electron kinetic energy (ZEKE) spectra of fluorobenzene and fluorobenzene–argon have been investigated using a spectator orbital model to interpret the rotational structure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Unlike a frozen core model this model relates to the electronic structure in both final and initial states.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">A new ZEKE electron detection scheme was employed to record <IT>ZEKE excitation spectra</IT> as a function of the S<SB>1</SB> ← S<SB>0</SB> excitation laser photon energy, with fixed photon energy of the ionization laser.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="None" advantage="None">These <IT>ZEKE excitation spectra</IT> are a sensitive probe of the rotational constants of all three states involved, the S<SB>0</SB> and S<SB>1</SB> of the neutral and the D<SB>0</SB> of the cation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rotational constants of the fluorobenzene cation were found to be <IT>A</IT><SP>+</SP> = 5406.8 ± 5.3 MHz, <IT>B</IT><SP>+</SP> = 2689.7 ± 3.5 MHz, and <IT>C</IT><SP>+</SP> = 1812.1 ± 1.8 MHz.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rotational constants for the argon complex were found to be <IT>A</IT>′ = 1773.3 ± 1.7 MHz, <IT>B</IT>′ = 1148.9 ± 1.4 MHz, and <IT>C</IT>′ = 996.83 ± 0.98 MHz in the intermediate S<SB>1</SB> state, and <IT>A</IT><SP>+</SP> = 1848.8 ± 1.8 MHz, <IT>B</IT><SP>+</SP> = 1076.6 ± 1.4 MHz, and <IT>C</IT><SP>+</SP> = 908.37 ± 0.89 MHz in the cationic D<SB>0</SB> state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Two structural parameters of the complex were derived from these rotational constants, the distance between the argon atom and the aromatic ring, <IT>r</IT><SB><IT>z</IT></SB> and the distance in the plane of the aromatic ring between the centre of mass and the argon atom <IT>r</IT><SB><IT>x</IT></SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">These two parameters were determined as <IT>r</IT><SB><IT>x</IT></SB> = 0.78 Å and <IT>r</IT><SB><IT>z</IT></SB> = 3.33 Å in the S<SB>1</SB> state and <IT>r</IT><SB><IT>x</IT></SB> = 0.36 Å and <IT>r</IT><SB><IT>z</IT></SB> = 3.76 Å in the D<SB>0</SB> state.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="1.">Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In many studies of the rotational structure of electronic excitations, it has not been possible to resolve individual rotational transitions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Despite this, the band profile for these transitions has often proved sufficient to obtain reliable rotational constants.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">A prime example comes from early rotational analyses of the S<SB>1</SB> ← S<SB>0</SB> spectrum of benzene<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF> that were successfully carried out using rotational band contour analysis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This study was able to demonstrate some of the effects of the high symmetry of benzene on the observed spectra.</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Presently, the use of rotational band contour analysis to obtain rotational constants from S<SB>1</SB> ← S<SB>0</SB> spectra has become a more or less standard spectroscopic technique.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2 cit3 cit4">2–4</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, for transitions from a neutral molecule to an ion core, such as observed in rotationally resolved ZEKE spectroscopy, the situation is much less clear.</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">For ionizing transitions or transitions to Rydberg states the selection rules for the change in angular momentum between the neutral and ionic states do not arise simply from the interaction with the photon.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Instead, angular momentum is transferred to the continuum or Rydberg electron in the final state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hence, in order to apply rotational band contour analysis to ZEKE spectra a model must be employed to account for the ionisation dynamics.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In rotationally resolved ZEKE spectroscopy, the selection rules for changes in total angular momentum between the neutral (<IT>J</IT>) and ionic rotational states (<IT>J</IT><SP>+</SP>) are not just given by Δ<IT>J</IT> = <IT>J</IT><SP>+</SP>–<IT>J</IT> = 0, ±1 since angular momentum can be transferred to the final state Rydberg electron.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6 cit7 cit8 cit9">5–9</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The conservation of angular momentum requires that the vector sum of the angular momenta involved, <IT>i.e.</IT> of the initial (neutral) rotational state (<IT>J</IT>), the photon (1), the final (ionic) rotational state (<IT>J</IT><SP>+</SP>) and the Rydberg electron (<IT>l</IT>) is equal to zero.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ammonia molecule was the first polyatomic molecule studied by ZEKE spectroscopy for which full rotational resolution in the cation was achieved.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10 cit11">10,11</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">This was followed by a study on the rotational structure of benzene.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In both cases, the selection rules that exist for these highly symmetric molecules were illustrated.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">To do this, a compound state was introduced as an intermediate between the initial and final states in the ZEKE transition, using this model, selection rules for allowed transitions could be deduced.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11 cit13">11,13</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The recorded spectra were found to be in good agreement with the symmetry selection rules that arise from the compound state model.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">A number of other models have been used previously to analyze the rotational structure in ZEKE spectra: Multichannel quantum defect theory (MQDT)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF> has been employed to predict the line intensities for the spectra arising from small molecules such as hydrogen<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF> and water,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF> where it was demonstrated to be a valuable tool, particularly with respect to final state interactions (<IT>i.e.</IT> rotational autoionization), which can have an additional effect on the intensities of ZEKE transitions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The role of autoionization in these smaller molecules is important.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, for larger molecules, the final state interactions are expected to even out,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF> and furthermore the parameters necessary for applying MQDT become harder to obtain as the molecular core becomes less atomic-like as in ammonia.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">A model by Wang and McKoy has been developed to analyse rotationally resolved ZEKE spectra.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19">19</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The method relies on <IT>ab initio</IT> calculations, which treat the final state wavefunction as the product between the ionic core and scattering wavefunctions found in the field of the ionic core.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The model has been applied to many, mainly diatomic, molecules and, most recently, the complex formed between sodium and water.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">This approach has given very good agreement for rotationally resolved ZEKE spectra and also for photoelectron spectra including their angular distributions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Also, the photoionization dynamics have been very successfully described in terms of bound-free one-electron radial matrix elements and phase shifts for the interpretation of angular photoelectron distributions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6 cit7 cit8 cit9">5–9</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">All this work has so far not been extended to larger molecular systems, in particular asymmetric rotor molecules and molecular clusters.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The spectator model, which is the method presented in this paper, has successfully been shown to reproduce the transition intensities in the fully rotationally resolved ZEKE spectra of benzene,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF> despite the fact that no account has been taken of the final state interactions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The model used here is also used to highlight interesting ionisation dynamics in the ZEKE spectroscopy of butylbenzene.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">In this paper, we present a novel approach to describe the ionization dynamics, based on a <IT>Rydberg-like spectator orbital</IT> description.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This spectator model is simple enough that it can be reliably applied to larger, asymmetric top molecules where final state interactions do not have a significant effect on the relative intensities of ZEKE transitions, and thus facilitate rotational band contour analysis of ZEKE spectra.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2 cit22 cit23 cit24 cit25">2,22–25</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fluorobenzene molecule is an ideal prototype molecule for spectroscopic studies in a supersonic jet expansion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The molecule has a relatively high vapour pressure, and hence it can be seeded into the jet without difficulty.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, the monosubstituted aromatic ring gives rise to strong electronic transitions to the S<SB>1</SB> state, which are symmetry allowed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fluorobenzene has been well characterised by spectroscopy in the S<SB>0</SB>, S<SB>1</SB> and the D<SB>0</SB> (cation) states.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26 cit27 cit28 cit29">26–29</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ground state rotational constants are available from microwave spectroscopy,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26">26</REF> whilst S<SB>1</SB> state rotational constants have been obtained using high-resolution laser induced fluorescence (LIF)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27">27</REF> spectroscopy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fluorobenzene cation has been studied using mass-analysed threshold ionisation (MATI) spectroscopy,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29">29</REF> but until now no rotational constants have been obtained for the cation.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Systems with simple structures such as fluorobenzene, stand as a useful test for the application of the spectator model to asymmetric tops; the equilibrium structure (and even the harmonic frequencies) of such molecules can generally be obtained with sufficient accuracy to reproduce experimentally determined rotational constants using electronic structure methods.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30 cit31">30,31</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, weaker interactions with shallow potential minima can be poorly reproduced by electronic structure methods as these interactions arise mainly from electron correlation, hence the rotational constants of weakly bound clusters are much more informative.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is therefore useful to show that the spectator model can be successfully applied in the study of weakly bound clusters; hence this study is also applied to fluorobenzene argon.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Many studies using complexes of argon with aromatic compounds have shown unambiguously from the band profile that, in a supersonic jet expansion, argon will preferentially bind above the aromatic ring.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2 cit32 cit33">2,32,33</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">These studies are also useful probes of how the argon binding changes on excitation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Typically, the argon is more closely bound in the excited state, which is reflected in a red shift from the monomer excitation to that in the complex (<IT>i.e.</IT> the vibrationless band origin appears to lower energy for the complex as opposed to the monomer).</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is indeed the case for fluorobenzene–argon,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit34">34</REF> whose structure is depicted in Fig. 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The two structural parameters, <IT>r</IT><SB><IT>z</IT></SB> and <IT>r</IT><SB><IT>x</IT></SB>, required to define the position of the argon atom are indicated in this figure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ground state of the complex has been studied using Fourier transform microwave spectroscopy by Stahl and Grabow.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit34">34</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Precise rotational constants were obtained, with the argon structural parameters evaluated as <IT>r</IT><SB><IT>z</IT></SB> = 355 pm and <IT>r</IT><SB><IT>x</IT></SB> = –46 pm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">These results are further supported by the <IT>ab initio</IT> work of Hobza <IT>et al.</IT>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit35">35</REF> which involved the use of an extended basis set for the argon atom ([7s4p2d]) to recover the correlation energy using the MP2 method.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Three intermolecular modes have been observed for fluorobenzene argon in the S<SB>1</SB> state using REMPI spectroscopy by Bieske <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit36">36</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The cation has been studied on three occasions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29 cit37 cit38">29,37,38</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">A vibrational progression in the <IT>b</IT><SB><IT>x</IT></SB> mode (see Fig. 1) was observed in the ZEKE spectra recorded by Shinohara <IT>et al.</IT>;<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit38">38</REF> a Franck–Condon analysis of this progression led to the conclusion that the argon atom was shifted by 7° along the bending coordinate on ionisation from the S<SB>1</SB> state; a calculation based on <IT>ab initio</IT> atomic charges in the neutral and the cation led to the conclusion that the argon moves toward the fluorine atom.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">A similar situation is observed with argon complexes with other electron withdrawing groups such as aniline<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit39">39</REF> and benzonitrile.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit40">40</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Given that the rotational constants of the monomer are known, it is possible to obtain zero-point vibrationally averaged values for the structural parameters <IT>r</IT><SB><IT>x</IT></SB> and <IT>r</IT><SB><IT>z</IT></SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Assuming the geometric structure of the monomer is not significantly perturbed by the presence of the argon atom,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit32">32</REF> the two structural parameters can be obtained by combining the two sets of rotational constants.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rotational band contour in ZEKE spectroscopy additionally reflects the electronic structure of the molecule; hence it is expected to give an indication of the perturbation of the electronic structure by the argon atom.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.">Theoretical details</HEADER><P><s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The main premise behind the spectator model, used to reproduce the ZEKE band contour, is to treat the initial state in the ZEKE transition (using a two photon ionisation scheme, this is the intermediate state) with an <IT>N</IT> electron wavefunction, <IT>Ψ</IT>′, as a Rydberg-like state, having a separate spectator electron coupled to the ionic core with <IT>N</IT> – 1 electron wavefunction, <IT>Ψ</IT><SP>+</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This arises as the first term in an expansion of the intermediate state wavefunction in terms of all the possible states of the ion, <IT>Ψ</IT><SB><IT>n</IT></SB><SP>+</SP>, and a single electron wavefunction, that arises from the projection of a given state of the ion on the intermediate state wavefunction eqn. (1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Only the first term in this expansion is important, as higher terms will not contribute to the intensity of the ZEKE transition, as they would have no overlap with the ionic wavefunction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Rydberg-like orbital in this initial state is therefore termed the spectator orbital, <IT>Ψ</IT>′<SB>s</SB>, which is obtained as the projection of the <IT>N</IT>–1 electron ionic core wavefunction, <IT>Ψ</IT><SP>+</SP>, on to <IT>Ψ</IT>′. </annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This expansion gives rise to a set of orbitals that are non-orthogonal, the spectator orbital is therefore quite different to the orbitals obtained in a Hartree–Fock calculation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">As the ionising photon interacts only with the spectator orbital (the ion core, <IT>Ψ</IT><SP>+</SP>, is already fully electronically relaxed) the ionisation process is effectively reduced from a complex multi-electron process to a single electron process.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Rotational angular momentum in the initial state can be decoupled into the angular momentum of the spectator electron and rotational angular momentum of the ionic core.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The various angular momenta are referred to according to the symbols listed in Table 1, corresponding to the symmetric top basis functions used to describe the asymmetric top wavefunctions.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The symmetry of the spectator electron is restricted to the product of the symmetry of the ionic core state and the initial state in the ZEKE transition (eqn. (2)) <IT>Γ</IT><SB><IT>Ψ</IT>′<SB>s</SB></SB> = <IT>Γ</IT><SB><IT>Ψ</IT>′</SB> ⊗ <IT>Γ</IT><SB><IT>Ψ</IT><SP>+</SP></SB></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This can be used to restrict the number of coefficients required to describe the spectator electron.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The values of the <IT>l</IT>′ and <IT>λ</IT>′ that are allowed are determined using symmetry correlation tables projecting the cylindrical group <IT>D</IT><SB>∞h</SB> onto the molecular symmetry group of the molecule in question.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the values depend upon the choice of <IT>z</IT>-axis, which can logically lie along any of the three principal inertial axes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The selection rules,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF> which arise from the triangle conditions of angular momentum coupling,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit41">41</REF> are given by eqn. (3).</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None"><IT>J</IT>′ + <IT>l</IT>′ ≥ <IT>N</IT><SP>+</SP> ⩾ |<IT>J</IT>′ – <IT>l</IT>′|,<IT>K</IT><SP>+</SP> = <IT>K</IT>′ – <IT>λ</IT>′</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">An advantage of the spectator model over the compound state model arises, because the symmetry selection rules are not dependent on the interaction of the photon to form the compound state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hence, only the symmetry of the spectator orbital needs to be considered.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, it should be noted that this is a limiting case, and in the spectator model, there is no allowance for the fact that the photon angular momentum can be transferred to the core.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The spectator model is an appropriate description; in a dynamic picture, the excited electron will not spend long in the core region after the interaction with the photon.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The expression for the two photon ZEKE transition intensity for an asymmetric top from this model can be shown to be given by eqn. (4).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The background for the derivation of eqn. (4) can be found in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11 cit42 cit43">refs. 11, 42 and 43</REF>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Any of the three inertial axes can be taken as the <IT>z</IT>-axis; for fluorobenzene, the <IT>c</IT>-axis is chosen in order to reflect the symmetry axis in the analogous benzene system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The model treats ionization as having occurred from an orbital produced by the projection of the cationic state electronic wavefunction onto that of the intermediate state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The expression for the transition intensities is dependent on the radial matrix elements, which relate to the angular distribution of the spectator orbital.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The radial matrix elements resolve effectively to a series of parameters, <IT>γ</IT>, which are dependent on only the angular momentum of the spectator electron, <IT>l</IT>′, and its projection <IT>λ</IT>′.</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the expression for the intensity the term <IT>γ</IT><SB><IT>l′λ′</IT></SB> appears, which carries information about the angular distribution of the spectator orbital from which ionisation occurs.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">These are the expansion coefficients, <IT>γ</IT><SB><IT>l′λ′</IT></SB> = 〈<IT>l′λ′</IT>|<IT>Ψ</IT>′<SB>s</SB>〉 = 〈<IT>l′λ′</IT><IT>Ψ</IT><SP>+</SP>|<IT>Ψ</IT>′〉.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The expression for the transition intensities, in terms of the ground state (S<SB>0</SB>) angular momentum, <IT>J</IT>″, the intermediate state (S<SB>1</SB>) angular momentum <IT>J</IT>′, the cationic angular momentum excluding electron spin<SUP TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" />, <IT>N</IT><SP>+</SP>, the population in the intermediate state, <IT>ρ</IT>, and the polarizations of the first and second photon, <IT>p</IT>′ and <IT>p</IT>″, is given by eqn. (4).</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In eqn. (4) the sums over <IT>K</IT><SP>+</SP> and <IT>K</IT>′ come from the expansion of the asymmetric rotor wavefunctions of the ion and the neutral in their respective symmetric rotor basis functions with expansion coefficients <IT>α</IT><SB><IT>K</IT><SP>+</SP></SB> and <IT>α</IT><SB><IT>K</IT>′</SB> and [<IT>l</IT>] ≡ [2<IT>l</IT> + 1]. </annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Expression (4) contains terms arising from <IT>k</IT> = 0, 1 and 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The non-zero values of <IT>k</IT> originate from the effect of polarization in the two-photon ionization process.</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The <IT>k</IT> = 1 term is non-zero only for circular polarizations (<IT>p</IT>″ = ±1 and <IT>p</IT>′ = ± 1) or crossed linear polarizations and is zero for linear parallel photon polarizations as used in the present experiments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The <IT>k</IT> = 2 term appears complicated, however, our calculations have shown that the <IT>k</IT> = 2 term is only about 5% of the <IT>k</IT> = 0 term and hence only makes a minor contribution when parallel linear photon polarizations are used in the experiment.</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the <IT>k</IT> = 2 term cannot be neglected when circular polarizations or crossed linear polarizations are used.</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Discarding the <IT>k</IT> = 2 term (and the <IT>k</IT> = 1 term) the transition probability becomes just the one-photon transition probability eqn. (5), which is a simple equation giving intensities that depend only on the values of <IT>γ</IT><SB><IT>l′λ′</IT></SB>. </annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The simplicity of eqn. (5) becomes apparent when considering the radial matrix elements <IT>R</IT><SB><IT>ll</IT></SB>′.</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the sum over <IT>λ</IT>′, <IT>K</IT><SP>+</SP>,<IT>K</IT>′ does not contain <IT>l</IT> (the Rydberg or continuum angular momentum) the sum over <IT>l</IT> can effectively be carried out, thus defining the parameters describing the ionization dynamics as solely the spectator orbital coefficients <IT>γ</IT><SB><IT>l</IT>′<IT>λ</IT>′</SB> and a constant radial part <IT>R</IT><SB><IT>l</IT>′</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this way, the Rydberg or continuum part of the problem has thus effectively been removed from the problem.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since fluorobenzene (FB) is an asymmetric top, the choice of <IT>z</IT>-axis for the spectator orbital angular momentum can be assigned to any of the three principal axes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">As with butylbenzene,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF> the <IT>c</IT>-axis, which is approximately perpendicular to the aromatic plane in FB, is chosen.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">(the <IT>a</IT> and <IT>b</IT>- axes both lie in the aromatic plane, respectively along and across the direction of the side chain).</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although a number of parameters are necessary to describe the spectator orbital, the values of <IT>l</IT>′ and <IT>λ</IT>′ determine the selection rules, hence each parameter will have a specific effect on the branch structure of the spectra, and can therefore be independently determined.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">If the first term in eqn. (1) were sufficient to describe the electronic structure of the intermediate state, the charge density difference between the cation and the intermediate state (<IT>i.e.</IT> |〈<IT>Ψ</IT>′|<IT>Ψ</IT>′〉|<SP>2</SP>–|〈<IT>Ψ</IT><SP>+</SP>|<IT>Ψ</IT><SP>+</SP>〉|<SP>2</SP>) would be an exact representation of the spectator orbital (<IT>i.e.</IT> |〈<IT>Ψ</IT><SP>+</SP>|<IT>Ψ</IT>′〉|<SP>2</SP>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None">As the first term of the expansion would not fully describe the electronic structure, the difference in charge density is an approximate representation of the spectator orbital that can be readily obtained using standard <IT>ab initio</IT> methods.</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">As an example the charge density difference between the S<SB>1</SB> state in fluorobenzene and the ground state fluorobenzene cation, calculated using the complete active space self-consistent field (CASSCF) method using eight electrons in the seven orbitals of aromatic character, is depicted in Fig. 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Scrutiny of the charge density difference reveals it to take both positive and negative values, indicating there are some regions where the electron density is in fact higher in the cation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The presence of the negative regions is highlighted in the plot of the charge density difference given in Fig. 3, which has been radially averaged about the centre of charge.</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is an indication of the approximate nature of this method for obtaining the spectator electron, as the negative parts can only arise as a consequence of the higher terms in the expansion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The shift in electron density, which for fluorobenzene accounts for less than 1% of the charge density difference, is reflected in a reduction in the overall intensity of ZEKE transitions independently of the rotational sublevels involved, as seen for two butylbenzene isomers.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit44 cit23">44,23</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Estimates for the parameters, <IT>γ</IT><SB><IT>l</IT>′<IT>λ</IT>′</SB>, were first obtained from an expansion about the centre of mass of the radially averaged electron density presented in Fig. 3 in angular momentum functions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">From these starting parameters the rotational structure in the ZEKE spectra was fitted to optimized parameters <IT>γ</IT><SB><IT>l</IT>′<IT>λ</IT>′</SB> by a least squares procedure using eqn. (5).</annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Then, eqn. (4) was employed for the final fit of the rotational structure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">It was found that when using the full two-photon transition formula the rotational band profile was still insensitive to the radial matrix elements <IT>R</IT><SB><IT>ll</IT>′</SB>, hence in the fit only <IT>γ</IT><SB><IT>l</IT>′<IT>λ</IT>′</SB> was optimised.</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is due to the minor contribution of the <IT>k</IT> = 2 term in eqn.(4).</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">This <IT>k</IT> = 2 term contribution is so insignificant that the weighting of the two radial matrix elements <IT>R</IT><SB><IT>l</IT>–1<IT>l</IT>′</SB> and <IT>R</IT><SB><IT>l</IT>+1<IT>l</IT>′</SB> cannot be obtained from the fit.</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">It should be noted, however, that this should be possible for measurements with crossed or circular polarizations for which the <IT>k</IT> = 2 (and, of course, the <IT>k</IT> = 1) term in eqn. (4) will be enhanced relatively to the <IT>k</IT> = 0 term.</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Also, it should be noted that there is always an uncertainty in the absolute sign of <IT>γ</IT><SB><IT>l</IT>′<IT>λ</IT>′</SB> obtained from either the electron density, or fitting to the spectra.</annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The only way to obtain the absolute sign of the parameters is to calculate the expansion coefficients directly, from the spectator orbital<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit45">45</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.">Experimental</HEADER><P><s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The experimental spectra presented were recorded using the apparatus described in .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit46">ref. 46</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both the S<SB>1</SB> ← S<SB>0</SB> transition and the ionising transition, in the monomer and the complex, were promoted using the frequency doubled output from two (Radiant Narrowscan) dye lasers, using Coumarin-153 dissolved in isopropyl alcohol, pumped by the third harmonic of the Nd:YAG (Continuum Surelite III) laser.</annotationART></s> <s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to accurately calibrate the lasers, each spectrum was recorded simultaneously with an iodine absorption spectrum.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fluorobenzene was introduced into the supersonic jet expansion by passing argon, at a stagnation pressure of 500 mbar, over a sample holder (containing fluorobenzene) situated outside the vacuum chamber.</annotationART></s> <s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fluorobenzene monomer was produced in the molecular beam with a rotational temperature of approximately 6 K. In order to produce fluorobenzene argon clusters in the source, the stagnation pressure of the argon was increased to 2 bar.</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">REMPI spectra were recorded using a 1 kV extraction pulse to accelerate the ions into the reflectron.</annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">ZEKE spectra were recorded synchronously with high resolution MATI spectra using the pulse sequence given in .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit46">ref. 46</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The discrimination field was set at 0.67 V cm<SP>–1</SP>, whereas the ionisation field was 0.33 V cm<SP>–1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The resolution obtained for the ZEKE spectra was found to be 0.27 ± 0.01 cm<SP>–1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ions were accelerated with a 1 kV extraction pulse, and the reflectron voltage was reduced to remove the kinetic energy compensation.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">A resonant two-photon ZEKE spectrum is in effect a two-dimensional spectrum; the signal depends both upon the energy from the excitation laser and the ionisation laser.</annotationART></s> <s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The excitation laser determines which subset of the rotational levels is populated prior to the ZEKE transition, and the ionisation laser determines the transition energy between the rotational levels.</annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, the rotational band structure forms a contour.</annotationART></s> <s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">An impression of the two-dimensional contour associated with fluorobenzene is given in Fig. 4; the width of the peaks is taken to be that expected under experimental conditions (excitation laser FWHM = 0.08 cm<SP>–1</SP>, ZEKE line width FWHM = 0.2 cm<SP>–1</SP>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">To record such a contour experimentally would be impractical due to the number of data points required.</annotationART></s> <s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, by obtaining a series of well calibrated spectra, scanning either the excitation laser to give a ZEKE excitation spectrum (corresponding to a horizontal slice from Fig. 4), or the ionising laser to give a conventional ZEKE spectrum (corresponding to a vertical slice from Fig. 4), the contour can be effectively sampled giving a greater amount of data with which to obtain fitting parameters than can be obtained simply by recording conventional ZEKE spectra.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.">Results and analysis</HEADER><P><s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The REMPI spectrum recorded for the origin band of the S<SB>1</SB> ← S<SB>0</SB> transition in fluorobenzene, with a simulation based on the rotational constants from <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27">ref. 27</REF> is shown in Fig. 5; the rotational temperature of the band was found to be 6.8 K, this was used as the temperature in all subsequent simulations for the monomer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The origin band of the D<SB>0</SB> ← S<SB>1</SB> transition was probed giving both ZEKE (Fig. 6) and ZEKE excitation (Fig. 7) spectra.</annotationART></s> <s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although all the band profiles presented were found to be reproducible, daily optimisation of the experimental conditions was found to subtly change the effective magnitude of the extraction field, which is seen as a small shift in the band origin of the MATI spectra, thus to remove the necessity of a separate parameter for the origin of each ZEKE spectrum, all the data presented had to be recorded in one sitting.</annotationART></s> <s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The four ZEKE spectra presented in Fig. 6 and the nine ZEKE excitation spectra presented in Fig. 7 were all able to be reproduced, in each case the ionising and excitation laser energies for all these spectra are indicated in the figure captions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The trend for the ZEKE band to get broader as the excitation laser is moved away from the band centre results from the fact that the higher <IT>J</IT> states probed have more widely spaced energy levels.</annotationART></s> <s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The apparently similar trend for the ZEKE excitation spectra is misleading, as the width of the band does not change.</annotationART></s> <s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The stronger signals from the centre of the band disappear, increasing the relative height of the high <IT>J</IT> wings of the P and R branches.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="143"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rotational constants and the spectator orbital coefficients, <IT>γ</IT><SB><IT>l</IT>′<IT>λ</IT>′</SB>, were simultaneously fit to all the experimental spectra using a least squares fitting procedure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="144"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The initial guess for <IT>γ</IT><SB><IT>l</IT>′<IT>λ</IT>′</SB> were obtained from the single centre expansion of the electron density difference, whereas <IT>ab initio</IT> values were used for the rotational constants.</annotationART></s> <s sid="145"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The symmetry restrictions on the values of <IT>l</IT>′ and <IT>λ</IT>′ depend on the symmetry of the spectator orbital and the choice of <IT>z</IT>-axis for the expansion of the spectator orbital.</annotationART></s> <s sid="146"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The symmetry of the S<SB>1</SB> state is A<SB>2</SB>, which corresponds to an S<SB>1</SB> ← S<SB>0</SB> transition moment polarised along the <IT>b</IT>-axis (the short axis in the plane of the molecule) the symmetry of the D<SB>0</SB> state is B<SB>1</SB>, hence according to eqn. (2), the spectator orbital must have b<SB>2</SB> symmetry.</annotationART></s> <s sid="147"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Taking the <IT>c</IT>-axis in fluorobenzene, which is perpendicular to the plane of the molecule, to be the <IT>z</IT>-axis means that b<SB>2</SB> symmetry correlates to values of <IT>l</IT>′ and <IT>λ</IT>′ such that odd values of <IT>l</IT>′ correspond to symmetric (+) combinations of even |<IT>λ</IT>′| (<IT>i.e.</IT> |<IT>λ</IT>′〉 + |–<IT>λ</IT>′〉) whereas, even values of <IT>l</IT>′ correspond to antisymmetric (–) combinations of odd |<IT>λ</IT>′| (<IT>i.e.</IT> |<IT>λ</IT>′〉 – |–<IT>λ</IT>′〉) these are denoted as <IT>λ</IT><SP>±</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="148"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The angular distribution of the radially averaged electron density difference was expanded to give the approximate values of the spectator orbital coefficients as listed in Table 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="149"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fitted values of <IT>γ</IT><SB><IT>l</IT>′<IT>λ</IT>′</SB> are listed alongside the calculated values in Table 2; the rotational constants obtained are listed in Table 3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="150"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The adiabatic ionisation potential of fluorobenzene was found to be 74227.09 ± 0.18 cm<SP>–1</SP>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="151"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rotational constants for the S<SB>1</SB> state of fluorobenzene argon were not available from previous literature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="152"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, values for the ground state rotational constants could be taken from the work of Stahl <IT>et al.</IT>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit34">34</REF> using which, a fit could be made to the experimental REMPI spectra yielding the S<SB>1</SB> state rotational constants.</annotationART></s> <s sid="153"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The experimental and simulated spectra are presented in Fig. 8; the simulation could not be relied upon to yield useful information as a wide range of parameters could be used to reproduce the spectrum equally well.</annotationART></s> <s sid="154"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ZEKE spectra presented in Fig. 9 were each recorded <IT>via</IT> the intermediate resonances as indicated in the figure caption.</annotationART></s> <s sid="155"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Each of the ZEKE excitation spectra given in Fig. 10 were recorded with the ionisation laser fixed at the energies indicated in the figure caption.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="156"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The simulations in Fig. 9 and Fig. 10 correspond to the optimised values of the <IT>γ</IT><SB><IT>l</IT>′<IT>λ</IT>′</SB> parameters listed in Table 4, which are listed against the values associated with the spectator orbital of the monomer, which differ from those listed in Table 2 as they had to be transformed, using rotation matrices, into the correct inertial frame.</annotationART></s> <s sid="157"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is necessary due to the fact that the argon atom does not necessarily bind above the centre of mass of the monomer causing the <IT>a</IT>-axis in the complex to deviate from the direction of the <IT>c</IT>-axis in the monomer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="158"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the inertial frame of the fluorobenzene argon complex, there are more contributions to the spectator orbital because the symmetry is reduced from B<SB>2</SB> (<IT>C</IT><SB>2v</SB>) in the monomer to A″ (<IT>C</IT><SB>s</SB>) in the complex.</annotationART></s> <s sid="159"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Taking the rotational constants obtained for the S<SB>1</SB> state of the complex from the REMPI spectrum it was found that the inertial frame is rotated by 25° about the <IT>b</IT>-axis of the monomer relative to the aromatic plane.</annotationART></s> <s sid="160"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the simulations in Fig. 9 the spectator orbital coefficients were optimised, allowing for the perturbation caused by the argon atom on the spectator orbital.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="161"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Values for the rotational constants in the S<SB>0</SB>, S<SB>1</SB> and D<SB>0</SB> states are presented in Table 5.</annotationART></s> <s sid="162"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Two values are given for the S<SB>1</SB> state; those obtained by fitting the REMPI spectra, and those obtained by fitting to the ZEKE excitation spectra.</annotationART></s> <s sid="163"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The band origin for the S<SB>0</SB> ← S<SB>1</SB> transition was found to be 37790.50 ± 0.04 cm<SP>–1</SP>, giving a field corrected<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit47">47</REF> adiabatic ionisation potential of 74003.99 ± 0.18 cm<SP>–1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="164"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the basis of the ZEKE excitation spectra, the rotational temperature in the molecular beam was 2.1 K.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="165"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Zero-point vibrationally averaged values for the structural parameters <IT>r</IT><SB><IT>x</IT></SB> and <IT>r</IT><SB><IT>z</IT></SB> are obtained by combining the experimentally obtained moments of inertia from the monomer with those from the complex.</annotationART></s> <s sid="166"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus <IT>r</IT><SB><IT>x</IT></SB> and <IT>r</IT><SB><IT>z</IT></SB> can be obtained.</annotationART></s> <s sid="167"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, for any given position of the argon atom there is an angle, <IT>θ</IT>, which represents the rotation of the principal axis system about the (monomer) <IT>b</IT> axis relative to the aromatic plane, this should not be confused with the <IT>b</IT><SB><IT>x</IT></SB> coordinate, which describes the asymmetric intermolecular bend.</annotationART></s> <s sid="168"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The values obtained for the S<SB>1</SB>and D<SB>0</SB> states are given in Table 6, along with those calculated for the ground state in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit34">ref. 34</REF></annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="5.">Discussion</HEADER><P><s sid="169"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the spectroscopy of the fluorobenzene cation, it may seem inappropriate to use the ZEKE excitation spectra as a basis for measuring the cationic rotational constants.</annotationART></s> <s sid="170"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, many advantages can be gained as a result of using these spectra.</annotationART></s> <s sid="171"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The dependence of the simulations on the rotational constants in the ion is illustrated in Fig. 11 and Fig. 12.</annotationART></s> <s sid="172"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="None" advantage="None">A series of ZEKE spectra recorded by scanning the excitation and ionisation lasers respectively are shown as a function of the <IT>A</IT> rotational constant, which is varied by 5% from the <IT>ab initio</IT> values obtained in the CASSCF calculation.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="173"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is apparent from Fig. 12 how the profiles of the spectra recorded by scanning the excitation laser have a much stronger dependence on the rotational constants.</annotationART></s> <s sid="174"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">This can be a significant advantage for experimental reasons.</annotationART></s> <s sid="175"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">It takes a shorter time to record these spectra as the signal to noise ratio is better.</annotationART></s> <s sid="176"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, the range of these spectra are shorter as signals correspond to the transitions in the S<SB>1</SB> ← S<SB>0</SB> transition, which is governed by the Δ<IT>J</IT> = 0, ±1 selection rule.</annotationART></s> <s sid="177"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">(The D<SB>0</SB> ← S<SB>1</SB> transition energy, which is fixed in these scans, covers a much broader range due to the possibility of higher angular momentum transfer) The fact that these spectra show a greater dependence on the rotational constants does not mean the ZEKE spectra recorded in the conventional manner (scanning the ionisation laser) are unnecessary.</annotationART></s> <s sid="178"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">The energy of the fixed laser is not calibrated introducing an uncertainty, which is addressed by having a combination of both ZEKE and ZEKE excitation spectra.</annotationART></s> <s sid="179"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, the branch structure of the conventional ZEKE spectra correlates directly with the spectator orbital parameters, which are needed to simulate the ZEKE excitation spectra.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="180"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reproduction of the ZEKE intensities for fluorobenzene using the spectator model does not appear to suffer from rotational state dependent autoionisation, as was observed for benzene.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="181"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">This may be due to the fact that there are too many bands overlapping in a given spectrum to notice the effect.</annotationART></s> <s sid="182"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the number of pathways for rotational autoionisation should be much higher from any given state in an asymmetric rotor as opposed to a symmetric rotor.</annotationART></s> <s sid="183"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, the cross-section for rotational autoionisation will not be so strongly state dependent.</annotationART></s> <s sid="184"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, it may still be expected that ZEKE signals arising from cations with a higher rotational angular momentum will be depleted to a greater extent by rotational autoionisation, or conversely, transitions into lower angular momentum states are enhanced more by pseudo autoionisation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="185"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None">This effect can be seen as the simulated ZEKE spectra exhibit stronger signals in the blue end of the spectrum than are seen in the experimental spectra.</annotationART></s> <s sid="186"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the analysis of the rotationally resolved ZEKE spectra of nitric oxide,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit48">48</REF> this was proposed as being a dominant effect on the ZEKE intensity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="187"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">The effect does not appear to be very significant, perhaps as consequence of the experimental conditions.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="188"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">The values obtained for the rotational constants are close enough to those from the <IT>ab initio</IT> calculation to assume that the calculated geometry is an accurate representation of the molecule.</annotationART></s> <s sid="189"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is unsurprising, as <IT>ab initio</IT> methods should work very well for smaller molecular systems such as fluorobenzene, which do not have any weak intramolecular interactions that can have an effect on the structure.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="190"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The values of <IT>γ</IT><SB><IT>l</IT>′<IT>λ</IT>′</SB> calculated from the electron density difference bear some relation to those obtained by fitting to the experiment.</annotationART></s> <s sid="191"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">The experimental uncertainty in the parameters is not as great as may be expected given the number of parameters present, as each value of <IT>γ</IT><SB><IT>l</IT>′<IT>λ</IT>′</SB> corresponds to a markedly different part of the profile: different values of <IT>l</IT>′ give rise to different Δ<IT>J</IT> selection rules, and different values of <IT>λ</IT>′ give rise to different Δ<IT>K</IT> propensities (that is preferred values Δ<IT>K</IT><SB><IT>a</IT></SB> and Δ<IT>K</IT><SB><IT>c</IT></SB>, or in the ZEKE spectroscopy of symmetric tops the Δ<IT>K</IT> selection rules).</annotationART></s> <s sid="192"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore the presence of these parameters does not really affect the uncertainty in the rotational constants.</annotationART></s> <s sid="193"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The former are a function of the energy of the transitions and the latter are a function of the intensity of the transitions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="194"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The mechanism through which the value of <IT>l</IT> affects the line intensity is down to the number of differently polarised final states that can be accessed with a given <IT>l</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="195"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hence, in order to reliably probe the values of the radial matrix elements, the rotational band profile can be studied as a function of the polarisation of the ionising and excitation lasers.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="196"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs19" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the fluorobenzene argon complex S<SB>1</SB> ← S<SB>0</SB> spectrum we encountered great difficulty in fitting the band contour.</annotationART></s> <s sid="197"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" advantage="None">A major reason for this is due to the congestion of the spectra limiting the number of resolved bands.</annotationART></s> <s sid="198"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs20" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the relatively large shift in the equilibrium position of the argon causes a rotation of the inertial axes by 17° between the S<SB>0</SB> and S<SB>1</SB> states (corresponding to a change in the <IT>b</IT><SB><IT>x</IT></SB> coordinate by 6.3°).</annotationART></s> <s sid="199"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs20" novelty="None" advantage="None">This gives rise to perturbations in the transition intensities by an effect referred to as axis tilting,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit49 cit50">49,50</REF> which has not been taken into account in the simulation of the S<SB>1</SB> ← S<SB>0</SB> transition.</annotationART></s> <s sid="200"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">As axis tilting only perturbs the intensities of transitions, the rotational transition energies are not affected; hence, the rotational constants obtained for the intermediate state using the much less congested ZEKE excitation spectra should be reliable.</annotationART></s> <s sid="201"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The effect of axis tilting on ZEKE intensities may be reflected in a perturbation of the spectator orbital, whereupon it will be compensated for by small changes in the spectator orbital coefficients.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="202"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None">The structural parameters derived from the rotational constants listed in Table 6 are consistent with structural changes that may be expected to occur.</annotationART></s> <s sid="203"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None">The change in the <IT>b</IT><SB><IT>x</IT></SB> bending coordinate of 7° between the S<SB>1</SB> state and the cation predicted in ref. <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit38">38</REF> from a Franck–Condon analysis is supported by the structures determined from the rotational coordinates, which indicate a change in the coordinate of 7.7°.</annotationART></s> <s sid="204"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None">The movement of the argon atom away from the fluorine atom on excitation can be attributed to an increased charge separation in the excited state, bringing about both an attraction to the positive charge in the aromatic ring region, and a repulsive interaction with the increased electron density in the region of the fluorine atom.</annotationART></s> <s sid="205"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None">Upon ionisation, the opposite effect is seen as the reduced negative charge causes the fluorine atom to exert a lesser repulsive force on the argon atom than in the S<SB>0</SB> and S<SB>1</SB> states.</annotationART></s> <s sid="206"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is consistent with the charge-induced dipole calculations carried out by Shinohara <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit38">38</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="207"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res29" novelty="None" advantage="None">The changes in the spectator orbital coefficients between the monomer and the complex are significant for four coefficients.</annotationART></s> <s sid="208"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res29" novelty="None" advantage="None">There is a reduction in the magnitude of the <IT>γ</IT><SB>31<SP>+</SP></SB> and <IT>γ</IT><SB>33<SP>+</SP></SB> coefficients, whereas there a significant increase is seen in the <IT>γ</IT><SB>55<SP>+</SP></SB> and <IT>γ</IT><SB>53<SP>+</SP></SB> coefficients.</annotationART></s> <s sid="209"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res29" novelty="None" advantage="None">All these contributions have a symmetry which would correspond to an imbalance between the electron density above and below the aromatic ring.</annotationART></s> <s sid="210"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res29" novelty="None" advantage="None">The combination of these changes indicates an increased probability of ionisation away from the centre of positive charge.</annotationART></s> <s sid="211"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">From this it is inferred that the presence of the argon atom causes an increase in the probability of ionisation from the region between the argon atom and the centre of positive charge in the cation.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="6.">Concluding remarks</HEADER><P><s sid="212"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">ZEKE spectroscopy of fluorobenzene and its complex with argon, <IT>via</IT> the S<SB>1</SB> intermediate states, yield rotational band contours that were successfully simulated using a Rydberg-like spectator orbital model.</annotationART></s> <s sid="213"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">By recording band profiles as a function of both the ionising and excitation lasers, reliable values for the cationic rotational constants can be obtained—even for a reasonably large molecular cluster.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="214"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The estimated angular momentum contributions were found to be a useful approximation to those found by obtaining fits to the experimental spectra.</annotationART></s> <s sid="215"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The method used to estimate these parameters could be improved upon by resorting to higher level configuration interaction <IT>ab initio</IT> methods.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="216"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of the complex, the difficulties in finding rotational constants in the S<SB>1</SB> state with REMPI spectroscopy are overcome by additional information on the S<SB>1</SB> ← S<SB>0</SB> transition available from ZEKE excitation spectra.</annotationART></s> <s sid="217"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The movement of the argon atom in transitions between the three states studied is consistent with previous studies and empirical calculations that have been carried out for the system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="218"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The effect of the argon atom on the spectator orbital is small but significant; the changes between the monomer spectator orbital projected into the inertial frame of the complex and those found for the complex can be reasonably accounted for as being a consequence of the perturbation of the electronic structure by the argon atom.</annotationART></s> <s sid="219"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, some of the observed changes in the spectator orbital coefficients may be reflecting the presence of axis-tilting transitions.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
