<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b313717a" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Studies on apparent molar volumes and heat capacities of several pluronics (triblock copolymers) in aqueous solutions of sodium dodecyl sulfate at 298.15 and 318.15 K<XREF TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" /></annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Density and heat capacity measurements were performed in order to investigate the interactions between the ionic surfactant sodium dodecyl sulfate (SDS) and some triblock copolymers of poly(ethylene oxide) and poly(propylene oxide), at 298.15 and 318.15 K. The pluronics L31, L35, 10R5, L64, F68 and P123, were selected as copolymers because of their convenient hydrophilic-hydrophobic ratio and critical micellar temperature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Molar volumes and heat capacities of transfer of either SDS or copolymer from water to an aqueous mixed solution were calculated from the density and heat capacity values and analysed as a function of the surfactant concentration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">It was found that the transfer properties depend mainly on the state of the copolymers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the unassociated copolymers, the molar volumes of transfer of both SDS and copolymer are positive.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The initial sharp increase seen in the corresponding plots against surfactant molality signals the formation of a surfactant-copolymer complex up to the saturation of the copolymer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thereafter, the constant values of transfer volumes of copolymers depend mainly on the length of the poly(propylene oxide) block.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the associated copolymers, negative volumes of transfer of either SDS or copolymer were observed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">They are ascribed to interactions between SDS and copolymer micelles that give rise to a rapid breakdown of the aggregates.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The profiles of the transfer heat capacity curves show more complicated trends through the critical micellar concentration region, which are interpreted as being due to the large positive contribution of the relaxation terms related to the equilibrium shifts induced by the temperature.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Water-soluble triblock copolymers poly(ethylene oxide)–poly(propylene oxide)–poly(ethylene oxide), currently abbreviated E<SB><IT>x</IT></SB>–P<SB><IT>y</IT></SB>–E<SB><IT>x</IT></SB>, are commercially available under the trade name “pluronics”.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">They are widely used in various industrial applications, especially in pharmaceutical formulations, cosmetics and food industry, because of their low toxicity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In aqueous solutions, they exhibit interesting structural and phase behaviour which have been investigated in many fundamental studies.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2 cit3 cit4 cit5 cit6 cit7 cit8 cit9 cit10 cit11 cit12">1–12</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The prominent interest of these copolymers lies in their flexible molecular architecture.</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">It can be modulated by varying the propylene oxide (PO)/ethylene oxide (EO) ratio and the molecular weight of each block and, therefore, gives rise to various structures in aqueous solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">From the viewpoint of chemical thermodynamics, their main interest consists in their complex aggregation behaviour in terms of their architecture, concentration and temperature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The self-assembly occurs above a critical micelle concentration (c.m.c.) and gives rise to micelles whose hydrophobic core is formed by weakly solvated poly(propylene oxide) (PPO) blocks and surrounded by an outer shell of fully hydrated poly(ethylene oxide) (PEO) chains.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The difference in hydration of EO and PO units is dependent on temperature and leads to a thermally reversible aggregation process.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">A small increase in temperature may result in a drastic decrease of c.m.c.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">This behaviour has led to the concept of critical micellar temperature (c.m.t.) which has been shown to be a very useful micellar parameter.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In many industrial applications of the copolymers, ionic surfactants are widely used in processes of commercial formulations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">They may associate into different microstructures that are likely to affect the functional properties of the systems.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, it is very important to study the interactions between the copolymers and the ionic surfactants which control the structural behaviour of mixtures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Recently, extensive studies were carried out using mainly calorimetry, emf- and <IT>T</IT>-jump measurements and several scattering techniques.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13 cit14 cit15 cit16 cit17 cit18 cit19 cit20 cit21 cit22 cit23">13–23</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Nevertheless, results are still scarce and available informations are far from being sufficient to understand the complex mechanisms of copolymer–surfactant interactions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Especially, few quantitative data concerning thermodynamic properties of these systems are presently available.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24 cit25 cit26 cit27 cit28">24–28</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Most studies were focused on mixtures of a well-known ionic surfactant, sodium dodecyl sulfate (SDS), with pluronics L64(E<SB>13</SB>P<SB>30</SB>E<SB>13</SB>),<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13 cit17 cit28">13,17,28</REF> F68(E<SB>75</SB>P<SB>30</SB>E<SB>75</SB>),<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF> F88(E<SB>100</SB>P<SB>39</SB>E<SB>100</SB>),<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15 cit24">15,24</REF> P123(E<SB>20</SB>P<SB>69</SB>E<SB>20</SB>)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15 cit22">15,22</REF> and F127(E<SB>97</SB>P<SB>69</SB>E<SB>97</SB>).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14 cit15 cit16 cit18 cit19 cit20 cit21 cit22">14–16,18–22</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">It was shown that the mechanism of interaction between surfactant and copolymer is specific of the systems where different binding modes of SDS have been observed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">These depend mainly on the structural state of the copolymer.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18 cit19 cit20 cit21 cit22">18–22</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the first mode, the interactions between monomers and SDS are similar to those between polymers (either PEO or PPO).</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Small SDS aggregates are bound onto the copolymer chain up to the saturation of the polymer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In so far as SDS is added, these bound aggregates are growing in size until the copolymer becomes saturated by normal SDS micelles.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the second mode, the interactions between SDS and copolymer micelles lead to the formation of mixed micelles followed by their progressive breakdown into smaller mixed aggregates.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The binding process continues until only pluronic monomers are remaining.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Isothermal titration calorimetry and differential scanning calorimetry proved to be very appropriate techniques for the study of polymer–surfactant interactions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18 cit19 cit20 cit21 cit22">18–22</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, a few other thermodynamic properties were investigated.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24 cit25 cit26 cit27 cit28">24–28</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">To the best of our knowledge, the most reliable studies are due to de Lisi <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25 cit26 cit27">25–27</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">They report measurements of volumes, heat capacities and enthalpies of mixing of aqueous mixtures of L64 and F68 with different surfactants.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Their primary aim consisted in studying the effects of the surfactant headgroups and of the ratio PO/EO of the copolymer on the interactions between monomers with surfactants, at 298.15 K.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26">26</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">These authors also investigated the behaviour of an associated copolymer in the sodium decanoate/L64 aqueous system.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27">27</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, at 298.15 K, L64 is still partially associated even at high concentrations.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The present contribution aims a better understanding of interactions in systems of ionic surfactants and copolymers showing different hydrophobic properties, as revealed by their thermodynamic properties.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">For this purpose, the volumetric properties and the heat capacities of the aqueous systems of ionic surfactant (SDS) + some copolymers were measured.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to perform a systematic study of both unassociated and associated copolymers at the same fixed low concentration, measurements were carried out far from the c.m.t. at 298.15 and 318.15 K. Our goal is to describe the effects of the copolymer architecture, namely the ratio PO/EO together with the mass of the PPO block.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Also, it is to determine the influence of the structural state of the copolymer on the intricate nature of the copolymer–surfactant interactions which determine the behaviour of these systems.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Experimental</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Materials</HEADER><P><s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Sodium dodecyl sulfate, SDS, was a pure grade reagent (&gt;99%) provided by Merck.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">It was used without further purification after drying under vacuum at a temperature below 330 K. Poly(ethylene oxide)<SB><IT>x</IT></SB>–poly(propylene oxide)<SB><IT>y</IT></SB>–poly(ethylene oxide)<SB><IT>x</IT></SB> triblock copolymers where <IT>x</IT> and <IT>y</IT> are the numbers of EO and PO units respectively (abbreviated to E<SB><IT>x</IT></SB>P<SB><IT>y</IT></SB>E<SB><IT>x</IT></SB> and P<SB><IT>y</IT></SB>E<SB><IT>x</IT></SB>P<SB><IT>y</IT></SB> for the “<IT>reverse</IT>” structure) are compounds whose trade names are Pluronic or Pluronic-R, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The selected pluronics, whose properties are summarized in Table 1, namely L31, L35, L64, F68, P123 and 10R5 (“<IT>reverse</IT>” of L35), were purchased from Aldrich.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Like SDS, the copolymers were used without further purification, since previous analyses have shown that the molar mass distribution has no significant influence on volumes or heat capacities, contrary to some other more sensitive techniques such as light scattering.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10 cit17 cit29">10,17,29</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">All solutions were prepared by mass at room temperature, with a precision of 0.1 mg, from copolymer and freshly deionised and degassed water samples.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The copolymer concentration is expressed in terms of molalities using an equation based on the mean molar mass and the PO/EO ratio of the copolymer provided by the manufacturer.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Apparatus and procedures</HEADER><P><s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The density measurements were performed at 298.15 and 318.15 K using a Picker vibrating tube flow densimeter (Model 03-D, Sodev Inc.), whose sensitivity is about 3 ppm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The temperature was controlled to within ±0.005 K by means of a closed-loop liquid circulation temperature controller (Model CT-L, Sodev Inc.).</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The densimeter was calibrated using deionised and doubly distilled water, whose densities were taken from literature<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30">30</REF> and vacuum.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The heat capacities by volume unit were measured by means of a Picker flow microcalorimeter (Setaram) at 298.15 K. It operates on the principle of a thermal balance at a constant flow rate of about 0.7 cm<SP>3</SP> min<SP>–1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The temperature increment was equal to about 0.5 K, using water as reference liquid.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Temperature was controlled in the same way as for density measurements.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The specific heat capacities were calculated from the density values of solutions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both apparatus, calibration and operating procedures have been previously described in detail.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit31 cit32">31,32</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The density and specific heat capacity measurements were assumed to be reproducible to within 3 × 10<SP>–6</SP> g cm<SP>–3</SP> and 5 × 10<SP>–4</SP> J K<SP>–1</SP> g<SP>–1</SP>, respectively.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Thermodynamic properties</HEADER><P><s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The apparent molar volumes, <IT>V</IT><SB><IT>φ</IT>,S</SB>, and heat capacities, <IT>C</IT><SB><IT>φ</IT>,S</SB>, of SDS in aqueous copolymer solutions at a fixed pluronic concentration were calculated from density, <IT>ρ</IT>, and specific heat capacity, <IT>c</IT><SB><IT>p</IT></SB>, using the following equations:<IT>M</IT><SB>S</SB> and <IT>m</IT><SB>S</SB> are the mean molar mass and the molality of SDS in the binary solvent, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None"><IT>ρ</IT> and <IT>c</IT><SB><IT>p</IT></SB> hold for the density and the specific heat capacity in the ternary systems, while <IT>ρ</IT><SB>o</SB> and <IT>c</IT><SB><IT>p</IT>,o</SB> are the corresponding properties in the aqueous copolymer solutions, respectively.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The apparent molar properties, <IT>V</IT><SB><IT>φ</IT>,P</SB> and <IT>C</IT><SB><IT>φ</IT>,P</SB> of the pluronic solute in the aqueous surfactant solutions are calculated using also eqns. (1) and (2) from the same density and heat capacity values of the ternary systems.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Here, <IT>M</IT><SB>P</SB> and <IT>m</IT><SB>P</SB> are the molar mass and the molality of the copolymer, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Molalities of the solutes, SDS and pluronic, need to be recalculated by taking into account the variation of concentration due to the change of the solvent (water + SDS) used as the liquid reference.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit33">33</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">For ternary systems, the molar properties of a solute are generally discussed in terms of the transfer properties (Δ<IT>Y</IT>) from water to binary solutions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">When the solute is transferred at the same concentration of either solution, Δ<IT>Y</IT><SB>P</SB> is calculated from the apparent molar properties <IT>V</IT><SB><IT>φ</IT>,P</SB> or <IT>C</IT><SB><IT>φ</IT>,P</SB> using the following relation:Δ<IT>Y</IT><SB>P</SB> = <IT>Y</IT><SB><IT>φ</IT>,P</SB>(water + SDS) – <IT>Y</IT><SB><IT>φ</IT>,P</SB>(water)When the molality of the solute is sufficiently low, the solute–solute interactions can be neglected.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">It ensues that the values of transfer quantities are mainly representative of solute–solvent interactions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">They characterize the distribution of the solute between the micellar and aqueous phases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">When their variations are plotted against the surfactant concentration, they clearly show the changes in micellar solution, especially when a transition occurs.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Results and discussion</HEADER><P><s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Apparent molar volumes of SDS, <IT>V</IT><SB><IT>φ</IT>,S</SB>, for the different aqueous pluronic solutions at a fixed composition (1 or 2% by mass) <IT>vs.</IT> the molality of SDS, <IT>m</IT><SB>S</SB>, have been calculated at 298.15 and 318.15 K, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Apparent molar heat capacities, <IT>C</IT><SB><IT>φ</IT>,S</SB>, <IT>vs.</IT><IT>m</IT><SB>S</SB> in the same solutions, were determined only at 298.15 K. For sake of consistency, the apparent molar volumes and heat capacities of SDS in pure water were calculated from separate runs at the same experimental conditions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Original experimental density and heat capacity values in the water/pluronic/SDS systems, are reported in the electronic supplementary information (ESI) together with the related apparent molar properties of SDS and molar transfer properties of pluronics.<SUP TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" /></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Depending on the nature of the pluronic or on the temperature, the changes of <IT>V</IT><SB><IT>φ</IT>,S</SB> against <IT>m</IT><SB>S</SB> are shifted towards higher or lower values compared to those in water.</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Volumes of transfer of SDS, Δ<IT>V</IT><SB>S</SB>, <IT>i.e.</IT> the difference between the values of <IT>V</IT><SB><IT>φ</IT>,S</SB> in aqueous pluronic solution and in water, are plotted against <IT>m</IT><SB>S</SB> at 298.15 and 318.15 K in Figs. 1 and 2, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Similar trends are observed for positive Δ<IT>V</IT><SB>S</SB> values.</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">A sharp maximum is observed at a molality lower than the c.m.c. of SDS in water (0.0083 mol kg<SP>–1</SP>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thereafter, Δ<IT>V</IT><SB>S</SB> is decreasing slowly and tends to zero, that is <IT>V</IT><SB><IT>φ</IT>,S</SB> merges with its value in water at higher SDS concentrations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Conversely, the negative Δ<IT>V</IT><SB>S</SB> values appear to be somewhat more dependent on both the nature of the pluronic and the temperature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 3 shows the plots of the transfer heat capacities, Δ<IT>C</IT><SB>S</SB>, <IT>vs.</IT><IT>m</IT><SB>S</SB> in the aqueous pluronic solutions, at 298.15 K. Large positive values are observed at a concentration far lower than the c.m.c.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The maximum cannot be defined because of the intrinsic accuracy of measurements.</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Afterwards, Δ<IT>C</IT><SB>S</SB> decreases steeply towards a flat negative minimum before it tends to zero, like the Δ<IT>V</IT><SB>S</SB> values.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">When the pluronic P123 is considered, the Δ<IT>C</IT><SB>S</SB> values are starting from large negative values and tend slowly to zero with increasing SDS concentration.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Typical plots of molar volumes of transfer of some pluronics from water to aqueous SDS solutions, Δ<IT>V</IT><SB>P</SB><IT>vs.</IT><IT>m</IT><SB>S</SB>, are reported in Figs. 4–6 at 298.15 and 318.15 K. Like the transfer volumes of SDS, the changes in Δ<IT>V</IT><SB>P</SB> can be either positive or negative.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 7 shows the trends in the molar heat capacities of transfer, Δ<IT>C</IT><SB>P</SB>, of some pluronics at 298.15 K. Beyond the c.m.c. the Δ<IT>C</IT><SB>P</SB> values are negative.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">For P123, Δ<IT>C</IT><SB>P</SB> is highly negative (see insert in Fig. 7).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In a previous study,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF> the interpretation of thermodynamic properties of the same copolymers in water allowed to characterize accurately their structural state in the concentration/temperature phase diagram.</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The different regions,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">2</REF> namely monomer species, monomers–micelles at equilibrium and micelles, were clearly identified.</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, at the considered concentrations, L31, L35, 10R5, L64 and F68 are in a monomeric state at 298.15 K, while P123 is partly associated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">At 318.15 K, the mostly hydrophilic pluronics, <IT>i.e.</IT> L35, 10R5 and F68, whose EO content is large, remain unassociated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The aggregation of L31 and L64 is thermally induced and their solutions contain both monomers and micelles at equilibrium.</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The hydrophobic P123, whose PO content is large, is fully micellized in aqueous solution.</annotationART></s></P><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>SDS/unassociated pluronic interactions</HEADER><P><s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The plots <IT>vs.</IT><IT>m</IT><SB>S</SB> of both transfer properties of SDS and pluronics are similar to those observed when nonionic polymers (PEG or PPO) are bound to SDS.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit34 cit35">34,35</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, a sharp initial increase of Δ<IT>V</IT><SB>S</SB> is observed at the lowest concentrations investigated in this work.</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">That means that the critical aggregation concentration (c.a.c.) is still lower.</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Δ<IT>V</IT><SB>S</SB> values exhibit rather similar profiles for the various aqueous solutions of unassociated copolymers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, some slightly different trends may be observed when scrutinising Figs. 1 and 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">For example, at 298.15 K, the maximum occurs at a lower SDS concentration when the PPO mass is larger, <IT>e.g.</IT> at <IT>m</IT><SB>S</SB> ≈ 0.004 mol kg<SP>–1</SP> for L64 or F68 (30 PO) and at <IT>m</IT><SB>S</SB> ≈ 0.008 mol kg<SP>–1</SP> for L31 or L35 (17 PO).</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Also, the width of the peak is quite enlarged with increasing pluronic concentration (1 and 2% L64).</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Likewise, increasing the temperature appears to have a minor effect, as evidenced by the plots of Δ<IT>V</IT><SB>S</SB> against <IT>m</IT><SB>S</SB> at 298.15 and 318.15 K for 10R5 and F68.</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The magnitude of the positive changes observed on Δ<IT>C</IT><SB>S</SB> curves in Fig. 3 is dependent on the hydrophobic character of the pluronic.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is also very sensitive to the pluronic concentration (1 and 2% L64).</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The area is getting larger and the following minimum is occurring at higher SDS concentrations, 0.02 and 0.04 mol kg<SP>–1</SP>, respectively.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The shapes of the changes of Δ<IT>V</IT><SB>P</SB><IT>vs.</IT><IT>m</IT><SB>S</SB> are also similar.</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Δ<IT>V</IT><SB>P</SB> shows a steep initial increase and then tends to an approximate plateau, whose values are dependent on the mass of the pluronic.</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Some values of the transfer quantities of pluronics are reported in Table 2 at two characteristic molalities of SDS, <IT>i.e.</IT> in the increasing part of Δ<IT>V</IT><SB>P</SB> and on the plateau.</annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">For L64 at 298.15 K (Fig. 5) and L35 at 318.15 K (Fig. 6), Δ<IT>V</IT><SB>P</SB> passes through a shallow maximum at concentrations beyond the c.m.c. of SDS.</annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Similar results were observed on parent systems (sodium decanoate + L64).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27">27</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 5 shows that this maximum is more smooth and shifted to higher <IT>m</IT><SB>S</SB> with increasing copolymer concentration (1% and 2% L64).</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">This maximum is probably due to the contribution of relaxation terms, as foreseen by current thermodynamic models,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit36 cit37 cit38 cit39 cit40">36–40</REF> because the experimental temperature is close to that of the onset of the thermally induced aggregation of the pluronic.</annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Interestingly, at 298.15 K, the increase of Δ<IT>V</IT><SB>P</SB> is identical for F68 and L64 whose number of PO units is equal.</annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Indeed, the same values are shown in Table 2, at the molality 0.015 m.</annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Similarly, the increase of Δ<IT>V</IT><SB>P</SB> is almost identical for F68 at 298.15 and 318.15 K. For the series of pluronics with 17 PO units (Figs. 4 and 6), the positive slope of Δ<IT>V</IT><SB>P</SB> is getting weaker.</annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this series, increasing EO content and temperature have also an effect on Δ<IT>V</IT><SB>P</SB> values, as shown in Table 2 by the different Δ<IT>V</IT><SB>P</SB> values at the molality 0.02 m.</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Similar features are observed in Fig. 7 about the dependence of molar transfer heat capacities on <IT>m</IT><SB>S</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Δ<IT>C</IT><SB>P</SB> exhibits a sharp maximum located at very low <IT>m</IT><SB>S</SB>, followed by constant negative values at higher <IT>m</IT><SB>S</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The more hydrophobic the pluronic, the more pronounced the initial maximum and the steeper the following decrease.</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The broadness of the peak is also largely dependent on the concentration of L64 and the decrease spans over a larger SDS concentration range.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">From a thermodynamic point of view, the composition dependence of the apparent molar or transfer quantities may be interpreted as the combination of various contributions arising from the equilibrium shifts in solution, due to either the addition of the solute or the temperature changes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The thermodynamic models that were used in order to explain the behaviour of hydrophobic solutes in the micellization processes of surfactants were related to either the mass action law or the pseudo-phase models.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit36 cit37 cit38 cit39 cit40">36–40</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The large positive Δ<IT>V</IT><SB>S</SB> or Δ<IT>V</IT><SB>P</SB> values in aqueous micellar solutions of pluronics include the terms related to the equilibrium shifts.</annotationART></s> <s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">They are characteristic of both the dehydration of the surfactant and the copolymer and the changes in the micellar structure arising from the formation of small SDS aggregates bound onto the copolymers.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit34 cit35">34,35</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The changing composition dependence of apparent molar or transfer heat capacities of SDS or pluronics arises from the fact that the heat capacity is a second derivative of the Gibbs free energy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this case, additional positive relaxation terms due to the temperature changes are expected.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit36 cit37 cit38">36–38</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the copolymer–SDS systems, these positive contributions occurring at the onset of the SDS binding appear to be quite large.</annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Upon further addition of SDS, their magnitude decreases steeply until it vanishes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Afterwards, the decrease of Δ<IT>C</IT><SB>S</SB> or Δ<IT>C</IT><SB>P</SB> arises from the hydrophobic interactions which develop throughout the association process.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Strong attractive interactions between SDS molecules and pluronic monomers have been evidenced by EMF and ITC measurements.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18 cit19 cit20 cit21">18–21</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">They lead to the formation of a stable copolymer–surfactant complex at a concentration well below the c.m.c. of SDS.</annotationART></s> <s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The increasing Δ<IT>V</IT><SB>S</SB> values can be related to the formation of these copolymer/SDS bound aggregates complexes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thereafter, upon further addition of SDS, the following decrease of Δ<IT>V</IT><SB>S</SB> is assumed to result from the increase of the aggregation number of the bound SDS micellar aggregates until normal micelles are bound onto copolymer chain.</annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The apparent molar properties of SDS are nearly equal to those in pure water, or else the transfer quantities tend to zero when the binding process is brought to its close.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The initial increase of Δ<IT>V</IT><SB>P</SB> reveals in the same way the formation of copolymer–surfactant complexes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is proceeding until the saturation of the copolymer is reached, <IT>i.e.</IT> when the solution is supposed to contain only mixed pluronic–SDS aggregates.</annotationART></s> <s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None">For example, the maximum for 1% L64 occurs at <IT>m</IT><SB>S</SB> = 0.018 mol kg<SP>–1</SP> (Fig. 5).</annotationART></s> <s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The resulting ratio SDS/L64 is close to 5, <IT>i.e.</IT> it is similar to either the composition of mixed aggregates deduced from fluorescence decay analysis on this system, namely 17–20 SDS and 4–5 L64 monomers,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF> or to the ratio found for a complex containing about four surfactant molecules bound on a copolymer chain.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16 cit27">16,27</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None">This maximum is shifted to 0.032 mol kg<SP>–1</SP> for 2% L64.</annotationART></s> <s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The same ratio, <IT>i.e.</IT> 5, is obtained.</annotationART></s> <s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The copolymer saturation occurs at quite similar <IT>m</IT><SB>S</SB> values for F68 monomers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">This means that about the same number of SDS molecules is bound to the pluronic.</annotationART></s> <s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">A lesser number of SDS molecules may be bound to pluronics having a shorter PPO block (17 PO units).</annotationART></s> <s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">It ensues that the copolymer gets saturated at larger <IT>m</IT><SB>S</SB>, where a quasi-plateau is reached at <IT>m</IT><SB>S</SB> &gt; 0.05 mol kg<SP>–1</SP> (Figs. 4 and 6).</annotationART></s> <s sid="143"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The same effects are prevailing for the molar transfer heat capacities (Fig. 7).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="144"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Further addition of SDS gives rise to more or less constant values of the transfer properties.</annotationART></s> <s sid="145"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Two separate groups of Δ<IT>V</IT><SB>P</SB> and Δ<IT>C</IT><SB>P</SB> values are reported in Figs. 4 and 7, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="146"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" advantage="None">They correspond to pluronics having about 17 PO and 30 PO repeat units.</annotationART></s> <s sid="147"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Some values are reported in Table 2 at a given SDS molality.</annotationART></s> <s sid="148"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" advantage="None">For species with 17 PO units, Δ<IT>V</IT><SB>P</SB> values are close to 20–26 cm<SP>3</SP> mol<SP>–1</SP> (Fig. 6), while for those containing 30 PO units, such as L64 or F68, they can reach 50 to 60 cm<SP>3</SP> mol<SP>–1</SP> (Figs. 4 and 5).</annotationART></s> <s sid="149"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Likewise, Fig. 7 shows that the Δ<IT>C</IT><SB>P</SB> values lie in the respective negative ranges 700–1000 J K<SP>–1</SP> mol<SP>–1</SP> and 2500–3000 J K<SP>–1</SP> mol<SP>–1</SP> for the above considered species.</annotationART></s> <s sid="150"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">These almost steady values let assume that the major contribution to the property is due to the hydrophobic interactions between SDS aggregates and PPO blocks.</annotationART></s> <s sid="151"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">A scrutiny of either Δ<IT>V</IT><SB>P</SB> or Δ<IT>C</IT><SB>P</SB> curves or of data reported in Table 2 provides some evidence of the less prominent role of the EO content.</annotationART></s> <s sid="152"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs20" novelty="None" advantage="None">When the PPO mass is equal, the increase of EO percentage is accompanied by an increase of volume, as shown in Fig. 6, and a decrease of Δ<IT>C</IT><SB>P</SB> (Fig. 7).</annotationART></s> <s sid="153"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">This may be due to an additive contribution of the interactions between the PEO chains and the SDS aggregates.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit34">34</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="154"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs21" novelty="None" advantage="None">No noticeable influence of the architecture of the copolymer on Δ<IT>V</IT><SB>P</SB> is observed when L35 is compared with 10R5 (Fig. 6).</annotationART></s> <s sid="155"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs21" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, this may result from the small size of the different blocks giving rise to a more expanded conformation of the chain.</annotationART></s> <s sid="156"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs22" novelty="None" advantage="None">Likewise, the Δ<IT>V</IT><SB>P</SB> values are independent on the pluronic concentration (<IT>cf.</IT> 1 and 2% L64 in Fig. 5).</annotationART></s> <s sid="157"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs22" novelty="None" advantage="None">As long as pluronics are exclusively in a monomeric state, Δ<IT>V</IT><SB>P</SB> is not so dependent on the temperature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="158"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs22" novelty="None" advantage="None">Such a trend is clearly visible in Fig. 4 where the curves for F68 are nearly superimposed at 298.15 and 318.15 K. For the 17 PO series (Fig. 6), although some difference is observed at lower <IT>m</IT><SB>S</SB> at these two temperatures, the Δ<IT>V</IT><SB>P</SB> curves join up all together at higher <IT>m</IT><SB>S</SB>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>SDS/associated pluronic interactions</HEADER><P><s sid="159"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs23" novelty="None" advantage="None">Negative values of the transfer properties of SDS and pluronics are generally observed when pluronics are existing in an aggregated state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="160"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs23" novelty="None" advantage="None">When they are partly associated (for instance, L64 at 318.15 K or P123 at 298.15 K), Δ<IT>V</IT><SB>S</SB> curves pass through a narrow positive maximum located below the c.m.c. of SDS (Figs. 1 and 2) whose magnitude is dependent on the concentration (1% and 2% for L64).</annotationART></s> <s sid="161"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs23" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thereafter, in their negative part, they intercept at 0.015 mol kg<SP>–1</SP>, superimpose and level off to zero with increasing SDS concentration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="162"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs23" novelty="None" advantage="None">For P123 at 318.15 K, when the aggregation process is supposed to be completed,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF> all of the Δ<IT>V</IT><SB>S</SB> values are negative while the minimum is shifted to a higher concentration, located at 0.02 mol kg<SP>–1</SP>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="163"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs24" novelty="None" advantage="None">The trends in Δ<IT>V</IT><SB>P</SB> are shown in Fig. 5 (L64 at 318.15 K) and in Fig. 4 (P123 at 298.15 K and 318.15 K).</annotationART></s> <s sid="164"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs24" novelty="None" advantage="None">For micellized P123 at 318.15 K, Δ<IT>V</IT><SB>P</SB> decreases until <IT>m</IT><SB>S</SB> is nearly equal to 0.04 mol kg<SP>–1</SP> and then remains constant.</annotationART></s> <s sid="165"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs24" novelty="None" advantage="None">When the pluronic is partly associated, a positive maximum may be observed at very low <IT>m</IT><SB>S</SB> values.</annotationART></s> <s sid="166"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs24" novelty="None" advantage="None">This peak is dependent on the ratio monomer/micelle in solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="167"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs24" novelty="None" advantage="None">The larger the amount of monomers, the greater the positive peak, as evidenced in Fig. 5 for 1% and 2% L64 at 318.15 K. It is very narrow for P123 at 298.15 K, for which Δ<IT>V</IT><SB>P</SB> is decreasing to still constant, albeit values are less negative than at 318.15 K (see Fig. 4).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="168"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs25" novelty="None" advantage="None">Tremendously large negative Δ<IT>C</IT><SB>p</SB> values are observed for P123 (–28 000 J K mol<SP>–1</SP>, as shown in the insert of Fig. 7).</annotationART></s> <s sid="169"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">They should be related to the contribution of the large enthalpy of micellization of P123, due to both the hydrophobic character of P123 (69 PO units) and the high degree of conversion of monomers into micelles.</annotationART></s> <s sid="170"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this case, this large contribution of the relaxation terms superimposes that one of the hydrophobic interactions (certainly lower than –8000 J K<SP>–1</SP> mol<SP>–1</SP>), if it is compared to that of copolymers having 30 PO units, like L64 or F68.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="171"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Previous investigations using several techniques (EMF, ITC, LS, SANS)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16 cit18 cit19 cit20">16,18–20</REF> have shown that SDS is bound to pluronic micelles and gives rise to the formation of mixed micelles.</annotationART></s> <s sid="172"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">The hydrophobic interactions between PPO and SDS are stronger than those between the PPO blocks, which involves the removal of bound water molecules from both the micellar surface and the copolymer chain.</annotationART></s> <s sid="173"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">The PPO–PPO interactions are weakened to a large extent while the SDS binding leads to a rapid breakdown of pluronic micelles, giving rise to smaller mixed aggregates of varying composition until only monomers are remaining.</annotationART></s> <s sid="174"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">Afterwards, the binding process follows the same way than for an unassociated copolymer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="175"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The binding of SDS to copolymer micelles gives rise to lower values of the apparent molar volume of SDS, <IT>i.e.</IT> to negative transfer volumes, since the neighborhood of the hydrocarbon chain of SDS is comparatively more hydrophilic in pluronic micelles than in SDS aggregates.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="176"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">Trends in transfer properties of pluronics have been interpreted as the result of simultaneous contributions of the two modes of binding of SDS with monomers and pluronic micelles.</annotationART></s> <s sid="177"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">A positive contribution is assumed to be due to the strong attractive hydrophobic monomer–SDS interactions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="178"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">As seen in the first part, this contribution is mostly independent on the temperature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="179"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">A negative contribution may be ascribed to the interactions between the SDS molecules and the pluronic micelles.</annotationART></s> <s sid="180"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this case, the PPO blocks are removed from their hydrophobic environment inside the micellar core towards the aqueous phase where their hydrophobic hydration is restored.</annotationART></s> <s sid="181"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">Consequently, this contribution appears to be related to the properties of rehydration of monomers and dependent on the equilibrium between monomers and micelles.</annotationART></s> <s sid="182"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, the decrease of Δ<IT>V</IT><SB>P</SB> may be due to the progressive disruption of pluronic micelles until their complete breakdown which occurs at <IT>m</IT><SB>S</SB> ≈ 0.04 mol kg<SP>–1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="183"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs26" novelty="None" advantage="None">When SDS is added beyond <IT>m</IT><SB>S</SB> ≈ 0.04 mol kg<SP>–1</SP>, only monomers remain present.</annotationART></s> <s sid="184"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs26" novelty="None" advantage="None">Then, small SDS aggregates are bound on the copolymer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="185"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs26" novelty="None" advantage="None">Their aggregation number increases while Δ<IT>V</IT><SB>P</SB> is mainly constant.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="186"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs26" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this concentration range, Δ<IT>V</IT><SB>P</SB> values for L64 are close to –32 cm<SP>3</SP> mol<SP>–1</SP> at 318.15 K, while the contribution for the sole interactions between the L64 monomer and the SDS micelles is nearly equal to +48 cm<SP>3</SP> mol<SP>–1</SP> at 298.15 K (Fig. 5 or Table 2).</annotationART></s> <s sid="187"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, the contribution arising from the disruption of L64 micelles can be estimated to be close to –80 cm<SP>3</SP> mol<SP>–1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="188"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">This value agrees well with that of the experimental change of the apparent molar volume of aggregation of 1% L64 at 318.15 K, which was previously found equal to +77 cm<SP>3</SP> mol<SP>–1</SP>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="189"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs27" novelty="None" advantage="None">For P123, Δ<IT>V</IT><SB>P</SB> values are less negative at 298.15 K than at 318.15 K (Fig. 4), because it depends on the ratio monomer/micelle in solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="190"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">For SDS concentrations higher than 0.04 mol kg<SP>–1</SP>, <IT>i.e.</IT> when pluronic micelles are assumed to be entirely broken up, the Δ<IT>V</IT><SB>P</SB> values should be decreasing with increasing temperature across the entire range of the thermally induced aggregation process.</annotationART></s> <s sid="191"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs28" novelty="None" advantage="None">It varies from the positive value ascribed to the sole contribution of interactions between pluronic monomers and bound SDS micelles (only monomers are present at <IT>T</IT> &lt; 293 K)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF> to a nearly constant negative value when the micellization of the pluronic is completed at <IT>T</IT> ≈ 308 K.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="192"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">From our previous results dealing with the volumes of aggregation of P123 in water,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF> the variations of apparent molar volumes corresponding to the aggregation of 1% P123 were considered to be equal to +210 cm<SP>3</SP> mol<SP>–1</SP> and +260 cm<SP>3</SP> mol<SP>–1</SP> at 298.15 and 318.15 K, respectively, if additivity laws are assumed to be valid for the volumes of pluronics in their monomeric state.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="193"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs29" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Δ<IT>V</IT><SB>P</SB> values plotted in Fig. 4 are nearly equal to –100 and –160 cm<SP>3</SP> mol<SP>–1</SP>, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="194"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" advantage="None">This means that the contribution to the volume of interactions between the P123 monomers and the bound SDS aggregates may be expected to lie within 100–110 cm<SP>3</SP> mol<SP>–1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="195"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since this contribution has been shown to be mainly dependent on the number of PO units in the PPO block and independent on the temperature, an estimate of +110 cm<SP>3</SP> mol<SP>–1</SP> may be expected for Δ<IT>V</IT><SB>P</SB> of the P123 monomer when compared with those of L35 (+25 cm<SP>3</SP> mol<SP>–1</SP>) and L64 (+48 cm<SP>3</SP> mol<SP>–1</SP>), whose EO percentage is quite similar.</annotationART></s> <s sid="196"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" advantage="None">This value agrees well with that obtained from measurements carried out at 288.15 K, where P123 is only in monomeric state<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit41">41</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Conclusion</HEADER><P><s sid="197"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">The apparent molar volumes and heat capacities of some water/copolymer(pluronic)/surfactant systems have been investigated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="198"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results obtained for the transfer properties of either SDS or pluronic have clearly shown the prominent role of the aggregation state of pluronics in solution on the interactions between copolymer and surfactant.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="199"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">When pluronics are in monomeric state, at low concentration range of SDS, the rapid increase in the molar volumes of transfer of SDS and pluronic points to the enhancement of strong interactions between monomers and SDS molecules leading to the formation of copolymer–surfactant complexes up to the saturation of the copolymer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="200"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thereafter, with increasing SDS concentration, the constant and positive values of the transfer volumes of pluronics reveal that the main contribution stems from hydrophobic interactions between PPO blocks and bound SDS aggregates.</annotationART></s> <s sid="201"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Consequently, the transfer volumes are mainly linked to the PPO mass in the pluronic molecule.</annotationART></s> <s sid="202"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">It was also found that they barely change with increasing temperature.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="203"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">A different behaviour is prevailing for the associated copolymers, for which negative values of transfer volumes are observed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="204"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">These should result from the rapid breakdown of pluronic micelles by SDS molecules, which form mixed aggregates until the pluronic micelles are fully disrupted.</annotationART></s> <s sid="205"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The values of the molar transfer volumes of pluronics are interpreted as resulting from two contributions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="206"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">A negative one may be due to the rehydration of PPO blocks when monomers are removed from copolymer micelles to the aqueous phase, while a positive one involves the hydrophobic monomer–SDS interactions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="207"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">It ensues that their balance is strongly linked to the monomer–micelle equilibrium and to the temperature effect on the aggregation progress in the aqueous pluronic solution.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="208"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Analysis of the corresponding molar heat capacities of transfer has revealed a similar behaviour.</annotationART></s> <s sid="209"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, close to the c.m.c. of SDS, the changes in the molar transfer heat capacities were found to be influenced to a large extent by the relaxation terms arising from temperature effects on association equilibria.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
