<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b314189f" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Details and consequences of the nonadiabatic coupling in the Cl(<SP>2</SP>P) + H<SB>2</SB> reaction</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In an investigation of nonadiabaticity in the Cl + H<SB>2</SB> reaction we examine the various coupling terms responsible.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">By neglecting various of these terms, we show that the spin–orbit coupling in the Cl atom is primarily responsible for non Born–Oppenheimer effects in this reaction, and that the anisotropies in the contributing electronic potential energy surfaces as well as Coriolis terms, are considerably weaker in their effect.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Neglect of all coupling except spin–orbit leads to little change in the calculated reaction probabilities both for the Born–Oppenheimer allowed [Cl(<SP>2</SP>P<SB>3/2</SB>) + H<SB>2</SB>] and Born–Oppenheimer forbidden [Cl(<SP>2</SP>P<SB>1/2</SB>) + H<SB>2</SB>] reactions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This implies that one can safely neglect the coupling between different values of the electronic projection quantum number <IT>ω</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Consequently, the computational effort involved in an accurate quantum scattering treatment of this (and, hopefully, other similar reactions) can be substantially reduced.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Because of their experimental accessibility, the reactions of F and Cl with H<SB>2</SB> and its isotopomers have become paradigms for triatomic abstraction reactions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2">1,2</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Experimental interest in the Cl + H<SB>2</SB> reaction goes back more than 100 years.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Numerous quasiclassical trajectory and various quantum scattering investigations have been reported<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3 cit4 cit5 cit6">3–6</REF> on several potential energy surfaces (PESs).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7 cit8 cit9">7–9</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Approach of the H<SB>2</SB> molecule to a Cl atom splits the degeneracy of the <SP>2</SP>P state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">As shown schematically in Fig. 1, two electronic states (1<SP>2</SP>A′ and 1<SP>2</SP>A″; <SP>2</SP>Σ<SB>1/2</SB><SP>+</SP> and <SP>2</SP>Π<SB>3/2</SB> in linear geometry) correlate adiabatically with the ground-state atomic reactant (<SP>2</SP>P<SB>3/2</SB>) while a third state (2<SP>2</SP>A′; <SP>2</SP>Π<SB>1/2</SB> in linear geometry) correlates adiabatically with the excited-state atomic reactant (<SP>2</SP>P<SB>1/2</SB>).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Of these, only the 1<SP>2</SP>A′ electronic state correlates with the electronic ground state of the products [HCl(X <SP>1</SP>Σ<SP>+</SP>) + H(<SP>2</SP>S)].</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The two other electronic states correlate with electronically excited states of the products [HCl(a <SP>3</SP>Π) + H(<SP>2</SP>S)] which are considerably higher in energy<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF> and, consequently, energetically inaccessible at low to moderate collision energies.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is common to assume that the motion of the atoms in a chemical reaction occurs on a single potential energy surface (PES).</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">This description is a consequence of the Born–Oppenheimer (BO) approximation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">For bimolecular reactive collisions this assumption is supported by the majority of past experimental work.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In recent molecular beam experiments, Liu and co-workers<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF> used two different Cl atom sources to separate the reactivity of the two SO states of the Cl atom.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Strikingly, except at the lowest collision energies, they conclude that the excited SO state has a significantly larger reactive cross section.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">As can be seen in Fig. 1, reaction of the spin–orbit excited Cl atom (<SP>2</SP>P<SB>1/2</SB>) can occur only by a non-Born–Oppenheimer transition from the non-reactive <SP>2</SP>Π<SB>1/2</SB> PES to the reactive <SP>2</SP>Σ+1/2 PES.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">When the two PESs are widely separated, there is little likelihood that this transition can occur.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hence, non-adiabaticity in the Cl + H<SB>2</SB> reaction, possibly to the extent suggested by the experiments of Liu and co-workers, must be a result of couplings between the various PESs in the entrance channel of the reaction.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Theoretical investigations of the role of excited electronic surfaces in the F + H<SB>2</SB> reaction date back to the pioneering work of Tully.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Several years ago, we presented the framework for the essentially exact quantum determination of cross sections for abstraction reactions involving an atom in a <SP>2</SP>P electronic state.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">This treatment involves six three-dimensional hypersurfaces, four of which describe the diabatic potential energy functions and two of which describe the coordinate dependence of the spin–orbit coupling.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">All Coriolis coupling terms are included.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">More recently, we applied<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF> this methodology to the reaction of Cl with molecular hydrogen, using new <IT>ab initio</IT> potential energy surfaces developed by Capecchi and Werner (the CW PESs).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Calculated integral cross sections for the non-Born–Oppenheimer reaction of the spin–orbit excited atom, which are a measure of the degree of non-adiabaticity in the reaction, were found to be markedly smaller than those for the Born–Oppenheimer allowed reaction of the ground spin–orbit state.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The degree of non-adiabaticity was even less than found in our earlier investigation of the F + H<SB>2</SB> reaction.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15 cit16">15,16</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is not surprising, since the spin–orbit splitting in the Cl atom (882.35 cm<SP>–1</SP> = 2.528 kcal mol<SP>–1</SP>) is more than twice as large as that of the F atom (404 cm<SP>–1</SP>).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Only at the lowest collision energies, where the ground-state channel is suppressed by the high barrier (Fig. 1), will reaction of the spin–orbit excited atom dominate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">These theoretical results stand in direct contrast to the conclusions of Liu and co-workers.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">This past year<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF> we have determined differential cross sections for the Cl + H<SB>2</SB> reaction.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Differential cross sections for the adiabatically-forbidden reaction of Cl* (<SP>2</SP>P<SB>1/2</SB>) are backward peaked, similar to those for reaction of the ground spin-obit state, but are much smaller in magnitude.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Because of the continuing disagreement between experiment<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF> and theory,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF> it is worthwhile to examine in more detail the factors which control the degree of non-adiabaticity in the Cl + H<SB>2</SB> reaction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Coupling between the adiabatically allowed and forbidden pathways is due to (<IT>i</IT>) the spin–orbit Hamiltonian, (<IT>ii</IT>) electronic mixing of the two states of A′ symmetry, and (<IT>iii</IT>) Coriolis coupling between the rotational motion of the nuclei and the spin and electronic-orbital angular momenta of the Cl atom.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="None" advantage="Yes">One great advantage of a theoretical simulation, as compared to experiment, is that each of these terms may be altered (or eliminated) in turn to allow their effect to be examined.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is the goal of the present article.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Hamiltonian, potential surfaces, and couplings</HEADER><P><s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">We write the total Hamiltonian for collision of Cl (<SP>2</SP>P) with H<SB>2</SB> (or any other diatomic) molecule as <IT>H</IT>(<IT>R⃑</IT>,<IT>r⃑</IT>,<IT>q⃑</IT>) = <IT>T</IT><SB>nuc</SB>(<IT>R⃑</IT>,<IT>r⃑</IT>) + <IT>H</IT><SB>el</SB>(<IT>q⃑</IT>;<IT>R⃑</IT>,<IT>r⃑</IT>) + <IT>H</IT><SB>so</SB>(<IT>q⃑</IT>;<IT>R⃑</IT>,<IT>r⃑</IT>).Here <IT>q⃑</IT> is a collective notation for the electronic coordinates, <IT>H</IT><SB>el</SB> is the electronic Hamiltonian, which, in the Born–Oppenheimer sense, depends parametrically on the positions of the three nuclei, and <IT>H</IT><SB>so</SB> is the spin–orbit Hamiltonian, which is not included in <IT>H</IT><SB>el</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The nuclear coordinates <IT>R⃑</IT> and <IT>r⃑</IT> in eqn. (1) designate the Jacobi vectors<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19">19</REF> in any one of the three chemical arrangements (Cl + HH, H + HCl, or HCl + H).</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In terms of the mass-scaled Jacobi coordinates <IT>S</IT> and <IT>s</IT>, one defines Delves hyperspherical coordinates <IT>ρ</IT> and <IT>θ.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19">19</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">At each value of the hyperradius <IT>ρ</IT> we expand the total wavefunction in an overcomplete basis of rotational-vibrational-electronic wavefunctions in each arrangement.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the Cl + H<SB>2</SB> arrangement there are six electronic states.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">For a halogen atom with a p<SP>5</SP> electron occupancy these states correspond to the three spatial orientations of the <IT>p</IT> hole and the two possible spin-projection quantum numbers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the HCl, the lowest excited state is of Π symmetry, and lies far above the ground state (X <SP>1</SP>Σ<SP>+</SP>) in the region of the molecular minimum.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">If we neglect these excited Π states, then, in each H + HX arrangement, we need retain only two states, which correspond to the HX molecule in its ground electronic state (<SP>1</SP>Σ<SP>+</SP>) combined with the two possible spin-projection quantum numbers of the H atom.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In each arrangement the basis functions are<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15 cit20 cit21">15,20,21</REF> Here <IT>J</IT> is the total angular momentum, with projection <IT>M</IT> along the space-frame <IT>z</IT>-axis and projection <IT>K</IT> along the Jacobi vector <IT>R⃑</IT> of the relevant arrangement.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The quantum number <IT>j</IT> designates the rotational angular momentum of the diatomic moiety in the same arrangement, with projection <IT>k</IT> along <IT>R⃑</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Here, also, <IT>D</IT><IT>J</IT>*<IT>MK</IT>(<IT>Ω</IT>) is a Wigner rotation matrix element,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF><IT>Y</IT><SB><IT>jk</IT></SB>(<IT>γ</IT>,0) is a spherical harmonic,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF> and <IT>φ</IT><SB><IT>vj</IT></SB>(<IT>θ</IT>;<IT>ρ</IT>) is the solution of a “vibrational” reference problem corresponding to motion in the hyperangle <IT>θ</IT> at the given (fixed) value of <IT>ρ.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The quantities <IT>λ</IT> and <IT>σ</IT> in eqn. (2) are the projection of the electronic orbital and spin angular momenta along <IT>R⃑</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since we consider here only doublet electronic states, the spin part of the wavefunction corresponds to <IT>s</IT> = 1/2 and <IT>σ</IT> = ±1/2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The projection quantum numbers are related as follows <IT>K</IT> = <IT>k</IT> + <IT>λ</IT> + <IT>σ</IT>.To solve the close-coupled reactive scattering equations, one must first construct surface functions in each sector,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20 cit24">20,24</REF> by diagonalizing the total Hamiltonian, exclusive of the kinetic operator corresponding to radial motion in the hyperradius <IT>ρ</IT>, in the multiple arrangement basis consisting of the states defined by eqn. (2).</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition to the electrostatic interaction potential and the spin–orbit Hamiltonian, it is also necessary to determine matrix elements of the orbital angular momentum <B><IT>L</IT></B><SP>2</SP> = (<B><IT>J</IT></B> – <B><IT>l</IT></B> – <B><IT>s</IT></B> – <B><IT>j</IT></B>)<SP>2</SP>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In evaluating the matrix elements of the electrostatic interaction potential one first integrates over the electronic coordinates to obtain formally 〈<IT>λ</IT>′<IT>σ</IT>′|<IT>H</IT><SB>el</SB>(<IT>q⃑</IT>;<IT>R</IT><IT>⃑</IT>,<IT>r⃑</IT>)|<IT>λ</IT><IT>σ</IT>〉 = δ<SB><IT>σσ</IT>′</SB><IT>V</IT><SB><IT>λ</IT>′<IT>λ</IT></SB>(<IT>ρ</IT>, <IT>θ</IT>, <IT>γ</IT>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Similarly, the matrix elements of the spin–orbit interaction potential involve the initial determination of the electronic matrix elements 〈<IT>λ</IT>′<IT>σ</IT>′|<IT>H</IT><SB>so</SB>(<IT>q⃑</IT>;<IT>R⃑</IT>,<IT>r⃑</IT>)|<IT>λ</IT><IT>σ</IT>〉 = <IT>W</IT><SB><IT>λ</IT>′<IT>σ</IT>′<IT>λσ</IT></SB>(<IT>ρ</IT>,<IT>θ</IT>,<IT>γ</IT>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Once these matrix elements, which are functions of the three internal coordinates, are evaluated, the scattering calculations are no different from that of a triatomic reaction on a single potential energy surface.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Capecchi and Werner<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF> used internally-contracted multi-reference configuration-interaction (IC-MRCI) calculations, based on state-averaged (three-state) complete active space self-consistent field (CASSCF) eference wavefunctions with very large atomic basis sets, to determine the three electronically adiabatic Cl + H<SB>2</SB> PESs in the reactant arrangement: 1A′, 2A′, and 1A″.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">These all correlate with Cl(<SP>2</SP>P) + H<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">These three adiabatic electronic states are the IC-MRCI approximations to the three lowest eigenfunctions of <IT>H</IT><SB>el</SB>, namely <IT>H</IT><SB>el</SB>(<IT>R⃑</IT>,<IT>r⃑</IT>;<IT>q⃑</IT>)<IT>ψ</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB>(<IT>R⃑</IT>,<IT>r⃑</IT>;<IT>q⃑</IT>) = <IT>E</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB>(<IT>R⃑</IT>,<IT>r⃑</IT>)<IT>ψ</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB>(<IT>R⃑</IT>,<IT>r⃑</IT>;<IT>q⃑</IT>), where the subscript <IT>i</IT> = 1,2,3 designates the |1A′〉, |2A′〉, and |1A″〉 states.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The coordinate dependence of the eigenvalues <IT>E</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB> defines the three adiabatic PESs.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">We define the interaction potential by subtracting the energies of the reactants at infinite Cl–H<SB>2</SB> separation, so that <IT>V</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB>(<IT>R⃑</IT>,<IT>r⃑</IT>) = <IT>E</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB>(<IT>R⃑</IT>,<IT>r⃑</IT>) – <IT>E</IT><SB>Cl</SB> – <IT>E</IT><SB>H<SB>2</SB></SB>(<IT>r</IT><SB>e</SB>).Here <IT>E</IT><SB>Cl</SB> designates the electronic energy of the Cl atom in its <SP>2</SP>P state exclusive of the spin–orbit Hamiltonian.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The zero of energy will be defined by the equilibrium internuclear separation of the H<SB>2</SB> molecule as determined in the IC-MRCI calculations, so that <IT>V</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB>(|<IT>R⃑</IT>| = ∞, |<IT>r⃑</IT>| = <IT>r</IT><SB>e</SB>) = 0,where <IT>r</IT><SB>e</SB> is the equilibrium internuclear separation of the H<SB>2</SB> molecule.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">By analysis of the coefficients in the CI expansion of the ClH<SB>2</SB> electronic wavefunctions, the two PES's of <IT>A</IT>′ reflection symmetry are transformed to an approximate diabatic basis,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25 cit26">25,26</REF> in which the orientation of the p hole on the Cl atom is fixed with respect to the plane defined by the three atoms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Here we take <IT>R⃑</IT> to define the <IT>z</IT>-axis and chose the <IT>y</IT>-axis to be perpendicular to the triatomic plane.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">We shall designate the diabatic states by the projections of the electronic orbital and spin angular momenta along <IT>R⃑</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">We use the compact Cartesian notation |Π<SB><IT>x</IT></SB>〉, |Π<SB><IT>y</IT></SB>〉, and |Σ〉.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The two adiabatic states of A′ symmetry correspond to a 2 × 2 rotation of the |Π<SB><IT>x</IT></SB>〉 and |Σ〉 diabatic states, namely whereHere the transformation angle <IT>ζ</IT> depends on <IT>R</IT>, <IT>θ</IT> and <IT>γ</IT> (or, equivalently, <IT>ρ</IT>, <IT>s</IT> and <IT>γ</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since there is no coupling between the |Π<SB><IT>y</IT></SB>〉 state, of A″ reflection symmetry, with the |Π<SB><IT>x</IT></SB>〉 and |Σ〉 states, of <IT>A</IT>′ reflection symmetry, the adiabatic and diabatic states of A″ reflection symmetry are identical.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Alternatively, we can define the diabatic states in terms of signed-<IT>λ</IT>, rather than Cartesian, projections, namely |Π<SB>1</SB>〉, |Π<SB>–1</SB>〉, and |Σ〉.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">These signed –<IT>λ</IT> states are those that appear above in the expansion of the scattering wavefunction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that the state we designate as “Σ” corresponds to <IT>λ</IT> = 0.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">As presented in detail in an earlier paper,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF> the matrix of the interaction potential, in the 6 × 6 basis defined by the three Cartesian diabatic states and the two possible spin projections (which are also defined with respect to <IT>R⃑</IT>) can be described in terms of three diagonal, electronically diabatic PES's: <IT>V</IT><SB><IT>xx</IT></SB>, <IT>V</IT><SB><IT>yy</IT></SB>, and <IT>V</IT><SB><IT>zz</IT></SB>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27">27</REF> as well as a fourth PES, <IT>V</IT><SB><IT>xz</IT></SB>, which is the coupling between the two states of <IT>A</IT>′ symmetry.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Each of these four PES's is a function of the three internal coordinates.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, the description of the interaction in the electronically diabatic basis, which involves these four potential energy functions, is equivalent to the description in the electronically adiabatic basis, which involves three potential energy surfaces (<IT>V</IT><SB>1A′</SB>, <IT>V</IT><SB>2A′</SB>, and <IT>V</IT><SB>1A″</SB>) plus the coordinate dependent mixing angle <IT>ζ</IT>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the basis of the signed-<IT>λσ</IT> states, which are used in eqn. (2) in the expansion of the scattering wavefunction, the matrix of the interaction potential, which we represented schematically as <IT>V</IT><SB><IT>λ</IT>′<IT>λ</IT></SB>(<IT>ρ</IT>,<IT>θ</IT>,<IT>γ</IT>) in eqn. (4), is Here, a bar over the state label designates a spin projection of –1/2 (<IT>β</IT> spin).</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The relation between the matrix elements in eqn. (11), and those determined by the <IT>ab initio</IT> calculations, which are carried out in a Cartesian basis, are <IT>V</IT><SB>Σ</SB> = <IT>V</IT><SB><IT>zz</IT></SB>, <IT>V</IT><SB>Π</SB> = (<IT>V</IT><SB><IT>yy</IT></SB> + <IT>V</IT><SB><IT>xx</IT></SB>)/2, <IT>V</IT><SB>2</SB> = (<IT>V</IT><SB><IT>yy</IT></SB> – <IT>V</IT><SB><IT>xx</IT></SB>)/2, and <IT>V</IT><SB>1</SB> = <IT>V</IT><SB><IT>xz</IT></SB>/2<SP>1/2</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In collinear geometry both <IT>V</IT><SB>1</SB> and <IT>V</IT><SB>2</SB> vanish.</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In perpendicular geometry <IT>V</IT><SB>1</SB> also vanishes while <IT>V</IT><SB>2</SB> goes through a relative minimum.</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Figs. (2) and (3) display contour plots of the four diabatic PES's (<IT>V</IT><SB>Σ</SB>, <IT>V</IT><SB>Π</SB>, <IT>V</IT><SB>1</SB> and <IT>V</IT><SB>2</SB>).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that the ordering of the states is here grouped by values of <IT>ω</IT> = <IT>λ</IT> + <IT>σ</IT>, and is consequently different form that chosen in our earlier paper.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">As seen in Fig. 1, four states correlate with the Cl(<SP>2</SP>P<SB>3/2</SB>) + H<SB>2</SB> reactant (<IT>ω</IT> = ±1/2 and <IT>ω</IT> = ±3/2).</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Only two states correlate with the Cl(<SP>2</SP>P<SB>1/2</SB>) + H<SB>2</SB> reactant (<IT>ω</IT> = ±1/2).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The matrix of the spin–orbit Hamiltonian is determined fully by two components,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26">26</REF><IT>A</IT>(<IT>R</IT>, <IT>r</IT>, <IT>θ</IT>) ≡ <IT>i</IT>〈Π<SB><IT>y</IT></SB>|<IT>H</IT><SB>so</SB>|Π<SB><IT>x</IT></SB>〉 and <IT>B</IT>(<IT>R</IT>, <IT>r</IT>, <IT>θ</IT>) ≡ 〈<SB><IT>x</IT></SB>|<IT>H</IT><SB>so</SB>|Σ〉, where The spin–orbit functions <IT>A</IT> and <IT>B</IT> can be determined in the <IT>ab initio</IT> calculations, along with the PESs.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The dependence of these on the reactant arrangement Jacobi coordinates are shown in Fig. 4.</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In terms of <IT>A</IT> and <IT>B</IT>, the matrix of the spin–orbit Hamiltonian in the |<IT>λσ</IT>〉 basis is If the <IT>V</IT><SB>1</SB> and <IT>V</IT><SB>2</SB> terms are neglected, then the electrostatic Hamiltonian [eqn.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">(11)] is diagonal in the <IT>λσ</IT> basis while the matrix of the spin–orbit Hamiltonian [eqn.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">(15)] is blocked into two identical 2 × 2 matrices and two single channels.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Consequently, the matrix of <IT>H</IT><SB>el</SB> + <IT>H</IT><SB>so</SB> in the <IT>ω</IT> = 1/2 (or equivalently, <IT>ω</IT> = –1/2) states, is At long, range, where <IT>V</IT><SB>Σ</SB> and <IT>V</IT><SB>Π</SB> vanish, this can be diagonalized by transforming to a coupled (<IT>j</IT><SB><IT>a</IT></SB><IT>ω</IT>) basis (where <IT>j</IT><SB><IT>a</IT></SB> is the total electronic angular momentum of the molecule), with energies –<IT>A</IT>/2 for the <IT>j</IT><SB><IT>a</IT></SB> = 3/2 states and +<IT>A</IT> for the <IT>j</IT><SB><IT>a</IT></SB> = 1/2 states.</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">As short range, where the splitting between <IT>V</IT><SB>Π</SB> and <IT>V</IT><SB>Σ</SB> is much larger than the spin–orbit constant, the Hamiltonian is approximately diagonal in the (uncoupled) <IT>λσ</IT> basis.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Early work on inelastic collisions of atoms in <SP>2</SP>P states has shown<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28">28</REF> that non-adiabatic transitions will take place predominately at the value of <IT>R</IT> where the difference between the diagonal terms in eqn. (16), which increases as the collision partners approach, becomes equal to the off-diagonal term.</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">At this point a frame transformation takes place.</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">This point (or two-dimensional seam in the three-dimensional ClH<SB>2</SB> PES) is marked by a heavy line in Fig. 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is in the neighborhood of this seam that the nonadiabatic transitions will occur, mixing the <IT>ω</IT> = ±1/2 states which correlate with Cl(<SP>2</SP>P<SB>1/2</SB>) and the <IT>ω</IT> = ±1/2 states which correlate with Cl(<SP>2</SP>P<SB>3/2</SB>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">We observe that this transition point occurs well outside the barrier to reaction.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Further, we observe from Fig. 3 that in the region of this seam both the <IT>V</IT><SB>1</SB> and <IT>V</IT><SB>2</SB> coupling potentials are considerably smaller than the off-diagonal spin–orbit coupling (2<SP>1/2</SP><IT>B</IT> ≅ 3.57 kcal mol<SP>–1</SP>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 5 compares the off-diagonal coupling in eqn. (16), the splitting between the diagonal terms, (<IT>V</IT><SB>Π</SB> + <IT>A</IT> – <IT>V</IT><SB>Σ</SB>), and <IT>V</IT><SB>1</SB>, as a function of <IT>R</IT> for the hydrogen molecule held at its equilibrium distance (1.4 bohr) and a fixed Jacobi angle of <IT>γ</IT> = 45°.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Finally, we observe, by comparing Figs. 2 and 4, that in the region of the seam in Fig. 2, where, presumably, nonadiabatic transitions are most likely to occur, the two spin–orbit terms are little changed from their asymptotic value.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">We see from matrices (11) and (16) that both the spin–orbit and electrostatic Hamiltonians can cause transitions between the spin–orbit excited reactant channel to the <IT>ω</IT> = ±1/2 and ±3/2 states which correlate with the ground spin–orbit reactant channel.</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, off-diagonal Coriolis coupling, which arises from the expansion of the orbital (end-over-end) angular momentum operator for the relative (end-over-end) motion of Cl with respect to H<SB>2</SB>, can also contribute to spin–orbit changing transitions.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since <B><IT>L</IT></B> = (<B><IT>J</IT></B> – <B><IT>l</IT></B> – <B><IT>s</IT></B> – <B><IT>j</IT></B>), one can show, that the effect of <B><IT>L</IT></B><SP>2</SP> on the |<IT>JMK</IT><IT>v</IT><IT>jkλσ</IT>〉 states of eqn. (2) is where, for simplicity, we have suppressed the <IT>J</IT>,<IT>M</IT>,<IT>v</IT>,<IT>j</IT> quantum numbers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Here, we define <IT>a</IT><SB>±</SB> ≡ 〈<IT>λ</IT> ± 1|<B><IT>l</IT></B><SB>±</SB>|<IT>λ</IT>〉.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Premultiplying by various 〈<IT>JMK</IT>′<IT>v</IT>′<IT>j</IT>′<IT>k</IT>′<IT>λ</IT>′<IT>σ</IT>′| states will give the matrix of the rotational Hamiltonian.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The first term in eqn. (17) is responsible for the diagonal matrix elements.</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The second, third and fourth terms, which all vary roughly linearly with <IT>J</IT>, will make a more significant contribution than the other terms, which are independent of <IT>J</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The former terms give rise to the matrix element This term is to be multiplied, of course, by 1/(2<IT>µ</IT><IT>R</IT><SP>2</SP>), where <IT>µ</IT> is the Cl–H<SB>2</SB> reduced mass (1.96 u).</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The third term in eqn. (18) is identical to the off-diagonal Coriolis term which appears in the standard centrifugally decoupled (coupled-states) treatment of atom-molecule collisions without electronic degrees of freedom.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29 cit30">29,30</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Because of the δ<SB><IT>λ</IT>′<IT>λ</IT></SB>δ<SB><IT>σ</IT>′<IT>σ</IT></SB> factor, this term will mix the two <IT>ω</IT> = 1/2 states which correlate with the two spin–orbit manifolds.</annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the region of the non-adiabatic mixing seam (Fig. 1), the magnitude of this term will be approximately 2.5 × 10<SP>–3</SP><IT>jJ</IT> kcal mol<SP>–1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The other two terms will have magnitudes approximately 2.5 × 10<SP>–3</SP><IT>J</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Consequently, since the rotational angular momentum of the H<SB>2</SB> molecule (<IT>j</IT>) will never be larger than 4 or 5, we predict that the contribution of the off-diagonal Coriolis coupling to nonadiabaticity in the Cl + H<SB>2</SB> reaction will be important only for total angular momentum <IT>J</IT> greater than about 25.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="None" advantage="Yes">As discussed in the introduction, theoretical simulation allows us to vary (or eliminate) one (or more) of these terms which contribute to the nonadiabaticity in the reaction and hence investigate the relative importance of these various terms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This will be explored in the next Section.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Calculations</HEADER><P><s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The time-independent, close-coupling calculations we use to investigate the scattering (both reactive and inelastic) of Cl by H<SB>2</SB> have been described in detail in several earlier publications.</annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod11" novelty="None" advantage="None">For each value of the hyperradius <IT>ρ</IT>, we expand the total scattering wavefunction as outlined by eqn. (2).</annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">A log-derivative method<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit31">31</REF> is used to propagate the solution numerically, from small <IT>ρ</IT> to large <IT>ρ</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The parameters which control the accuracy of the integration are increased until the desired quantities (transition probabilities, integral and/or differential cross sections) have converged to within a reasonable limit.</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="None" advantage="None">For abstraction reactions dominated by linear (or near linear) barriers, converged results can be obtained with only a few values of <IT>K</IT>, which greatly reduces the necessary computer time.</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod12" novelty="None" advantage="None">We use the ABC code of Manolopoulos and co-workers,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23 cit32">23,32</REF> extended to include the electronic degrees of freedom and multiple PESs.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6 cit15">6,15</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod12" novelty="None" advantage="None">To reduce further the number of basis functions which must be simultaneously considered, we use definite-parity linear combinations of the signed-<IT>K</IT> rotation–vibration–electronic basis functions (eqn. (2)).</annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Further reduction in the size of the basis can be made by using eigenfunctions of the H ↔ H interchange symmetry.</annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The propagation of the solutions to the CC equations are carried out entirely in the fully-uncoupled, body-frame basis of eqn. (2).</annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod12" novelty="None" advantage="None">At the end of the propagation, where all the PESs (<IT>V</IT><SB>Σ</SB>, <IT>V</IT><SB>Π</SB>, <IT>V</IT><SB>1</SB>, and <IT>V</IT><SB>2</SB>) are negligibly small, but before extraction of the <IT>S</IT> matrix, we transform the log-derivative matrix into a partially-coupled basis which diagonalizes the residual spin–orbit coupling [eqn.</annotationART></s> <s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod12" novelty="None" advantage="None">(16)].</annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod12" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this partially-coupled basis, the electronic states, which correspond to the Russell–Saunders spin–orbit states of the Cl atom, are labeled by the total electronic angular momentum of the atom, <IT>j</IT><SB><IT>a</IT></SB>, and the projection of <B><IT>j</IT></B><SB><IT>a</IT></SB> along <IT>R⃑</IT>, which we designate <IT>k</IT><SB><IT>a</IT></SB>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Figs. 6 and 7 display the total probability of reaction (summed over all energetically accessible rotational and vibrational states of the HCl products) as a function of collision energy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">These figures refer to reaction of H<SB>2</SB> in <IT>v</IT> = 0, <IT>j</IT> = 0 (the lowest state of <IT>para</IT>-H<SB>2</SB>) at the lowest possible value of the total angular momentum <IT>J</IT> = 1/2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results shown refer to states of positive overall parity; the results for the states of negative parity are virtually identical.</annotationART></s> <s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Results are shown for calculations with the full Hamiltonian, including all couplings (spin–orbit, electrostatic, and Coriolis) as well as from calculations in which we (a) eliminated <IT>V</IT><SB>1</SB> (the coupling between the two states of A′ reflection symmetry), (b) eliminated <IT>V</IT><SB>1</SB> and <IT>V</IT><SB>2</SB> (the coupling between the two Π states), (c) held the two spin–orbit constants to their asymptotic value (<IT>A</IT> = <IT>B</IT> = 2.52 kcal mol<SP>–1</SP>), or (d) eliminated all off-diagonal Coriolis coupling.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The probabilities for reaction out of the ground (<SP>2</SP>P<SB>3/2</SB>) and excited (<SP>2</SP>P<SB>1/2</SB>) spin–orbit states are shown separately in Fig. 6, and together in Fig. 7.</annotationART></s> <s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">As we have remarked earlier,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF> the stair-case structure in the energy dependence of the probabilities for reaction of Cl(<SP>2</SP>P<SB>3/2</SB>) correspond, in a transition-state model, to the opening of successively higher bend-stretch states of the ClH<SB>2</SB> complex at the transition states.</annotationART></s> <s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The position of the lower of these states is shown in Fig. 1.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">We observe that the results change little when the approximations discussed in the preceding paragraph are introduced.</annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Accurate reaction probabilities can be obtained by retaining only the spin–orbit coupling, and, further, without taking into account the small variation of these constants with the approach of the H<SB>2</SB> molecule.</annotationART></s> <s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">We might have anticipated this result from the discussion in the preceding Section.</annotationART></s> <s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the region where significant non-adiabatic transitions will occur, at the point where the off-diagonal spin–orbit coupling (2<SP>1/2</SP><IT>B</IT>) is equal to the splitting between the two <IT>ω</IT> = 1/2 states, the <IT>V</IT><SB>1</SB> and <IT>V</IT><SB>2</SB> coupling potentials are only a small fraction of this off-diagonal coupling.</annotationART></s> <s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">In reality, this relative size difference will be greater than is seen in the comparison of Figs. 3 and 5, because all Jacobi angles <IT>γ</IT> are sampled during the collision.</annotationART></s> <s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both <IT>V</IT><SB>1</SB> and <IT>V</IT><SB>2</SB> reach the maximum values shown in Fig. 3 at <IT>γ</IT> = 45° and decline sharply as <IT>γ</IT> goes to zero (where they both vanish) or to 90° (where <IT>V</IT><SB>1</SB> vanishes and where <IT>V</IT><SB>2</SB> goes through a local minimum).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None">We also observe that the off-diagonal Coriolis coupling contributes little to the nonadiabaticity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa3" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, since three of the off-diagonal Coriolis terms increase roughly linearly with <IT>J</IT>, it may be worthwhile to investigate the effect of neglecting the Coriolis coupling at higher values of the angular momentum.</annotationART></s> <s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 8 shows the dependence on the collision energy of the total reaction probabilities for several values of the total angular momentum.</annotationART></s> <s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The total reaction probability decreases with increasing <IT>J</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is a consequence of the the increasingly large centrifugal barrier which shifts the threshold to higher energy.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" advantage="None">To investigate the effect of increasing <IT>J</IT> on the validity of the approximations made earlier, we present in Fig. 9 plots of the total reaction probabilities out of H<SB>2</SB>(<IT>v</IT> = 0, <IT>j</IT> = 0), positive parity states at <IT>J</IT> = 17.5.</annotationART></s> <s sid="143"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although the spread in calculated transitions probabilities, as a function of the various simplifying approximations, is a bit larger than seen in Fig. 6 at <IT>J</IT> = 0.5, nevertheless, we see that the conclusion made earlier for <IT>J</IT> = 0.5 is still valid, namely that the degree of inelasticity in the Cl + H<SB>2</SB> reaction can be determined to a high degree of accuracy by neglecting all off-diagonal couplings other than the spin–orbit coupling.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Discussion</HEADER><P><s sid="144"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">As we have seen here, the overall degree of inelasticity in the Cl + H<SB>2</SB> reaction is governed, almost exclusively, by the spin–orbit coupling.</annotationART></s> <s sid="145"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">If the smaller <IT>V</IT><SB>1</SB> and <IT>V</IT><SB>2</SB> PESs, as well as Coriolis coupling, can be safely neglected, then the computational problem becomes considerably reduced.</annotationART></s> <s sid="146"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">We see from eqns. (11), (15), and (16), that neglect of <IT>V</IT><SB>1</SB> and <IT>V</IT><SB>2</SB> as well as the off-diagonal Coriolis coupling block-diagonalizes the coupling matrix into four blocks corresponding to the four possible values of <IT>ω</IT>(±1/2 and ±3/2).</annotationART></s> <s sid="147"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">For <IT>ω</IT> = ±1/2, the blocks, of dimension 2, are identical.</annotationART></s> <s sid="148"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">For <IT>ω</IT> = ±3/2 the blocks, also identical, are of dimension 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="149"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">One consequence is that the two <IT>ω</IT> = ±3/2 states, which correlate with the <SP>2</SP>Π<SB>3/2</SB> PES, will not contribute to reaction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="150"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is consistent with the validity of the approximation, used earlier by several groups,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit33">4,33</REF> that cross sections and rate constants for halogen-H<SB>2</SB> abstraction reactions determined from calculations on a single PES should be reduced by a factor of 1/2 to account for the flux which, in reality, is associated with the <IT>ω</IT> = ±3/2 states and hence follows the nonreactive <SP>2</SP>Π<SB>3/2</SB> PES.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="151"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">A second consequence is that the dimensionality of the quantum scattering calculation is reduced by a factor of 3, at least in the reactant arrangement, since one need include only two electronic states in the expansion of the wavefunction in eqn. (2), namely the state with <IT>ω</IT> = ±1/2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="152"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the difficulty of any close coupling calculation goes as the cube of the number of states (channels) included in the expansion of the wavefunction, this implies that the computational effort will be reduced by at least an order of magnitude.</annotationART></s> <s sid="153"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is not insubstantial.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="154"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Because the calculation of the overall reactivity of the excited spin–orbit state of Cl is insensitive to the neglect of Coriolis coupling, calculations of this can be carried out within the computationally faster centrifugal-decoupling (coupled states) approximation.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30">30</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="155"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">This will further decrease the computational effort, by block-diagonalizing the channel coupling into blocks of one value of <IT>K</IT>, the body-frame projection of the total angular momentum.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="156"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Finally, we see from the discussion in Section II, that nonadiabaticity in the Cl + H<SB>2</SB> reaction will be determined by the relative size of the spin–orbit constant (which can be considered a fixed number), and the splitting between the reactive and repulsive, nonreactive, PESs, particularly in the region where these two terms are equal in magnitude.</annotationART></s> <s sid="157"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the ClH<SB>2</SB> system, this occurs (Fig. 2) at a Cl–H<SB>2</SB> separation of roughly 6 <IT>a</IT><SB>0</SB>, very near the minimum in the van der Waals well for this system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="158"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The equilibrium geometry of the Cl–H<SB>2</SB> negative ion occurs in linear geometry at a Cl–H<SB>2</SB> separation of 5.7 <IT>a</IT><SB>0</SB>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit34">34</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="159"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Consequently, the recent photodetachment experiments of Neumark and co-workers<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit35">35</REF> will probe the ClH<SB>2</SB> PESs in exactly the region responsible for the nonadiabatic transitions which will contribute to the reactivity of Cl in its excited spin–orbit state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="160"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">As a result, a theoretical simulation of these experiments will provide an invaluable assessment of the accuracy of the CW PESs in this region.</annotationART></s> <s sid="161"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Work along these lines is already in progress.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
