<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b314070a" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Solvation properties and stability of ribonuclease A in normal and deuterated water studied by dielectric relaxation and differential scanning/pressure perturbation calorimetry</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">A change in solvent can have dramatic effects on the physico-chemical properties of a protein and its stability.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this paper we demonstrate by a study of solutions of the enzyme ribonuclease A (RNase A) in normal water (H<SB>2</SB>O) and deuterated water (D<SB>2</SB>O), to what extend a solvent isotopic substitution affects the structural and dynamic properties of a protein and its stability.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Differential scanning calorimetry (DSC) indicates a shift of the transition temperature from the native to the unfolded state from about 62 °C in H<SB>2</SB>O to 66 °C in D<SB>2</SB>O. Pressure perturbation calorimetry (PPC), a relatively new and efficient technique, is used to study the volumetric properties of RNase A in its native and unfolded state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In PPC, the coefficient of thermal expansion of the partial volume of the protein, <IT>α</IT>, is deduced from the heat consumed or produced after small isothermal pressure jumps (±5 bar).</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None"><IT>α</IT> and its temperature coefficient, d<IT>α</IT>/d<IT>T</IT>, strongly depend on the interaction of the protein with the solvent at the protein–solvent interface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both quantities are markedly affected by H<SB>2</SB>O/D<SB>2</SB>O substitution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Dielectric spectroscopy in the MHz and GHz regime is used to characterize the H<SB>2</SB>O/D<SB>2</SB>O isotope effect upon the tumbling time and dipole moment of the protein.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The analysis of the isotope effects gives evidence for a decrease of the dipole moment and hydrodynamic radius of the protein in D<SB>2</SB>O. An intriguing result is that the observed changes in thermodynamic properties reflect not only a stronger and more compact hydration in D<SB>2</SB>O, but also an increase in protein compactness.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">A similar result is obtained from dielectric relaxation experiments on another small globular protein, ubiquitin.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="1">Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Many protein functions are known to depend drastically on the structure and dynamics of the solvent.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2 cit3 cit4 cit5">1–5</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">For example, Fenimore <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF>. have distinguished between “slaved” and “non-slaved” protein processes, depending on whether they are coupled to the solvent fluctuations or not.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Because the coupling of the protein to the surrounding solvent bath is controlled by the properties of the protein–solvent interface, the characterization of protein hydration is essential for understanding these phenomena.</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This does not only require an understanding of the solvent effects upon the properties of the protein, but, <IT>vice versa</IT>, also of the effect of the protein, for instance the topology of the protein surface and its interfacial dynamics, on the solvent.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6 cit7 cit8">6–8</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The present paper aims at contributing to a more detailed understanding of protein hydration by investigating effects of H<SB>2</SB>O–D<SB>2</SB>O substitution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Isotopic substitution is used in many experiments on biomolecular systems to exploit properties of the deuterium nucleus not shown by protons, or to generate solute/solvent contrast.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">For example, the properties of the deuterium nucleus render D<SB>2</SB>O to be the solvent of choice in neutron scattering studies of protein and hydration<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3 cit9">3,9</REF> and in NMR studies of biomolecular and hydration dynamics.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10 cit11 cit12 cit13">10–13</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Deuterium is also used as a tracer, for instance, in kinetic studies of enzymatic reactions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thereby, it is commonly assumed that the biomolecular interactions are not modified by the solvent isotopic substitution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast, we focus here on the structural and dynamical changes associated with protein–water interactions in H<SB>2</SB>O and D<SB>2</SB>O, respectively, and their consequences for the thermodynamic properties of the system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">We consider the enzyme ribonuclease A (RNase A, 124 amino acids, molecular mass <IT>M</IT> = 13.7 kDa) as a prototypical protein used in many studies of protein folding.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">RNase A is a single-domain pancreatic enzyme protein which catalyses the cleavage of single-stranded RNA.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Its crystal<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF> and solution<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF> structure comprise three helices and a large β-sheet region.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is known since a long time that H<SB>2</SB>O–D<SB>2</SB>O substitution increases the thermal unfolding temperature of RNase A.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Such temperature shifts are found with other proteins as well.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18 cit19 cit20 cit21">18–21</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Some additional measurements were also performed, for comparison, for the small globular protein ubiquitin (76 amino acids, <IT>M</IT> = 8565 Da).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">At the molecular level, H<SB>2</SB>O–D<SB>2</SB>O isotope effects result from the fact that deuterium bonds in water are stronger than hydrogen bonds, because the larger mass of the deuteron lowers the zero-point vibrational energy of the intermolecular modes.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22 cit23">22,23</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The resulting increase in the solvent structure of D<SB>2</SB>O and in D<SB>2</SB>O–D<SB>2</SB>O affinity reveals itself in distinct isotope effects on the thermodynamic and dynamical properties of pure water and aqueous solutions of simple solutes.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rationale is that the increase in solvent structure causes a stronger solvation of hydrophilic and a less efficient solvation of hydrophobic species.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In protein solutions, such effects might cause polypeptides to reduce their solvent exposure by adopting a more compact shape or by associating into larger aggregates.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19 cit25 cit26 cit27 cit28">19,25–28</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">This conjecture does not only explain the observed temperature shifts of unfolding transitions, but also the promotion of protein aggregation in D<SB>2</SB>O.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27 cit28">27,28</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, such an interpretation is not unambiguous, and by a detailed analysis of entropy and enthalpy contributions, some authors have come to the opposite conclusion that the native protein should be destabilized by D<SB>2</SB>O.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20 cit21">20,21</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Important information on properties of the protein–water interface can also be deduced from volumetric properties.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">For example, it has been shown that the apparent thermal expansion coefficient, <IT>α</IT>, of the protein and its temperature coefficient, d<IT>α</IT>/d<IT>T</IT>, are drastically influenced by protein–solvent interactions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">By a rather new and sensitive technique called pressure perturbation calorimetry (PPC), <IT>α</IT>(<IT>T</IT>) can now be measured with very high precision.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29 cit30 cit31">29–31</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In PPC, the coefficient of thermal expansion of the protein is deduced from the heat consumed or produced after small isothermal pressure jumps.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Using this technique, we have recently studied the solvation properties RNase A in its native and unfolded state in the presence of several chaotropic and kosmotropic co-solvents.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30">30</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the course of these studies we have found that the substitution of H<SB>2</SB>O by D<SB>2</SB>O has drastic effects on the volumetric properties, indicating a stabilization of the native form in D<SB>2</SB>O. In the present work, we reconsider these isotope effects in more detail, and probe local isotope effects at the protein–water surface by dielectric relaxation experiments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Dielectric relaxation in the MHz region is a standard technique for studying the structure and dynamics of protein solutions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit32 cit33">32,33</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Recent extensions over a broader frequency band up to the GHz regime<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit34 cit35">34,35</REF> and data evaluation assisted by molecular dynamics (MD) simulations<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit36 cit37">36,37</REF> considerably increase its power.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2">Methods</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Samples</HEADER><P><s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Solutions of bovine pancreatic RNase A (Sigma Chemical Co.) were prepared with 10 mM Na<SB>2</SB>HPO<SB>4</SB> buffer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The experiments in H<SB>2</SB>O were performed at pH = 5.5, at which DSC traces indicated the highest stability of the native form.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Solutions in D<SB>2</SB>O (Aldrich, D-content &gt; 99.9 atom-%) were adjusted to the same proton activity as in H<SB>2</SB>O. This implies that the value of pD, <IT>e.g.</IT> recorded by a conventional glass electrode was 5.9 (<IT>i.e.</IT> pH + 0.4).</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Lyophilized and essentially salt-free ubiquitin from bovine red blood cells (Fluka, protein content &gt; 90%) was dissolved in buffer-free H<SB>2</SB>O and D<SB>2</SB>O solutions.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>DSC and PPC experiments</HEADER><P><s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The thermal unfolding of RNase A in H<SB>2</SB>O and D<SB>2</SB>O was measured by means of a high precision VP DSC micro-calorimeter (MicroCal, Northamption, MA, USA).</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The same instrument, supplemented by the MicroCal PPC accessory, was used in the PPC experiments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Experimental details can be found in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29 cit30">refs. 29 and 30</REF>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">As the PPC technique is comparatively new, a brief description is given here.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">PPC measures the heat consumed or released by a sample after small isothermal pressure jumps.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the differential PPC experiment two cells of equal volume (here 0.5 mL), containing the protein solution and the buffer, are subject to the same pressure jump.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In a decompression step, a pressure of 5 bar (here 5 bar by using nitrogen) is applied and is then released to ambient pressure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">After equilibration, the gas is used to initiate a compression step.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">During the pressure jumps, constant temperature is achieved by active compensation of the heat changes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Integration of the supplied power yields the heat released or consumed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The heat peaks in the compression and decompression steps should be equal in value, but are of opposite sign.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thermodynamics relates the pressure coefficient (∂<IT>Q</IT><SB>rev</SB>/∂<IT>p</IT>)<SB><IT>T</IT></SB> of the heat <IT>Q</IT><SB>rev</SB> exchanged in a reversible process to the coefficient of thermal expansion, <IT>α</IT> = (1/<IT>V</IT>)(∂<IT>V</IT>/∂<IT>T</IT>)<SB><IT>p</IT></SB>, of the sample volume.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">For a sufficiently dilute solution containing <IT>m</IT><SB>S</SB> grams of solute and <IT>m</IT><SB>0</SB> grams of solvent, the volume is given by <IT>V</IT> = <IT>m</IT><SB>0</SB><IT>V</IT><SB>0</SB> + <IT>m</IT><SB>S</SB><IT>V̄</IT><SB>S</SB>, where <IT>V</IT><SB>0</SB> is the specific volume of the solvent and <IT>V̄</IT><SB>S</SB> the partial specific volume of the solute.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">One then finds (∂<IT>Q</IT><SB>rev</SB>/∂<IT>p</IT>)<SB><IT>T</IT></SB> = −<IT>TVα</IT> = −<IT>T</IT>[<IT>m</IT><SB>0</SB><IT>V</IT><SB>0</SB><IT>α</IT><SB>0</SB> + <IT>m</IT><SB>S</SB><IT>V̄</IT><SB>S</SB><IT></IT><SB>S</SB>].<IT>α</IT><SB>0</SB> = (1/<IT>V</IT><SB>0</SB>)(∂<IT>V</IT><SB>0</SB>/∂<IT>T</IT>)<SB><IT>p</IT></SB> and <IT></IT><SB>S</SB> = (1/<IT>V̄</IT><SB>S</SB>)(∂<IT>V̄</IT><SB>S</SB>/∂<IT>T</IT>)<SB><IT>p</IT></SB> are the coefficients of thermal expansion associated with the solvent volume and the solute partial volume, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In a differential PPC experiment, the volume occupied by the solute in the sample cell, <IT>m</IT><SB>S</SB><IT>V̄</IT><SB>S</SB>, is replaced by the same volume of solvent in the reference cell.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Within small pressure intervals, the pressure dependence of <IT>V</IT> and <IT>α</IT> can be neglected, and eqn. (1) can be integrated to yield the working equation Δ<IT>Q</IT><SB>rev</SB> = −<IT>T</IT>[<IT>m</IT><SB>S</SB><IT>V̄</IT><SB>S</SB><IT></IT><SB>S</SB> − <IT>m</IT><SB>S</SB><IT>V̄</IT><SB>S</SB><IT>α</IT><SB>0</SB>]Δ<IT>p</IT> Then, <IT></IT><SB>S</SB> can be determined, if <IT>α</IT><SB>0</SB> is known.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In practice, it is a good approximation, to replace the partial specific quantities <IT></IT><SB>S</SB> and <IT>V̄</IT><SB>S</SB> by the corresponding apparent quantities, in the following denoted by <IT>α</IT> and <IT>V</IT>, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, all volumetric properties refer to apparent molar volumes and apparent expansibilities of the protein.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Dielectric relaxation</HEADER><P><s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Dielectric spectroscopy monitors the real part (dielectric dispersion <IT>ε</IT>′(<IT>ω</IT>)) and imaginary part (dielectric loss <IT>ε</IT>″(<IT>ω</IT>)) of the complex dielectric permittivity of a sample as a function of the angular frequency <IT>ω</IT> = 2π<IT>ν</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Accounting processes in the optical and vibrational regime by an effective limiting value <IT>ε</IT><SB>∞</SB> of the real part, the complex dielectric permittivity is given by<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit32 cit33 cit38">32,33,38</REF><IT>ε</IT>*(<IT>ω</IT>) = <IT>ε</IT>′(<IT>ω</IT>) − i<IT>ε</IT>″(<IT>ω</IT>) = <IT>ε</IT><SB>∞</SB> + Δ<IT>ε</IT>′(<IT>ω</IT>) − iΔ<IT>ε</IT>″(<IT>ω</IT>) + <IT>σ</IT>/i<IT>ε</IT><SB>0</SB><IT>ω</IT> (i<SP>2</SP> = −1).<IT>ε</IT>″(<IT>ω</IT>) shows a low-frequency divergence which depends on the static (dc) conductivity, <IT>σ</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The latter contribution can be determined at low frequencies, where only the <IT>σ</IT>/i<IT>ε</IT><SB>0</SB><IT>ω</IT> term survives.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None"><IT>ε</IT><SB>0</SB> is the permittivity of the vacuum.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The relaxational contributions, Δ<IT>ε</IT>′ and Δ<IT>ε</IT>″(<IT>ω</IT>), depend on the same set of microscopic parameters.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the first set of experiments, we used the network analyzer 8712 ES from Agilent Technology (former Hewlett Packard) in combination with a coaxial line terminating in a home-made sample cell described by Kaatze and coworkers<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit39">39</REF> to measure <IT>ε</IT>*(<IT>ω</IT>) in the range from <IT>ν</IT> = 1 MHz to <IT>ν</IT> = 1.3 GHz.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the second series, the network analyzer HP 8720 (Hewlett Packard) was used at 200 MHz ≤ <IT>ν</IT> ≤ 20 GHz in combination with the commercially available probe HP 85070B.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3">Results and data evaluation</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>DSC results</HEADER><P><s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 1 shows the background-corrected DSC traces of the buffered RNase A solution in H<SB>2</SB>O and D<SB>2</SB>O at a protein concentration of 0.5 wt.%.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In H<SB>2</SB>O, the protein begins to unfold at about 55 °C, and the temperature of the unfolding midpoint is <IT>T</IT><SB>m</SB> = (62.0 ± 0.2) °C.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Table 1 summarizes the resulting thermodynamic data.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The enthalpy change, obtained by integration over the DSC peak, is Δ<IT>H</IT> = (435 ± 4) kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The increase in the apparent molar heat capacity from the native to the unfolded state, Δ<IT>C</IT><SB><IT>p</IT></SB> = (5.2 ± 0.2) kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> K<SP>−1</SP>, is typical for proteins in H<SB>2</SB>O. Substitution by D<SB>2</SB>O shifts <IT>T</IT><SB>m</SB> to (66.2 ± 0.2) °C.</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The enthalpies of unfolding in H<SB>2</SB>O by D<SB>2</SB>O are almost the same, but Δ<IT>C</IT><SB><IT>p</IT></SB> in D<SB>2</SB>O is only about half of that in H<SB>2</SB>O.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>PPC results</HEADER><P><s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 1 shows that the maxima in <IT>C</IT><SB><IT>p</IT></SB> at the unfolding transition correspond to minima in the temperature dependence of the apparent thermal expansion coefficient, <IT>α</IT>(<IT>T</IT>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None"><IT>T</IT><SB><IT>m</IT></SB> values extracted from the PPC curves agree within experimental error with those determined from the DSC traces.</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Volumetric data derived from the PPC curves are summarized in Table 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the native regime the PPC curves in both H<SB>2</SB>O and D<SB>2</SB>O show two major features: First, the apparent thermal expansion coefficient, <IT>α</IT>, of the protein is high, for example <IT>α</IT><SB>10</SB> = 0.76 × 10<SP>−3</SP> K<SP>−1</SP> at 10 °C in H<SB>2</SB>O. Second, there is a steep slope in the temperature dependence of <IT>α</IT>(<IT>T</IT>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In H<SB>2</SB>O between 10 and 40 °C <IT>α</IT> decreases almost linearly with a slope d<IT>α</IT>/d<IT>T</IT> = −4.3 × 10<SP>−6</SP> K<SP>−2</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The curve of <IT>α</IT>(<IT>T</IT>) in D<SB>2</SB>O lies above that of H<SB>2</SB>O, and <IT>α</IT> is more steeply decreasing with increasing temperature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Quantitatively, <IT>α</IT> in D<SB>2</SB>O is by about 17% higher than in H<SB>2</SB>O, and the negative slope, d<IT>α</IT>/d<IT>T</IT>, is enhanced by 46% (Table 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In both H<SB>2</SB>O and D<SB>2</SB>O, <IT>α</IT> increases upon unfolding.</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The increase, Δ<IT>α</IT> = 1.6 × 10<SP>−4</SP> K<SP>−1</SP>, is typical for proteins.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The relative volume change upon unfolding can be calculated by integration of the <IT>α</IT>(<IT>T</IT>) transition curve after baseline subtraction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In H<SB>2</SB>O, we obtain Δ<IT>V</IT>/<IT>V</IT> = −2.7 × 10<SP>−3</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Based on the partial specific volume of RNase A (0.704 mL g<SP>−1</SP>), the absolute volume change is Δ<IT>V</IT> = −26 mL mol<SP>−1</SP>, which amounts to 0.27% of the total protein volume.</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In D<SB>2</SB>O, the volume change is 40% below the value found for H<SB>2</SB>O (Table 1).</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Dielectric relaxation data</HEADER><P><s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have determined dielectric relaxation spectra of solutions of RNase A (1.5 wt.%) and ubiquitin (2.5 wt.%) in H<SB>2</SB>O and D<SB>2</SB>O at 25 °C.</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The RNase A concentration was chosen as a compromise between the desire to reproduce the conditions of the PPC experiments and the need for sufficient amplitudes of the protein peaks in the spectra.</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 2 shows as an example the real and conductivity-corrected imaginary parts of the permittivity of RNase A in H<SB>2</SB>O. The spectra exhibit a multi-modal structure with diffusive, so-called “Debye behavior” of each dispersion step, characterized by amplitudes <IT>S</IT><SB><IT>j</IT></SB> and relaxation times <IT>τ</IT><SB><IT>j</IT></SB>:<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit38">38</REF> For an accurate representation of the spectrum of RNase A, four terms were needed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Numbering the dispersions from low to high frequencies, processes 1 and 4 are dominant and cause the apparent bimodal shape of the spectrum shown in Fig. 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The low-frequency dispersion, often termed “β-relaxation”, results from protein tumbling, the high-frequency dispersion 4 reflects bulk water reorientation.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit32 cit33 cit34 cit35 cit36 cit37">32–37</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The interpretation of two further processes (2 and 3) at intermediate frequencies is subject to some debate, but probably they are related to protein–water interactions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">At the low concentrations applied here, their amplitudes were too weak to be able to extract meaningful parameters.</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Processes 2 and 3 will not be considered further.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of ubiquitin, it made only sense to fit a three-term expression, as the difference in frequency of dispersions 2 and 3 was small.</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fit parameters are summarized in Table 2.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4">Discussion</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>A scenario for the volumetric behaviour</HEADER><P><s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Before considering changes in the volumetric behavior induced by H<SB>2</SB>O–D<SB>2</SB>O substitution, we discuss a simple scenario, in which the partial specific volume of a protein may be decomposed into three contributions:<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit40 cit41 cit42">40–42</REF><IT>V</IT> ≈ <IT>V</IT><SB>intr</SB> + δ<IT>V</IT><SB>hydr</SB> + <IT>V</IT><SB>therm</SB>.The intrinsic volume, <IT>V</IT><SB>intr</SB>, of the protein results from the van der Waals volume of the atoms plus the volume of water-inaccessible voids in its interior.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The hydrational or interaction term, δ<IT>V</IT><SB>hydr</SB>, describes the solvent volume changes associated with the hydration of the solvent-accessible hydrophobic, polar or charged protein atomic groups.</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The thermal volume, <IT>V</IT><SB>therm</SB>, the volume of the void space surrounding the solute molecule, arises from mutual thermally induced vibrations and reorientations of the solute and solvent.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Scaled particle theory, by employing statistical mechanical and geometrical arguments to describe the dissolution of a solute, allows one to evaluate the intrinsic and thermal contributions (<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit42">ref. 42</REF> and references therein).</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The thermal volume contribution has been found to be slightly larger in D<SB>2</SB>O than in H<SB>2</SB>O, respectively.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit42">42</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The sum of the intrinsic (geometrical) volume and the thermal volume thus represents the partial molar volume of the cavity enclosing the solute.</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">In eqn. (5), a minor term taking into account the coefficient of isothermal compressibility of the solvent has been neglected.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit40">40</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Certainly, as there is no rigorous way of disentangling the partial molar volume of a protein into its components here, other dissections of <IT>V</IT> may be conceivable.</annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Owing to the qualitative discussion of the various contributions, this does not affect the conclusions drawn, however.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">From the measured partial specific volume and simple models for <IT>V</IT><SB>intr</SB> and <IT>V</IT><SB>therm</SB>, a rough estimate of δ<IT>V</IT><SB>hydr</SB> can be given for the native state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Such an analysis, conducted for RNase A in H<SB>2</SB>O in<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30">ref. 30</REF>, yields as a highly negative value for δ<IT>V</IT><SB>hydr</SB>, about δ<IT>V</IT><SB>hydr</SB> = −0.2 cm<SP>3</SP> g<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">A negative value implies a smaller partial molar volume, <IT>i.e.</IT> a higher density, of water at the protein surface compared to bulk water.</annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Such a higher density is evidenced by combined neutron and X-ray scattering experiments.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit43">43</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Its origin in terms of the properties and topology of the protein–water surface has recently been addressed by MD simulations.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Eqn. (5) implies that a similar dissection may hold for the temperature derivatives of the partial specific volume, <IT>i.e.</IT> the apparent thermal expansion coefficient, <IT>α</IT>, and its temperature coefficient, d<IT>α</IT>/d<IT>T</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Only δ<IT>V</IT><SB>hydr</SB> and <IT>V</IT><SB>therm</SB> contribute significantly, to <IT>α</IT> and d<IT>α</IT>/d<IT>T</IT>, because the intrinsic volume of the native protein does not depend markedly on temperature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">In fact, the thermal expansivity of the protein interior has been measured over a limited temperature range, and the changes observed are rather small.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit44 cit45 cit46 cit47 cit48">44–48</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The thermal volume is expected to increase with temperature, giving a positive contribution to <IT>α</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">As pointed out by Lin <IT>et al.</IT>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29">29</REF><IT>α</IT> and, in particular, d<IT>α</IT>/d<IT>T</IT> are primarily controlled by the hydrational contributions, suggesting that d<IT>α</IT>/d<IT>T</IT> is a direct measure of the effect of solvation upon volumetric properties of proteins.</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In fact, the hydrational contribution to the thermal expansibility is known to depend drastically on the nature of the protein–water interface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hydrophilic groups in contact with water show the characteristic pattern of structure-breakers with large positive values of <IT>α</IT>, which decrease drastically with increasing temperature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rationale is that the hydrophilic groups bind more adjacent water at low temperatures, which at higher temperatures are released by thermal agitation, and do no more contribute to <IT>α</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast, solvent-exposed hydrophobic groups act as structure makers, resulting in a decrease in the water density around hydrophobic groups.</annotationART></s> <s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this case <IT>α</IT> is negative, and the temperature coefficient, d<IT>α</IT>/d<IT>T</IT>, is positive.</annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This picture adopted here for proteins, also evolves from studies of volumetric properties of inorganic and organic electrolytes and small model compounds such as hydrophilic and hydrophobic amino acids (see <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit41 cit42">refs. 41,42</REF>).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our data for RNase A in H<SB>2</SB>O and D<SB>2</SB>O indicate high apparent thermal expansion coefficients of the protein and steeply decreasing slopes in their temperature dependence.</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, they classify RNase A as a protein with a significant number of hydrophilic side groups at the protein surface.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30">30</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Even much steeper slopes of d<IT>α</IT>/d<IT>T</IT> are found for proteins with more charged side groups, such as SNase<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit31">31</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Volumetric behavior and protein stability in D<SB>2</SB>O</HEADER><P><s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Water deuteration quite generally displaces the transition temperature of unfolding, <IT>T</IT><SB><IT>m</IT></SB>, to higher values (Table 1).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17 cit18 cit19 cit20 cit21">17–21</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Intuitively, this temperature shift is attributed to a higher stability of the native protein in D<SB>2</SB>O. However, the transition temperature only signals the equality of the Gibbs free energy of the native and unfolded state which results from enthalpy-entropy compensation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">By a more detailed analysis of entropy and enthalpy behavior, some authors have concluded that at low temperatures the native protein is destabilized by D<SB>2</SB>O.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20 cit21">20,21</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Guzzi <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF>. have argued that at the microscopic level this destabilization in D<SB>2</SB>O originates from a less efficient solvation of solvent-exposed apolar side groups.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">For RNase A in D<SB>2</SB>O, both the absolute value of the thermal expansion coefficient at low temperatures, as well as its temperature coefficient, are markedly higher than in H<SB>2</SB>O (Table 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">In particular, the large isotope effect on d<IT>α</IT>/d<IT>T</IT> is notable.</annotationART></s> <s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">These volumetric effects of H<SB>2</SB>O–D<SB>2</SB>O substitution are in the same direction as obtained for proteins with a significant number of charged groups, for instance SNase,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit31">31</REF> and also observed by addition of kosmotropic co-solvents such as glycerol or sorbitol.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30">30</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This evidences a prime role of the enhanced solvation of the hydrophilic amino acid groups by D<SB>2</SB>O, and clearly points towards a stabilization of the native form by D<SB>2</SB>O. This would also be in agreement with the value of the Gibbs free energy of unfolding at room temperature, Δ<IT>G</IT>°(25 °C), deduced from the calorimetric data by assuming that the heat capacity change upon unfolding is independent of temperature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">In that case, Δ<IT>G</IT>°(25 °C) values of 37 and 46 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> K<SP>−1</SP> are obtained in H<SB>2</SB>O and D<SB>2</SB>O, respectively.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Finally, the volume change, Δ<IT>V</IT>, that accompanies the unfolding in D<SB>2</SB>O, is 40% lower than in H<SB>2</SB>O (Table 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">A considerable part of this reduction may arise from a strong temperature dependence of Δ<IT>V</IT>, because as <IT>T</IT><SB>m</SB> increases, Δ<IT>V</IT> decreases significantly.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit48 cit49">48,49</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">It might, at least partially, also be due to a more compact state of RNase A in the unfolded state, however.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Protein stabilization as inferred from dielectric relaxation data</HEADER><P><s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">An intriguing question is, whether the increased hydration and stabilization in D<SB>2</SB>O seen in the thermal and volumetric experiments leads to a change in the protein fold.</annotationART></s> <s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">Our strategy is to compare the isotope effect upon the protein relaxation time, <IT>τ</IT><SB>1</SB>, with the isotope effect upon the bulk viscosity, and also to compare the amplitudes <IT>S</IT><SB>1</SB> of the protein peaks in H<SB>2</SB>O and D<SB>2</SB>O, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both types of information can be converted into structural data: <IT>τ</IT><SB>1</SB> contains information on the hydrodynamic radius of the protein, and <IT>S</IT><SB>1</SB> permits the calculation of the protein's dipole moment.</annotationART></s> <s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have conducted these experiments for RNase A and, for comparison, also for ubiquitin.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="143"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="None" advantage="None">As noted, the relaxation time <IT>τ</IT><SB>1</SB> reflects protein tumbling.</annotationART></s> <s sid="144"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">This process is considered to be a prototypical example for a process controlled by the hydrodynamic friction of the solvent,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit32 cit33">32,33</REF> and can be described by Debye's equation for the rotation of a dipolar sphere in a surrounding medium of viscosity <IT>η</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit38">38</REF><IT>V</IT><SB>hydr</SB> is the hydrodynamic volume of the protein, <IT>a</IT> the hydrodynamic radius, and <IT>k</IT><SB><IT>B</IT></SB> is Boltzmann's constant.</annotationART></s> <s sid="145"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Because large deviations from spherical shape are needed to invalidate eqn. (6),<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit38">38</REF> this relation is also applicable to RNase A, which can be pictured as an ellipsoid with an axial ratio of about 1.5.</annotationART></s> <s sid="146"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The viscosity of the buffer solutions were found to differ less than 1% from those of pure H<SB>2</SB>O, <IT>η</IT><SB>H</SB> = 0.894 × 10<SP>−3</SP> kg m<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP> at 25 °C, and of pure D<SB>2</SB>O, <IT>η</IT><SB>D</SB> = 1.101 × 10<SP>−3</SP> kg m<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="147"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus their ratio is <IT>η</IT><SB>D</SB>/<IT>η</IT><SB>H</SB> = 1.232,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF> where the subscripts H and D stand for H<SB>2</SB>O and D<SB>2</SB>O, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="148"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Table 3 shows that, within experimental error, this ratio is indeed observed for the bulk water relaxation times <IT>τ</IT><SB>4</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="149"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the protein relaxation times,<IT>τ</IT><SB>1</SB>, this ratio is significantly smaller.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="150"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Before discussing this isotope effect in detail, we compare the hydrodynamic radius deduced for RNase A with estimates from other sources.</annotationART></s> <s sid="151"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The most direct comparison is possible with <SP>15</SP>N magnetic relaxation data.</annotationART></s> <s sid="152"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Magnetic relaxation monitors protein tumbling, as described by correlation functions associated with second rank (<IT>l</IT> = 2) spherical harmonics.</annotationART></s> <s sid="153"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Dielectric relaxation refers to first rank (<IT>l</IT> = 1) spherical harmonics.</annotationART></s> <s sid="154"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the diffusive limit of single-particle reorientation, we have <IT>τ</IT><SB>1</SB> = 3<IT>τ</IT><SB>NMR</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="155"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">From <SP>15</SP>N relaxation data for RNase A by Cole and Loria,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit50">50</REF> we then estimate <IT>τ</IT><SB>1</SB> = 20 ns and <IT>a</IT> ≅ 1.90 nm, in comparison with <IT>τ</IT><SB>1</SB> = 27 ns and <IT>a</IT> ≅ 2.10 nm actually observed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="156"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ifference is beyond experimental uncertainty, but one may note that the applied conversion, <IT>τ</IT><SB>1</SB> = 3<IT>τ</IT><SB>NMR</SB>, holds only for processes reflecting single-particle motions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="157"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">For many simple systems, including water, collective reorientational motions cause the dielectric relaxation time <IT>τ</IT><SB>1</SB> to differ substantially from 3<IT>τ</IT><SB>NMR</SB>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit51">51</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="158"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have shown elsewhere<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit35">35</REF> that protein-protein dipolar correlations lead to a concentration dependence of <IT>τ</IT><SB>1</SB> which can account for the discrepancy of dielectric and NMR data.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="159"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">In all cases, the hydrodynamic radii are larger than the radii estimated from structural data.</annotationART></s> <s sid="160"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Molecular mass–volume correlations for globular proteins, for example given in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit40 cit54">refs. 40 and 54</REF>, predict an intrinsic radius of bare RNase A of 1.54 nm only (a thermal contribution of about 1 nm may be added).</annotationART></s> <s sid="161"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Similar discrepancies between hydrodynamic and structural radii are found for other proteins as well,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit32 cit33">32,33</REF> and have been commonly attributed to a shell of hundreds of water molecules contributing to the hydrodynamic radius of the protein.</annotationART></s> <s sid="162"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">A common assumption is that these water molecules are bound on the time scale of protein reorientation, <IT>i.e.</IT> in the microseconds time regime.</annotationART></s> <s sid="163"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">This result is highly inconsistent with results of NMR exchange studies<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13 cit52 cit53">13,52,53</REF> and MD simulations,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit54 cit55">54,55</REF> which clearly show that residence times of water molecules at protein surfaces are only on the sub-nanosecond time scale.</annotationART></s> <s sid="164"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The apparent differences between hydrodynamic and structural radii can be removed by computing the friction tensors from the protein shape on an atomic scale,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit56 cit57">56,57</REF> and by assuming a non-uniform solvent viscosity near the protein surface.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit52">52</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="165"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Turning to the effect of H<SB>2</SB>O–D<SB>2</SB>O substitution, we find the viscosity ratio of <IT>η</IT><SB>D</SB>/<IT>η</IT><SB>H</SB> = 1.232 to be reflected by the ratio of the relaxation times <IT>τ</IT><SB>4</SB> of bulk water, but not by the ratio of the protein relaxation times <IT>τ</IT><SB>1</SB> of RNase A and ubiquitin.</annotationART></s> <s sid="166"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">There are two options for rationalizing this observation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="167"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">First, as already noted, one expects a non-uniform solvent viscosity near the protein surface.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit52">52</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="168"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, one possible explanation may presume that, owing to differences in hydration, the local isotope effect <IT>η</IT><SB>D</SB>/<IT>η</IT><SB>H</SB> differs from that in the bulk solvent.</annotationART></s> <s sid="169"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Alternatively, one may rationalize the observed behavior by assuming that, upon H<SB>2</SB>O–D<SB>2</SB>O substitution, the hydrodynamic radii of RNase A and ubiquitin shrink by about 5%.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="170"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Two observations indicate that the isotope effects may indeed reflect a change in the hydrodynamic radius, and that this effect results from changes in the protein fold.</annotationART></s> <s sid="171"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">First, it has been found in an elaborate small-angle neutron scattering (SANS) study<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit43">43</REF> that the radius of gyration of lysozyme decreases from <IT>R</IT><SB>g</SB> = 1.38 nm in H<SB>2</SB>O to 1.24 nm in D<SB>2</SB>O. The order of magnitude of this effect (11%) is even larger than that observed here.</annotationART></s> <s sid="172"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">In SANS, the contrast at the protein–water interface is higher than obtained by small-angle X-ray scattering (SAXS), and the radius of gyration essentially refers to the bare protein.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit43">43</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="173"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, the change in the radius of gyration may well result from a change in the protein fold.</annotationART></s> <s sid="174"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In a more indirect way, such an effect has also been deduced from phosphorescence lifetime studies of several proteins.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25">25</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="175"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Second, an interpretation in terms of a more compact fold in D<SB>2</SB>O is consistent with the behavior of the amplitudes <IT>S</IT><SB>1</SB> of the protein tumbling mode, which provide values for the effective dipole moments, <IT>μ</IT><SB>eff</SB>, of the proteins in solution (which differ from the dipole moments of the isolated proteins).</annotationART></s> <s sid="176"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The evaluation of <IT>S</IT><SB>1</SB>slightly depends on details of the dielectric model.</annotationART></s> <s sid="177"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">For example, the Onsager–Oncley model<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit32 cit33">32,33</REF> yields values of 276 D and 175 D (1 D = 3.30 × 10<SP>−30</SP> C·m) for RNase A and ubiquitin, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="178"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Such high dipole moments are typical for proteins.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit32 cit33">32,33</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="179"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Any model yields, however, the same expression for the amplitude ratio where <IT>ρ</IT> is the number density of the protein molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="180"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Table 3 indicates that <IT>μ</IT><SB>eff,D</SB> is by about 5–10% smaller than <IT>μ</IT><SB>eff,H</SB>, indeed indicating a more compact state of the protein in D<SB>2</SB>O, in which the charge distribution is spread over a smaller space than in H<SB>2</SB>O.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="5">Conclusions</HEADER><P><s sid="181"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">H<SB>2</SB>O–D<SB>2</SB>O substitution has been found to be an effective tool for singling out hydration effects on the thermodynamic behavior of proteins and their stability.</annotationART></s> <s sid="182"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In particular, the volumetric behavior reflected by the apparent thermal expansion coefficient, <IT>α</IT>, and its temperature coefficient, d<IT>α</IT>/d<IT>T</IT>, changes drastically upon isotopic substitution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="183"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">These changes are intrinsically related to hydration properties and the interplay between hydrophilic and hydrophobic groups at the protein–water interface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="184"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The volumetric data clearly point toward a stabilization of the native form of RNase A in D<SB>2</SB>O.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="185"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">An assessment of the underlying molecular processes can certainly not been done by considering the thermal and volumetric properties alone.</annotationART></s> <s sid="186"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">As noted by Finney,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF> in studying the subtle effects associated with protein hydration, as many techniques as possible should be applied.</annotationART></s> <s sid="187"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Here, we have complemented the DSC and PPC experiments by dielectric relaxation experiments for RNase A and ubiquitin.</annotationART></s> <s sid="188"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">These experiments yield evidence that the stabilization of the native form in D<SB>2</SB>O reflects a more compact fold.</annotationART></s> <s sid="189"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">A more compact fold in D<SB>2</SB>O follows also from SANS data for another protein, lysozyme.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit43">43</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="190"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Presumably, the stronger solvation of hydrophilic groups and less effective solvation of hydrophobic groups at the protein surface cause the protein to reduce the solvent-exposure of the hydrophobic groups.</annotationART></s> <s sid="191"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">These changes, in particular for enzymes with highly flexible surface groups, may very well alter the protein function in D<SB>2</SB>O.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
