<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b316260e" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Tests of second-generation and third-generation density functionals for thermochemical kinetics<XREF TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" /></annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">We report tests of second- and third-generation density functionals, for pure density functional theory (DFT) and hybrid DFT, against the BH6 representative barrier height database and the AE6 representative atomization energy database, with augmented, polarized double and triple zeta basis sets.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">The pure DFT methods tested are G96LYP, BB95, PBE, mPWPW91, VSXC, HCTH, OLYP, and OPW91 and the hybrid DFT methods tested are B1B95, PBE0, mPW1PW91, B97-1, B98, MPW1K, B97-2, and O3LYP.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">The performance of these methods is tested against each other as well as against first-generation methods (BP86, BLYP, PW91, B3PW91, and B3LYP).</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">We conclude that the overall performance of the second-generation DFT methods is considerably better than the first-generation methods.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The MPW1K method is very good for barrier height calculations, and none of the pure DFT methods outperforms any of the hybrid DFT methods for kinetics.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The B1B95, VSXC, B98, OLYP and O3LYP methods perform best for atomization energies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Using a mean mean unsigned error criterion (MMUE) that involves two sizes of basis sets (both with polarization and diffuse functions) and averages mean unsigned errors in barrier heights and in atomization energy per bond, we find that VSXC has the best performance among pure functionals, and B97-2, MPW1K, and B1B95 have the best performance of all hybrid functionals tested.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER /><P><s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hybrid density functional theory<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF> (mixing Hartree–Fock exchange with pure DFT) has become generally recognized as the electronic structure method of choice for calculations on large systems.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Methods of this type can be justified theoretically by the adiabatic connection theory,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">2</REF> and hence they are sometimes called adiabatic connection methods.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The adiabatic connection theory indicates that more accurate results can be obtained by replacing some DFT exchange by Hartree–Fock exchange.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hartree–Fock exchange does not suffer from the self-interaction error of DFT, which can be very important when hydrogen atoms are present, and this is one way to understand why mixing in exact exchange can reduce the error; however, DFT exchange is inseparable from DFT dynamical correlation, and it introduces some static correlation,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF> so the optimum fraction of HF exchange is not 100%.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The performance of hybrid DFT for thermochemistry is well documented.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2 cit4 cit5 cit6 cit7 cit8 cit9 cit10 cit11 cit12 cit13 cit14 cit15 cit16 cit17 cit18 cit19 cit20 cit21">1,2,4–21</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">At present, despite the successes of hybrid DFT, one is not completely satisfied for several reasons.</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">First, the method is not systematically improvable.</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Second, the mixture of Hartree–Fock theory into DFT restricts the choice of algorithms such that the most efficient computational strategies used for pure DFT are inapplicable.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Third, the most generally successful hybrid DFT methods are less accurate for kinetics than for thermochemistry.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16 cit20 cit22 cit23">16,20,22,23</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since Hartree–Fock theory usually overestimates barrier heights for chemical reactions, and pure DFT usually underestimates them,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF> many workers noticed that more accurate results can be obtained for kinetics by increasing the fraction of Hartree–Fock exchange;<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF> however, it was questionable whether this approach was physically meaningful.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">It was soon learned that the popular B3LYP hybrid method,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25 cit26 cit27">25–27</REF> with 20% Hartree–Fock exchange, still systematically underestimates barrier heights,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22 cit23">22,23</REF> but raising the fraction of Hartree–Fock exchange usually deteriorated the quality of the prediction of the theory for other quantities more rapidly than it increased the quality of barrier height predictions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">However the hybrid mPW1PW91 method<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF> is more stable than the popular B3LYP hybrid method when the fraction of Hartree–Fock exchange is increased,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF> and this observation was used to optimize the MPW1K method for kinetics.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">MPW1K gives remarkably accurate barrier heights with only slight deterioration of reaction energies.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20 cit23 cit28">20,23,28</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The number of available density functionals is increasing rapidly.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Boese <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF>. have pointed out that “Many DFT users are overwhelmed by the sheer number of functionals and possibilities….</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Very often because of sheer user inertia, first-generation functionals are applied rather than more accurate second-generation functionals….</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Meanwhile, systematic studies on the dependency of the basis set and functionals remain sparse.” Furthermore, with a few exceptions,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12 cit16 cit18 cit20 cit23 cit28 cit29 cit30">12,16,18,20,23,28–30</REF> those systematic tests that are available are dominated by thermochemistry, and much less attention has been paid to quantities like barrier heights that are important for kinetics.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Recently, a representative database of six barrier heights was developed<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit31">31</REF> such that the errors calculated for this database correlate extremely well with errors calculated for a much larger database<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20 cit32">20,32</REF> of 44 barrier heights.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The small database is called BH6.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The small size of this database makes it more straightforward to test a wide assortment of second-generation density functionals for kinetics, and the representative character of the database makes us expect that the conclusions are consistent with what would be concluded from tests against a much larger database.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The same paper<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit31">31</REF> developed a representative database of atomization energies, containing six molecules and called AE6, such that performance on this database is indicative of performance on a much larger 109 molecule database.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19 cit20">19,20</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The average number of bonds per molecule in AE6 is 4.833.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the present paper we report errors in the AE6 data base as mean signed error (MSE) and mean unsigned error (MUE) in kcal mol<SP>–1</SP> per bond by dividing the total MSE and MUE by 4.833.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Small representative databases can play an important role in allowing a wide variety of methods to be tested on the same data.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Small databases will not necessarily uncover the interesting difficult cases, but it is reasonable to ask first how a method performs for typical cases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">One advantage of the AE6 and BH6 databases is that they correspond to electronic energy contributions (including nuclear repulsion), exclusive of vibrational zero point energy and vibrational–rotational thermal energies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus they can be used to test electronic energy calculations without the complication of vibrational energy considerations.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">All calculations in this paper are single-point calculations at QCISD/MG3 geometries, where QCISD is quadratic configuration interaction with single and double excitations,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit33">33</REF> and MG3 is the modified<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit34 cit35">34,35</REF> G3Large<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit36">36</REF> basis set.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The MG3 basis set,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit34">34</REF> also called G3LargeMP2,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit35">35</REF> is the same as 6-311++G(3d2f,2df,2p)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit37">37</REF> for H–Si, but improved<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit36">36</REF> for atoms heavier than Si.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The QCISD/MG3 greometries for all molecules in BH6 and AE6 can be obtained from the database website of our group.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit38">38</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The effect of spin–orbit coupling is also added to open shell systems from a compendium given else where.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit39">39</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">We used the GAUSSIAN03<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit40">40</REF> program to test all pure and hybrid DFT methods except OLYP and O3LYP<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit41">41</REF> (acronyms for density functionals are explained below).</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">We found that O3LYP in GAUSSIAN03 cannot reproduce the atomization energies published in the original<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit41 cit42">41,42</REF> O3LYP paper, and therefore O3LYP and OLYP calculations were carried out with the PQS <IT>ab initio</IT> program developed by Parallel Quantum Solutions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit43">43</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Baker and Pulay<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF> used PQS to assess O3LYP and OLYP for organic reactions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that the local correlation functional in O3LYP and OLYP is Vosko, Wilk, and Nusair's correlation functional V (VWN5),<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit44">44</REF> while in B3LYP the local correlation functional is the Vosko, Wilk, and Nusair's correlation functional III (VWN3).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit44">44</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the printed part of this article we will give MSE and MUE for BH6 and MSE per bond and MUE per bond for AE6 with two highly recommended basis sets, namely a recommended<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19 cit28">19,28</REF> augmented polarized double zeta set, 6-31+G(d,p),<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit45 cit46">45,46</REF> and a recommended augmented polarized triple zeta set, MG3S.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In tables 6-31+G(d,p) is abbreviated DIDZ (desert-island double zeta).</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The MG3S basis<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19">19</REF> is the same as MG3 except it omits diffuse functions on hydrogens.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The supporting information gives the following additional information that may be of interest to specialists: root-mean square errors, results for four more basis sets (6-31G(d), 6-31+G(2d,p), 6-311G(3d,2pd), and 6-311+G(2df,2p)), and results for the subsets of the databases that contain only H–F, where the latter values exclude molecules and barrier heights for systems that include Si and S. We simply comment that the trends in relative performance on the full AE6 and BH6 are mirrored in these subsets, and the conclusions about relative performance drawn from the two recommended basis sets are similar to those for the other four basis sets.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">With regard to comparison of basis sets, the results in supporting information support our previous conclusion<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19">19</REF> that inclusion of diffuse functions on atoms heavier than H make the results more generally reliable.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">These tables are also consistent with our previous conclusion, based on previous results,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19 cit20 cit23">19,20,23</REF> that if one were confined to a desert island with only one valence double zeta basis set and one valence triple zeta basis set, 6-31+G(d,p) and MG3S would be two very excellent choices (kudos to the Pople group<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit36 cit37 cit45 cit46">36,37,45,46</REF> for their work in optimizing the basis functions in these basis sets).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Table 1 gives results for first-generation functionals, both pure DFT (<IT>X</IT> = 0) and hybrid DFT (<IT>X</IT> &gt; 0).</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In particular, the first-generation functionals we tested are BP86, BLYP, PW91, B3LYP and B3PW91.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">BP86 is a pure DFT method using Becke's 1988 gradient corrected exchange functional (B)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25">25</REF> and Perdew's 1986 gradient corrected correlation functional (P86).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit47">47</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">When one combines Becke's 1988 gradient corrected exchange functional (B) with Lee, Yang, and Parr's gradient corrected correlation functional (LYP),<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26">26</REF> one obtains the BLYP method.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">PW91 is a pure DFT method that incorporates Perdew and Wang's 1991 gradient corrected exchange and correlation functional.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit48 cit49">48,49</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">B3PW91 is Becke's three parameter hybrid DFT method which includes 20% Hartree–Fock exchange.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">B3LYP is the most popular hybrid DFT method; it was developed by Stephens <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27">27</REF>. by following Becke's three-parameter hybrid DFT strategy.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Table 2 gives some results for DFT methods involving second-generation functionals (mPW1PW91 and MPW1K) that have already been widely tested against our databases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Barone and Adamo<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF> developed mPW1PW91 as a Becke-style one-parameter hybrid functional using their modified Perdew–Wang (mPW or MPW) exchange functional, Perdew and Wang's 1991 (PW91) correlation functional, and 25% of Hartree–Fock exchange.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">MPW1K is a method optimized against a kinetics database by our group;<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF> it uses the same functionals as mPW1PW91, but the fraction of Hartree–Fock exchange is 42.8%.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Table 3 and Table 4 give results for second-generation and third-generation pure and hybrid DFT functionals that have not previously been tested against our databases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The tests in Table 3 and Table 4 are the main new results in the present paper.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">By testing so many methods against the same representative databases, including barrier heights, we can put the new functionals in better perspective and thereby provide guidance to the “many DFT users” mentioned in the third paragraph as well as to developers of new density functionals and computational strategists.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In particular, Tables 3 and 4 include the following second-generation methods (in alphabetical order):</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">(<IT>i</IT>) B97-1: Hamprecht <IT>et al.</IT>'s modification to Becke's 1997 hybrid functional (B97)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit12">8,12</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">(<IT>ii</IT>) B98: Becke's 1998 revisions to B97<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit10">8,10</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">(<IT>iii</IT>) B97-2: Wilson, Bradley and Tozer's modification to B97<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit16">8,16</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">(<IT>iv</IT>) G96LYP: Gill's 1996 exchange<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit50">50</REF> and LYP correlation<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26">26</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">(<IT>v</IT>) HCTH: Hamprecht, Cohen, Tozer, and Handy's exchange–correlation<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF> (this is also sometimes called HCTH/407)</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">(<IT>vi</IT>) OLYP: Handy and Cohen's OPTX<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit41">41</REF> exchange and LYP<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26">26</REF> correlation</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">(<IT>vii</IT>) O3LYP: Handy and Cohen's three parameter hybrid functional<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit42">42</REF> using OPTX<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit41">41</REF> exchange and LYP<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26">26</REF> correlation</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">(<IT>viii</IT>) OPW91: OPTX<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit41">41</REF> exchange and PW91<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit48">48</REF> correlation</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">(<IT>ix</IT>) PBE: Perdew, Burke, and Ernzerhof's exchange and correlation<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit51">51</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">(<IT>x</IT>) PBE0: One-parameter hybrid functional using Perdew, Burke and Ernzerhof's 1996 exchange and correlation<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit51 cit52">51,52</REF> and three third-generation methods:</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">(<IT>i</IT>) B1B95: One-parameter hybrid functional using Becke's 1988 exchange<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25">25</REF> and 1995 kinetic-energy-dependent correlation<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">(<IT>ii</IT>) BB95: same as B1B95 but with no Hartree–Fock exchange<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">(<IT>iii</IT>) VSXC: van Voorhis and Scuseria's kinetic-energy-dependent exchange–correlation<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit53">53</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The second-generation functionals, like the first-generation functionals of Table 1 that brought DFT and hybrid DFT to its present state of popularity, are generalized gradient approximation (GGAs) and their hybrid generalizations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The third generation functionals are sometimes called meta-GGAs or MGGAs; they incorporate kinetic energy density and are a possible area of future systematic improvement.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit17 cit53 cit54 cit55 cit56">5,17,53–56</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Previous work<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit56">56</REF> has shown that the VSXC functional is more accurate than the more recent Perdew–Kurth–Zupan–Blaha<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit57">57</REF> (PKZB) MGGA, and so we did not include the PKZB functional here (very recently an improved MGGA, called TPSS, has been presented, and it would be interesting to study that in future work).</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Because the MGGAs can do a much better job of eliminating the self-interaction energy than GGAs, one expects less improvement upon making hybrid versions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit54 cit55">54,55</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Nevertheless we test one MGGA in both pure and hybrid form, namely BB95<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF> and B1B.95<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">(Boese and Handy<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF> found only a small improvement in the HCTH functional upon adding kinetic energy density, and so we do not test the functional that they obtained by that addition.) Dependence of the density functional on the kinetic energy density is a special case of functional dependence on the Kohn–Sham orbitals, which are in turn functionals of the density; more general orbital dependencies (fourth-generation functionals) have also been studied,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit58">58</REF> but are not considered here.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">From Tables 1–4 we can see that new generations of DFT methods outperform the first-generation methods.</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Among the pure DFT methods, VSXC and OLYP give the best performance for atomization energies, and VSXC also gives the best performance for barrier heights.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In comparison to the best pure DFT first-generation functional (BLYP) in Table 1, we see that VSXC improves performance by factor of 1.6–2.6, which is a dramatic advance.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Among the hybrid DFT methods, MPW1K gives the best results for BH6, while B1B95, O3LYP, and B98 give the best results for AE6.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">As compared to the best first-generation hybrid functional (B3PW91) in Table 1, MPW1K improves the barrier heights by a factor of 3.1, but increases the mean unsigned error in the atomization energies by factor of 2.6–3.8.</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast, the third-generation B1B95 functional improves the barrier heights by a factor of only 1.2 but also improves the atomization energies by factors of 1.1 (computed from unrounded MUEs) to 2.0.</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">None of the seven second-generation hybrid functionals in Table 2 and 4 improve the MUE for both BH6 and AE6 for both basis sets.</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The good results obtained in this paper with VSXC and B1B95 provide good support for the value of including kinetic energy density in the functionals.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">A desirable quality that one seeks for density functionals is that one can obtain good results with small basis sets as well as large basis sets.</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Also, it is important for density functionals to perform well for both barrier heights and bond energies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to make it a little easier to put the large number of results in this paper in perspective, we calculated a mean MUE, by the formula MMUE = 1/4[MUE(BH6,DIDZ) + MUE(BH6,MG3S) + MUE(AE6,DIDZ) + MUE(AE6,MG3S)] where the MUEs for AE6 are on per bond basis as in Tables 1–4.</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Table 5 lists all the methods in this paper in order of increasing MMUE.</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Clearly eqn. (1) is not a unique measure of quality (for example, if one is not interested in kinetics and potential energy surfaces, one might prefer a criterion based only on atomization energies, or if one is interested in eliminating the largest errors (“difficult cases”), one needs a larger database), but nevertheless it is one reasonable measure of representative performance, and so we can draw some conclusions.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">From the MMUE in Table 5, we can see that most of the hybrid DFT methods outperform pure DFT.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">One exception is VSXC, which is the best pure DFT method, and it outperforms PBE0 and B3LYP.</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The large margin by which VSXC outperforms the second-best pure functional is quite impressive.</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The good performance of HCTH, OLYP, and OPW91 is also noteworthy and provides a significant testimonial to the work of the Handy group.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Table 5 also shows that most second-generation DFT methods outperform the first-generation DFT methods.</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">B97-2 is the very best method in that it has the lowest MMUE.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">We previously concluded that mPW91PW91 was systematically better than B3LYP,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20 cit23 cit28">20,23,28</REF> in agreement with the original conclusion of Adamo and Barone<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF> (who, however, did not systematically test barrier heights).</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Table 5 shows that, at least using eqn. (1), B97-2, MPW1K, and B1B95 are significantly better, on average, than mPW1PW91.</annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Of these methods, MPW1K achieve its place mainly by superior performance on barrier heights, whereas B97-2 and B1B95 outperform mPW91PW91 for all four MUEs in Tables 2 and 4.</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, these two methods are good candidates for general-purpose hybrid DFTs, while MPW1K remains the best hybrid DFT for kinetics.</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">None of the pure DFT methods in Tables 1, 2, or 3 outperforms any of the hybrid DFT methods in Tables 1, 2, or 4 for barrier heights.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
