<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b404078n" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Analysis of an algebraic model for the chromophore vibrations of CF<SB>3</SB>CHFI</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">We extract the dynamics implicit in an algebraic fitted model Hamiltonian for the hydrogen chromophore’s vibrational motion in the molecule CF<SB>3</SB>CHFI.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">The original model has four degrees of freedom, a conserved polyad allows the reduction to three degrees of freedom.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">For most quantum states we can identify the underlying motion that when quantized gives the said state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Most of the classifications, identifications and assignments are done by visual inspection of the already available wave function semiclassically transformed from the number representation to a representation on the reduced dimension toroidal configuration space corresponding to the classical action and angle variables.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The concentration of the wave function density to lower dimensional subsets centered on idealized simple lower dimensional organizing structures and the behavior of the phase along such organizing centers already reveals the atomic motion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Extremely little computational work is needed.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="1.">Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In recent years we have developed methods to investigate algebraic models (spectroscopic Hamiltonians) for the vibrations of molecules.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2 cit3 cit4 cit5">1–5</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Hamiltonians reproduce and encode by their construction the experimental data.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6 cit7 cit8 cit9 cit10 cit11 cit12">6–12</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the mentioned examples the system is reducible to two degrees of freedom.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="None" advantage="None">As the next logical step we have turned to systems where after all possible reductions three degrees of freedom remain.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="None" advantage="None">A first example of this kind has been treated in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">ref. 13</REF>, in the present paper we treat as further example the molecule CF<SB>3</SB>CHFI for which in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">ref. 14</REF> an algebraic model has been presented for the motion of the H atom (chromophore).</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This model has four degrees of freedom and it has one conserved polyad which can be used to reduce it to three degrees of freedom.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">From known wave functions represented in the toroidal configuration space of action/angle variables<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF> we show that we can visually sort most of the states into ladders of states with similar topology.</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Each ladder has a relatively simple spectrum.</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Complexity arises from their interleaving.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">We also can recognize underlying classical lower dimensional organizing structures by the fact that for these inherently complex functions the eigenstate density (magnitude squared) is concentrated around them and the phase has simple behavior near them.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The position of these structures in angle space reveals the nature of the resonance interaction causing the topology.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">It also allows the reconstruction of the motion of the atoms which underlie this particular quantum state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">By counting nodes in plots of the density and of the phase advances in corresponding plots of the phase quantum excitation numbers can be obtained.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In many cases, along with the polyad quantum number itself, we thereby obtain a complete set of quantum numbers for a state even though the corresponding classical motion is nonintegrable.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">These classification numbers can be interpreted as quasi-conserved quantities for this particular state or for the ladder of states based on the same dynamic organizational element.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the Hamiltonian used here has the same functional structure as the one used in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">ref. 13</REF> and since also the methods of investigation are the same, we mainly present results for the present molecule and refer to <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">ref. 13</REF> for the detailed explanations of the method.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.">The model</HEADER><P><s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the description of the chromophore dynamics of the molecule CF<SB>3</SB>CHFI we use the model set up in .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">ref. 14</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is based on four degrees of freedom as required by the nature of the observed overtone spectroscopy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The index s stands for the stretch of the H atom, the index a labels its bend in the HCCF<SB>(4)</SB> plane, the index b labels its bend perpendicular to this plane, and the index f stands for the transpositioned C–F stretch.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the exact atomic motion belonging to these four degrees of freedom see Fig. 2 in .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">ref. 14</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The algebraic Hamiltonian fitted to experiment and to calculations on a fitted potential surface has a natural decompositioninto a diagonal part(here the indices <IT>j</IT> and <IT>m</IT> run over the four degrees of freedom a, b, f, s) and an interaction partwhere <IT>a</IT><SB><IT>j</IT></SB> and <IT>a</IT><SB><IT>j</IT></SB><SP>†</SP> are the usual harmonic destruction and creation operators of degree of freedom <IT>j</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In eqn. (3) the indices <IT>j</IT> and m run over the three degrees of freedom a, b, f.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the coefficients we use the ones given in column 6 in Table 1 in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">ref. 14</REF> where we see that roughly <IT>ω</IT><SB>s</SB> ≈ 2<IT>ω</IT><SB>a</SB> ≈ 2<IT>ω</IT><SB>b</SB> ≈ 2<IT>ω</IT><SB>f</SB> giving rise to the Fermi resonances anticipated by the terms of eqn. (3) and the Darling–Dennison resonances anticipated by the terms of Eqs.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">(4–6).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This Hamiltonian has as a conserved quantity, the polyad <IT>P</IT>, defined aswith the corresponding operator given as <IT>P̂</IT> by replacing <IT>n</IT><SB><IT>j</IT></SB> → <IT>a</IT>†<IT>j</IT><IT>a</IT><SB><IT>j</IT></SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">One can now study each polyad separately.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The expansion of the eigenfunctions <IT>Ψ</IT><SB><IT>j</IT></SB> into number statesis gotten from the diagonalization of the <IT>H</IT>-matrix in number state basis.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">To construct the corresponding classical Hamiltonian in action/angle variables <IT>I</IT>/<IT>ϕ</IT> we use the substitution rules ,after bringing all operators into symmetrical order, then the classical action <IT>I</IT><SB><IT>j</IT></SB> corresponds to <IT>n</IT><SB><IT>j</IT></SB> + 1/2.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.">Semiclassical wave functions and their analysis</HEADER><P><s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Semiclassically we represent a number state (basis state in our case) as a periodic plane wave on the configuration torus of the coordinates <IT>ϕ</IT><SB><IT>j</IT></SB>:Then from eqn. (8) we get That is, the expansion of the eigenstate into number states from eqn. (8) is converted into a Fourier decomposition on the torus.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Dimension reduction can now be carried out by noting that, using the polyad of eqn. (7) to eliminate the fast degree of freedom s, the <IT>j</IT>th eigenstate can be written By the last equation the reduced wave function <IT>χ</IT><SB><IT>j</IT></SB><SP><IT>P</IT></SP> is defined.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This shows that the eigenfunctions in a given polyad <IT>P</IT> have a common phase factor dependence on <IT>ϕ</IT><SB>s</SB> and really only depend on the reduced wave function <IT>χ</IT><SB><IT>j</IT></SB><SP><IT>P</IT></SP> which is a function of the three anglesor <IT>j</IT> = a,b,f.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">These three angles make up a three dimensional toroidal configuration space <IT>T</IT><SP>3</SP> upon which <IT>χ</IT><SB><IT>k</IT></SB><SP><IT>P</IT></SP> is situated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The angle transformation of eqn. (14) plus the trivial transformationcan be supplemented to give a canonical transformation by introducing the new actions again for <IT>j</IT> = a,b,f and <IT>θ</IT> is a cyclic angle, therefore the conjugate action <IT>K</IT> can be treated as parameter and the system is reduced to one with three degrees of freedom.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The atomic motion belonging to a trajectory in reduced phase space is gotten as follows.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">First we integrate the Hamilton equations for <IT></IT> the cyclic angle; second we undo the canonical transformation for all variables.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">And third we assume a harmonic model for the transition from action/angle variable to position variables in each degree of freedom.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">We call this reconstruction the “lift” (for details see <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">ref. 13</REF>).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The wave functions are manifestly complex function and in the following we use their representation by absolute value and phase as Their inspection is key to our analysis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Their magnitudes (or densities) and phases are both plotted in the cube whose sides are associated with the <IT>ψ</IT><SB><IT>j</IT></SB> on the 0 to 2π range.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Periodic boundary conditions are used so as to associate properly with the 3D configuration torus.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Symmetry properties of the system will show up in the following.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Hamiltonian is invariant under a simultaneous shift of all angles <IT>ψ</IT><SB><IT>j</IT></SB> by π.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore the reduced configuration torus <IT>T</IT><SP>3</SP> covers the original configuration space twice and all structures show up in double, even though they really exist only once.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition the system is invariant under a shift of any angle <IT>ψ</IT><SB><IT>j</IT></SB> by 2π and it is invariant under a reflection where all angles go over into their negatives.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The basis functions have constant density and therefore any eigenstate dominated by a single basis function has a density without sharp localization.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Resonances as for example 2<IT>ω</IT><SB>a</SB> ≈ <IT>ω</IT><SB>s</SB> will be seen to cause localization about a line <IT>ψ</IT><SB>a</SB> = constant.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">This follows as <IT>ψ</IT><SB>a</SB> = <IT>ϕ</IT><SB>a</SB> − <IT>ϕ</IT><SB>s</SB>/2 = <IT>constant</IT> when differentiated with respect to time gives the frequency relation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hence it is seen that resonances are associated with localization and the fact that d<IT>ψ</IT><SB><IT>j</IT></SB>/d<IT>t</IT> = 0.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">It can be claimed that by using angle coordinates that slow to zero velocity at resonance we here assure that the wave function will “collapse” onto and about a lower dimensional subspace called the organization center.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">This in reverse gives a way to recognize the influence of resonances, namely localization of the wave function on the configuration torus.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Each linearly independent locking of angles therefore reduces by 1 the dimension of the subset of configuration space around which the wave function is concentrated.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The nodal structures will be visible and countable in directions perpendicular to the organization element and clearly will be associated with a localized direction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The count of such transversal nodes supplies for each direction of localization a transverse quantum number <IT>t</IT>, that replaces an original mode quantum number <IT>n</IT> which has been destroyed by the resonant interaction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The wave function in all the localized directions can be considered as qualitatively similar (a continuous deformation) of an oscillator state of the corresponding dimension.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The transverse quantum numbers <IT>t</IT><SB><IT>k</IT></SB> are the corresponding oscillator excitation numbers.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The phase functions <IT>Φ</IT> according to eqn. (18) are smooth and close to a plane wave in subsets parallel to the organization center (usually they are subsets of high density) and have jumps by π and singularities in other parts of the configuration space.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore phase advances along fundamental cycles inside such distinguished subsets are well defined and are necessarily integer multiples of 2π.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">They provide longitudinal quantum numbers <IT>l</IT><SB><IT>k</IT></SB> which also replace the interacting mode quantum numbers.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.">The motion behind individual quantum states</HEADER><P><s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The configuration space is a three-dimensional torus which we can represent as a cube with identified opposite boundary points.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Three dimensional (perspective) plots of the semiclassical state functions look too often like large globes of ink and were not informative.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Here we will resort to cuts of the cube (e.g. cut <IT>ψ</IT><SB>a</SB> = <IT>ψ</IT><SB>b</SB>) and plot density and phase in such cuts.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The appropriate choice of the cuts is found partially by trial and error and partially by the following considerations: In CF<SB>3</SB>CHFI a resonance with a rather close frequency is <IT>ω</IT><SB>f</SB> ≈ <IT>ω</IT><SB>b</SB> and its associated <IT>k</IT><SB>b,f</SB> in the Hamiltonian is largest.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">This suggests that modes b and f should be coupled in planes <IT>ψ</IT><SB>f</SB> = <IT>ψ</IT><SB>b</SB> + constant which assures <IT>ω</IT><SB>f</SB><SP>eff</SP> = <IT>ω</IT><SB>b</SB><SP>eff</SP>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The simultaneous Fermi coupling conditions <IT>ω</IT><SB>s</SB> = 2<IT>ω</IT><SB>a</SB> and <IT>ω</IT><SB>s</SB> = 2<IT>ω</IT><SB>f</SB> give by similar reasoning the organizing line <IT>ψ</IT><SB>a</SB> = <IT>c</IT><SB>1</SB>, <IT>ψ</IT><SB>f</SB> = <IT>c</IT><SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">For some states several organizing structures could be used and the same dynamics revealed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our experience is to choose those corresponding resonances which seem more important in <IT>H</IT> and which give longer ladders of states.</annotationART></s></P><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.1.">Scheme for a large number of states throughout the polyad</HEADER><P><s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Starting at the bottom of the polyad we find 64 states that definitely lie in the Darling–Dennison <IT>ω</IT><SB>f</SB> = <IT>ω</IT><SB>b</SB> resonance class in that they have densities localized about planes all denotable as <IT>ψ</IT><SB>f</SB> = <IT>ψ</IT><SB>b</SB> + constant.</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">They also have simple phase plots in these planes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">At the lower end a few of them could also be organized by the <IT>ω</IT><SB>s</SB> = 2<IT>ω</IT><SB>f</SB>, <IT>ω</IT><SB>s</SB> = 2<IT>ω</IT><SB>b</SB> Fermi resonances, i.e. about a line in the “a” direction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">But they occur when the stretch excitation is zero and this classification is not very physical.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Some of the lowest states could also be assigned for all modes by quantum numbers <IT>n</IT><SB><IT>j</IT></SB> and correspond to continuous deformations of basis functions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although these <IT>n</IT><SB><IT>j</IT></SB> are useful in the lift for obtaining actions these assignment misses the phase and frequency locking and the localization of the density.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition we looked very carefully for primary tori in the classical phase space at the corresponding energy and did not find any.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore Einstein–Brillouin–Keller (EBK) quantization cannot be applied.</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hence classical dynamics shows that the assignment by <IT>n</IT><SB>j</SB> for <IT>j</IT> = a,b,f is unphysical.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the organization center <IT>ψ</IT><SB>f</SB> = <IT>ψ</IT><SB>b</SB> + constant. the modes “a” and “s” are uncoupled and the Darling–Dennison resonance couples “f” and “b” such that mode “b”, a true mode of the hydrogen atom motion, is driven by the generic source mode f which represents the effect of the motion of the rest of the molecule on the hydrogen atom motion.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The organization plane has the topological structure of a two dimensional torus.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore it has two fundamental loops which are used for phase counts to get two longitudinal quantum numbers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">One of these loops runs into the “a” direction and provides the excitation number <IT>l</IT><SB>a</SB> = <IT>n</IT><SB>a</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The other fundamental loop of the organization plane corresponds to the combination of a loop in the “b” direction with a loop in the “f” direction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Accordingly a phase count along this loop gives a number <IT>l</IT><SB>b+f</SB> representing the excitation of the coupled b/f motion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Then the polyad number implies the value of <IT>n</IT><SB>s</SB> as <IT>n</IT><SB>s</SB> = <IT>P</IT> − <IT>n</IT><SB>a</SB>/2 − <IT>l</IT><SB>b+f</SB>/2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None">Finally we need a transverse quantum number representing the degree of excitation perpendicular to the plane <IT>ψ</IT><SB>f</SB> = <IT>ψ</IT><SB>b</SB> + constant.</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">What at first was confusing was that perpendicular structures appeared to be organized about one of two parallel planes at low energy and at higher energy about third and fourth planes lying in between.</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">At low energy this observation and the fact that pairs of states with identical (<IT>n</IT><SB>s</SB>,<IT>n</IT><SB>a</SB>,<IT>l</IT><SB>f+b</SB>,<IT>t</IT>) assignments appeared, led to the discovery of a dynamic nearly symmetric double well or double “valley”.</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Two organizing planes at <IT>ψ</IT><SB>f</SB> = <IT>ψ</IT><SB>b</SB> and <IT>ψ</IT><SB>f</SB> = <IT>ψ</IT><SB>b</SB> + π, each run along one of the valleys.</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The <IT>ψ</IT><SB>f</SB> = <IT>ψ</IT><SB>b</SB> valley is slightly deeper making the <IT>ψ</IT><SB>b</SB> → <IT>ψ</IT><SB>b</SB> + π invariance only approximate.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">This asymmetric “double well” becomes also evident from an “accessibility diagram”.</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is a plot of regions of configuration space, i.e. the values of <IT>ψ</IT><SB>a</SB>, <IT>ψ</IT><SB>b</SB> and <IT>ψ</IT><SB>f</SB> that satisfy <IT>E</IT> = <IT>H</IT>(<IT>J</IT><SB>a</SB>, <IT>J</IT><SB>b</SB>, <IT>J</IT><SB>f</SB>, <IT>ψ</IT><SB>a</SB>, <IT>ψ</IT><SB>b</SB>, <IT>ψ</IT><SB>f</SB>; <IT>P</IT>), at each <IT>E</IT>, for given <IT>P</IT> and any compatible actions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Around 11100 cm<SP>−1</SP> (well below the lowest quantum state of polyad 5 and near to the classical lower end of polyad 5) it was noted that only two slabs of configuration space were accessible; these are our wells.</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">At the energy of the lowest quantum state all configuration space is accessible but the wells act as two attractive regions that cause quantum localization above them.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">For some of the lower states, the energy in the “mode f–mode b” lock is low enough that these states are primarily localized in the <IT>ψ</IT><SB>f</SB> = <IT>ψ</IT><SB>b</SB> or the <IT>ψ</IT><SB>f</SB> = <IT>ψ</IT><SB>b</SB> + π well.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">As energy increases the states are roughly speaking “above the barrier” of the “double well” with density on both sides and they fall into near symmetric (+) and antisymmetric (−) pairs (with the same <IT>n</IT><SB>s</SB>,<IT>n</IT><SB>a</SB>,<IT>l</IT><SB>a+b</SB>,<IT>t</IT>) reflecting the approximate invariance <IT>ψ</IT><SB>b</SB> → <IT>ψ</IT><SB>b</SB> + π.</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Each member of these pairs has a slight density preference for one of the wells.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ladders with an even <IT>l</IT><SB>a</SB> start with a + state and ladders with an odd <IT>l</IT><SB>a</SB> start with a − state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The lowest state in any ladder of constant <IT>l</IT><SB>a</SB> always has most of its density near the plane <IT>ψ</IT><SB>f</SB> = <IT>ψ</IT><SB>b</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">In Table 1 this (±) classification label appears.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">In Table 1 we give the transverse quantum number as seen from the planes <IT>ψ</IT><SB>b</SB> = <IT>ψ</IT><SB>f</SB> and <IT>ψ</IT><SB>f</SB> = <IT>ψ</IT><SB>b</SB>π as <IT>t</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">For higher states it sometimes becomes difficult to count <IT>t</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reason for this can be traced to the fact that a slice transverse to the organizing plane should ideally reveal wave functions that represent oscillators.</annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The density would then be the highest in two planes running parallel and on opposite sides of the organizing plane.</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Now consider that for higher states the density is localized about both planes (albeit with a preference for one plane).</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">As excitation increases then the outer lobes of the transverse oscillator will move toward the planes in between (recall all features appear by symmetry in doubles) the two original planes i.e. the planes <IT>ψ</IT><SB>f</SB> = <IT>ψ</IT><SB>b</SB> ± π/2 on which the highest density will now accumulate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hence it now make sense to count transverse nodes between these now bigger intensities.</annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The corresponding transverse quantum number is called <IT>t</IT>′.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">As always the transverse quantum number indicates to which extent the coupled motion goes out of exact phase lock.</annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is a measure of the width of the phase distribution.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">A feature that further complicates and hides the true interpretation of the states is mixing due to the accidental degeneracies of two or three states.</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The mixed final eigenstates that result are spotted by noting their near degenerate energies and their lack of almost all of the above discussed features.</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Trial and error demixing using various weights yields states with the above features.</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The notation s/s′ or s/s″/s″ indicates in Table 1 that this particular state is a demixing of s + s′ etc.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The dynamical importance of the <IT>ψ</IT><SB>b</SB> = <IT>ψ</IT><SB>f</SB> + <IT>c</IT> planes is further confirmed by running many long classical trajectories that show that the motion, i.e. the flow of the trajectories, is mainly parallel to the <IT>ψ</IT><SB>f</SB> = <IT>ψ</IT><SB>b</SB> plane and in addition is mainly in the direction of the space diagonal i.e. guided by the condition <IT>ψ</IT><SB>f</SB> = <IT>ψ</IT><SB>b</SB> = <IT>ψ</IT><SB>a</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is not totally unexpected as <IT>ω</IT><SB>a</SB> ≈ <IT>ω</IT><SB>b</SB> ≈ <IT>ω</IT><SB>f</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None">This effect is reflected in the observation that in the organizing planes <IT>ψ</IT><SB>f</SB> = <IT>ψ</IT><SB>b</SB> and <IT>ψ</IT><SB>f</SB> = <IT>ψ</IT><SB>b</SB> + π the wave functions tend to have fibers of density running along the diagonal.</annotationART></s> <s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In fact a diagonal classification could have served many states as the organizing structure and assignment might have been made relative to it.</annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">We chose the planes as the organizing structures as breaks in this diagonal fibration often made assignment less than clear.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">To illustrate our ideas let us consider two states, state <IT>s</IT> = 7 and <IT>s</IT> = 43 at the bottom and the middle of the ladder respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both states are organized about <IT>ψ</IT><SB>f</SB> = <IT>ψ</IT><SB>b</SB> giving a DD <IT>ω</IT><SB>f</SB> = <IT>ω</IT><SB>b</SB> expectation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None">State 7 is a low state with its density running up the valley in the middle of the well as seen in Fig. 1c and 1a.</annotationART></s> <s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Recall again that due to the symmetry property mentioned in the section 3 all features come in double.</annotationART></s> <s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 1a looks down on the organizing plane and Fig. 1c looks sideways.</annotationART></s> <s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs19" novelty="None" advantage="None">In Fig. 2 the higher excited case is exhibited.</annotationART></s> <s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The highest density is in the plane <IT>ψ</IT><SB>f</SB> = <IT>ψ</IT><SB>b</SB> + π/8.</annotationART></s> <s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs20" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 2a and 2b look down on this plane of high density and Fig. 2c and 2d show a view from the side that shows transverse excitation.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs20" novelty="None" advantage="None">From the phase plots we see the quantum numbers <IT>n</IT><SB>a</SB> = 2 for state 7 (Fig. 1b) and <IT>n</IT><SB>a</SB> = 1 for state 43 (Fig. 2b) and <IT>l</IT><SB>b+f</SB> = 8 for state 7 and <IT>l</IT><SB>b+f</SB> = 7 for state 43.</annotationART></s> <s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs21" novelty="None" advantage="None">Using the polyad number <IT>P</IT> = 5 this implies <IT>n</IT><SB>s</SB> = <IT>P</IT> − (<IT>n</IT><SB>a</SB> + <IT>l</IT><SB>b+f</SB>)/2 = 0 for state 7 and <IT>n</IT><SB>s</SB> = 1 for state 43.</annotationART></s> <s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs21" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note: For state 43 phase simplicity only happens in the organizing plane.</annotationART></s> <s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs22" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 2d shows no useful phase information.</annotationART></s> <s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs22" novelty="None" advantage="None">The plot shows jumps along lines and ramp singularities where the phase value depends on the direction of approach.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs23" novelty="None" advantage="None">The transverse structure of the states becomes evident in density plots in some appropriate plane transverse to the plane of high density.</annotationART></s> <s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs23" novelty="None" advantage="None">In Fig. 1c we see that state 7 has <IT>t</IT> = 0 and in Fig. 2c we see that state 43 has <IT>t</IT> = 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs23" novelty="None" advantage="None">The number <IT>t</IT>′ does not make sense for state 7 and the number <IT>t</IT>′ = 2 for state 43 is rather unclear from Fig. 2c.</annotationART></s> <s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs24" novelty="None" advantage="None">However the phase plot in Fig. 2d shows two lines of phase jumps near the lines <IT>ψ</IT><SB>a</SB> = <IT>ψ</IT><SB>b</SB> ± π/2 and these lines of phase jumps indicate nodal lines of the density.</annotationART></s> <s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs24" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since this is a somewhat indirect indication of the value <IT>t</IT>′ = 2, in Table 1 the number <IT>t</IT>′ = 2 for state 43 is set in brackets.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs24" novelty="None" advantage="None">At this point 64 states for <IT>P</IT> = 5 can be assigned clearly by the same scheme.</annotationART></s> <s sid="143"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs25" novelty="None" advantage="None">An additional 38 states seem to resemble this picture.</annotationART></s> <s sid="144"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs25" novelty="None" advantage="None">The resemblance is only seen as trends from the systematic following of the 64 other ones.</annotationART></s> <s sid="145"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs25" novelty="None" advantage="None">For these, increasing but still smaller effects of many other resonances are taking their toll and they significantly degrade the assignable states into unassignable more heavily mixed quantum analogues of classical chaos.</annotationART></s> <s sid="146"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs26" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Table 1 indicates which states have less certain assignments.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="147"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">By comparing the phase function at the <IT>ψ</IT><SB>f</SB> = <IT>ψ</IT><SB>b</SB> (plane 1) and <IT>ψ</IT><SB>f</SB> = <IT>ψ</IT><SB>b</SB> + π (plane 2) wells for each pair of states with the same quantum numbers the (+) and (−) assignment can be made.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="148"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Even at this stage where other ladders discussed below are omitted spectral complexity arises from the interlacing of energy levels of different subladders.</annotationART></s> <s sid="149"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs27" novelty="None" advantage="None">The roughly 100 states on the ladder which only demands the DD-f/b lock for its construction gives a complex spectrum and nontransparent energy spacings.</annotationART></s> <s sid="150"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs27" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition the individual ladders appear irregular by the mixing of states.</annotationART></s> <s sid="151"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs28" novelty="None" advantage="None">A sequence of states which are pure excitations of a single organization element would form a regular ladder of energy levels looking like the spectrum of one anharmonic oscillator.</annotationART></s> <s sid="152"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs28" novelty="None" advantage="None">However by the mixing the eigenstates are mixtures of various pure excitations and thereby their energies are shifted and thereby the ladders appear more irregular.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="153"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs29" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reader will note that some ladder states in Table 1 are missing.</annotationART></s> <s sid="154"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs29" novelty="None" advantage="None">These states could not be found but their disappearance is confirmed using the anharmonic models expected energy spacing.</annotationART></s> <s sid="155"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs29" novelty="None" advantage="None">Formally these states lie among the highly mixed (chaotic?) states we discuss below.</annotationART></s> <s sid="156"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">They are mixings of more than two dynamically identifiable states and do not show the near degeneracy that our demixing process identifies.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="157"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">If we go back to displacements <IT>q</IT><SB><IT>j</IT></SB> corresponding to the original degrees of freedom, then we find the following for the motion of the H atom in states based on the above described organization element: In projections into the (<IT>q</IT><SB>s</SB>, <IT>q</IT><SB>a/b/f</SB>) planes a roughly rectangular region is seen whose sides are proportional to and .</annotationART></s> <s sid="158"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The hydrogen trajectories motion interior to the rectangle will be quasiperiodic motion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="159"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The exact trajectory depends on the initial choices of <IT>ϕ</IT><SB>s</SB> and <IT>ϕ</IT><SB>a/b/f</SB> and is really not important.</annotationART></s> <s sid="160"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the (<IT>q</IT><SB>a</SB>, <IT>q</IT><SB>b</SB>) plane we find ellipses whose relative ranges (excursion from zero displacement) in the (<IT>q</IT><SB>a</SB>, <IT>q</IT><SB>b</SB>) variables are .</annotationART></s> <s sid="161"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ellipses eccentricity depends on the organizing structures phase shift, <IT>viz.</IT><IT>ψ</IT><SB>a</SB> = <IT>ψ</IT><SB>b</SB> + <IT>δ</IT> → <IT>ϕ</IT><SB>a</SB> = <IT>ϕ</IT><SB>b</SB> + <IT>δ</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="162"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None"><IT>δ</IT> = 0 and π give zero angular momentum and something approaching a straight line motion while <IT>δ</IT> = ±π/2 gives maximal angular momentum and elliptical motion which becomes circular if <IT>n</IT><SB>a</SB> = <IT>n</IT><SB>b</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="163"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">The <IT>t</IT> value is the out of phase motion and causes fluctuations of the eccentricity.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.2.">Scheme for the upper end of the polyad</HEADER><P><s sid="164"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs30" novelty="None" advantage="None">At the upper end of the polyad we take to start states 160 and 161.</annotationART></s> <s sid="165"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs30" novelty="None" advantage="None">A cut in <IT>ψ</IT><SB>b</SB> = 0 (or any other value of <IT>ψ</IT><SB>b</SB>) reveals as we see in Fig. 3 for state 160 what looks like two columns of density localized around <IT>ψ</IT><SB>a</SB> = π and <IT>ψ</IT><SB>f</SB> = π.</annotationART></s> <s sid="166"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs30" novelty="None" advantage="None">In comparison state 161 (not shown) only has one column.</annotationART></s> <s sid="167"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs30" novelty="None" advantage="None">A cut in the plane <IT>ψ</IT><SB>b</SB> = <IT>constant</IT> is called to see that the columns really exist.</annotationART></s> <s sid="168"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs31" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 3 shows that they do for state 160 and it also holds for state 161.</annotationART></s> <s sid="169"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs31" novelty="None" advantage="None">Clearly for both these states the line <IT>ψ</IT><SB>a</SB> = π, <IT>ψ</IT><SB>f</SB> = π is the organizing structure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="170"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs31" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since it loops in <IT>ψ</IT><SB>b</SB>, mode b is decoupled and the phase picture for both states shows (Fig. 3 for state 160, state 161 not shown) that as <IT>ψ</IT><SB>b</SB> → <IT>ψ</IT><SB>b</SB> + 2π along the organizing line no wave fronts are crossed and hence there is no phase advance.</annotationART></s> <s sid="171"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs31" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hence <IT>l</IT><SB>b</SB> = <IT>n</IT><SB>b</SB> = 0.</annotationART></s> <s sid="172"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs32" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the upper end of the polyad also classical dynamics shows a flow in b direction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="173"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs32" novelty="None" advantage="None">As always the figures show all structures in two copies which in reality are only one structure.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="174"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs32" novelty="None" advantage="None">Now the <IT>ψ</IT><SB>a</SB> = <IT>ψ</IT><SB>f</SB> = π organizing structure implies that the phase locks are <IT>ϕ</IT><SB>a</SB> = <IT>ϕ</IT><SB>s</SB>/2 and <IT>ϕ</IT><SB>f</SB> = <IT>ϕ</IT><SB>s</SB>/2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="175"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">Time differentiation of these relations show that the frequency locks are of 2:1 Fermi type with the stretch mode locking with the bend mode a and the mode f.</annotationART></s> <s sid="176"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">Clearly for the organizing structure <IT>ψ</IT><SB>a</SB> = <IT>ψ</IT><SB>f</SB> then <IT>ϕ</IT><SB>a</SB> = <IT>ϕ</IT><SB>f</SB> is a valid phase lock and <IT>ω</IT><SB>a</SB> = <IT>ω</IT><SB>f</SB> is a DD 1 ∶ 1 frequency lock.</annotationART></s> <s sid="177"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since all three types of terms appear in the Hamiltonian we can be assured that all three frequencies are in lock and that the quantum numbers <IT>n</IT><SB>a</SB>, <IT>n</IT><SB>f</SB> and <IT>n</IT><SB>s</SB> no longer exist.</annotationART></s> <s sid="178"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">They must be replaced by three quantum numbers of the lock one of which can be <IT>P</IT> and the other two can be taken as the number of nodes seen in the <IT>ψ</IT><SB>a</SB> = 0 cut along the antidiagonal as <IT>t</IT><SB>1</SB> = 1 and along the diagonal as <IT>t</IT><SB>2</SB> = 0.</annotationART></s> <s sid="179"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">For state 161 since one column exists <IT>t</IT><SB>1</SB> = <IT>t</IT><SB>2</SB> = 0.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="180"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs33" novelty="None" advantage="None">If energy decreases from the top, then the classical flow turns into the space diagonal direction rather soon and accordingly only the four highest quantum states show (partly after demixing) a clean fiber structure in b direction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="181"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs33" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fiber is always sharp in the a direction but broad in the f direction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="182"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs34" novelty="None" advantage="None">This demonstrates again an emerging b–f mixing in the system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="183"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs34" novelty="None" advantage="None">The next seven states still show some tendency towards fibers in b direction (they are no longer really clean), but at the same time also show the beginning of fibers in the diagonal direction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="184"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs34" novelty="None" advantage="None">Their assignment as states organized along b fibers is less clear but still they continue the trends seen in the four highest states (partly after demixing).</annotationART></s> <s sid="185"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs35" novelty="None" advantage="None">The corresponding assignments for the 11 highest states are compiled in Table 2.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="186"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">An idea of the internal motion of the deuterium and the CF stretch can be obtained from the actions, phase relations and the <IT>t</IT><SB>1</SB> and <IT>t</IT><SB>2</SB> values.</annotationART></s> <s sid="187"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In all (<IT>q</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB>,<IT>q</IT><SB><IT>j</IT></SB>) planes the actions again define the maximal displacement of each <IT>q</IT><SB><IT>j</IT></SB> from its equilibrium.</annotationART></s> <s sid="188"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Clearly this range is meant in the sense that an average is made over the values of the two variables not represented in the plane.</annotationART></s> <s sid="189"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs36" novelty="None" advantage="None">The plane (<IT>q</IT><SB>b</SB>, <IT>q</IT><SB><IT>j</IT></SB>), <IT>j</IT> = a,f,s will show rectangularly bound quasiperiodic motion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="190"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs36" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the (<IT>q</IT><SB>s</SB>, <IT>q</IT><SB>a/f</SB>) plane a U shaped region is swept out.</annotationART></s> <s sid="191"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs36" novelty="None" advantage="None">Here <IT>q</IT><SB>a/f</SB> reaches its extreme values as <IT>q</IT><SB>s</SB> reaches its maximum displacement and <IT>q</IT><SB>s</SB> sweeps its range twice for each sweep of <IT>q</IT><SB><IT>a</IT>/<IT>f</IT></SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="192"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">Increasing <IT>t</IT><SB>1</SB> and/or <IT>t</IT><SB>2</SB> causes the lifted trajectory to oscillate in a tube about this basic U lift.</annotationART></s> <s sid="193"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">Of course <IT>q</IT><SB>f</SB> and <IT>q</IT><SB>a</SB> reach their maxima (minima) in phase as the three modes s, a and f are phase locked.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.3.">Patterns in the dense region of the polyad</HEADER><P><s sid="194"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs37" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the middle of the polyad there are approximately 35 states with very complicated wave functions which we could not classify in any scheme.</annotationART></s> <s sid="195"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is possible that further and closer analysis could reveal some systematics.</annotationART></s> <s sid="196"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs38" novelty="None" advantage="None">These states are dispersed among the states mentioned in subsection 4.1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="197"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs38" novelty="None" advantage="None">But interestingly a few simple states which do not fall into any scheme discussed so far are also dispersed in this region.</annotationART></s> <s sid="198"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs38" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this subsection we present a few of them.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="199"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs39" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 4 shows the structure of state 82, parts a and b give density and phase respectively in the plane <IT>ψ</IT><SB>f</SB> = 0 and parts c ans d show the plane <IT>ψ</IT><SB>b</SB> = <IT>ψ</IT><SB>a</SB> + 0.29 * 2π.</annotationART></s> <s sid="200"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs39" novelty="None" advantage="None">Part a demonstrates some concentration around <IT>ψ</IT><SB>a</SB> = ±π/2 and at the same time around <IT>ψ</IT><SB>a</SB> = <IT>ψ</IT><SB>b</SB> ±π/2 with a transverse excitation <IT>t</IT> = 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="201"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs39" novelty="None" advantage="None">Plots of the phases in various planes show that planes <IT>ψ</IT><SB>a</SB> = <IT>ψ</IT><SB>b</SB> + <IT>constant</IT> are the only planes with a simple phase structure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="202"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs40" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 4d shows it in the plane of highest density.</annotationART></s> <s sid="203"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs40" novelty="None" advantage="None">The phase function comes very close to a plane wave with <IT>l</IT><SB><IT>a</IT>+<IT>b</IT></SB> = 8 and <IT>l</IT><SB>f</SB> = 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="204"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">Together with the above mentioned transverse quantum number <IT>t</IT> = 1 this gives the complete assignment of the state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="205"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs41" novelty="None" advantage="None">In Fig. 4 notice that also the interaction between the degrees of freedom f and s has an effect, it concentrates the density mainly around <IT>ψ</IT><SB>f</SB> = 0 and <IT>ψ</IT><SB>f</SB> = π.</annotationART></s> <s sid="206"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs41" novelty="None" advantage="None">There are a few other examples (states 93, 111, 114, 122 and 136) which show such a clean phase function in planes <IT>ψ</IT><SB>b</SB> = <IT>ψ</IT><SB>a</SB> ±π/2 but do not show a clean phase function in any other plane.</annotationART></s> <s sid="207"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs41" novelty="None" advantage="None">There are approximately 5 other states where the phase function is not as clean as in Fig. 4d but comes close to a continuous deformation of a plane wave only in a plane of this type.</annotationART></s> <s sid="208"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs41" novelty="None" advantage="None">The motion of all these states is a circular motion of the H atom, two orthogonal bends with relative phase shift locked at ±π/2.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="209"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs42" novelty="None" advantage="None">Numerical results for state 80 are shown in Fig. 5, part a and b show density and phase respectively in the plane <IT>ψ</IT><SB>b</SB> = <IT>ψ</IT><SB>a</SB> ± <IT>ψ</IT><SB>f</SB> + π/2 which is the plane of high density and thereby the organizing structure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="210"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs42" novelty="None" advantage="None">Part c and d show density and phase respectively in the transverse plane <IT>ψ</IT><SB>f</SB> = 0.</annotationART></s> <s sid="211"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs42" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the plane of high density the phase function comes close to a plane wave with <IT>l</IT><SB>a+b</SB> = 6 and <IT>l</IT><SB>f+b</SB> = 5.</annotationART></s> <s sid="212"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs42" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is the only plane where the phase function is a continuous deformation of a plane wave.</annotationART></s> <s sid="213"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs42" novelty="None" advantage="None">This case is something new in so far as there is a plane with a simple phase function and at the same time not a single <IT>n</IT><SB><IT>j</IT></SB> has a definite value.</annotationART></s> <s sid="214"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs43" novelty="None" advantage="None">There is a locking involving all modes without implying a locking in any pair of modes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="215"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs43" novelty="None" advantage="None">A few other states (75,83,87,118) fall into the same scheme, i.e. they have simple phase functions only in a plane of the form <IT>ψ</IT><SB>b</SB> = <IT>ψ</IT><SB>a</SB> + <IT>ψ</IT><SB>f</SB> + <IT>constant</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="216"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">The implications for the motion of the atoms are as follows.</annotationART></s> <s sid="217"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the nonreduced variables the locking condition is <IT>ϕ</IT><SB>b</SB> + <IT>ϕ</IT><SB>s</SB>/2 − <IT>ϕ</IT><SB>a</SB> − <IT>ϕ</IT><SB>f</SB> = ±π/2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="218"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">This can be interpreted as a locking of the beat frequency between a pair of degrees of freedom to the beat frequency of the remaining pair of degrees of freedom.</annotationART></s> <s sid="219"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have two possibilities to group the four modes into appropriate pairs.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="5.">Conclusions</HEADER><P><s sid="220"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have shown how our previously developed methods can also be applied to systems with three degrees of freedom after reduction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="221"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">For 75 percent of the states the strategy works successfully.</annotationART></s> <s sid="222"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="New" advantage="None">We investigate the wave functions constructed on a toroidal configuration space.</annotationART></s> <s sid="223"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj5" novelty="New" advantage="None">We investigate on which subsets the density is concentrated and evaluate the phase function on this subset of high density and in addition the nodal structure perpendicular to it.</annotationART></s> <s sid="224"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" advantage="None">This allows us to obtain a set of excitation numbers and a complete assignment of the state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="225"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" advantage="None">The excitation numbers can be interpreted as quasi-conserved quantities for this particular state.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="226"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">The success of the method is based on three properties of our strategy which more traditional approaches starting from potential surfaces do not have.</annotationART></s> <s sid="227"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">First, we start from an algebraic Hamiltonian which naturally decomposes into an unperturbed <IT>H</IT><SB>0</SB> and a perturbation <IT>W</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="228"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">Perturbation theory assures us that <IT>W</IT> contains only the dominant interactions, leaving out those that do not affect the qualitative organization of the states.</annotationART></s> <s sid="229"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">In addition having the ideal <IT>H</IT><SB>0</SB> results in the classical Hamiltonian being formulated from the start in action and angle variables belonging to <IT>H</IT><SB>0</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="230"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">For a potential surface it is very complicated to construct an appropriate <IT>H</IT><SB>0</SB> and the corresponding action/angle variables.</annotationART></s> <s sid="231"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">Our knowledge of the correct <IT>H</IT><SB>0</SB> allows the continuous deformation connection of some eigenstates of <IT>H</IT> with the corresponding eigenstates of <IT>H</IT><SB>0</SB> which was useful for many states.</annotationART></s> <s sid="232"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">Second in the algebraic Hamiltonian the polyad (which for the real molecule is only an approximate conserved quantity) is an exactly conserved quantity and allows the reduction of the number of degrees of freedom.</annotationART></s> <s sid="233"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">We always deal with one degree of freedom less than the number of degrees of freedom on the potential surface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="234"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">Third, our strategy depends to a large extent on having a compact configuration space with nontrivial homology where the phase of the wave function is important and where the phase advances divided by 2π along the fundamental cycles of the configuration space provide a large part of the excitation numbers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="235"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None">In part also feature one is responsible for the importance of the phases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="236"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is an essential difference to working in usual position space.</annotationART></s> <s sid="237"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In total we have found a semiclassical representation of the states which is actually much simpler to view than the usual position space one.</annotationART></s> <s sid="238"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">We emphasize that no calculation is required to produce these states since theare gotten from eqn. (8).</annotationART></s> <s sid="239"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None">As discussed in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">ref. 13</REF>, when localization occurs it is often possible to lift the organizing structure back to molecular space in a qualitative manner and hence avoiding even the need to compute any trajectories.</annotationART></s> <s sid="240"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None">Qualitative pictures of the motion upon which the states are quantized are then available.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="241"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None">The classical dynamics of the system shows rather little regular motion and is strongly unstable.</annotationART></s> <s sid="242"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Then the question arises in which way the quantum states reflect anything from the classical chaos.</annotationART></s> <s sid="243"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">We propose the following answer: In the middle of the polyad a large number of states do not show any simple organization pattern.</annotationART></s> <s sid="244"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">For some of those states it might be that we simply have not found the right representation in which to see the organizational center.</annotationART></s> <s sid="245"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">However we doubt that this is the case for many states.</annotationART></s> <s sid="246"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs44" novelty="None" advantage="None">For many of the complicated states the wave function is really without a simple structure, it seems to be a complicated interference between several organizational structures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="247"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs44" novelty="None" advantage="None">Then immediately comes the idea to mix these states with their neighboring states to extract simple structures in the way as we did it for example for states 22 and 24.</annotationART></s> <s sid="248"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res29" novelty="None" advantage="None">For most of the complicated states this method does not lead to any success.</annotationART></s> <s sid="249"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">This indicates that underlying simple patterns are distributed over many states so that demixing becomes rather hopeless and maybe also meaningless.</annotationART></s> <s sid="250"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the spirit of reference<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF> this indicates that the density of states is already so high that many states fall into the energy interval over which states are considered almost degenerate and mix strongly.</annotationART></s> <s sid="251"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is a strong difference to the systems which could be reduced to two degrees of freedom.</annotationART></s> <s sid="252"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">There the density of states was much lower such that mixing only occurred occasionally between two neighboring states.</annotationART></s> <s sid="253"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">This stronger mixing gives some clue as to how the quantum wave functions become complicated for classically chaotic systems and for sufficiently high quantum excitation.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="254"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Finally there may come up the question why we do not use some of the common statistical procedures (like random matrix theory) to treat our system when effects of classical chaos become evident in a quantum system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="255"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The answer is: We are not satisfied with only generic (universal) properties of the system or with the investigation to which extent such universal properties are realized by our system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="256"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa3" novelty="None" advantage="None">We aim to investigate each individual quantum state one after the other and to work out its individual properties in order to arrive in the best case at a complete set of quantum numbers and in addition at a detailed description of the atomic motion underlying the individual state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="257"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Previous examples have shown that our procedure provides a complete classification for simpler systems which can be reduced to two degrees of freedom.</annotationART></s> <s sid="258"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">As the example presented in this paper shows, this program is doable with good success for a large number of states even in a system with originally four degrees of freedom, reducible only to three degrees of freedom and with a complicated classical dynamics.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
