<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b405013d" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Collective ionic motion in oxide fast-ion-conductors</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Structural correlations and dynamic disorder in the oxide fast-ion-conductor Ba<SB>2</SB>In<SB>2</SB>O<SB>5</SB> are deduced from a systematic study of the energy-hypersurface using periodic density-functional theory examining 2 × 10<SP>4</SP> local energy minima.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The structure observed experimentally is interpreted as a time and spatial average of those minima which are energetically-accessible.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The nature of these has extensive implications for the ionic conductivity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Transition paths connecting minima, characterized using the nudge-elastic-band method, indicate that low-energy collective ion movements must play important rôles in oxide fast-ion conductors such as Ba<SB>2</SB>In<SB>2</SB>O<SB>5</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Saddle-points energies for collective transport are lower in energy than those for conventional single-jump mechanisms.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER /><P><s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The complexity of grossly disordered structures hinders fundamental understanding of the functional properties of many classes of advanced materials.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Links between the dynamic structure, thermodynamic behaviour and ionic and electronic conductivity are central themes in contemporary solid-state science and disordered materials remain a challenge both to experiment and theory.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The present contribution focuses on fast-ionic conduction, using Ba<SB>2</SB>In<SB>2</SB>O<SB>5</SB> as a model system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Ba<SB>2</SB>In<SB>2</SB>O<SB>5</SB> exhibits a discontinuous jump in the ionic conductivity of more than one order of magnitude at 1173 K giving an ionic conductivity equal in magnitude to that of the widely used stabilized zirconias.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The increase in conductivity is attributed to an order–disorder transition involving oxygen atoms and vacancies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The structural aspects of the disordering and how this relates to the mechanism of ionic conductivity are of intense interest.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Present models most often describe the structures and thermodynamics of this and related materials in terms of random distributions of oxygen atoms and oxygen vacancies on the available oxygen sites and their dynamic behaviour in terms of single or correlated ion-jump mechanisms.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">2</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The purpose of this letter is to present a new, different model for grossly non-stoichiometric oxides in which significant vacancy–vacancy interactions strongly influence the local structural environment and to discuss the implications for the ionic conductivity.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The generic brownmillerite crystal structure A<SB>2</SB>B<SB>2</SB>O<SB>5</SB> adopted by Ba<SB>2</SB>In<SB>2</SB>O<SB>5</SB> consists of alternating two-dimensional layers of cooperatively tilted BO<SB>6</SB> octahedra and ordered arrangements of BO<SB>4</SB> tetrahedra.</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">There are three crystallographically distinct oxygen sites: O(1) in the equatorial plane of the octahedra, O(2) at the apices of the octahedra and O(3) those oxygens in the tetrahedra which are not shared with the octahedra.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">We investigate the structural features of Ba<SB>2</SB>In<SB>2</SB>O<SB>5</SB> at high temperatures through a thorough study of the full energy hypersurface of a 2 × 2 × 2 cell containing 36 atoms constructed by doubling a primitive cubic unit cell along each of the crystallographic directions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">All possible arrangements of the oxygen vacancies are considered.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Initially 20 oxygen atoms are distributed over the 24 oxygen lattice sites of the ABO<SB>3</SB> supercell (giving 10626 <IT>initial unrelaxed</IT> arrangements).</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">A symmetry routine reduces this total to 78 <IT>initial unrelaxed</IT> crystallographically non-equivalent arrangements.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Structural optimizations (with respect to <IT>all</IT> unit cell dimensions and atomic coordinates) of each arrangement are performed within periodic density functional theory (DFT) and the generalized gradient approximation (GGA) using a sufficiently large basis of projected augmented plane waves (a constant energy cut-off of 700 eV), as implemented in the Vienna <IT>ab initio</IT> simulation program (VASP).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3 cit4">3,4</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The optimizations are accompanied by large structural changes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Inspection of the optimized configurations guides our approach for finding additional local energy minima.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">At this stage other possible crystallographic sites (eight additional active sites for O(3)) within the initial cell are considered.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">A final total of 81 <IT>relaxed</IT> crystallographic non-equivalent configurations (CNCs) are thus obtained which, using the symmetry routine to determine the degeneracy of each CNC, gives a total of 21 500 <IT>relaxed</IT> local energy minima configurations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">We stress the importance of full structural optimizations of the configurations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">These are crucial since large energy changes accompany the structural relaxations and these determine not only the magnitude of the energy differences between the CNCs but even the relative order of energies.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The final energy <IT>vs</IT>. degeneracy plot for the 2 × 2 × 2 cell is given in Fig. 1, where each symbol refers to a separate <IT>relaxed</IT> crystallographic non-equivalent configuration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The numbers given in brackets for some CNCs represent the number of indium atoms with 2, 3, 4, 5 and 6 oxygen nearest neighbours, <IT>e.g.</IT> (00404) denotes four four-coordinate In-atoms and four six-coordinate In-atoms in the cell.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our choice of supercell does not permit formation of the stacking of tetrahedral layers observed experimentally in the ordered low-temperature form<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6">5,6</REF> (see structure marked C in Fig. 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The energy of this structure is calculated from an orthorhombic 18-atom cell and shown by a blue star in Fig. 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Several of the lowest-energy CNCs contain 50% octahedra and 50% tetrahedra (as indicated by red stars) and resemble the brownmillerite-type structure in that their structures consist of alternate layers of InO<SB>4</SB>-tetrahedra and InO<SB>6</SB>-octahedra.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the lowest energy CNC for the 2 × 2 × 2 cell, the tetrahedra are linked to form chains (see the chains in blue below the graph in Fig. 1) as in the low-temperature form<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6">5,6</REF> but the stacking from one tetrahedral layer to the next differs as illustrated in the lower part of Fig. 1 (compare structures marked C and B).</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Other types of connectivities within the tetrahedral layers are also observed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The zig-zag arrangement marked A in Fig. 1 represents one type of connectivity whereas others involves edge-sharing tetrahedra.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although we are using a 2 × 2 × 2 super cell and only see a limited range of the low energy configurations the calculations relate well to the different types of disorder observed in brownmillerite-structured compounds by transmission electron microscopy.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7 cit8 cit9">7–9</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In our interpretation, these reflect quenched-in higher-temperature dynamic disorder.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The CNC closest in energy to these low energy (00404)s is a (00080) (given by green symbols in Fig. 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">In all (00080)s one oxygen ion is removed from each InO<SB>6</SB>-octahedron yielding structures built up from corner-sharing square pyramids and the lowest energy (00080)-CNC resembles the ordered structure adopted by related compounds such as Sr<SB>2</SB>Mn<SB>2</SB>O<SB>5</SB>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Other low energy configurations contain mixtures of tetrahedra, square pyramids and octahedra.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our detailed systematic search of the potential energy hypersurface also allows us to consider the properties of higher energy CNCs.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">For example, the highest-energy (00404), marked by a blue triangle in Fig. 1, is closely related to the structure observed for La<SB>2</SB>Ni<SB>2</SB>O<SB>5</SB>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this and other high energy (00404)s, unlike the low-energy (00404)s, the four-coordinate geometry involves a square planar entity which for Ba<SB>2</SB>In<SB>2</SB>O<SB>5</SB> is much less favourable than tetrahedral.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">This feature is very important for ion transport and will be discussed further below.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The configurations which are energetically accessible at a given temperature can be thought of as representing snapshots of small regions of the disordered materials; the calculations thus identify local structural environments and structural correlations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is in accordance with the observation of short-length-scale non-cubic micro-domains in NMR experiments<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF> and the average structure observed experimentally can be interpreted as a time and spatial average of the different local environments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fractions of the different polyhedra as a function of temperature, are plotted in Fig. 2a.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">These are obtained by evaluating the appropriate thermodynamic (Boltzmann) average over all the configurations studied.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13 cit14">13,14</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Vibrational contributions to the Gibbs energy of each configuration are ignored.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fractions of octahedra and tetrahedra both remain close to 0.5 up to 2100 K. On increasing the temperature further, the number of square pyramids increases giving a smaller number of tetrahedra and octahedra.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The high-energy configurations contribute to thermodynamic properties only to a very limited degree even at high temperatures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The red dashed area of Fig. 1 shows the CNCs that contribute significantly at 2500 K; all other CNCs together contribute about 0.2%.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although the overall fractions of the various polyhedra remain almost constant up to 2100 K, the disorder arising from different arrangements of these polyhedra and thus the configurational entropy are significant even at lower temperatures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our results are in line with the entropy of the disordered phase being considerably lower than the ideal value obtained by the usual assumption that the oxygen atoms and vacancies are distributed randomly on the oxygen sub-lattice of the perovskite-type structure.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15 cit16">15,16</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reduced entropy is due the small number of energetically accessible configurations at the temperatures considered here.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The energies of the different local structural environments give valuable information that must be taken into account when considering mechanisms of ion transport.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">A conventional vacancy jump mechanism requires different types of local short-range order that we show here are high in energy and thus make a negligible contribution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ionic movement is highly restricted by the local symmetry as seen e.g. by the high energy of the square-planar relative to the tetrahedral entity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The occupancy of the O(1), O(2) and O(3) sites shown in Fig. 2b completes the picture.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">O(1) and O(2) are fully populated up to 2100 K after which the population of O(2) decreases significantly.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">O(1) is fully populated even at significantly higher temperatures which supports the two-dimensional disorder and conductivity at intermediate temperatures reported previously.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, the nature of the low-energy structural configurations has extensive implications for the ionic conductivity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa4" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have investigated transition paths connecting low-energy CNCs using the climbing image nudged-elastic-band method.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17 cit18">17,18</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">A set of <IT>initial</IT> configurations representing a discrete path between two local minima configurations is constructed using some (usually linear) interpolation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Neighbouring configurations are connected with spring forces.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">A constrained minimisation of the total energy (including both true interaction energy and unphysical spring energies) is carried out in which the parallel component of the true interaction force and the perpendicular component of the net spring force are projected out.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results indicate strongly that collective ion movements are important in fast oxide-ion conductors such as Ba<SB>2</SB>In<SB>2</SB>O<SB>5</SB>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">We use the minimum energy path connecting the (00404)-CNC with a zig-zag pattern of tetrahedra (marked A in both Figs. 1 and 3) and the (00404)-CNC with chains of tetrahedra (marked B in both in Figs. 1 and 3) as an example to illustrate the collective ionic movement.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Structural aspects of the reconstructive transformation are illustrated in Fig. 3 showing the local environment at selected reaction coordinates.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The intermediate CNC is structurally similar to A, although here every alternate tetrahedron is considerably distorted compared to A. The energy barrier between these two zig-zag configurations is less than 0.1 eV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The subsequent energy barrier for the formation of B which is crucial for ion transport is only 0.48 eV (for our 36-atom supercell).</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Using symmetry we can also construct pathways connecting a large number of local energy minima.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None">As an example, a reflection of the path in Fig. 3 through the origin provides a mechanism by which any local energy minimum along the path can be transformed into one which is symmetrically equivalent.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, the chain configuration marked B can transform into a mirror-image through a complex pathway passing through three local energy minima.</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">This particular transport mechanism involves O(3)-oxygen sites exclusively in agreement with an earlier NMR-study <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF> and the ionic movements thus takes place in the <IT>ab</IT>-plane giving two-dimensional conductivity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Other energy pathways connecting (00404)-CNC’s have saddle-points with comparable energy barriers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The energy barrier of the transition path connecting the (00404)-CNC with chains of tetrahedra (marked B in Fig. 3) to the lowest energy (00080), involving motion of both O(3) and O(2) ions, is found to be somewhat higher and so contributes much less to the ion transport.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs19" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is important to stress that the minimum energy pathway gives a saddle-point energy lower in energy than the lowest energy configuration obtained from configuration B in Fig. 1 by moving only one oxygen atom.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">This shows that collective transport of this kind is energetically significant compared to single-jump mechanisms, the cost of which is high as they involve the breaking of an indium-oxygen bond as the oxygen ion climbs out of its Madelung well.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast the collective transport mechanism in Ba<SB>2</SB>In<SB>2</SB>O<SB>5</SB> involves different low-energy local structural environments and simultaneous bond making and bond breaking.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs20" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition to the movement of the oxygen ions giving rise to the transport, other ions are involved and even the Ba- and In-atoms move appreciably in a cooperative fashion along the transition pathway.</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">A larger unit cell will give rise to other types of similar (00404) configurations with different stacking of two or more tetrahedral layers and different connectivities within each tetrahedral layer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The energy barrier for transitions between these will be similar and the cell size does not affect our interpretation of the general features of the transition paths that gives rise to collective ionic motion.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our approach combining periodic DFT, efficient use of symmetry and transition state location allows us to obtain a unified picture of the link between dynamic structure, energetics and ion transport in oxide fast-ion conductors such as Ba<SB>2</SB>In<SB>2</SB>O<SB>5</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although the small cell size to which we are restricted by the cost of the first principles calculations approximates the density of states, and thus the temperature scale, our qualitative interpretation of the local order in the disordered state is unaffected.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our method, in which all configurations are explicitly relaxed, differs from the cluster variation method<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19">19</REF> which has proved problematic for perovskites<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF>.<IT>Ab initio</IT> molecular dynamics is still unfeasible for these systems due to inaccessible long sampling times.</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, the use of interatomic potentials, needed for classical molecular dynamics, has proved unreliable (unpublished work) mainly due to the large variations in local structure.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The collective ionic motion suggested has similarities to the recent reports of quasi-collective surface diffusion involving several atoms for metal surfaces by transmission electron microscopy<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF> and by density-functional theory nudge-elastic-band calculations.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this paper we have identified a collective diffusion mechanism in a bulk ionic material with strong electrostatic interactions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is tempting to suggest that this type of collective ionic motion is a characteristic of fast ionic conductors in general.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
