<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b407297a" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Vibrational deactivation studies of OH X <SP>2</SP>Π (<IT>v</IT> = 1–5) by N<SB>2</SB> and O<SB>2</SB></annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">The deactivation kinetics of vibrationally excited OH X <SP>2</SP>Π (<IT>v</IT> = 1–5) were studied using a pulsed laser photolysis-pulsed laser induced fluorescence technique.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">Temporal profiles of OH (<IT>v</IT>) were obtained by exciting off-diagonal (Δ<IT>v</IT> = −1,−3) transitions in the A–X band of OH and monitoring the diagonal, blue shifted fluorescence.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Photolysis of O<SB>3</SB> at 266 nm was used to produce O<SP>1</SP>D which reacted rapidly with H<SB>2</SB>, CH<SB>4</SB> and H<SB>2</SB>O to produce OH (<IT>v</IT>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Deactivation rate coefficients for OH (<IT>v</IT> = 1–5) with O<SB>2</SB> and N<SB>2</SB> and for OH (<IT>v</IT> = 2,1) with O<SB>3</SB> were obtained.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The deactivation rate coefficients show an exponential dependence on vibrational level for both O<SB>2</SB> and N<SB>2</SB>, however O<SB>2</SB> is much more efficient.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="1.">Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">An understanding of the kinetics of relaxation of vibrational levels of the OH radical is a topic of considerable interest both from fundamental and practical standpoints.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2 cit3">1–3</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the troposphere and stratosphere the reaction of O(<SP>1</SP>D) with water produces OH in the first three vibrationally excited levels and with considerable rotational excitation.O(<SP>1</SP>D) + H<SB>2</SB>O → 2 OH (<IT>v</IT> ≤ 3)Reaction (1) is the main source of the hydroxyl radical in the lower atmosphere.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reaction has been studied extensively<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF> and it is clear that the OH radical containing the old hydrogen-oxygen bond is produced vibrationally “cold” with 90% of the molecules in the <IT>v</IT> = 0 level, while the newly formed OH radical is produced with up to three quanta of vibrational excitation, the thermodynamic limit.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In a study of the reaction of O<SP>1</SP>D with H<SB>2</SB><SP>18</SP>O, Saunder <IT>et al</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">(1992)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF> reported relative OH vibrational populations of 0.39(<IT>v</IT> = 0):0.29(<IT>v</IT> = 1):0.3(<IT>v</IT> = 2) and we have observed population in <IT>v</IT> = 3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Under tropospheric and stratospheric conditions N<SB>2</SB>, O<SB>2</SB>, and H<SB>2</SB>O are the potential quenchers for the vibrationally excited OH.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rate of relaxation determines the extent of any deviation from local thermodynamic equilibrium.</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition collisions with H<SB>2</SB>O are potentially reactive with implications for the isotopic distribution of tropospheric H<SB>2</SB>O. Reaction (1) is also the main source of interference in laser based sensors which utilize laser induced fluorescence (LIF) for the measurement of the OH radical.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">A detailed knowledge of OH relaxation rates in the lower atmosphere requires state specific relaxation rate coefficients for OH (<IT>v</IT> = 1–3) with N<SB>2</SB>, O<SB>2</SB>, and H<SB>2</SB>O. These rate coefficients are also required to model, and devise strategies to minimize, OH interference effects in laser based OH sensors.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reaction of H atoms with ozone produces OH with up to nine quanta of vibrational excitation and an inverted vibrational population distribution.H + O<SB>3</SB> → OH (<IT>v</IT> ≤ 9) + O<SB>2</SB>The vibrationally excited ground state OH radicals emit light in the infrared and red spectral region, hence reaction (2) is responsible for the intense Meinel emission from OH X <SP>2</SP>A which occurs in the 80–100 km region and is one of the dominant features of the atmospheric nightglow.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2">1,2</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The spectral characteristics of these emissions are important to provide a comprehensive analysis of the chemistry taking place in the earth’s mesosphere and mesopause.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6">5,6</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Analysis of the temporal and spatial structures in these emissions can be used to study the propagation of atmospheric gravity waves through the mesosphere.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Accurate vibrational deactivation coefficients of highly vibrationally excited OH are a critical component of models of nighttime airglow emissions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2 cit8">2,8</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">However the database on vibrational deactivation of OH with potential atmospheric quenchers is limited.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">There have been several measurements of deactivation of OH (<IT>v</IT> = 1,2,3) with H<SB>2</SB>O, including one from our laboratory.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">There have been measurements on deactivation of OH with up to 12 quanta of vibrational excitation in collision with O<SB>2</SB> but the database is limited,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10 cit11 cit12 cit13 cit14 cit15">10–15</REF> and there are no reported measurements of deactivation by the most abundant atmospheric gas, nitrogen, for vibrational levels below <IT>v</IT> = 8.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this work we report deactivation coefficients for OH with up to five quanta of vibrational excitation by O<SB>2</SB> and N<SB>2</SB> and, in addition, some preliminary measurements on deactivation of OH (<IT>v</IT> = 1,2) with O<SB>3</SB>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.">Experimental</HEADER><P><s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Our experimental approach has been described in detail elsewhere:<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF> We utilized the pulsed laser photolysis-pulsed laser induce fluorescence (PLP-PLIF) technique to measure temporal profiles of OH(<IT>v</IT> = 1–5) under pseudo-first-order conditions at different pressures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="None" advantage="None">OH radicals were produced by reaction of O(<SP>1</SP>D) with an H-atom donor: H<SB>2</SB>, H<SB>2</SB>O, or CH<SB>4</SB>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Experiments were performed in an octahedral stainless steel cell having internal volume of about 3.2 L. Two Pyrex glass cylindrical side arms, 4 cm internal diameter and 5 cm long, were attached on opposite sides of the cell.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Photolysis and probe lasers were aligned on the same axis, entering the cell through a quartz window.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The O(<SP>1</SP>D) was produced by the pulsed laser photolysis of O<SB>3</SB> using the 266 nm fourth harmonic output from a Nd-YAG laser (Quanta-Ray GCR 16).</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Typical initial O(<SP>1</SP>D) concentrations were calculated to be 8 × 10<SP>12</SP> atoms cm<SP>−3</SP>, based on laser fluence and ozone concentration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The OH radical, formed by the reaction between the O(<SP>1</SP>D) and the H-atom donor, was then excited by a Nd:YAG pumped, frequency doubled, tunable dye laser or, alternatively, by an optical parametic oscillator (OPO: Quanta-Ray MOPO-730), pumped by the third harmonic of a Nd-YAG laser (Quanta-Ray PRO 270).</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Vibrationally excited OH radicals were monitored by LIF exciting Δ<IT>v</IT> = −1 or −3 transitions in the A–X band at the wavelengths listed in Table 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fluorescence was monitored <IT>via</IT> the A–X (0–0, 1–1 and 2–2) transitions at 308–320 nm using a photomultiplier tube, and using appropriate filters to minimize scattered light.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The photomultiplier output was appropriately terminated and fed to a 500-MHz digital oscilloscope to obtain the integrated voltage averaged for (typically) 100 laser shots.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Kinetic information was obtained by varying the delay between the photolysis and the probe lasers using a digital delay generator.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Experiments were performed under “slow-flow” conditions in order to avoid buildup of by-products.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Flows were monitored using calibrated mass flow meters.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">N<SB>2</SB> and O<SB>2</SB> were used without further purification.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Bulbs containing dilute mixtures of the H-atom donors were made up manometrically.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Ozone was produced by flowing pure oxygen through a commercial ozonizer and freezing the product on silica gel in an ozone trap cooled by a dry-ice–methanol slush (196 K).</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Ozone concentrations were measured by photometry at 254 nm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ozone cross section used to calculate the concentration was <IT>σ</IT> = 1.15 × 10<SP>−17</SP> cm<SP>−2</SP>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Concentrations of O<SB>2</SB> were calculated from flows.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Concentrations of N<SB>2</SB> were calculated from flows and, because of the large partial pressures of N<SB>2</SB>, were measured barometrically.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Agreement between the concentrations measured barometrically and those based on flows was excellent.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The pure gases and chemicals used in this study had the following stated minimum purities: H<SB>2</SB>, 99.999%; CH<SB>4</SB>, 99.99%, O<SB>2</SB> 99.99%, He 99.99%.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">They were used without any further purification.</annotationART></s></P><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.1.">OH(<IT>v</IT>) production and detection</HEADER><P><s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">OH radicals were produced by the following sequence of reactions:O<SB>3</SB> + <IT>hv</IT><SB>266nm</SB> → O<SB>2</SB>(<SP>1</SP>Δ) + O(<SP>1</SP>D)O(<SP>1</SP>D) + CH<SB>4</SB> → OH(<IT>ν</IT>) + CH<SB>3</SB>O(<SP>1</SP>D) + H<SB>2</SB> → OH(<IT>ν</IT>) + HO(<SP>1</SP>D) + H<SB>2</SB>O → 2 OH(<IT>ν</IT> ≤ 3)As noted above LIF was excited by long wavelength off-diagonal transitions with fluorescence detection on the strong (0,0), (1,1) and (2,2) transitions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="New" advantage="None">This excitation/detection approach has two advantages, firstly we observe fluorescence which is blue shifted relative to the excitation wavelengths minimizing probe laser scatter.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">Secondly, ozone does not absorb at the excitation wavelengths, eliminating the production of OH by the probe laser.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The LIF signal from OH generated by the probe laser can be a significant source of interference when excitation transitions utilizing Δ<IT>v</IT> = 0, +1 branches are used since the absorption coefficient of ozone is significant at these wavelengths.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">OH (<IT>v</IT> = 1,2) were monitored exciting the hydroxyl radical on Δ<IT>v</IT> = −1 transitions at 345.9 nm and 350.9 nm respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The OH (<IT>ν</IT> = 4, 5) were monitored exciting the hydroxyl radical on Δ<IT>v</IT> = −3 transitions at 451 nm and 453.3 nm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">OH (<IT>v</IT> = 3) was monitored using both approaches at 356.5 nm and 449 nm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The transitions and wavelengths are summarized in Table 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">We used Lifbase<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF> simulations to model and assign the observed OH LIF spectra and found very good agreement between the simulations and the experimental spectrum assuming that the OH is rotationally thermalized.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Figs. 1 and 2 show sections of the LIF spectra of the (0–3),(1–4) and (2–5) transitions of the OH radical produced in reaction (4).</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The lines used for kinetic studies of <IT>v</IT> = 4 and 5 are labeled.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Simulations computed with Lifbase are included for comparison.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rotational temperatures used in the simulations are 298 K. The relative vibrational populations of <IT>v</IT> = 3, 4 and 5 were taken to be 5:1:0.4 and give good agreement between the experimental spectra and the simulations.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Knowledge of the vibrational product distributions in reactions (1), (4) and (5) is important in determining an experimental strategy for the excitation of the various vibrational levels and for assessing possible complications from vibrational cascading.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Product distributions for the reaction of O(<SP>1</SP>D) with hydrogen and methane have been extensively studied using LIF and infrared emission spectroscopy although attempts to determine the full product vibrational distribution are limited.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18 cit19 cit20 cit21">18–21</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">We calculate Δ<IT>H</IT><SB>r,298</SB>° = −43.0 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> for reaction 4 with CH<SB>4</SB> as the H donor and −43.7 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> for reaction (5) with H<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">These values of Δ<IT>H</IT><SB>r,298</SB>° would limit OH production to levels with 4 quanta of vibrational excitation or less.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">However the translational energy of of O<SP>1</SP>D produced by reaction 3 is considerable.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Dylewski <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF>. have measured the energy and angular distribution of O<SP>1</SP>D produced from ozone photolysis at wavelengths between 235 nm and 305 nm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">At 265 nm they find that O<SB>2</SB>(<SP>1</SP>Δ) is formed predominantly in <IT>v</IT> = 0 with O<SP>1</SP>D being produced with 0.6 eV of translational energy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">This additional translational energy makes production of OH (<IT>v</IT> = 5) exothermic and we observe its production in both reactions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">This appears to be the first observation of <IT>v</IT> = 5 production in reactions (4) and (5).</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The LIF and infrared emission studies suggest the vibrational distributions are similar for both reactions (4) and (5).</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The population distribution peaks in <IT>v</IT> = 2 with about 25% of the population, approximately 20% is in <IT>v</IT> = 0,1,3 and approximately 10% in <IT>v</IT> = 4.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have not attempted to accurately quantify the relative vibrational distributions and the distributions noted above for reaction (4) may be partially relaxed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">We did not perform extensive spectral scans for reaction (5).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">We observed production of vibrationally excited OH in <IT>v</IT> = 1, 2, and 3 in the reaction of O(<SP>1</SP>D) with H<SB>2</SB>O. As noted above the dynamics of the reaction between <SP>16</SP>O(<SP>1</SP>D) with H<SB>2</SB><SP>18</SP>O has been studied extensively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Sauder <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF>. measured the vibrational distribution in the newly formed <SP>16</SP>OH and reported relative populations 0.39 (<IT>v</IT> = 0): 0.29 (<IT>v</IT> = 1): 0.3 (<IT>v</IT> ≥ 2) while the OH radical with the old bond was formed predominantly in the ground state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Again, while we made no attempt to accurately quantify the nascent OH product distribution from this latter reaction, we were able to observe the production of OH(<IT>v</IT> = 3).</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Population of OH(<IT>v</IT> = 3) has been previously observed in this laboratory.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The formation of OH(<IT>v</IT> = 3) from thermal reactants would be slightly endothermic using Δ<SB>f</SB><IT>H</IT><SB>298</SB>(OH) = 9.31 ± 0.29 kcal/mol as suggested in the JANAF compilation.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">However Δ<SB>f</SB><IT>H</IT><SB>298</SB>(OH) has been recently re-evaluated by Ruscic <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Using their revised Δ<SB>f</SB><IT>H</IT><SB>298</SB>(OH) = 8.89 ± 0.09 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>, the formation of OH(<IT>v</IT> = 3) is slightly exothermic.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">As for reactions (4) and (5), the translational energy associated with the O<SP>1</SP>D reactant could allow exothermic production of OH (<IT>v</IT> = 3) using either thermochemistry.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.">Results</HEADER><P><s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The kinetic analysis that is appropriate to our experimental conditions has been described in detail by Silvente <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">O<SP>1</SP>D is produced by photolysis of ozone and reacts rapidly to produce vibrationally excited OH.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The timescale for reaction of 99% of the O<SP>1</SP>D was typically 15 μs at the lowest reactant concentrations, producing both vibrationally and rotationally excited OH.</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Rotational equilibration is known to be fast,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF> and this was confirmed by our experimentally measured LIF spectra which showed no deviation from 300 K rotational distributions on timescales as short as 1 μs at low pressure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">We are confident that all kinetic measurements monitored rotationally thermalized OH.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fast OH production was followed by relatively slow decay of each vibrationally excited OH level.</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Under our typical experimental concentrations [O<SB>3</SB>] = 1.6 × 10<SP>14</SP> cm<SP>−3</SP>; [H<SB>2</SB>] = 6.5 × 10<SP>14</SP> cm<SP>−3</SP>; [CH<SB>4</SB>] = 6.5 × 10<SP>14</SP> cm<SP>−3</SP>; [H<SB>2</SB>O] &lt; 6.5 × 10<SP>13</SP> cm<SP>−3</SP>, relaxation by the OH precursors was small compared with the measured vibrational decay rates.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our data analysis was identical to the procedure adopted previously in our study of deactivation rates of OH (<IT>v</IT> = 1,2,3).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">If we assume pseudo-first-order conditions ([R] ≫ [O(<SP>1</SP>D)]), the temporal decay profiles for each vibrational level can be described by an analytical expression<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF>.[OH(<IT>v</IT>)]<SB><IT>t</IT></SB> = <IT>C</IT><SB><IT>v</IT></SB>exp(−<IT>k</IT>′<IT>t</IT>)where<IT>k</IT>′ is the pseudo-first order loss rate of OH (<IT>v</IT>) <IT>i.e.</IT><IT>k</IT><SB><IT>v</IT></SB>[O<SB>2</SB>] or <IT>k</IT><SB><IT>v</IT></SB>[N<SB>2</SB>]</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None"><IT>k</IT><SB>L</SB> is the pseudo-first-order loss rate of O(<SP>1</SP>D), <IT>i.e.</IT> k<SB>O(<SP>1</SP>D)+R</SB>[R] and R is the OH precursor</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None"><IT>p</IT><SB><IT>v</IT></SB> is the fractional population produced in vibrational level <IT>v</IT>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Solutions give a complex double exponential expression with production and loss terms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">If cascading is negligible the deactivation process produces only OH(<IT>v</IT> = 0) and all vibrational levels follow an identical expression.</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">If cascading, <IT>i.e.</IT> stepwise quenching, is included, a more complex expression is obtained which contains the detailed state-to-state quenching rate coefficients, as described in appendix 1 of Silvente <IT>et al</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fitting to the detailed analytical expression which includes quenching becomes impractical but the profiles are still described to a good approximation by eqn. (I) if <IT>k</IT><SB>q</SB> increases significantly as a function of increasing vibrational level.</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this case, the quenching rate constant for any given level becomes limiting at long times, as all higher levels have already decayed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Under these conditions the decay portion of the temporal profile is described by a simple exponential loss.[OH]<SB><IT>v</IT></SB> = <IT>C</IT> exp (−<IT>k</IT>′<IT>t</IT>)In some cases complete temporal profiles were obtained including both production and loss of OH(<IT>v</IT>) and these profiles were fitted to the eqn. (I) containing the exponential production and loss terms but neglecting quenching.</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The decay section of these profiles was also fit by the simplified single exponential loss expression eqn. (II).</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">In all cases the pseudo-first-order decay rates obtained using eqn. (I) agreed well with those obtained from the single exponential fit, eqn. (II).</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">However this requires acquisition of many data points at short reaction times to give the fast production portion of the temporal profile and this does not give any information on the quantity of interest, the deactivation rate coefficient.</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this work most of the temporal profiles included only a few points at short reaction times and decays were evaluated visually and the exponential portions of the decay were fitted to the single exponential expression, eqn. (II) to give the pseudo first order decay rate <IT>k</IT>′.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 3 shows an example of such decays for deactivation of <IT>v</IT> = 4 in N<SB>2.</SB> The decays show good exponential behavior over greater than three 1/e decay times.</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The vibrational deactivation rate coefficient, <IT>k</IT><SB><IT>v</IT></SB>, was then obtained by plotting <IT>k</IT>′ as a function of the concentration of the quenching gas, as shown in Figs. 4–6.</annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">By using three OH production schemes with different chemistry and different vibrational product distributions we attempted to ensure that the influence of secondary chemistry and vibrational cascading on our measured rates was minimal.</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Individually measured rate coefficients together with 2<IT>σ</IT> errors of precision are detailed in Table 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The averages of these rate coefficients for each vibrational level are summarized in Table 3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The errors in Table 3 are ±30% and represent a conservative estimate of overall accuracy based on our ability to reproduce well established thermal OH rates.</annotationART></s></P><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.1.">O<SB>2</SB> Deactivation rate coefficients</HEADER><P><s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Experiments using oxygen as collider, were typically carried out between 30 and 130 Torr of total pressure, helium being the buffer gas and with O<SB>2</SB> partial pressures of up to 40 Torr being used in measurements on <IT>v</IT> = 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Experiments were performed using all three H-atom donors for measurements on OH(<IT>v</IT> = 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">For <IT>v</IT> = 2–5 two production schemes were used for each level.</annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Deactivation rate coefficients were obtained by plotting the pseudo-first order decay rate as a function of O<SB>2</SB> concentration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 4 shows plots of pseudo-first-order decay rate <IT>vs.</IT> [O<SB>2</SB>] for OH(<IT>v</IT> = 2,4,5).</annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The deactivation rate coefficients obtained in the O<SB>2</SB> experiments are summarized in Table 2 which lists the rate coefficients obtained with the individual H-atom donors.</annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Typical 2<IT>σ</IT> errors of precision are less than 5% and it can be seen that the rate coefficients obtained using the different OH production schemes are in excellent agreement suggesting that errors due to cascading effects or secondary chemistry are negligible.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.2.">N<SB>2</SB> Deactivation rate coefficients</HEADER><P><s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Experiments in N<SB>2</SB> were performed using all three H-atom donors for OH (<IT>v</IT> = 1,2) and both the H<SB>2</SB> and CH<SB>4</SB> were used for measurements on OH (<IT>v</IT> = 3,4,5).</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Due to the extremely low efficiency of nitrogen in the relaxation process, pressures of up to 400 Torr were required to measure significant decay rates for OH (<IT>v</IT> = 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 5 shows a plot of the pseudo-first-order decay rate <IT>vs.</IT> [N<SB>2</SB>] for OH (<IT>v</IT> = 3,4,5).</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results are summarized in Table 2 with the rate coefficients obtained using each H-atom donor listed individually, and, again, we obtain excellent agreement between the rate coefficients obtained using the different precursors.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.3.">O<SB>3</SB> Deactivation rate coefficients</HEADER><P><s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to be able to assess the effects of O<SB>3</SB> on vibrational deactivation, rate coefficients were measured for deactivation of OH (<IT>v</IT> = 1,2) with O<SB>3</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">These experiments were much more limited in scope with single sets of measurements being made for each level.</annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Reaction 4 was used for OH production.</annotationART></s> <s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">At higher ozone concentrations there was evidence for complications from secondary chemistry manifested by an initial rise in the signal, an initial fast decay and then a slow decay.</annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Simulations indicated that the initial fast decay represents the vibrational deactivation rate and that the “tail” is caused by slow generation of vibrationally excited OH <IT>via</IT> the reaction of H atoms with ozone.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 6 shows a plots of pseudo first order decay rate as a function of O<SB>3</SB> concentration for OH (<IT>v</IT> = 1,2) with the pseudo first order decay rate calculated from the initial fast decay.</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rate coefficients are listed in Table 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The 2<IT>σ</IT> errors of precision in these measurements are ∼20% for each measurement, considerably higher than the errors of precision in the N<SB>2</SB> and O<SB>2</SB> data.</annotationART></s> <s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, given the limited number of measurements made and the complications from secondary chemistry at high O<SB>3</SB> we consider the uncertainty in these rate coefficients to be considerably higher than for those measured with O<SB>2</SB> and N<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">However effects of secondary chemistry should only lead to an underestimation of the actual deactivation coefficient and they should be considered as good lower limits to the actual deactivation rate coefficients.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.">Potential sources of error</HEADER><P><s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Cascading and secondary chemistry are the main potential sources of error in these experiments and this is discussed in detail by Silvente <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Cascading effects are errors caused by the relaxation from higher vibrational levels into the vibrational level being monitored.</annotationART></s> <s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Such an effect would result in the measured deactivation rate coefficient being too slow.</annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">For this effect to be significant there must be an appreciable population of higher vibrational levels relaxing into the level which is being monitored and the relaxation rates must be similar.</annotationART></s> <s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Secondary chemistry results in the production of vibrationally excited OH on long time scales and again will result in measured deactivation rate coefficient being too slow.</annotationART></s> <s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Production of H atoms and their subsequent reaction with ozone is the most important potential source of artifacts due to secondary chemistry and can occur with H<SB>2</SB> and to a lesser extent CH<SB>4</SB> as the H-atom donor.</annotationART></s> <s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">This should not be a problem with H<SB>2</SB>O. It can be made insignificant if low ozone concentrations are used.</annotationART></s> <s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">An analysis of secondary chemistry using Acuchem suggests that at the ozone concentrations used here such effects are indeed negligible for the O<SB>2</SB> and N<SB>2</SB> measurements.</annotationART></s> <s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">As noted above elevated O<SB>3</SB> levels are required to measure its deactivation rate and complications from secondary chemistry are unavoidable.</annotationART></s> <s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the O<SB>2</SB> and N<SB>2</SB> measurements, the good agreement between rate coefficients obtained using the different H-atom donors suggests that artifacts due to secondary chemistry and vibrational cascading are negligible.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="5.">Discussion</HEADER><P><s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Table 3 summarizes the vibrational deactivation coefficients measured by LIF during this study together with the prior results for O<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Three prior experimental studies have reported rate coefficients on the deactivation of the lower vibrational levels of the OH radical by O<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Rensberger <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF>. selectively produced OH(<IT>v</IT> = 2) by infrared excitation and measured the vibrational deactivation rate by LIF.</annotationART></s> <s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">This experimental approach should preclude complications from cascading from higher vibrationally excited states to <IT>v</IT> = 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="143"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Dodd <IT>et al</IT>. used electron beam excitation of O<SB>3</SB>/O<SB>2</SB>/H<SB>2</SB>/Ar mixtures to produce vibrationally excited OH <IT>via</IT> reaction (2).</annotationART></s> <s sid="144"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The OH was then monitored by infrared emission.</annotationART></s> <s sid="145"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Their initial work used a single quantum deactivation model to interpret their data and rate coefficients were reported for deactivation of OH (<IT>v</IT> = 1–3).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="146"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">In a subsequent publication<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF> they reported rate coefficients for deactivation of OH (<IT>v</IT> = 1–6) based on a more extensive analysis using a model which included multiquantum deactivation and more detailed chemistry.</annotationART></s> <s sid="147"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our results for OH(3–5) are in good agreement with the results of Dodd <IT>et al</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="148"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">However our measured rate coefficients are significantly slower than the values reported by Rensberg <IT>et al</IT>. and Dodd <IT>et al</IT>. for <IT>v</IT> = 2 and by Dodd <IT>et al</IT>. for <IT>v</IT> = 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="149"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reasons for this discrepancy are unclear.</annotationART></s> <s sid="150"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">As we note above vibrational cascading is a potential problem in chemical production of vibrationally excited OH and this might influence the results for low vibrational levels when CH<SB>4</SB> or H<SB>2</SB> are used as precursors, however the amount of <IT>v</IT> = 3 produced with H<SB>2</SB>O as a precursor appears to very small and both cascading effects and complications from secondary chemistry should be negligible for our <IT>v</IT> = 2 measurement.</annotationART></s> <s sid="151"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">If cascading were producing an artifact in our measurements the very different vibrational product distributions for reaction (1) as compared with reactions (4) and (5) should produce significantly different deactivation rate coefficients.</annotationART></s> <s sid="152"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">As we show below the variation of the deactivation rate coefficients for N<SB>2</SB> are very well described by a power law dependence.</annotationART></s> <s sid="153"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">For O<SB>2</SB> neither an exponential nor a power law fit gives a good functional fit to the dependence of the deactivation rate coefficient on vibrational level.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="154"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">There have been no previous reports of rate coefficients for vibrational deactivation of <IT>v</IT> = 1–5 by N<SB>2</SB> although upper limits of <IT>k</IT><SB>deactivation</SB> &lt; 1 × 10<SP>−14</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−3</SP> have been reported for <IT>v</IT> = .2–4<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12 cit14 cit19">12,14,19</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="155"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Deactivation rate coefficients for <IT>v</IT> = 8, 10 and 12 have been reported.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15 cit25">15,25</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="156"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 7 shows the rate coefficients measured here together with prior values for <IT>v</IT> = 8,10 and 12.</annotationART></s> <s sid="157"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">Kaufman and coworkers<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26">26</REF> used a power law dependence to fit deactivation rate coefficients of HF and HD and such a dependence provides an extremely good fit to our data for <IT>v</IT> = 1–5, although the high <IT>v</IT> data is not well represented.</annotationART></s> <s sid="158"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 7 shows the best fit of our data to a power law function which gives:<IT>k</IT><SB><IT>v</IT>,N<SB>2</SB></SB> = 1.47 × 10<SP>−15</SP><IT>v</IT><SP>2.22</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>We are unaware of any previous results on deactivation of lower vibrational levels by O<SB>3</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="159"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">There have been two reports of deactivation coefficients of <IT>v</IT> = 9 by O<SB>3</SB>, both of which reports rates in excess of 1 × 10<SP>−10</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27 cit28">27,28</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="160"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">One theoretical study reports rates for deactivation of OH (<IT>v</IT> = 1,2) which are approximately an order of magnitude smaller than our measured rates.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29">29</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="161"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">As noted above the rates reported here may be influenced by secondary chemistry which would have the effect of producing anomalously low rates.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="162"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">We discussed the role of chemical bonding in mediating the deactivation processes in our previous work which was limited to deactivation of OH (<IT>v</IT> = 1–3).</annotationART></s> <s sid="163"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The limiting case appears to be a situation in which the deactivating molecule can form a stable molecule <IT>via</IT> three body recombination.</annotationART></s> <s sid="164"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this case the rate coefficient for vibrational deactivation appears to be a good proxy for the high pressure limit for three body recombination.</annotationART></s> <s sid="165"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this case one might expect the deactivation rate coefficient to be independent of vibrational level and the mechanism of deactivation to proceed predominantly through multiquantum deactivation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="166"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">In recent work in our laboratory we have measured the deactivation of OH (<IT>v</IT> = 1–5) with NO<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="167"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">We measure a fast deactivation rate coefficient, <IT>k</IT><SB>deactivation</SB> = (6.4 ± 0.1) × 10<SP>−11</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP>s<SP>−1</SP>, which is independent of vibrational level and is in very good agreement with the directly measured high pressure limit for the recombination reaction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="168"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our experimental approach precludes any determination of the deactivation mechanism.</annotationART></s> <s sid="169"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Theoretical studies have examined the deactivation efficiencies of both O<SB>2</SB> and N<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="170"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Shalashilin <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30">30</REF>. and Caridade <IT>et al</IT>.,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit31">31</REF> have considered the role of the HO<SB>3</SB> surface in promoting the efficiency of vibrational deactivation by O<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="171"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">In both cases they calculate deactivation efficiencies that are considerably greater than the experimental values, particularly for lower vibrational levels.</annotationART></s> <s sid="172"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">It appears that while the HO<SB>3</SB> surface clearly influences the deactivation dynamics any complex that is formed it is too short lived and weakly bound to allow a statistical randomization of energy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="173"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Shalashilin <IT>et al</IT>. examined the deactivation efficiency of N<SB>2</SB> in collisions with vibrationally excited OH and OD.</annotationART></s> <s sid="174"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">They find that deactivation of OH is extremely inefficient and calculate rate coefficients which are significantly slower than our experimental values.</annotationART></s></P><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Atmospheric implications</HEADER><P><s sid="175"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">We can now quantitatively evaluate the relative efficiencies of significant atmospheric colliders in the deactivation of vibrationally excited OH formed in the troposphere.</annotationART></s> <s sid="176"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our results confirm that O<SB>2</SB> is much more efficient in deactivation of the lower vibrational levels than N<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="177"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">However the contribution of N<SB>2</SB> is not negligible and accounts for 13% of the deactivation of <IT>v</IT> = 1 by N<SB>2</SB> + O<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="178"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our results suggest that under typical conditions in the tropical marine boundary layer, collision with H<SB>2</SB>O is the dominant deactivation process.</annotationART></s> <s sid="179"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">O<SB>2</SB> and H<SB>2</SB>O contribute equally to deactivation at H<SB>2</SB>O partial pressures of ∼0.6 Torr.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="6.">Conclusions</HEADER><P><s sid="180"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have used the pulsed laser photolysis-laser induced fluorescence technique to measure the vibrational deactivation coefficients for OH(<IT>ν</IT> = 1–5) with O<SB>2</SB> and N<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="181"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our results in O<SB>2</SB> are in excellent agreement with the only previous experimental result present in the literature for OH(<IT>v</IT> = 3–5), while they are approximately a factor of two lower than previous measurements for OH(<IT>v</IT> = 1,2).</annotationART></s> <s sid="182"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is the first work to report vibrational deactivation coefficients for OH (<IT>v</IT> = 1–5) with N<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="183"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our results confirm that oxygen is much more efficient in deactivating vibrationally excited hydroxyl radical than nitrogen.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
