<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b409258a" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">The performance of the semi-empirical AM1 method on small and nanometre-sized N<SB>2</SB>O clusters</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Large N<SB>2</SB>O clusters containing up to 177 molecules were simulated using the semiempirical AM1 method.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Simulated spectra of different cluster sizes show excellent agreement with experimental spectra.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The vibrational band shape of the strong N–N stretching vibration is more strongly influenced by shape and size than that of the N–O stretching vibration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Stabilization energies and spectral band shapes confirm a crystal like structure of N<SB>2</SB>O clusters generated in supersonic jet expansions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The AM1 results are carefully checked against experiment and high-level <IT>ab initio</IT> methods.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Overall, AM1 reproduces experimental results (structure and vibrational frequencies) and MP2 dissociation energies of small N<SB>2</SB>O clusters far better than any other quantum mechanical method studied here, although AM1 is not explicitly calibrated for the (N<SB>2</SB>O)<SB><IT>n</IT></SB> van der Waals system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The good performance of AM1 allows us to simulate N<SB>2</SB>O clusters built from hundreds of molecules, a size range neither accessible by <IT>ab initio</IT> nor by continuum methods.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="1.">Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Clusters containing up to several thousands of molecules represent intermediate states of matter between the gas and the condensed phase.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the past, oligomers like dimers, trimers, and tetramers as well as small particles with diameters ranging from nanometres to a few micrometres were studied extensively.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is now well known that even clusters built out of one billion molecules do not match the dynamic properties of the bulk phase in every detail, although their microscopic structure is often the same.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Some examples are clusters of N<SB>2</SB>O,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2 cit3 cit4 cit5 cit6 cit7 cit8 cit9">2–9</REF> CO<SB>2</SB>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit10 cit11 cit12 cit13 cit14">8,10–14</REF> SF<SB>6</SB>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15 cit16 cit17">15–17</REF> and H<SB>2</SB>O.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18 cit19 cit20 cit21">18–21</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The theoretical treatment of such large clusters is restricted to model potentials and typically involves molecular dynamics, Monte Carlo and exciton approaches.</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the less studied intermediate size regime, more rigorous quantum chemical methods may come into play, although high-level <IT>ab initio</IT> approaches are still restricted to small clusters.</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this work we validate the exceptionally good performance of the semiempirical AM1 method<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22 cit23">22,23</REF> on N<SB>2</SB>O clusters, which allowed us to study their structural, energetical and dynamical properties up to 177 monomer units and to compare them with experimental and theoretical results obtained previously.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">N<SB>2</SB>O clusters belong to the class of van der Waals clusters and a large experimental data set is available for them.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The dimer, with its slipped-antiparallel structure is by far the best characterized complex.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24 cit25 cit26 cit27">24–27</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Later the trimer<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28">28</REF> and tetramer<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29">29</REF> were studied in the region of the <IT>v</IT><SB>101</SB> combination band and the assignments were supported by <IT>ab initio</IT> calculations of the rotational constants.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The trimer structure can be derived from the dimer by placing a third N<SB>2</SB>O molecule diagonally over the other two, which are tilted against each other along the torsion coordinate.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28">28</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The tetramer is basically a sandwich structure of two dimers where all N<SB>2</SB>O molecules are parallel to each other and the oxygen atoms of adjacent molecules are pointing in opposite directions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29">29</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Only recently the first observation of a van der Waals mode in (N<SB>2</SB>O)<SB>2</SB> was reported by Havenith and co-workers.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30">30</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Infrared spectra of large N<SB>2</SB>O clusters were reported in supersonic jets <IT>via</IT> FTIR spectroscopy<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2 cit3 cit4 cit5">2–5</REF> and vibrational predissociation,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF> in collisional cooling cells,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF> diffusion traps<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF> and in free-standing argon crystals.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit31">31</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Electron diffraction studies on large clusters of the structurally related N<SB>2</SB>O<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF> and CO<SB>2</SB><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF> molecules indicate that their microscopic structure is similar to that in the crystalline solid.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the <IT>v</IT><SB>001</SB> (N–N-stretch) cluster band<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2 cit3 cit4 cit5">2–5</REF> is blue shifted by about 10 cm<SP>−1</SP> relative to the TO-mode of the crystalline solid,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit12 cit13 cit14 cit32 cit33 cit34 cit35">8,12–14,32–35</REF> even for large clusters with up to 10<SP>9</SP> molecules per cluster,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF> whereas the cubic structure of the crystalline solid is adopted at a cluster size as small as ≈30–40 molecules.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is worth noting that the cubic structure of the large clusters is quite different from the parallel alignment of the molecules in the dimer, trimer, and tetramer, which is probably the reason for the opposite <IT>v</IT><SB>100</SB> (N–O-stretch) vibrational band shifts of oligomers and large clusters.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit5">4,5</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Despite the experimental interest there are few theoretical studies on N<SB>2</SB>O and its clusters.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The N<SB>2</SB>O monomer was studied at various levels of theory.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit36 cit37 cit38 cit39 cit40 cit41 cit42">36–42</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Dutton <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit43">43</REF>. presented HF, MP2, and MP3 calculations of the dimer, confirming previous results by Nxumalo <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit44">44</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Kudoh <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit45">45</REF>. compared DFT results with matrix spectra and Miller and co-workers used the calculated rotational constants at the MP2 level of theory to assign their spectra to the N<SB>2</SB>O trimer<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28">28</REF> and tetramer.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29">29</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, up to now no systematic <IT>ab initio</IT> study of small N<SB>2</SB>O clusters is available at different levels of theory employing different basis sets.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Miller <IT>et al.</IT> simulated a cluster containing 55 molecules using semiclassical Monte Carlo simulations.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Molecular dynamics simulations were used to describe the orientational disorder in crystalline nitrous oxide.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit46 cit47 cit48 cit49 cit50">46–50</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Only recently Signorell demonstrated the applicability of the exciton model to clusters with spatial dimensions between 1 and 10 nm,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit51">51</REF> though it was noted that the vibrational band shape of N<SB>2</SB>O clusters is only in part controlled by resonant dipole–dipole coupling.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The major focus of the paper is to demonstrate the good performance of the AM1 method and to compare the results with systematic quantum chemical calculations at different levels of theory.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">As will be seen later, the interaction between the N<SB>2</SB>O subunits is dominated by dispersion forces.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Dipole–dipole interactions, arising from the small permanent dipole moment of N<SB>2</SB>O (0.16 D, <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit52">ref. 52</REF>), play only a minor role.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">N<SB>2</SB>O has three normal modes: <IT>v</IT><SB>100</SB> (mostly N–O-stretch), <IT>v</IT><SB>001</SB> (mostly N–N-stretch) and <IT>v</IT><SB>010</SB> (the doubly degenerate bending vibration).</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the following we will concentrate on the two stretching vibrations <IT>v</IT><SB>100</SB> and <IT>v</IT><SB>001</SB>, but we will discuss other modes as well where experimental data exist.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Because the frequencies of intermolecular van der Waals modes are more than one order of magnitude smaller than those of the intramolecular stretching vibrations, the principal nature of the stretching fundamentals does not change upon cluster formation and we can still describe the cluster vibrations as, <IT>e.g.</IT>, N–O-stretch vibrations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The paper is organized as follows: After a short section describing the computational details we present the <IT>ab initio</IT> results of the N<SB>2</SB>O monomer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The systematic analysis lays the footing for discussing the results on the dimer, trimer, and tetramer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The semiempirical AM1 method is found to describe the structure, energetics and dynamics of oligomeric N<SB>2</SB>O clusters well, without any further parametrization.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In section 4, the AM1 calculations are extended to nanometre-sized clusters containing up to 177 molecules per cluster and compared with experimental and theoretical results obtained earlier<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit5">4,5</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.">Computational details</HEADER><P><s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">All <IT>ab initio</IT> and most semiempirical calculations were carried out using the Gaussian 98 program package.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit53">53</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Semiempirical PM3, restricted Hartree–Fock (HF), hybrid density functional (B3LYP), and second-order Møller–Plesset (MP2) perturbation theory calculations were applied to the monomer, dimer, trimer, and tetramer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Basis sets ranging from 3-21G to double- and triple-<IT>ζ</IT> quality were used.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the DFT calculations the default pruned (75,302) grid of the Gaussian 98 package was used.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The MP2 calculations include only valence orbitals, <IT>i.e.</IT>, the frozen core approximation was used.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Geometry optimizations with the semiempirical Austin model 1 (AM1)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22 cit23">22,23</REF> were carried out using the Gaussian 98 program package.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">For the calculation of harmonic force constants and infrared intensities of clusters containing more than 79 molecules as well as the geometry optimization of (N<SB>2</SB>O)<SB>177</SB> the MNDO97<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit54">54</REF> program package was used.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In case of the dimer, trimer, and tetramer only the experimentally found isomers were calculated (Fig. 1a–c), which correspond to the most stable structures at all levels of theory.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28 cit29 cit43 cit44 cit45">28,29,43–45</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although basis set superposition errors (BSSE) may amount to up to 50% of the van der Waals binding energy in these systems when using medium-size basis sets,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit43 cit44">43,44</REF> a reordering of the isomers is only observed for small basis sets.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Energies given in this paper are not BSSE corrected.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The initial structures of large (N<SB>2</SB>O)<SB><IT>n</IT></SB> clusters were derived from the cubic structure of crystalline N<SB>2</SB>O.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit55">55</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This choice is justified by experiments, which showed that the clusters adopt the structure of the crystalline solid for cluster sizes as small as 30–40 molecules (see above).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Starting from a central N<SB>2</SB>O molecule a spherical section with radius <IT>r</IT> was cut out of the crystal structure, thereby generating approximately spherical particles with radii between 0.4 and 1.3 nm (Fig. 1d).</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast to CO<SB>2</SB> and because of the small permanent dipole moment of N<SB>2</SB>O, orientational disorder has to be considered.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit5 cit46 cit47 cit48 cit49 cit50 cit56 cit57 cit58 cit59 cit60">4,5,46–50,56–60</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore we generated several clusters of the same size with random orientation of the individual N<SB>2</SB>O molecules and averaged all properties over the different clusters.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Here, orientation means that a N<SB>2</SB>O molecule is either pointing in one direction or turned over by 180°, thus fixing the alignment in space to the one found in the crystalline solid.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">As expected, the effect of averaging is strongest for smaller clusters and less pronounced for larger clusters, where the number of N<SB>2</SB>O molecules is large enough for good statistics even within a single cluster.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">We calculated spherical (N<SB>2</SB>O)<SB><IT>n</IT></SB> clusters with <IT>n</IT> = 13, 19, 43, 55, 79, 135, and 177 molecules per cluster and averaged over <IT>N</IT> = 20, 16, 15, 10, 4, 3, and 1 structures, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to break the high symmetry of the cubic structure the N<SB>2</SB>O molecules were randomly displaced by a few tenths of an Å from the position in the crystalline solid, ensuring a C<SB>1</SB> symmetry of the initial geometry for the geometry optimization.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Columnar clusters (Fig. 1e) were built using a base of 2 × 2 unit cells and a length of 2, 3 and 4 unit cells, corresponding to cluster sizes of 63, 88 and 113 molecules per cluster, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Energetic and spectral properties of columnar clusters were averaged over three orientational distributions for each cluster size.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.">Oligomers</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.1.">Geometries</HEADER><P><s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Table 1 shows the calculated bond lengths <IT>r</IT><SB>NN</SB> and <IT>r</IT><SB>NO</SB> as well as the calculated dipole moment <IT>μ</IT> of N<SB>2</SB>O at different levels of theory for a range of basis sets.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The experimental values are given in the first row for comparison.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit52 cit61">52,61</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both semiempirical methods, AM1 and PM3, reproduce the experimental atomic distances quite well.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The HF calculations use rather modest basis sets and underestimate the N–N distances, as one would expect for a purely covalent system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The 3-21G basis set was included to have a measure of how well a simple <IT>ab initio</IT> method, applicable to clusters beyond ten molecules, describes the system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, HF/3-21G completely fails to give a reasonable agreement with the experimental N–O distance.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Upon inclusion of electron correlation at the MP2 level, the N–O distance improves, but the N–N distance is overestimated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">CCSD(T) calculations perform significantly better.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">No attempt was made to reach the basis set limit for the monomer, as we are aiming at cluster calculations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The B3LYP functional gives good structural results which are largely insensitive to the size of the basis set.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The difficulties in calculating the electric dipole moment <IT>μ</IT> of nitrous oxide (Table 1) were discussed in detail by several groups.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit39 cit40 cit41">39–41</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The direction of <IT>μ</IT> (|<IT>μ</IT>| = 0.16 D<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit52">52</REF>) was experimentally determined to be in agreement with a <SP>+</SP>NNO<SP>−</SP> charge distribution, corresponding to a negative sign of the dipole moment.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit62">62</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our results confirm those of a systematic study of Frisch and Del Bene at various levels of theory.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit39">39</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The dipole moments in Table 1 were calculated at the optimized geometries of the individual methods.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">MP2 predicts the wrong sign, because it overestimates the contribution of the resonance structure over .</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">All other methods predict the correct direction of <IT>μ</IT>, but only CCSD(T) reproduces its magnitude reasonably well.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Semiempirical and Hartree–Fock methods overestimate the contribution of and, hence, the magnitude of the dipole moment, though the sign is correct.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Table 2 summarizes the structural parameters for the N<SB>2</SB>O dimer, which is planar with <IT>C</IT><SB>2h</SB> symmetry (see Fig. 1a). <IT>r</IT><SB>c.m.</SB> is the center-of-mass distance of the N<SB>2</SB>O subunits and <IT>θ</IT> the small angle between the molecular N<SB>2</SB>O axis and the center-of-mass distance <IT>r</IT><SB>c.m.</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None"><IT>A</IT>, <IT>B</IT> and <IT>C</IT> are the usual rotational constants.</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Experimental values obtained from high-resolution infrared spectra of the <IT>v</IT><SB>101</SB>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF><IT>v</IT><SB>100</SB>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25">25</REF> and <IT>v</IT><SB>001</SB> bands<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26">26</REF> are included for comparison.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">First of all, the intramolecular N–N and N–O bond lengths (not shown) are barely influenced upon cluster formation, as one would expect for a weakly bound van der Waals cluster, though the N–O- and N–N-distances are systematically increasing or decreasing, respectively, by one or two thousandths of an Å.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">MP2 calculations give the best results for the intermolecular distance and angle.</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rotational constants are in good agreement with the experimental values as well, because small errors in the intramolecular distances have only little influence on the rotational constants.</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">AM1 is the next best method, despite an underestimation of the angle <IT>θ</IT> by about 5°.</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The latter is also the reason for the deviation of the rotational constant <IT>A</IT>, because the <IT>A</IT>-axis lies approximately along the intermolecular center-of-mass distance.</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None">PM3 fails to describe the intermolecular distance.</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The deviations for the HF calculations are not as large, but still off by about 0.1 Å.</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" advantage="None">As for the B3LYP calculations, the results are again independent of the size of the basis set, but <IT>r</IT><SB>c.m.</SB> is consistently overestimated by about 0.3 Å, causing the <IT>B</IT> and <IT>C</IT> constants to be too small.</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Considering that the interaction between the N<SB>2</SB>O molecules is dominated by dispersion forces this is not unexpected.</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Overall AM1 and MP2 describe the geometric properties of the N<SB>2</SB>O dimer best.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Table 3 summarizes the calculated and experimental<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28 cit29">28,29</REF> rotational constants of (N<SB>2</SB>O)<SB>3</SB> (C<SB>1</SB> symmetry, Fig. 1b) and (N<SB>2</SB>O)<SB>4</SB> (<IT>D</IT><SB>2d</SB> symmetry, Fig. 1c).</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Intramolecular bond lengths do not change much upon cluster formation (compare Table 2) and are not reported.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs19" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the comparison, one should note that the experimental values represent vibrationally averaged rotational constants.</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs19" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is especially important for the trimer having a floppy and flat potential with respect to the angle <IT>φ</IT> of the top N<SB>2</SB>O molecule lying across the other two.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28">28</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus the calculated equilibrium values may differ substantially from the experiment.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs20" novelty="None" advantage="None">The <IT>A</IT>-constant is sensitive to the angle <IT>θ</IT> of the two N<SB>2</SB>O molecules forming the dimer unit and in particular to the angle <IT>φ</IT> of the top N<SB>2</SB>O molecule with respect to the <IT>A</IT>-axis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs20" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus we expect <IT>A</IT> to have the largest deviations from the experimental values, which is confirmed by Table 3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs21" novelty="None" advantage="None">Agreement with the experimental values is best at the MP2 level.</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs22" novelty="None" advantage="None">AM1 overestimates the <IT>A</IT> constant.</annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs23" novelty="None" advantage="None">At PM3 level, the trimer structure studied here is not a minimum on the potential surface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs24" novelty="None" advantage="None">Similar to the dimer B3LYP underestimates the <IT>B</IT> and <IT>C</IT> constants, or, in other words, the intermolecular separation is calculated to be too large.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs25" novelty="None" advantage="None">In case of the more spherical tetramer the differences between the methods are smaller.</annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs26" novelty="None" advantage="None">Here, AM1 agrees well with the experiment.</annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs27" novelty="None" advantage="None">PM3 overestimates the intermolecular separation of the N<SB>2</SB>O molecules and, hence, gives rotational constants much smaller than the experimental values.</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The close match of the HF/6-31+G(d) calculation with the experiment is probably fortuitous, considering the previous results for the monomer, dimer and trimer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs28" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 1c shows a small tilting of the oxygen end of each N<SB>2</SB>O molecule toward the center-of-mass, which is more pronounced at the MP2 level and results in nearly identical values for all three rotational constants.</annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs29" novelty="None" advantage="None">B3LYP, again, overestimates the intermolecular separation, because it does not include dispersion explicitly.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Overall MP2 and AM1 best describe the geometric properties of small N<SB>2</SB>O clusters.</annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, AM1 does not reproduce floppy intermolecular angles well, while MP2 overestimates the intramolecular N–N distance.</annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">B3LYP and PM3 completely fail to describe the cluster geometries.</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">HF/3-21G, the simplest and fastest pure <IT>ab initio</IT> method used here fails for both intra- and intermolecular parameters.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.2.">Energies</HEADER><P><s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Stabilization energies of the clusters are crucial for an understanding of their formation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs30" novelty="None" advantage="None">Table 4 shows the dissociation energies <IT>D</IT><SB>0</SB> of the dimer, trimer and tetramer for fragmentation into monomers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs30" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to obtain <IT>D</IT><SB>0</SB> electronic energies were corrected by zero-point energy (ZPE), except for AM1 and PM3, which include the zero-point motion implicitly in the parametrization.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit63">63</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs30" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the trimer and tetramer at MP2/aug-cc-pVDZ level ZPE was estimated from the MP2/6-31+G(d) results, with an expected error on the order of 1 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs31" novelty="None" advantage="None">B3LYP deviates systematically from all other calculations in giving much smaller dissociation energies for all cluster sizes consistent with the overestimated intermolecular distance.</annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">DFT methods are well known for their deficiencies in calculating bond energies of weakly bound complexes.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit64 cit65 cit66 cit67">64–67</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">BLYP and B3LYP functionals tend to underestimate the attractive dispersion interaction (see <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit64">ref. 64</REF> and references therein) due to an erroneous asymptotic behavior at low densities.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit66 cit67">66,67</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Recently Zhang <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit66">66</REF>. and Wesolowski <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit67">67</REF>. suggested that the PW91 exchange and correlation functionals are possible alternatives to describe weakly bound complexes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs32" novelty="None" advantage="None">To verify this for the N<SB>2</SB>O system, we have included PW91 dissociation energies into Table 4.</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs32" novelty="None" advantage="None">They are indeed larger, but fall short of the MP2 results by roughly a factor of two.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">At the MP2 level the major contribution to the binding energy comes from electron correlation (see Table 4), reflecting the dominant part of dispersion interactions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the aug-cc-pVDZ basis the SCF part is even repulsive at the minimum geometry and the trimer and tetramer are only held together by correlation effects.</annotationART></s> <s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">This effect may become even more pronounced for larger basis sets.</annotationART></s> <s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs33" novelty="None" advantage="None">The cohesive energy in N<SB>2</SB>O clusters appears to be largely additive.</annotationART></s> <s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs33" novelty="None" advantage="None">As we go from the dimer to the trimer and tetramer the dissociation energy increases by a factor of about three and five to six, respectively, in line with the growing number of pairs.</annotationART></s> <s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs34" novelty="None" advantage="None">Dipole contributions are almost negligible.</annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs35" novelty="None" advantage="None">Quadrupole interactions are more sizeable, but dispersion forces dominate the direct neighbor interaction.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The coincidence between MP2/aug-cc-pVDZ and RHF/3-21G is due to basis set superposition, which behaves qualitatively like dispersion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs36" novelty="None" advantage="None">With increasing basis set size the dissociation energy at the HF level drops below the MP2 values.</annotationART></s> <s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs37" novelty="None" advantage="None">Similarly, PM3 describes the clusters as too weakly bound.</annotationART></s> <s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Except for the dimer, the agreement of the AM1 energies with the MP2 values is surprisingly good, despite a lack of polarization and diffuse functions and the fact that electron correlation is taken into account only implicitly in the parametrization.</annotationART></s> <s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Moreover, the reference data for the AM1 parametrization did not include polarizabilities<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23 cit63">23,63</REF> which are essential for describing dispersion interactions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The AM1 values for the parallel and perpendicular components of the polarizability tensor in N<SB>2</SB>O are 4.99 and 0.36 Å<SP>3</SP>, respectively, and thus smaller than the experimental values<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit52">52</REF> of 5.33 and 2.16 Å<SP>3</SP>, so that the interactions involving polarizabilities will be underestimated by AM1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The good agreement for the total interaction energies (see above) is thus fortuitous, but together with the performance for the cluster geometry, it suggests that the AM1 method may be applied to larger clusters, where high level <IT>ab initio</IT> calculations are not feasible.</annotationART></s> <s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is interesting to note that the related PM3 method fails in both categories, thus emphasizing the limited applicability of PM3 on nitrogen containing systems.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.3.">Vibrational frequencies</HEADER><P><s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Vibrational frequencies are most easily calculated at the harmonic level.</annotationART></s> <s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is common to apply a simple scaling factor to correct for the anharmonicity and for errors in the electronic structure approach.</annotationART></s> <s sid="143"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">For our purpose of simulating large clusters, it is sufficient if a common scaling factor can be applied to all vibrations, or, at least, to the same type of vibrations, for example stretching vibrations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="144"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs38" novelty="None" advantage="None">Table 5 summarizes the calculated harmonic frequencies for the N<SB>2</SB>O monomer at different levels of theory.</annotationART></s> <s sid="145"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs38" novelty="None" advantage="None">The experimental anharmonic values are given for comparison and the values in parentheses are the ratios of the experimental anharmonic and calculated harmonic frequencies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="146"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs39" novelty="None" advantage="None">MP2 calculations perform best in terms of a common scaling factor and also in terms of absolute frequencies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="147"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs39" novelty="None" advantage="None">The basis set size mostly affects the bending vibration <IT>ω</IT><SB>010</SB>, but the aug-cc-pVTZ basis set is sufficient to reproduce all experimental fundamentals within 1%.</annotationART></s> <s sid="148"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs40" novelty="None" advantage="None">The density functional calculations require scaling factors which vary only by a few percent between the three fundamentals.</annotationART></s> <s sid="149"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs40" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast the scaling factors for the HF frequencies vary by 8% or even more (HF/3-21G).</annotationART></s> <s sid="150"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs41" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both semiempirical approaches have difficulties in describing the bending vibration of N<SB>2</SB>O. It is underestimated by about 50 cm<SP>−1</SP>, indicating that the potential energy surface is too flat in the bending coordinate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="151"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs41" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, AM1 and PM3 give comparable scaling factors for the two stretch fundamentals.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="152"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">When discussing the infrared spectra of nanometre-sized N<SB>2</SB>O clusters we will compare the band-shapes of simulated and experimental spectra (see section 4.2).</annotationART></s> <s sid="153"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Calculated infrared absorption intensities should reflect the experimentally observed intensities.</annotationART></s> <s sid="154"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs42" novelty="None" advantage="None">Table 6 lists the calculated and experimental intensities of the three fundamental modes of N<SB>2</SB>O. Because absolute absorption intensities involve large errors, we will concentrate on the relative intensities, which are given in parentheses.</annotationART></s> <s sid="155"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs42" novelty="None" advantage="None">The intensity of the N–N-stretch vibration (<IT>I</IT><SB>001</SB>) was set to 100% for each calculation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="156"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs43" novelty="None" advantage="None">For MP2 and B3LYP the results are largely basis set independent.</annotationART></s> <s sid="157"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs43" novelty="None" advantage="None">Except for the N–O-stretch vibration, which is a factor of five too weak at the MP2 level, the absolute intensities agree within their expected uncertainty.</annotationART></s> <s sid="158"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs44" novelty="None" advantage="None">At the Hartree–Fock level neither the absolute nor the relative intensities are close to experiment.</annotationART></s> <s sid="159"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs45" novelty="None" advantage="None">The deviations are even larger when PM3 is used.</annotationART></s> <s sid="160"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs46" novelty="None" advantage="None">AM1 performs better, but it consistently overestimates all three intensities.</annotationART></s> <s sid="161"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs46" novelty="None" advantage="None">The <IT>I</IT><SB>100</SB>/<IT>I</IT><SB>001</SB> ratio is within 50% of the experimental value, and thus acceptable for the simulation of infrared N<SB>2</SB>O cluster spectra in the N–O- and N–N-stretch regions.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="162"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs47" novelty="None" advantage="None">Vibrational frequency shifts for the dimer, trimer and tetramer are summarized in Tables 7 and 8, together with the absorption intensities.</annotationART></s> <s sid="163"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs47" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the van der Waals interaction is weak, the frequency shifts are small.</annotationART></s> <s sid="164"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs47" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the dimer and tetramer only one mode of the N–O- and N–N-stretch vibrations is infrared active, the others not being listed in the tables.</annotationART></s> <s sid="165"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs47" novelty="None" advantage="None">Experimental values are only available for the dimer,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25 cit26 cit30">25,26,30</REF> where we also added the frequencies of the two lowest van der Waals modes (Table 7).</annotationART></s> <s sid="166"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs47" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the dimer, stretching frequency shifts are relatively small , comparable in size and opposite in sign.</annotationART></s> <s sid="167"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs48" novelty="None" advantage="None">The opposite sign is reproduced by all but the MP2 calculations, where both stretches are red-shifted and the <IT>ω</IT><SB>100</SB> shift is only a fraction of the observed value.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit5">4,5</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="168"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs49" novelty="None" advantage="None">AM1 shows perfect agreement with the experiment, followed by B3LYP, which slightly underestimates the frequency shifts.</annotationART></s> <s sid="169"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs50" novelty="None" advantage="None">PM3 predicts almost no shift at all for the N–N-stretch vibration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="170"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs51" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hartree–Fock overestimates both shifts by at least a factor of two.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="171"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The failure of MP2 cannot be explained simply by geometry effects, because the N–N- and N–O-bond lengths are changing by the same amount in all calculations (see Table 2) and imply opposite signs of the frequency shifts.</annotationART></s> <s sid="172"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Signorell pointed out that pure resonant dipole–dipole coupling would lead to a small blue shift of both stretch vibrations in the N<SB>2</SB>O dimer.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit51">51</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="173"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore other effects must play a crucial role in explaining the MP2 red shifts.</annotationART></s> <s sid="174"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the other hand the good B3LYP performance is inconsistent with the poor description of the interaction potential.</annotationART></s> <s sid="175"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is particularly true for the sensitive torsional van der Waals vibration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="176"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs52" novelty="None" advantage="None">All other calculations overestimate the torsional frequency, but MP2 is within the expected uncertainty for such a low frequency vibration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="177"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs52" novelty="None" advantage="None">Within their uncertainty, the predictions would also be consistent with the anti-geared bending vibration, but this is not the experimentally preferred assignment.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30">30</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="178"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs53" novelty="None" advantage="None">A similar situation is observed in case of the trimer and tetramer (Table 8).</annotationART></s> <s sid="179"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs53" novelty="None" advantage="None">The trimer has three infrared active modes for each vibration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="180"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs54" novelty="None" advantage="None">If we just consider the strongest trimer vibrations, then the N–O and N–N vibrational frequency shifts have again opposite sign, even at the MP2 level.</annotationART></s> <s sid="181"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs54" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the MP2 shifts are much smaller than, for example, at the AM1 or B3LYP level.</annotationART></s> <s sid="182"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs55" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of the tetramer we observe the same behavior as for the dimer, but the shift of the N–N-stretch is twice that of the N–O-stretch in all but the PM3 and HF calculations.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="183"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs55" novelty="None" advantage="None">The cluster infrared absorption intensities reflect the pattern of the monomer calculations (compare Table 6).</annotationART></s> <s sid="184"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs56" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast to H-bonded systems, there is no intensity amplification, at best a slight attenuation, upon cluster formation, which renders detection by direct absorption more difficult.</annotationART></s> <s sid="185"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs56" novelty="None" advantage="None">Most important, though, is the comparison between the different methods.</annotationART></s> <s sid="186"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">The relative intensity change with increasing cluster size (for example, of the N–O-stretch vibration) is comparable for all but the MP2 calculations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="187"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">This suggests that all methods but MP2 are suitable for spectral intensities of larger N<SB>2</SB>O clusters, although the absolute intensities are off in some cases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="188"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">AM1 is one of these cases, but it agrees best with the experimental frequency shifts.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.">Large clusters</HEADER><P><s sid="189"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the preceding sections we have demonstrated the suitability of the semiempirical Austin Model 1 (AM1) in describing the properties of small N<SB>2</SB>O clusters.</annotationART></s> <s sid="190"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">AM1 reproduces the structures, energetics, vibrational frequencies and absorption intensity changes with reasonable accuracy, but at a fraction of the cost of high level <IT>ab initio</IT> calculations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="191"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">It should be noted that none of the <IT>ab initio</IT> methods studied here describes all three categories (geometry, energetics, dynamics) equally well and fails to model at least one of them.</annotationART></s> <s sid="192"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Obviously, there is no theoretical justification for the good performance of AM1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="193"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">It seems to benefit from fortuituos error compensation and the results obtained here cannot be transferred easily to other systems, as was recently shown by Signorell for the structurally related CO<SB>2</SB> dimer.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit51">51</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="194"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our results encourage the application of AM1 to large (N<SB>2</SB>O)<SB><IT>n</IT></SB> (<IT>n</IT> &gt; 4) clusters, although we have no proof for scalability.</annotationART></s> <s sid="195"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">One should keep in mind that the microscopic structure of oligomers and large clusters is different.</annotationART></s> <s sid="196"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The former have a parallel arrangement of N<SB>2</SB>O molecules, whereas the latter are derived from the cubic structure of the crystalline solid, where no parallel arrangement of neighboring molecules occurs.</annotationART></s> <s sid="197"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the following sections we will present and discuss the properties of large N<SB>2</SB>O clusters at AM1 level.</annotationART></s></P><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.1.">Geometries and energies</HEADER><P><s sid="198"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Earlier in the paper the construction of large spherical N<SB>2</SB>O clusters from the cubic structure of the crystalline solid, with a single N<SB>2</SB>O molecule at the center of the sphere was described.</annotationART></s> <s sid="199"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to break the cubic symmetry each molecule was randomly displaced by 0.1 Å and randomly oriented along the molecular axis prior to the geometry optimization.</annotationART></s> <s sid="200"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 2a shows the radial atom number density of a (N<SB>2</SB>O)<SB>55</SB> cluster prior to the geometry optimization.</annotationART></s> <s sid="201"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">For easier visualization each atom position was convoluted with a Gaussian profile (<IT>γ</IT> = 1 pm). <IT>r</IT> is the distance of the atoms from the center-of-mass of the cluster.</annotationART></s> <s sid="202"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 2a reflects the regular cubic structure of the initial geometry.</annotationART></s> <s sid="203"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Each group of peaks corresponds to what we can call a shell of N<SB>2</SB>O molecules around the center-of-mass.</annotationART></s> <s sid="204"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs57" novelty="None" advantage="None">After geometry optimization with the semiempirical AM1 method (Fig. 2b) the geometry is slightly disturbed, but the cubic structure with its “shells” is largely maintained.</annotationART></s> <s sid="205"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs57" novelty="None" advantage="None">In a microscopic picture this is also true for the alignment of the individual N<SB>2</SB>O molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="206"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, the geometry optimization does not change the arrangement within the initial cubic structure, being in accord with experimental results that even N<SB>2</SB>O clusters containing only a few tens of molecules take up the cubic structure of the crystalline solid.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="207"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs58" novelty="None" advantage="None">At the same time we observe a contraction of the cluster by about 0.5 nm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="208"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">The contraction is a consequence of the cluster’s finite extent in space and also of the overestimated AM1 rotational constants (Tables 2 and 3).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="209"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs59" novelty="None" advantage="None">For comparison Fig. 2c shows the initial structure of a (N<SB>2</SB>O)<SB>55</SB> cluster with a random alignment of the molecules in space, while their position was not changed from the one in Fig. 2a.</annotationART></s> <s sid="210"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs59" novelty="None" advantage="None">The sharp peaks indicate the positions of the central N-atoms in each N<SB>2</SB>O molecule and “shell”.</annotationART></s> <s sid="211"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs59" novelty="None" advantage="None">Because of the random alignment, the positions of the nitrogen and oxygen ends are spread out.</annotationART></s> <s sid="212"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs60" novelty="None" advantage="None">After the geometry optimization (Fig. 2d) the atom number density is more uniformly distributed than in Fig. 2b, consistent with an amorphous structure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="213"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs61" novelty="None" advantage="None">The amorphous structure is about 70 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> less stable than the one with a crystal like alignment, consistent with the experimental observation.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="214"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs62" novelty="None" advantage="None">Random orientations of the molecules lead to a variation of the total stabilization energy between 10 and 20 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> or less than 0.5 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> per molecule.</annotationART></s> <s sid="215"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs63" novelty="None" advantage="None">It should be noted that a cluster with a crystal like head-tail orientation of the molecular dipole moments is not the most stable structure, but lies within the energy range mentioned above.</annotationART></s> <s sid="216"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">In general an orientation of the surface molecules with the oxygen-end pointing away from the center-of-mass is energetically favored.</annotationART></s> <s sid="217"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the energy differences per molecule are rather small and one would not expect a preferential orientation of the surface molecules under the experimental conditions of a supersonic expansion.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2 cit3 cit4 cit5">2–5</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="218"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore we did not include a Boltzmann factor while averaging over all calculated structures.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="219"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs64" novelty="None" advantage="None">With increasing cluster size the dissociation energy per molecule (<IT>D</IT><SB>0</SB>/<IT>n</IT>) converges to a limit of about 20 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> (Fig. 3).</annotationART></s> <s sid="220"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs64" novelty="None" advantage="None">Energies of clusters with <IT>n</IT> = 13, 19, 43, 55, 79, and 135 molecules were averaged over <IT>N</IT> = 20, 16, 15, 10, 4, and 3 structures, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="221"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs65" novelty="None" advantage="None">The dissociation limit is close to the experimental sublimation enthalpy of 24 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> at 136 K.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit56">56</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="222"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is consistent with a sublimation energy of ≈23 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>, indicating that AM1 can describe the energetics of large N<SB>2</SB>O clusters with reasonable accuracy.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.2.">Vibrational spectra</HEADER><P><s sid="223"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Vibrational band shapes are more sensitive to orientational disorder than energies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="224"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the spectroscopic level the orientational disorder relaxes the electric-dipole selection rules, resulting in a broadening of the vibrational band shapes, which is among the most significant differences between the structurally related systems N<SB>2</SB>O and CO<SB>2</SB>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit46 cit47 cit48 cit49 cit50 cit56 cit57 cit58 cit59 cit60">46–50,56–60</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="225"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">This effect was experimentally observed in infrared<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit68 cit69">68,69</REF> and Raman<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit35 cit70">35,70</REF> spectra of the crystalline solids and theoretically confirmed by molecular dynamics simulations.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit46 cit48 cit49">46,48,49</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="226"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The orientational disorder has no effect on the vibrational center.</annotationART></s> <s sid="227"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, we expect the finite cluster extent in space in combination with the orientational disorder to influence the infrared spectra of large N<SB>2</SB>O clusters.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="228"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">As was mentioned earlier, we generated several cluster structures with different orientational distributions for a given cluster size.</annotationART></s> <s sid="229"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 4a-g shows the infrared spectra in the N–O-stretch region of seven such structures of (N<SB>2</SB>O)<SB>43</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="230"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The calculated frequencies were folded with a Gaussian profile (<IT>γ</IT> = 3 cm<SP>−1</SP>) and scaled by 0.802,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit5">4,5</REF> which is the scaling factor for the monomer N–O-stretch vibration (compare Table 5).</annotationART></s> <s sid="231"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs66" novelty="None" advantage="None">Vibrational analysis shows that the major source of the differences between the spectra is the orientation of the molecules at the cluster surface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="232"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs66" novelty="None" advantage="None">The N–O-stretch wavenumbers of surface molecules with the oxygen-end pointing to or away from the center-of-mass of the cluster differ by ≈20 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="233"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the inner region, where each molecule is surrounded by neighbors, the wavenumbers of a molecule pointing in one or the other direction differ only by a few cm<SP>−1</SP>, confirming the results of molecular dynamic simulations of the crystalline solid.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit46 cit48 cit49">46,48,49</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="234"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs67" novelty="None" advantage="None">The large differences between the spectra also indicate that the clusters studied here are still too small to provide a statistical orientational ensemble within a single cluster.</annotationART></s> <s sid="235"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs67" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore it is necessary to average over several orientational distributions in order to compare simulated with experimental spectra.</annotationART></s> <s sid="236"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs67" novelty="None" advantage="None">The bottom trace in Fig. 4 is the average of all 15 calculated structures (<IT>n</IT> = 43).</annotationART></s> <s sid="237"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs67" novelty="None" advantage="None">It shows a broad, smeared-out band at about 1295 cm<SP>−1</SP> and two smaller bands of nearly equal intensity at lower frequencies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="238"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs68" novelty="None" advantage="None">We checked the significance of the features by block-averaging only half of the calculated structures.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="239"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs68" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 5 shows the evolution of the N–O-stretch spectrum as a function of cluster size.</annotationART></s> <s sid="240"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs68" novelty="None" advantage="None">The spectra were averaged over the same number of structures as for the energy calculations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="241"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs68" novelty="None" advantage="None">While the calculated frequencies were scaled by 0.802 (see above), no scaling or normalization was applied to the calculated intensities.</annotationART></s> <s sid="242"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs68" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 5 also includes an experimental jet-FTIR spectrum of a 7.5% mixture of N<SB>2</SB>O in helium.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit5">4,5</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="243"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs69" novelty="None" advantage="None">With increasing cluster size the band near 1295 cm<SP>−1</SP> (<IT>C</IT>) gains intensity relative to the weaker structures (<IT>S</IT>) at lower wavenumbers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="244"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs69" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, we can easily assign the band <IT>C</IT> to molecules in the cluster core.</annotationART></s> <s sid="245"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs70" novelty="None" advantage="None">A similar spectral evolution is observed in <IT>ragout</IT>-jet FTIR spectra as a function of N<SB>2</SB>O concentration,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2 cit4 cit5">2,4,5</REF> in agreement with our theoretical results.</annotationART></s> <s sid="246"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs71" novelty="None" advantage="None">It should be noted that <IT>C</IT> is very close to the N–O-stretch vibration of the crystalline solid (1292.5 cm<SP>−1</SP>).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit34">34</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="247"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None">The weaker bands (<IT>S</IT>) can be attributed to surface molecules, pointing toward or away from the center-of-mass of the cluster or lying parallel to the surface.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit5">4,5</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="248"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None">Indeed, these “surface modes” are spread over the full spectral region of the N–O-stretch vibration and are partly covered by the main cluster band <IT>C</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="249"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs72" novelty="None" advantage="None">The lowest frequency bands correspond to surface molecules with the oxygen-end pointing toward the center-of-mass, while molecules pointing in the other direction show spectral features underneath <IT>C</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="250"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None">Overall our simulated spectra resemble the spectral features and evolution of the experimental cluster spectra nicely.</annotationART></s> <s sid="251"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs73" novelty="None" advantage="None">Visual inspection would indicate a cluster size of about 100 molecules per cluster for the experimental spectrum in Fig. 5.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="252"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs74" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the N–N-stretch vibration, agreement with experiment is not as good as for the N–O-stretch band (Fig. 6).</annotationART></s> <s sid="253"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs75" novelty="None" advantage="None">The calculated frequencies in Fig. 6 were scaled by 0.829,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit5">4,5</REF> which is the scaling factor of the monomer N–N-stretch vibration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="254"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs75" novelty="None" advantage="None">Otherwise Fig. 6 was generated in the same way as Fig. 5.</annotationART></s> <s sid="255"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs75" novelty="None" advantage="None">An experimental jet-FTIR spectrum of 7.5% N<SB>2</SB>O in helium<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit5">4,5</REF> is included for comparison (bottom trace).</annotationART></s> <s sid="256"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs76" novelty="None" advantage="None">From experiment we know that the highest frequency band around 2245 cm<SP>−1</SP> (<IT>C</IT>) belongs to the cluster core and grows with increasing cluster size, but even under conditions favoring the formation of larger clusters <IT>C</IT> is less prominent than in the case of the N–O-band and we would not expect a similar prominent peak like in Fig. 5.</annotationART></s> <s sid="257"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs76" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our simulations show an increase of the band marked <IT>S</IT>2 (≈2236 cm<SP>−1</SP>) relative to <IT>C</IT> with increasing cluster size.</annotationART></s> <s sid="258"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">According to a detailed vibrational analysis both bands (<IT>C</IT> and <IT>S</IT>2) have similar contributions from the clusters interior and the effect of different orientations of surface molecules is less pronounced.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit5">4,5</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="259"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs77" novelty="None" advantage="None">It should be noted, however, that <IT>S</IT>2, the dominant band in our simulations, is rather close to the N–N-stretch frequency in the crystalline solid (2237 cm<SP>−1</SP>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit34">34</REF> marked with Cr in Fig. 6).</annotationART></s> <s sid="260"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res29" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hence, <IT>S</IT>2 reflects the dynamics of the crystalline solid rather than that of large clusters, whereas the experimental cluster band (<IT>C</IT>) is blue shifted by about 10 cm<SP>−1</SP> with respect to the crystalline solid.</annotationART></s> <s sid="261"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs78" novelty="None" advantage="None">A similar blue-shift was observed for the <IT>ν</IT><SB>001</SB>-band of nanometre-sized CO<SB>2</SB> clusters.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7 cit8 cit11 cit12 cit13 cit14 cit71">7,8,11–14,71</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="262"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the strong <IT>ν</IT><SB>001</SB> band, one should also consider shape effects due to through-space transition dipole coupling.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit51">1,51</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="263"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs79" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 7 compares simulated spectra for columnar clusters with those of the spherical shapes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="264"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs79" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of the weaker <IT>ν</IT><SB>100</SB> band (transition dipole moment of <IT>d</IT><SB>M</SB> = 0.130 D),<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit72">72</REF> the shape effect is not very pronounced and can be traced back to the increased surface of the columns.</annotationART></s> <s sid="265"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs79" novelty="None" advantage="None">Quite in contrast the differences are significant for <IT>ν</IT><SB>001</SB> (<IT>d</IT><SB>M</SB> = 0.249 D),<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit72">72</REF> making this band less suitable for the testing of the AM1 model, as long as the experimental shape remains unknown.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="266"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="None" advantage="None">So far we considered only spectra of clusters with the cubic structure of the crystalline solid.</annotationART></s> <s sid="267"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs80" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 8 shows the N–N- (a) and N–O-stretch (b) spectra of an amorphous like (N<SB>2</SB>O)<SB>55</SB> cluster (compare Fig. 2).</annotationART></s> <s sid="268"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs80" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both spectra were averaged over four structures with a random alignment of the molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="269"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs80" novelty="None" advantage="None">The amorphous like structure results in broad spectra with little resemblance to experimental and simulated spectra of crystal like clusters (compare Figs. 5 and 6).</annotationART></s> <s sid="270"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs80" novelty="None" advantage="None">We limit ourselves to four different structures, but obviously further averaging would reduce individual features even further.</annotationART></s> <s sid="271"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res30" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 8 indicates once again that N<SB>2</SB>O clusters containing a few tens of molecules adopt the cubic structure of the crystalline solid.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="272"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res30" novelty="None" advantage="None">Even surface molecules do not realign much during the geometry optimization, but rather retain the initial alignment of the underlying cubic structure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="273"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the <IT>S</IT> features of the N–O-stretch vibration (Fig. 5) are reproduced by our simulations and could be assigned to surface molecules,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit5">4,5</REF> we can conclude that the cubic structure is adopted even at the cluster surface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="274"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">A similar result was found experimentally for nanometre-sized CO<SB>2</SB> clusters<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10 cit73">10,73</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="5.">Discussion and conclusions</HEADER><P><s sid="275"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The semiempirical Austin Model 1 (AM1) was used to describe the structures, energetics and dynamics of N<SB>2</SB>O and its clusters.</annotationART></s> <s sid="276"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa3" novelty="None" advantage="None">We compared the performance of AM1 with higher level quantum chemical methods and experimental results.</annotationART></s> <s sid="277"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Overall AM1 gave a surprisingly good description of the monomer and small clusters (<IT>n</IT> ≤ 4).</annotationART></s> <s sid="278"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Indeed it is the only theoretical method studied here which describes the structures, energies and vibrational frequencies with consistently acceptable accuracy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="279"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">All other methods (PM3, HF, B3LYP, and MP2) show larger deviations in at least one of the categories.</annotationART></s> <s sid="280"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">PM3 and HF cannot describe either of them.</annotationART></s> <s sid="281"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">B3LYP overestimates intermolecular distances and largely underestimates dissociation energies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="282"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Among the <IT>ab initio</IT> methods, MP2 best reproduces the experimental geometries and can be assumed to be most reliable in the prediction of dissociation energies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="283"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">It fails to describe the frequency shift of the N–N-stretch vibration and the band strength of the N–O-stretch vibration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="284"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Except for intermolecular angles and absolute infrared absorption intensities AM1 reproduces experimental results and MP2 dissociation energies far better than expected for a semiempirical method, which is not explicitly calibrated for such systems.</annotationART></s> <s sid="285"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">AM1 describes the relative intensity and the intensity change upon cluster formation correctly.</annotationART></s> <s sid="286"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore AM1 can be used to predict spectral changes with increasing cluster size.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="287"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The good performance of AM1 for N<SB>2</SB>O clusters must be attributed to some fortuitous error compensation, though AM1 is known to describe nitrogen-containing compounds generally better than MNDO.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22 cit23">22,23</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="288"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" advantage="None">AM1 deviates from MNDO only in the explicit formulation of the core repulsion function that allows for a better tuning of the repulsions between atoms at about van der Waals distance.</annotationART></s> <s sid="289"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" advantage="None">It should be emphasized again that AM1 uses a minimal valence basis set without polarization or diffuse functions and that electron correlation is only included implicitly through the parametrization.</annotationART></s> <s sid="290"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" advantage="None">Moreover, intermolecular interactions were not considered during the AM1 parameterization:<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF> van der Waals and H-bonded clusters were not among the reference molecules, and the reference data did not include polarizabilities which are crucial for the description of dispersion interactions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit63">63</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="291"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" advantage="None">Given these limitations, the results of semiempirical calculations must be carefully checked against experiment or high-level <IT>ab initio</IT> methods.</annotationART></s> <s sid="292"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res32" novelty="None" advantage="None">A careful inspection is even more important for systems not included in the parametrization and effects that have only little influence on the physical properties of the reference systems.</annotationART></s> <s sid="293"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, in the present systematic work, we have carefully validated the use of AM1 for the modelling of N<SB>2</SB>O clusters.</annotationART></s> <s sid="294"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, this does not justify corresponding applications to other related systems: for example, AM1 fails to describe the vibrational frequency shifts of CO<SB>2</SB><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit51">51</REF> and is thus not suited for studying the properties of larger CO<SB>2</SB> clusters.</annotationART></s> <s sid="295"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res33" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is worth noting that PM3 cannot describe N<SB>2</SB>O clusters adequately, although AM1 and PM3 have the same theoretical underpinning and differ only in the amount of experimental reference data and the optimization techniques used in the parametrization.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="296"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res33" novelty="None" advantage="None">Based on the good results obtained for the oligomers we extended our AM1 study to nanometre-sized N<SB>2</SB>O clusters containing up to 177 molecules per cluster.</annotationART></s> <s sid="297"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs81" novelty="None" advantage="None">We observed an excellent agreement with experimental spectra in the case of the N–O-stretch vibration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="298"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs81" novelty="None" advantage="None">Weaker bands at the low frequency side (<IT>S</IT> in Fig. 5) could be assigned to molecules at the cluster surface, following an earlier vibrational analysis.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit5">4,5</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="299"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs82" novelty="None" advantage="None">The agreement between simulated and experimental N–N-stretch spectra is not as good.</annotationART></s> <s sid="300"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res34" novelty="None" advantage="None">This may be due to shape or size effects caused by the strong transition moment, resulting in an anomalous blue shift of the experimental main cluster band <IT>C</IT> (Fig. 6) relative to the crystalline solid.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2 cit4 cit5 cit6 cit7 cit8 cit11 cit12 cit13 cit14 cit71">2,4–8,11–14,71</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="301"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs83" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both, the energetics and the spectral band shapes, confirm a crystal like structure of the N<SB>2</SB>O clusters.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="302"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs83" novelty="None" advantage="None">With increasing cluster size the dissociation energy per molecule approaches a limit of around 20 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>, which is within 20% of the experimental sublimation enthalpy (Fig. 3).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit56">56</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="303"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs84" novelty="None" advantage="None">Oligomers and large clusters differ in their microscopic structure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="304"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs84" novelty="None" advantage="None">The parallel arrangement of molecules in the dimer, trimer and tetramer does not occur in the cubic structure of large clusters.</annotationART></s> <s sid="305"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res35" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the good agreement between simulated and experimental results justifies the use and scalability of AM1 to simulate the properties of large N<SB>2</SB>O clusters and confirms the conclusions derived from it.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit5">4,5</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="306"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs85" novelty="None" advantage="None">All simulated spectra were scaled by the monomer scaling factors, which differ only slightly for the N–O- and N–N-stretch vibrations (Table 5).</annotationART></s> <s sid="307"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs85" novelty="None" advantage="None">No further frequency adjustment was made to match simulated and experimental spectra.</annotationART></s> <s sid="308"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac20" novelty="None" advantage="None">Experimentally, all main cluster bands (<IT>v</IT><SB>100</SB>, <IT>v</IT><SB>001</SB> and <IT>v</IT><SB>101</SB>) are blue shifted with respect to the isolated molecule.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2 cit4 cit5">2,4,5</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="309"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac20" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast the <IT>v</IT><SB>100</SB> and <IT>v</IT><SB>101</SB> bands of the dimer, trimer (considering only the strongest band) and tetramer are red shifted,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24 cit25 cit27">24,25,27</REF> while the <IT>v</IT><SB>001</SB> band is again blue shifted.</annotationART></s> <s sid="310"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs86" novelty="None" advantage="None">AM1 reproduces the signs and magnitudes of the shifts for all but the main N–N-stretch cluster band (<IT>S</IT>2 in Fig. 6), the latter being underestimated by a factor of two, but matching the limit of the crystalline solid.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
