<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b411044g" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Adsorption kinetics of ammonium perfluorononanoate at the air–water interface</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The adsorption of the fluorocarbon surfactant, ammonium perfluorononanoate (APFN) has been studied in an overflowing cylinder (OFC).</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The equilibrium adsorption isotherm, determined by drop shape tensiometry, is well-described by the Volmer isotherm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The dynamic surface excess at the expanding surface of the OFC was measured by neutron reflectometry (NR).</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The dynamic surface excess was in good agreement with the predictions of a diffusion-controlled adsorption model.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Significant Marangoni effects were observed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The relationship between the mass transport equation in the OFC and the short and long-time asymptotes of the Ward–Tordai equation is noted.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The overflowing cylinder is a useful platform for studying adsorption kinetics and Marangoni effects (<IT>i.e.</IT>, surface-tension-driven hydrodynamic flows) in surfactant solutions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2 cit3 cit4 cit5 cit6 cit7 cit8 cit9 cit10 cit11 cit12 cit13 cit14 cit15">1–15</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The overflowing cylinder provides an extremely stable, continuously expanding, air–water interface with a surface age in the range of 0.1–1 s.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The large flat surface of the OFC is well-suited for a range of sensitive surface analytical techniques.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the presence of surfactants, surface tension gradients lead to large accelerations of the surface: the surface velocity can increase by more than an order of magnitude compared with pure water.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">More remarkably still, the interfacial properties are determined autonomously by the surfactant and become independent of the bulk flow rate or the dimensions of the cylinder (within certain limits).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit11">1,11</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although the range of timescales accessible in the OFC is less than in some other methods, such as the maximum bubble pressure (MBP) technique,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16 cit17">16,17</REF> the well-defined hydrodynamics and time-independence of the OFC allow precise testing of kinetic models for adsorption and provide a valuable complement to more traditional methods.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have shown recently<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF> that adsorption of the cationic surfactants C<SB><IT>n</IT></SB>TAB (CH<SB>3</SB>(CH<SB>2</SB>)<SB><IT>n</IT>−1</SB>N<SP>+</SP>(CH<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB>Br<SP>−</SP>, <IT>n</IT> = 12–16) at the surface of the OFC is diffusion-controlled at all concentrations below the critical micelle concentration (c.m.c.).</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">For C<SB>14</SB>TAB + NaBr, a model was developed incorporating micellar diffusion and adsorption was shown to be diffusion-controlled with fast micelle breakdown kinetics above the c.m.c.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">For C<SB>16</SB>TAB + NaBr, micelle breakdown kinetics become important and a rate constant for micelle breakdown was deduced.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this note, we present data on the adsorption of the fluorocarbon surfactant ammonium perfluorononanoate (APFN) in an OFC.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">This study is the first on the adsorption kinetics of a perfluorocarboxylate surfactant at the air–water interface.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Perfluorocarboxylate surfactants are highly surface-active molecules and can reduce the surface tension of water to &lt;20 mN m<SP>−1</SP>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18 cit19">18,19</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Synergistic effects in surfactant mixtures result in even lower surface tensions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Studies of the kinetics of adsorption of mixtures of APFN with hydrocarbon surfactants (where the interactions are primarily antagonistic) will be described elsewhere.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this preliminary study, we look at the adsorption kinetics of pure APFN.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The specific choice of APFN for this study was dictated by the desirability of a Krafft point that is below room temperature and by a critical micelle concentration (c.m.c. = 8.9 mM) that is not too high.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18 cit19">18,19</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">To model adsorption kinetics, one needs reliable data on both the equilibrium and dynamic properties of a surfactant.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the Results section, we first present measurements of the equilibrium surface tension and deduce the adsorption isotherm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">We then present measurements of the dynamic surface excess, <IT>Γ</IT><SB>dyn</SB>, on the OFC by neutron reflectometry at the spallation neutron source, ISIS.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">To interpret <IT>Γ</IT><SB>dyn</SB>, we need also to know the surface expansion rate, which is measured by laser Doppler scattering.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The surface expansion rate, <IT>θ</IT>, was found to be in the range <IT>θ</IT> = 1–3 s<SP>−1</SP>, which therefore defines the timescale over which information on the adsorption kinetics is accessible.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The experimental values of <IT>Γ</IT><SB>dyn</SB> are then compared with the predictions of a diffusion-controlled adsorption model and found to be in excellent agreement.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Finally, we draw an analogy between the kinetics of the overflowing cylinder and adsorption to a stagnant interface.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Experimental section</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Materials</HEADER><P><s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Ammonium perfluorononanoate was prepared by neutralisation of heptadecafluorononanoic acid (Fluorochem, 99%) with ammonium hydroxide solution (Aldrich, 28% NH<SB>3</SB> in water, 99.99+%) followed by freeze-drying and recrystallisation (3 times) from dichloromethane/isopropanol.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The tetra-ammonium salt of ethylenediamine tetra-acetic acid (EDTA) was prepared as either 74 or 130 mM aqueous solutions by neutralisation of EDTA (Aldrich, 99.999%) with 4 equivalents of ammonium hydroxide solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Ultra-high purity (UHP) water was obtained from a variety of water polishing systems.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Overflowing cylinder</HEADER><P><s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The design and operation of the overflowing cylinder has been described in detail previously.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Briefly, a gravity-fed solution flows upwards in a stainless steel cylinder (8 cm in diameter) and overflows the rim.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The flow at the surface is radially outwards from a stagnation point at the centre of the cylinder.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The surface expansion rate, <IT>θ</IT> = d ln<IT>A</IT>/d<IT>t</IT> (where <IT>A</IT> is the area of an element of surface) is approximately uniform over the surface of the cylinder.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Measurements on the OFC were conducted at a temperature of 298 K and a volume flow rate of 17 cm<SP>3</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>, corresponding to a mean vertical velocity in the cylinder of 0.34 cm s<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The total fluid volume in the OFC and pumping system was 1.6 dm<SP>3</SP>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Surface tensiometry</HEADER><P><s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Surface tensions were measured at 298 K by axisymmetric drop shape analysis (ITConcept, Longessaigne, France).</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Bubbles of air with a typical volume of 5 μl were formed in aqueous solutions of APFN containing 1 mol% of the tetra-ammonium salt of EDTA to complex calcium ions (the EDTA will be present in solution with varying degrees of ionisation, with the speciation dependent on the APFN concentration).</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">EDTA was not added to the solutions for dynamic measurements by NR and LDV (see below), since trace ions do not have time to exert a measurable effect on the expanding air–water interface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Bubbles were allowed to equilibrate for 1–45 min before measurements were taken.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The drift in the surface tension values was &lt;0.1 mN m<SP>−1</SP> min<SP>−1</SP>; 2–3 readings were acquired at each concentration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Tetra-ammonium EDTA was tested to ensure that it was not surface-active at the concentrations employed here.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Laser Doppler velocimetry (LDV)</HEADER><P><s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">A 10 mW HeNe laser beam was split into two equal parts, focused, and recombined on the surface of the OFC.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The APFN solution was seeded with a few mg of 2-μm TiO<SB>2</SB> particles.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">When these particles pass through the interference fringes formed by the crossed laser beams they scatter light with an intensity that is modulated at a frequency (in the range of 10<SP>4</SP> Hz) that is determined by the spacing of the fringes and the velocity of the particles.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Experimental details may be found elsewhere.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The surface velocity, <IT>u</IT><SB>s</SB>(<IT>r</IT>) was measured as a function of the radial position, <IT>r</IT>, and the surface expansion rate deduced from <IT>θ</IT> = <IT>r</IT><SP>−1</SP>d(<IT>ru</IT><SB>s</SB>)/d<IT>r</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None"><IT>θ</IT> was almost constant across the central 5 cm of the cylinder: the value at <IT>r</IT> = 0 is reported.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Neutron reflectometry (NR)</HEADER><P><s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Neutron reflection experiments on the OFC were carried out on the SURF beamline at the spallation neutron source ISIS (Didcot, UK) according to a protocol that has been described in detail previously.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3 cit15">3,15</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reflectivity was calibrated with a sample of pure D<SB>2</SB>O in the OFC before the sample runs and checked with a second calibration after the runs were complete.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The calibration factors differed by 2%.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The sample solutions were prepared in null-reflecting water (nrw = 0.08 D<SB>2</SB>O: 0.92 H<SB>2</SB>O by mole).</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Reflectivity profiles were acquired for between 20 min for the highest concentration of APFN and 130 min for the lowest concentration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The raw time-of-flight data were binned into intervals with a width of 5% of the momentum transfer and normalised by the calibration factor determined from the D<SB>2</SB>O runs.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The profiles were analysed on a simple three-layer model (air/monolayer/water) to yield a thickness, <IT>τ</IT>, and scattering length density, <IT>ρ</IT>, of the adsorbed monolayer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">These two parameters are strongly correlated, but the surface excess can be determined reliably from the equationwhere <IT>b</IT><SB>i</SB> is the scattering length of atom i and <IT>n</IT><SB>i</SB> is the number of times that atom i appears in the molecular formula for the surfactant.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Assuming that the ammonium counterion is fully exchanged with solvent and that all the counterions contribute to the reflectivity, the scattering length of APFN, ∑<IT>n</IT><SB>i</SB><IT>b</IT><SB>i</SB> = 165.3 fm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In studies of anionic surfactants with the tetramethyl ammonium counterion, Thomas and coworkers found that a fraction of the counterions in the electrical double layer (up to 90% in one case) were not detected by NR.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20 cit21">20,21</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, since the scattering length density of NH<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP> in nrw is close to zero, the counterions make very little contribution to the reflectivity here.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Neutron reflection can be used to determine the equilibrium adsorption isotherm of surfactants,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15 cit22">15,22</REF> but due to the limited availability of beamtime, surface tensiometry was used instead (see above).</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Results and discussion</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="1.">Equilibrium adsorption</HEADER><P><s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The equilibrium adsorption isotherm of APFN was determined by surface tensiometry.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The presence of divalent counterions, especially Ca<SP>2+</SP>, is known to interfere with interpretation of surface tension data for anionic surfactants,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF> so the tetra-ammonium salt of EDTA was added to the APFN solutions at a level of 1% of the surfactant concentration (by mole) to complex any trace Ca<SP>2+</SP> ions present in the surfactant or leached from the glassware.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">To determine the appropriate level of EDTA, we measured the surface tension of a 0.7-mM solution of APFN containing varying concentrations of EDTA.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the presence of trace divalent ions, the surface tension is expected to show a maximum with increasing EDTA concentration: at low concentrations, divalent ions complex to the surfactant at the interface and lower the surface tension; at high concentrations EDTA increases the ionic strength, which screens the electrostatic repulsions between adsorbed APFN molecules, increases the extent of adsorption and lowers the surface tension.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">For 0.7-mM APFN, the surface tension was constant at low EDTA concentrations and decreased at concentrations of EDTA above 8 mol%.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">A value of 1 mol% falls within the plateau region.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ammonium salt of EDTA was used in preference to the commercially available tetrasodium salt so as not to add a second counterion to the system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The surface tension of APFN as a function of bulk concentration, <IT>c</IT>, is shown in Fig. 1.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The Debye–Hückel Limiting Law was employed to convert the bulk concentrations into activities.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Various adsorption isotherms were explored to fit the surface tension data.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The most appropriate isotherm is the van der Waals’ isotherm with counterion binding.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24 cit25">24,25</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">To determine the four unknown parameters in this model with confidence it is usually necessary to make measurements both with and without added electrolyte.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">For APFN, however, we found that the interaction parameter between adsorbed molecules was very small, so the simpler Volmer isotherm could be used eqn. (2).where <IT>K</IT><SB>1</SB> = 4.6 × 10<SP>3</SP> m<SP>3</SP> mol<SP>−1</SP>, <IT>K</IT><SB>2</SB> = 1.2 × 10<SP>−3</SP> m<SP>3</SP> mol<SP>−1</SP>, <IT>Γ</IT><SB>∞</SB> = 5.74 μmol m<SP>−2</SP> and the concentrations of the surfactant ion (<IT>c</IT><SB>1</SB>) and counterion (<IT>c</IT><SB>2</SB>) immediately below the surface (<IT>z</IT> = 0) are determined by Gouy–Chapman theory.</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the ammonium salt, counterion binding is weak (<IT>K</IT><SB>2</SB> is very small); the isotherm is thus insensitive to the exact value of <IT>K</IT><SB>2</SB> and can be determined with reasonable confidence in the absence of data with added electrolyte.</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The equivalent surface tension isotherm is shown as a solid line in Fig. 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The intersection between this isotherm and a linear fit to the surface tension above the c.m.c. yields a value for the c.m.c. of 8.9 mM.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">This value is in agreement with a c.m.c. of 9.1 mM<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26">26</REF> obtained by electrical conductivity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The value of <IT>Γ</IT> at the c.m.c. is 4.3 μmol m<SP>−2</SP>; the limiting value of <IT>Γ</IT> &lt; <IT>Γ</IT><SB>∞</SB> because micelle formation places a cap on the chemical potential of the surfactant.</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None"><IT>Γ</IT><SB>∞</SB><SP>−1</SP> is the excluded area per molecule, <IT>A</IT><SB>0</SB>, in the van der Waals’ model.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The value we obtain for <IT>A</IT><SB>0</SB> = 0.29 nm<SP>2</SP> is very close to the cross-sectional area of a helical fluorocarbon chain (0.27 nm<SP>2</SP>)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27">27</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.">Dynamic surface excess</HEADER><P><s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Sample reflectivity profiles are shown in Fig. 2 for three concentrations of APFN, together with theoretical fits to a three-layer model (air, monolayer, nrw).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The dynamic surface excess obtained from such fits is plotted against the bulk concentration in Fig. 3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The equilibrium isotherm from surface tensiometry is shown as a solid line.</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">We would expect agreement between <IT>Γ</IT><SB>e</SB> and <IT>Γ</IT><SB>dyn</SB> at high concentrations where the mass transport to the surface is fast on the timescale of the OFC.</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the limiting value of <IT>Γ</IT><SB>dyn</SB> = 4.7 μmol m<SP>−2</SP> above the c.m.c. is significantly higher than the tensiometric value of 4.3 μmol m<SP>−2</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is not uncommon for there to be a small difference in scaling factors between surface coverages determined by NR and tensiometry, even in measurements on static surfaces.</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">There are several possible reasons for this discrepancy<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF> including impurities in the surfactant, approximations in the isotherm used to fit the surface tension data, and errors in the determination of the calibration factor in the NR experiments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of NR measurements on the OFC, obtaining an accurate calibration is complicated by the fact that the surface of the D<SB>2</SB>O calibration sample is significantly more curved than the surface of the surfactant solutions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">This curvature defocuses the reflected neutron beam and reduces the transmission through the final slit before the detector.</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The consequence is that the scale factor is too small and the surface excesses of the surfactant are more or less uniformly overestimated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">To mitigate this effect, the footprint of the neutron beam on the OFC is limited to 20 × 20 mm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">There are no equilibrium NR measurements on APFN in large planar troughs for comparison with the OFC data, but we can compare with measurements on the 8-carbon homologue, APFO.</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the presence of 0.1 M ammonium chloride, Simister <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28">28</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Downes <IT>et al</IT>.,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29">29</REF> and Lu <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30">30</REF>. all reported a value of <IT>Γ</IT><SB>e</SB> = 4.1 ± 0.2 μmol m<SP>−2</SP> for APFO at the c.m.c.</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">While APFN may have a slightly higher surface excess at the c.m.c. than APFO, it is unlikely to be 15% higher.</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">We therefore assign the discrepancy in Fig. 3 to an underestimation of the scale factor in the NR measurements.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">To enable comparison of the equilibrium and dynamic surface excesses, the NR data were scaled (by 0.9) to agree with the surface tension isotherm at high surfactant concentration (dotted line in Fig. 4).</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The dynamic surface excesses then fall slightly below the equilibrium values at lower surfactant concentrations, as would be expected on physical grounds.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.">Marangoni effects</HEADER><P><s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The surface expansion rate determined by LDV is shown in Fig. 5 as a function of the bulk concentration of APFN.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Surface accelerations are observed at all concentrations of APFN, with a maximum at 1.5 mM.</annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The general shape is characteristic of monomeric surfactants (<IT>cf.</IT> C<SB>14</SB>TAB<SP><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF></SP>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">At low concentrations, there is very little adsorbed surfactant and hence the gradients in surface excess and consequently in surface tension are small.</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">At high surfactant concentrations, mass transport to the surface is fast and the surface is close to equilibrium: again large surface tension gradients do not arise.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.">Adsorption kinetics</HEADER><P><s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Analysis of mass transport and convection at a surface under constant dilation yields a relationship between <IT>Γ</IT><SB>dyn</SB>, <IT>θ</IT>, the diffusion coefficient, <IT>D</IT>, the bulk concentration, <IT>c</IT>, and the subsurface concentration, <IT>c</IT><SB>s</SB>, at the edge of the electrical double layer.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit31 cit32">4,31,32</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the absence of added electrolyte, the effective diffusion coefficient <IT>D</IT> = 2<IT>D</IT><SB>PFN</SB><IT>D</IT><SB>NH<SB>4</SB></SB>/(<IT>D</IT><SB>PFN</SB> + <IT>D</IT><SB>NH<SB>4</SB></SB>), where <IT>D</IT><SB>PFN</SB> = 5.2 ± 0.2 × 10<SP>−10</SP> m<SP>2</SP> s<SP>−1</SP> is the self-diffusion coefficient of perfluorononanoate and <IT>D</IT><SB>NH<SB>4</SB></SB> = 1.96 × 10<SP>−9</SP> m<SP>2</SP> s<SP>−1</SP> is the diffusion coefficient of ammonium ions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit33">33</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">(<IT>D</IT><SB>PFN</SB> was determined by I. Furó by pulsed field gradient NMR of a 3-mM APFN solution in H<SB>2</SB>O at 295 K.) If adsorption is diffusion-controlled, then the interface is locally at equilibrium: <IT>i.e.</IT> the relationship between <IT>Γ</IT><SB>dyn</SB> and <IT>c</IT><SB>s</SB> is the same as between <IT>Γ</IT><SB>e</SB> and <IT>c</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">For a mixed kinetic-diffusion model, <IT>Γ</IT><SB>dyn</SB> (<IT>c</IT><SB>s</SB>) &lt; <IT>Γ</IT><SB>e</SB>(<IT>c</IT>).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The diffusion-controlled values of the surface excess are shown with a solid line in Fig. 4.</annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">For each pair of experimental parameters, <IT>θ</IT> and <IT>c</IT>, there are an infinite number of values of <IT>Γ</IT> and <IT>c</IT><SB>s</SB> that satisfy eqn. (3).</annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, in eqn. (3), <IT>Γ</IT><SB>dyn</SB> is a monotonically decreasing function of <IT>c</IT><SB>s</SB>, while in the equilibrium isotherm <IT>Γ</IT><SB>e</SB> is a monotonically increasing function of <IT>c</IT> = <IT>c</IT><SB>s</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Consequently, there is only one pair of values, <IT>Γ</IT> and <IT>c</IT><SB>s</SB>, that simultaneously satisfy the mass transport equations and the local equilibrium isotherm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">This value of <IT>Γ</IT> is plotted in Fig. 4.</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">As one would anticipate, the calculated values of the dynamic surface excess fall below the equilibrium values, since there has to be a concentration gradient to replenish the surfactant removed from the surface by dilation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The difference between <IT>Γ</IT><SB>dyn</SB> and <IT>Γ</IT><SB>e</SB> is greatest at low concentrations, where <IT>Γ</IT> is most sensitive to changes in <IT>c</IT><SB>s</SB>, and near the maximum in <IT>θ</IT>, where the mass transport away from the surface by dilation is greatest.</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The theoretical difference between <IT>Γ</IT><SB>dyn</SB> and <IT>Γ</IT><SB>e</SB> is never greater than 0.2 μmol m<SP>−2</SP>, or about 5% of a monolayer of APFN.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the diffusion-controlled model, the difference, Δ<IT>σ</IT>, between the dynamic surface tension, <IT>σ</IT><SB>dyn</SB>, and equilibrium surface tension, <IT>σ</IT><SB>e</SB>, is &lt;2 mN m<SP>−1</SP> and increases with increasing <IT>θ</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since it is surface tension gradients that drive Marangoni effects, it is not surprising that there is a correlation between <IT>θ</IT> and Δ<IT>σ</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None">We note that much larger values of Δ<IT>σ</IT> (≤30 mN m<SP>−1</SP>) are observed with more efficient surfactants, such as the cationic surfactant, CTAB [CH<SB>3</SB>(CH<SB>2</SB>)<SB>15</SB>N<SP>+</SP>(CH<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB>Br<SP>−</SP>], or the non-ionic surfactant, C<SB>12</SB>E<SB>8</SB> [CH<SB>3</SB>(CH<SB>2</SB>)<SB>11</SB>(OCH<SB>2</SB>CH<SB>2</SB>)<SB>8</SB>OH].</annotationART></s> <s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The maximum surface expansion rates for these surfactants are twice as high as for APFN.</annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">While this observation is intuitively reasonable, we do not yet have a sufficiently good understanding of the boundary conditions in the OFC to make quantitative predictions of surface expansion rates from the adsorption isotherm and transport properties of a surfactant alone.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">A comparison of the predicted and experimental values of <IT>Γ</IT><SB>dyn</SB> shows quantitative agreement (Fig. 4).</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have shown in a previous paper that electrostatic barriers to adsorption are not expected to be important at strain rates accessible on an OFC.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The agreement we observe here with a diffusion-controlled model shows that, on the timescale of the OFC, there are no steric barriers to adsorption for APFN either.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="5.">Relationship to kinetic measurements at a static liquid surface</HEADER><P><s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Finally, we comment briefly on the relationship between steady-state adsorption with convection on an OFC and adsorption at a clean surface in the absence of convection.</annotationART></s> <s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the latter case, the extent of adsorption is given by the classic Ward–Tordai equation<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit34">34</REF>(where <IT>t</IT> is the time since creation of the clean surface and <IT>τ</IT> is a dummy variable of integration).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">At long times, we can take <IT>c</IT><SB>s</SB> outside of the integral and eqn. (4) becomes<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Comparing eqns. (3) and (5), we see that there is an equivalence between the surface expansion rate, <IT>θ</IT>, and (2<IT>t</IT>)<SP>−1</SP> in the long-time asymptote of the Ward–Tordai equation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Consequently, measurements made on the OFC should map onto measurements of stagnant adsorption onto a clean surface in the long-time limit if the substitution <IT>t</IT> = (2<IT>θ</IT>)<SP>−1</SP> is made.</annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the experiments presented here, <IT>c</IT><SB>s</SB> &gt; 0.85<IT>c</IT> at all concentrations (see Fig. 6), so the long-time asymptote should be a good approximation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">One would therefore predict agreement with dynamic surface tension measurements made by, for example, the MBP method.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Similarly, to obtain the short-time asymptote of eqn. (4) (<IT>c</IT><SB>s</SB> → 0), we neglect the back-diffusion term and obtainwhich once again has the same form as the mass-transport equation in the OFC (eqn. (3)), with substitution <IT>t</IT> = (2<IT>θ</IT>)<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">While there is no direct parallel between the Ward–Tordai equation and eqn. (3) in the general case, since the mapping between <IT>θ</IT> and ½<IT>t</IT> holds in both the long-time and short-time limits, it is unlikely to lead to large errors at intermediate times.</annotationART></s> <s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">We note, however, that eqn. (3) holds under all conditions (below the c.m.c.) while eqns. (5) and (6) apply only in their respective asymptotic limits.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Conclusion</HEADER><P><s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">An analysis of the kinetics of adsorption of the fluorocarbon surfactant, APFN, at the air–water interface shows that adsorption is diffusion-controlled at all concentrations below the c.m.c.</annotationART></s> <s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The small deviations of the dynamic surface from equilibrium (Δ<IT>σ</IT> ≤ 2 mN m<SP>−1</SP>, Δ<IT>Γ</IT> ≤ 0.2 μmol m<SP>−2</SP>) are nevertheless sufficient to yield surface expansion rates in an OFC of up to 3 s<SP>−1</SP>, six times greater than pure water at the same flow rate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Significant Marangoni effects can occur even when interfaces are very close to equilibrium.</annotationART></s> <s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Under these conditions (<IT>c</IT> → <IT>c</IT><SB>s</SB>) there should be a direct correspondence between data from the OFC and from adsorption measurements at stagnant surfaces.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
