<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b413703e" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Ice template-assisted assembly of spherical PS-<IT>b</IT>-PAA micelles into novel layer-by-layer hollow spheres</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Novel microscale layer-by-layer hollow spheres are template-assembled by monodispersed spherical PS-<IT>b</IT>-PAA micelles during the sublimation of the frozen micellar solution.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER /><P><s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The aggregation of nanoscale building blocks, such as clusters,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF> spheres,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2 cit3">2,3</REF> and superlattices,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit5 cit6">4–6</REF> has attracted intense interest due to their importance in fundamental research and potential wide-ranging applications.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">To date, a wealthy of methods have been developed to assemble nanoparticles into two- and three-dimensional ordered aggregates, which offers opportunities to explore their novel collective optical, magnetic, and electronic properties.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7 cit8 cit9 cit10">7–10</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">For examples, Xia <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF>. produced various uniform aggregates of spherical colloids following an approach combining physical template and capillary forces.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Jenekhe and Chen<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF> obtained periodic structures assembled by poly(phenylquinoline)-<IT>block</IT>-polystyrene <IT>via</IT> solution evaporation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Stucky <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF>. gained micro-sized hollow spheres co-assembled by silica and gold nanoparticles based on cysteine–lysine diblock copolypeptides.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">These novel structures have potential applications ranging from electro-optical devices <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13 cit14">13,14</REF> and separation membranes <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15 cit16">15,16</REF> to active biomaterial coating <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17 cit18">17,18</REF> and nano-reactors.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18 cit19">18,19</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our group has been studying the micellization of amphiphilic block copolymers and the ordered aggregation of the polymeric micelles.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20 cit21">20,21</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Recently, we have prepared various morphological aggregates of micelles <IT>via</IT> different methods.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">One strategy is to control ordered flower-like aggregation of micelles on a adjustable template of water polycrystal.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The present study is focused on the formation of novel layer-by-layer hollow polymeric spheres by ice template-assisted aggregation of nanoscale micelles.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">To the best of our knowledge, this is the first report of obtaining such novel layer-by-layer hollow aggregates <IT>via</IT> such a simple and convenient method.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The PS<SB>30</SB>-<IT>b</IT>-PAA<SB>51</SB> micelles were firstly prepared as described elsewhere<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF> and characterized by dynamic laser scattering (DLS) and transform electronic microscopy (TEM).</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">A drop of the aqueous micelle solution was first placed onto a clean glass slide and quickly frozen in liquid nitrogen.</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Then the ice in the frozen micellar sample was sublimated by freeze-drying under vacuum and the resultant samples were observed by scanning electron microscopy (SEM).</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, the crystal formation process of pure water was monitored by polarized light microscopy (PLM).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 1a shows the hydrodynamic diameter (<IT>D</IT><SB>h</SB>) distribution <IT>f</IT>(<IT>D</IT><SB>h</SB>) of the PS<SB>30</SB>-<IT>b</IT>-PAA<SB>51</SB> micelles in aqueous solution obtained from DLS.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Obviously, the diameter distribution of the micelles is monodispersed and the average <IT>D</IT><SB>h</SB> of the micelles is about 58 nm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 1b displays the TEM images of the micelles and we can clearly see the spherical shape of the micelles with about 40 nm in diameter.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">It must be noted that the hydrodynamic diameter <IT>D</IT><SB>h</SB> of the micelles measured by DLS is much larger than that observed by TEM.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is because the micelles are swollen in water due to the soluble PAA block, while TEM observation shows the dried aggregates.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Usually, nanoparticles dispersed in water, such as the micelles shown in Fig. 1, aggregate to form random-shaped clusters when the water is removed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to achieve controlled aggregation of the nanoparticles, physical templates are usually used.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Can the solvent be used directly as a template to control the aggregation?</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">To the best of our knowledge, liquid water is not a suitable candidate, but ice may be.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Compared with other templates that can be added, the ice template can be formed and removed easily by freezing and sublimating.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 2 gives the typical PLM image of the thin layer of ice template formed by freezing a drop of water in liquid nitrogen.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The dark grid-like lines as shown in Fig. 2 divide the ice film into many micro-regions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">These micro-regions are supposed to shrink gradually to form spherical micro-regions during the slow sublimation of H<SB>2</SB>O, which is similar to the sublimation of ice in winter.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, it is reasonable to think that ice as shown in Fig. 2 can be used as a template to guide the aggregation of the micelles.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Herein, we aim to use this template to fulfil the controlled aggregation of the micelles shown in Fig. 1.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Upon first rapidly freezing the micellar aqueous solution in liquid nitrogen and then freeze-drying, the resultant samples were observed by SEM and the SEM images are shown in Fig. 3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The resultant sample shown in Fig. 3a looks greatly different from the spheres in Fig. 1b.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The most remarkable difference is the broken hollow spheres containing a cavity encapsulating a smaller spherical particle and the outer shell is about 100 nm in thickness, which can be seen in the insert-enlarged image in Fig. 3a.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fine structure of the shell can be seen in Fig. 3b.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Obviously, the shell is formed by the packed small particles, which corresponds to the nanoscale spherical PS<SB>30</SB>-<IT>b</IT>-PAA<SB>51</SB> micelles.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">These results confirm that the microscale layer-by-layer hollow spheres are just resulted from the assembly of the nanoscale PS<SB>30</SB>-<IT>b</IT>-PAA<SB>51</SB> micelles.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, it can be concluded that the ice template plays a key role in the ordered assembly of the dispersed PS<SB>30</SB>-<IT>b</IT>-PAA<SB>51</SB> micelles in water.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">According to what we have obtained above, we propose a schematic illustration of the ice template-assisted assembly of the nanoscale micelles into layer-by-layer hollow spheres in Fig. 4.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The first step is to freeze the micellar solution instantly (A in Fig. 4), where the micelles are uniformly dispersed in the ice template.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">It should be noted out the ice template is divided into many micro-regions as schematically magnified in step B. Second, during the H<SB>2</SB>O sublimation process, the micro-regions in the ice template gradually shrink and become spherical and the micelles adhered to the surface of the micro-regions in the ice template are piled gradually into a three-dimensional (3D) spherical arrangement (B→C→D).</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Sublimation continuously, a spherical core-shell structure forms (E), where the shell is composed of the packed nanoscale PS<SB>30</SB>-<IT>b</IT>-PAA<SB>51</SB> micelles and the core is still the frozen micellar solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The further sublimation of H<SB>2</SB>O molecule existing in the frozen core results in formation of a cavity between the obtained spherical polymeric shell layer and the shrunk frozen core (F).</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Further continuing the sublimation of H<SB>2</SB>O under high vacuum state till the ice template is completely removed, the novel layer-by-layer polymeric spheres (G) are obtained.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In summary, we have presented a convenient and simple approach to assemble nanoscale micelles into novel microscale layer-by-layer polymeric hollow spheres.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">This method can be extended to general polymeric micelles dispersed in water.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">We believe the method will broad a new way to produce novel structures as shown in this study.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
