<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b418708c" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">A model high surface area alumina-supported palladium catalyst</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">A catalyst preparative procedure is described that produces a high surface area alumina-supported palladium catalyst that yields an atypical chemisorbed carbon monoxide infrared spectrum.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">This inherently residue-free substrate provides a useful reference for evaluation of catalyst crystallite morphology and its effect on reactivity profiles.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER /><P><s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Continuing development of structure–activity relationships relevant to applied heterogeneous catalysis<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2">1,2</REF> requires benchmark catalysts in which crystallite morphology is well defined and in which residues, resulting from the synthesis, which can complicate reactivity profiles<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF> and the vibrational spectra of probe molecules,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF> are absent.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Alumina-supported palladium catalysts for this purpose are usually prepared by surface science methods<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6">5,6</REF> but this limits their ability to be tested in conventional microreactors.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This disadvantage has been overcome by the synthesis of a benchmark alumina supported palladium material, which is an active catalyst for alkyne hydrogenation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The novel synthetic feature is the use of thermally unstable tetramminepalladium(ii) tetraazidopalladate(ii)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF> as the precursor compound rather than conventional precursors such as PdCl<SB>2</SB><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF> or Pd(NO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>2</SB>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF> which can potentially leave residues on the activated catalyst that can affect catalytic performance.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10 cit11">10,11</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">The catalyst is prepared according to eqns. (1) and (2) <IT>via</IT> a controlled explosion of the precursor.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Tertramminepalladium(ii) tetraazidopalladate(ii) was synthesized by reaction of Pd(NH<SB>3</SB>)<SB>4</SB>Cl<SB>2</SB> with sodium azide in water.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">It was mixed with alumina (Degussa Oxid C, BET surface area 109 m<SP>2</SP> g<SP>−1</SP>) in a Pyrex evacuable reaction vessel to produce a Pd loading of <IT>ca.</IT> 10% w/w.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reactor was connected to a gas handling facility equipped with an evacuated reservoir of sufficient volume to contain the complete release of ammonia and nitrogen gas from the thermal decomposition of the tertramminepalladium(ii) tetraazidopalladate(ii).</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This material decomposes at 419 K <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF> and so the reaction mixture was progressively warmed from room temperature to 473 K to effect the decomposition process.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This resulted in the rapid breakdown of the starting material that permitted the remaining solid product to mix intimately with the support material.</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">To ensure no unstable residues remained within the mixture, the solid was then further warmed to 873 K in vacuum.</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This combination of procedures produced a free-flowing powder of uniform grey appearance.</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The sample was sealed in a glass sample container and was stable on exposure to air, where it was sieved to a grain size of 250–500 μm for subsequent analysis.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None"><B>CAUTION!</B> Even though the resulting Pd/Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> catalyst is stable, palladium azide compounds are explosive, see .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">ref. 7</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Analysis by atomic absorption spectroscopy showed the palladium loading to be 7.3%.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">BET analysis indicated a surface area of 94 m<SP>2</SP> g<SP>−1</SP>, indicating the new preparative method has no detrimental effect on total surface area.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Pulsed chemisorption of CO showed the catalyst to saturate at 45 μmol CO g<SP>−1</SP>, which corresponds to 5.42 × 10<SP>19</SP> surface Pd atoms g<SP>−1</SP>, assuming a Pd : CO surface stoichiometry of 2 : 1<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF> and represents a metal dispersion of 13.1%.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Assuming the metal particles are spheres of equal diameter, the chemisorption result equates to a mean particle size of 8.3 nm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Elemental analysis performed using a CE-440 elemental analyser prior to the reduction process<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit9">8,9</REF> was unable to detect the presence of nitrogen in either the support material or the Pd (azide)/Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> catalyst.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">A representative TEM micrograph for the catalyst is presented in Fig. 1; metal crystallites are clearly discernible.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Some of the particles exhibit a distinct hexagonal structure, consistent with cubo-octahedra, as described by Hardeveld and Hartog<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF> and observed elsewhere.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit13">1,13</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Recognition of the general shape of the particles indicates that, to a first approximation, the particle surface can be described in terms of a small number of low index planes, <IT>i.e.</IT> (111) and (100), as identified by STM for the surface science model catalysts.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6">5,6</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Overall, the catalyst exhibits mostly regular particles, with diameters clustered about <IT>ca.</IT> 5 nm and 15 nm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This range is generally consistent with the mean particle size predicted from CO chemisorption.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">High resolution TEM images show the Pd particles to be often composed of crystalline sub-units separated by grain boundaries, twin planes, <IT>etc</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">(insert in Fig. 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, the polyhedral nanoparticles are not always perfect single crystals but, nevertheless, they are still dominated by well developed low index facets with a low level of surface defects (one should note that distortions by the microcrystalline alumina support typically prevent high resolution imaging of particle facets).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The background subtracted diffuse reflectance spectrum in the region 1600–2300 cm<SP>−1</SP> for a saturation coverage of CO on the Pd(azide) catalyst, achieved using a pulse-flow arrangement at 293 K, is presented in Fig. 2(a).</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">This spectrum is atypical for CO chemisorption on a supported palladium catalyst, in that there is effectively no contribution from linear CO at <IT>ca.</IT> 2100–2050 cm<SP>−1</SP>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14 cit15 cit16">14–16</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">To illustrate this point the DRIFTS spectrum for a saturation CO coverage for a 1% Pd/Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> catalyst prepared <IT>via</IT> wet impregnation and using Pd(NO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>2</SB> as the precursor compound is presented in Fig. 2(b).</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Elemental analysis of this catalyst prior to reduction produced a nitrogen content of 0.42%.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">CO chemisorption showed this catalyst to have a metal dispersion of 78%, which corresponds to a mean paricle size of <IT>ca.</IT> 1.4 nm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The spectrum more closely resembles that presented for numerous Pd/Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> catalysts, <IT>e.g</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14 cit15 cit16">refs. 14–16</REF>., with a distinct signal due to linear CO clearly apparent.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Pd(azide)/Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> spectrum is characterised by two intense, symmetrical features: a broad band at 1923 cm<SP>−1</SP> and a sharp feature at 1984 cm<SP>−1</SP> (FWHM = 21 cm<SP>−1</SP>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the basis of CO adsorption studies on metal single crystal and nanoparticle model catalysts<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16 cit17 cit18 cit19">16–19</REF> the 1923 cm<SP>−1</SP> band is assigned to μ<SB>3</SB> hollow bonded CO and μ<SB>2</SB> bridge bonded CO on the (111) planes of the Pd particles.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The origin of the sharp 1984 cm<SP>−1</SP> feature is more complex.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">According to combined vibrational and density functional studies on Pd surfaces of varying roughness, it may originate from CO adsorbed on (100) facets and from CO bridge bonded to particle edges and steps.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, even these contributions cannot explain the high intensity of the 1984 cm<SP>−1</SP> peak and “intensity borrowing” from bridging CO on (111) facets (1923 cm<SP>−1</SP>) may therefore increase the intensity of the 1984 cm<SP>−1</SP> peak.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the pulse chemisorption arrangement employed here, only high purity helium is present over the catalyst during spectral acquisition.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">This situation equates to CO spectra recorded post-evacuation of CO for the more conventional equilibrium measurements, which typically produce CO bands in the 2100 cm<SP>−1</SP> region,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF> characteristic of linear (on-top) CO. Studies on model Pd–Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> catalysts revealed that more intense linear bands were observed for rougher surfaces.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6 cit19">5,6,19</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The effective absence of on-top CO in Fig. 2 is therefore interpreted as indicating that the present catalyst has a low concentration of relatively open sites of low metal coordination number.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this respect, the infrared data are broadly consistent with the electron microscopy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Recently published CO spectra for well-annealed Pd/MgO catalysts also exhibit a minimal linear CO contribution under comparable conditions; in contrast the behaviour of a Pd/γ-Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> catalyst (prepared from PdCl<SB>2</SB>) is less well defined and a significant contribution from linear CO is retained upon evacuation.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, since surface impurities such as carbon increase the amount of linear bonded CO,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF> the diffuse reflectance spectrum indicates that the Pd particles derived from the azide precursor exhibit clean facets.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">The synthetic approach described in this work has the advantage of producing structured metal particles on a high surface area alumina support, that is ubiquitous in heterogeneous catalysis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">In fact, alumina is thought to be the most widely used commercial carrier (support) material.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Given this wide application, future studies could examine the sensitivity of particle morphology to alumina structure by investigating structurally pure aluminas such as γ- and η-aluminas.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">To demonstrate that the Pd(azide)/Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> catalyst exhibits some effectiveness as a catalytic substrate, Fig. 3 presents the results for the hydrogenation of propyne at 293 K in a continuous flow reactor.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Under the selected reaction conditions, full conversion and complete hydrogenation of the propyne are observed, with no loss of activity apparent over the duration studied.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is acknowledged that operation at full conversion prevents a more complete analysis of the capability of the Pd(azide)/Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> catalyst to function as an alkyne hydrogenation catalyst, nevertheless, Fig. 3 clearly indicates this substrate to constitute an active catalyst, worthy of further investigation.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is worthwhile considering the value of this material.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is readily acknowledged that such an exotic (and potentially dangerous) preparative procedure could never be used to prepare industrial catalysts.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, the catalyst described here offers modest dispersion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, this latter attribute could be improved by moderating the anneal temperature.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25">25</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">Additionally, the preparative technique described inherently leads to a residue-free material and the chemisorbed CO infrared spectrum indicates well ordered metal crystallites.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Bertarione <IT>et al.</IT> note that the linear CO signal reflects the defect concentration of supported Pd catalysts.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Following this approach, Fig. 2(b) shows, in agreement with Bertarione <IT>et al.</IT>, that conventional catalyst preparations of alumina-supported Pd catalysts invariably lead to defect rich substrates.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast, Fig. 2(a) clearly shows the azide derived catalyst to exhibit a low concentration of defect sites.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, this catalyst then provides a reference material that could be used to evaluate the role that defect sites play in the surface chemistry/catalysis of supported palladium catalysts and is therefore ideally suited to <IT>in situ</IT> studies.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26">26</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although other preparative procedures could, in principle, also prepare such useful highly ordered catalysts, <IT>e.g.</IT> carefully controlled impregnation methods or MOCVD-based techniques,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27">27</REF> the azide based preparative route has the added advantage that it yields a minimal residue catalyst.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In summary, a novel preparative approach is described that inherently leads to a residue-free high surface area alumina-supported Pd catalyst, that presents a well defined crystallite morphology.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">A schematic representation of the adsorption sites populated at saturation CO coverage is shown in Fig. 4.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">This catalyst can be used to evaluate the role of low index planes in selective hydrogenation reactions and represents a useful benchmark against which preparative procedures, particle roughness, and catalytic activity can be evaluated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Work is in progress to explore these exciting possibilities.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
