<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b419201j" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Free volume anomalies in mixed-cation glasses revealed by positron annihilation lifetime spectroscopy (PALS)<XREF TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" /></annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">PALS experiments reveal a minimum in <IT>ortho</IT>-positronium (<IT>o</IT>-Ps) lifetimes and a maximum in the corresponding intensities that emerge when mixed-cation (Li/Na) borate glasses are heated from ambient temperatures up to 473 K. These free volume ‘anomalies’ appear to be a true manifestation of the mixed alkali effect (MAE).</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">They are consistent with a mechanism of ion transport involving cooperation between hops of unlike cations, resulting in increased disturbance of the glass network.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The result lends support to the dynamic structure model.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER /><P><s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The mixed alkali effect (MAE) remains one of the unsolved mysteries of glass science.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">It involves a wide range of phenomena, including deep minima in ionic conductivities, crossovers in diffusion coefficient, additional (and large) internal friction peaks, and minima in glass transition temperatures, <IT>T</IT><SB>g</SB>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2 cit3">1–3</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although significant progress has been made in recent years towards understanding some of the underlying chemical and physical principles, there is still disagreement concerning how far ion-hopping processes in either single or mixed cation glasses involve the cooperation of the glassy network.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Bunde <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit5">4,5</REF>. have described a ‘dynamic structure model’ that draws attention to the role played by cations in building their own sites, or ‘digging their own holes’, in the glass structure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">A mismatch arises when one type of cation, <IT>e.g.</IT> Li<SP>+</SP>, tries to enter a site created earlier by another, <IT>e.g.</IT> Na<SP>+</SP>, and this is identified as the prime cause of the mixed alkali effect.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The mismatch-opposed hops would be slower than the hopping of Li<SP>+</SP> ions into Li sites, which is the dominant process in single-cation Li<SP>+</SP> ion conducting glasses.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, there are divergent views<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF> as to whether ‘mismatch-opposed’ processes ever actually occur in glass, and whether such ion hops can trigger inter-site conversion processes below <IT>T</IT><SB>g</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">While there is indirect evidence that site conversions do occur below <IT>T</IT><SB>g</SB>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6 cit7">6,7</REF> other authors have argued <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit9 cit10">8–10</REF> that cations in mixed glasses simply avoid the ‘inappropriate’ sites and that the distribution of cation sites remains as it was frozen in at <IT>T</IT><SB>g</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">This divergence of opinion highlights the limitations to our current understanding of processes occurring in glass.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is especially unclear how far the network participates in the ion transport mechanism.</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, Angell<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11 cit12">11,12</REF> pointed out many years ago that for common inorganic glasses (phosphates, borates, silicates, <IT>etc</IT>.), the ratio, <IT>R</IT><SB><IT>τ</IT></SB> of the times required for structural relaxation to occur at <IT>T</IT><SB>g</SB> (as indicated by the step function in heat capacity in a DSC experiment) to the average residence time of the ions (as indicated by the electric field relaxation time from impedance spectroscopy) is very large, with values of <IT>R</IT><SB><IT>τ</IT></SB> falling in the range 10<SP>11</SP> to 10<SP>14</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">This result suggests that network relaxation can have only little influence on ion transport.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the other hand, Ingram <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13 cit14 cit15">13–15</REF>. have argued from the evidence of variable-pressure variable-temperature (VPVT) measurements that activation volumes, <IT>V</IT><SB>A</SB>, for ion transport are conveniently interpreted in terms of the ‘opening up’ of empty cation sites, a process which obviously does involve the glassy network to some extent (see Fig. 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">This figure shows schematically how a mobile cation hops from a site close to its compensating negative charge (shown here as a non-bridging oxygen (nBO)) into an empty site provided by the network.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None"><IT>V</IT><SB>A</SB> is identified<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13 cit14 cit15">13–15</REF> with the volume required to open up this second site.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">What would clearly be helpful is independent evidence concerning the available volume and how it is distributed in both single and mixed-cation glasses.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">An obvious technique to use is positron annihilation lifetime spectroscopy (PALS), which is widely used, for example, to explore cavity sizes in zeolites<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF> and ‘free volume’ in glassy polymers,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF> and to understand ion transport in polymer electrolytes.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18 cit19">18,19</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The PALS experiment measures the lifetimes of positron species by detecting ‘start quanta’ of 1.28 MeV associated with their birth (from the decay of <SP>22</SP>Na to <SP>22</SP>Ne) and ‘stop quanta’ of 511 keV associated with their death (annihilation).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="None" advantage="None">When a positron enters a material three separate processes may occur, each with a different lifetime.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20 cit21">20,21</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The shortest lifetime (100 to 200 ps) is attributed to the self-annihilation of a positron bound to an electron of opposite spin, <IT>i.e. para</IT>-positronium (<IT>p</IT>-Ps).</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The second lifetime (200 to 600 ps) is usually attributed to the annihilation of ‘free’ positrons or to those trapped in the material.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The third lifetime (600 ps upwards) arises from the annihilation of the semi-stable species <IT>ortho</IT>-positronium (<IT>o</IT>-Ps), which is a positron paired with an electron with spins in parallel.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">PALS spectra are composed of contributions from each annihilation event: these can be extracted by a non-linear least-squares fit of a weighted sum of exponentials:Here, <IT>τ</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB> denotes the mean lifetime of the positron state <IT>i</IT>, and <IT>I</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB> is the relative intensity of the lifetime component and <IT>n</IT> is the number of positron states.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Self-annihilation (<IT>p</IT>-Ps) gives little information on cavity characteristics.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the metastable <IT>ortho</IT>-positronium atoms, localised in cavities, have average lifetimes that depend on the cavity size.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The lifetime of <IT>o</IT>-Ps in a vacuum is 142 ns.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In condensed matter, lifetimes are shortened to a few ns since the annihilation rate depends on the probability of the overlap of the <IT>o</IT>-Ps wavefunction with the wavefunctions of the surrounding electrons, which is dependent on the cavity size.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The intensity of the <IT>o</IT>-Ps component is related to the <IT>o</IT>-Ps formation probability and reflects the concentration of cavities accessible to <IT>o</IT>-Ps.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">When <IT>o</IT>-Ps annihilates, it is assumed to do so in a potential well where the <IT>o</IT>-Ps wavefunction has a given penetration depth, Δ<IT>R</IT>, into the material surrounding the potential well.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">If the radius of the well is <IT>R</IT> (assuming a sphere<SUP TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn2" />), the <IT>o</IT>-Ps pickoff lifetime is usually related to the radius of the cavity by:<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23 cit24">23,24</REF>where <IT>τ</IT><SB><IT>o</IT>-Ps</SB> denotes the <IT>o</IT>-Ps pickoff lifetime.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The 1/2 pre-factor is the inverse of the spin averaged Ps annihilation lifetime and Δ<IT>R</IT> has been found empirically to equal 0.166 nm.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The volume of the sphere may then be calculated from <IT>R</IT>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">With this methodology, we are able now to compare the free-volume properties of single and mixed-cation glasses.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">For our investigations we have chosen a mixed Li/Na borate glass system, which shows a conventional mixed alkali effect, which intensifies with decreasing temperature and moreover has been thoroughly characterized with respect to its structure and dynamics using broadband conductivity spectroscopy<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25 cit26 cit27">25–27</REF> and NMR spectroscopy.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28 cit29 cit30">28–30</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Alkali borate glasses of composition 0.3[<IT>x</IT> Li<SB>2</SB>O·(1−<IT>x</IT>) Na<SB>2</SB>O]·0.7 B<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> (with <IT>x</IT> = 0.0,0.2,0.4,0.6,0.8,1.0) were prepared from dry mixtures of stoichiometric amounts of reagent grade powder chemicals Na<SB>2</SB>CO<SB>3</SB>, Li<SB>2</SB>CO<SB>3</SB> and B<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> which were heated in a platinum crucible at 1273 K for about 3 h.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The melt was poured into a rectangular graphite mould and held inside the furnace for another 10 min.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Then the samples were removed from the mould, immediately annealed at 20 K below their respective glass transition temperatures for 3 h and then cooled to ambient temperature at a rate of 0.5 K min<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Two slices of more than 1 mm thickness were cut from the raw glasses.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 2 shows the dc conductivity of glassy 0.3[<IT>x</IT> Li<SB>2</SB>O·(1 − <IT>x</IT>) Na<SB>2</SB>O]·0.7 B<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> at 373 K and features a pronounced minimum at <IT>x</IT> = 0.4.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The minimum in the DC conductivity coincides with the minimum of the glass transition temperature (see Fig. 2).</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">As the recent NMR results by Ratai <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28 cit29 cit30">28–30</REF>. show, these mixed alkali effects cannot be explained by ‘normal’ structural peculiarities.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Apparently, in all mixed-cation glasses of type 0.3[<IT>x</IT> Li<SB>2</SB>O·(1 − <IT>x</IT>) Na<SB>2</SB>O]·0.7 B<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB>, the ratio N<SB>4</SB> = [BO<SB>4</SB>]<SP>−</SP>/([BO<SB>3</SB>] + [BO<SB>4</SB>]<SP>−</SP>) remains the same.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, the tetrahedrally coordinated [BO<SB>4</SB>]<SP>−</SP>-groups and the trigonal planar coordinated [BO<SB>3</SB>]-groups as well as the cations are randomly distributed throughout the glass structure.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">PALS measurements have been performed using an automated EG&amp;G Ortec fast–fast coincidence system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Two identical samples (&gt;1 mm thick) of glass were placed on either side of a source consisting of a 2 mm diameter 25 μCi spot sandwiched between two 2.54 μm titanium foils.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The sample-source sandwich was placed between two mica-insulated heaters with a thermocouple placed close to the sample.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Temperature was controlled by a single variable voltage power supply attached to both heaters.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Data were collected at several temperatures and analysed using the PFPOSFIT program.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">At least two spectra of 30 000 peak counts were collected, with each spectrum taking approximately 3 h to collect.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">No source correction was used.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Statistical analysis resulted in spectra best fitted with two exponentials.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The first component is attributed to self-annihilation (<IT>p</IT>-Ps) and free positrons, and is not considered further.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The second component, with a lifetime <IT>ca.</IT> 800 ps is attributed to the lifetime of <IT>o</IT>-Ps localised in cavities, and is referred to as <IT>τ</IT><SB><IT>o</IT>-Ps</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Error bars in the experimental data were determined from repeated experiments on the same sample.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">These error bars are much larger than those determined from the fitting procedure.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Figs. 3–5 show how the <IT>o</IT>-Ps lifetimes and corresponding intensities for the Li–Na borate glasses vary with composition at three temperatures: 298 K, 373 K, and 473 K, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The sizes of the cavities for 473 K (see Fig. 4) are somewhat larger (<IT>ca.</IT> 6 cm<SP>3</SP> mol<SP>−1</SP>) than those of the mobile cations (<IT>ca.</IT> 1.5 cm<SP>3</SP> mol<SP>−1</SP> for Li<SP>+</SP>, and 3.5 cm<SP>3</SP> mol<SP>−1</SP> for Na<SP>+</SP>, based on recent activation volume data<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13 cit14 cit15">13–15</REF>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, they are clearly smaller than the [BO<SB>3</SB>] and [BO<SB>4</SB>]<SP>−</SP> units that constitute the network (between 15 and 20 cm<SP>3</SP> mol<SP>−1</SP>, respectively, based on the numbers of O<SP>2−</SP> ions present).</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The size of the cavities points to a glass system that is fairly dense, but not as close-packed as the ‘more ionic’ fluoride glasses studied earlier by Hill <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">At ambient temperature (298 K), there is no consistent dependence on composition in either the intensity, <IT>I</IT><SB><IT>o</IT>-Ps</SB>, or of the lifetime, <IT>τ</IT><SB><IT>o</IT>-Ps</SB>, although there is some suggestion of a small ‘ripple’ in both quantities, see also .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit31">ref. 31</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ripple, moreover, is clearly evident at 373 K. It takes the form of a maximum in <IT>I</IT><SB><IT>o</IT>-Ps</SB> on the Li-rich side and a corresponding minimum in <IT>τ</IT><SB><IT>o</IT>-Ps</SB>, and a maximum in <IT>τ</IT><SB><IT>o</IT>-Ps</SB> and a corresponding minimum in <IT>I</IT><SB><IT>o</IT>-Ps</SB> on the Na-rich side.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Further heating of the sample to 473 K leads to a new and much simpler pattern of behaviour with a single maximum in positronium intensity and a corresponding minimum in positronium lifetimes.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Analysis of this temperature dependence requires careful consideration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">One must take into account, for example, the well-known ‘thermometer’ effect,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2 cit3">1–3</REF> which involves volume inelasticities in mixed alkali glasses that are observed far below <IT>T</IT><SB>g</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">These delayed volume changes relate to different sites being occupied by mobile cations, and to the slowness (measured in days or weeks) of volume relaxations occurring in mixed cation glasses close to ambient temperature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">These glasses thus depart even further from internal thermal equilibrium than do single-cation glasses.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In other words, there are additional thermal history effects.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">These relaxations might be expected to influence the distribution of free volume in mixed cation glasses, and so may well influence the PALS data collected at these (lower) temperatures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Accordingly, we do not discuss further the low-temperature data, but focus instead on the pattern of behaviour observed at 473 K, which is some 200 K below <IT>T</IT><SB>g</SB> but high enough for the ‘thermometer effects’ to be avoided.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">We base our interpretation of this ‘high temperature’ data on the recent discussions of trends in activation volume.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13 cit14 cit15">13–15</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, in single cation glasses (Li or Na), we suggest that each ion migrates along clearly defined pathways where Li<SP>+</SP> ions hop into empty Li-sites, and Na<SP>+</SP> ions hop into empty Na-sites.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, if a Na<SP>+</SP> ion moves forward into a new site, it will leave behind an open Na-site, which will then immediately be reoccupied by a second Na<SP>+</SP> ion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">This process may be represented schematically as:Na<SP>+</SP>(2) + Na<SP>+</SP>(1) + ‘new site’ ⇒ Na<SP>+</SP>(2) + ‘open site’ + Na<SP>+</SP>(1)Na<SP>+</SP>(2) + ‘open site’ ⇒ ‘open site’ + Na<SP>+</SP>(2)The essential idea is that the ‘success’ of the hop made by Na<SP>+</SP> ion (1) will be facilitated by its original site being occupied by Na<SP>+</SP> ion (2).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In mixed cation glasses, the ‘wrong’ cation—in this case it could be a Li<SP>+</SP> ion—would fail to complete the second step in time, since it is forestalled by Na<SP>+</SP> ion (1) moving more readily back into its starting site.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The original hop will then prove ‘unsuccessful’ in the sense used by Funke and coworkers.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit32 cit33">32,33</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, a second mechanism may come into play in mixed cation glasses, especially at higher temperatures (like 473 K).</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is represented schematically as:Li<SP>+</SP> + Na<SP>+</SP>(1) + ‘new site’ ⇒ Li<SP>+</SP> + ‘open site’ + Na<SP>+</SP>(1)Li<SP>+</SP> + ‘second new site’ ⇒ ‘open site’ + Li<SP>+</SP>The additional feature is that the second ion, in this case it is the Li<SP>+</SP> ion, has taken the opportunity to open up a new site of its own close to the site originally occupied by the Na<SP>+</SP> ion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">This also has the effect of ‘pushing the Na<SP>+</SP> ion forward’, and hence of securing the success of the first ion’s hop.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the interaction between cations and network is now much stronger than in single cation glasses, since <IT>two</IT> new sites are being opened up in the cooperative process that facilitates ion transport.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The resulting increased disturbance in the network results in an increased number of cavities, as is indeed indicated by the observed maximum in the <IT>I</IT><SB><IT>o</IT>-Ps</SB> data (see Fig. 5).</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although we cannot quantify the absolute number of voids existing in single and mixed cation glasses, we will argue that the increased network disturbance also leads to the observed decreases in <IT>T</IT><SB>g</SB> displayed in Fig. 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus we are able to establish for the first time a link between activation volume anomalies in mixed cation glasses,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13 cit14 cit15">13–15</REF> the changes in cavity distribution reported here, and the ‘thermodynamic’ anomalies in mixed cation glasses (see Fig. 2).</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">To this extent at least, the present results lend positive support to the general approach described in the dynamic structure model of glass.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit5">4,5</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">It appears that the structural dynamics become increasingly important with increasing temperature.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">A particular feature of the approach being advanced here is the proposal for localised relaxations involved in the ‘opening up’ of closed sites.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit13 cit14 cit15">5,13–15</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">But how does such a process of site opening occur?</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">One might envisage in these borate glasses, for example, the participation of a bond-switching mechanism where there are negatively charged [BO<SB>4</SB>]<SP>−</SP> groups embedded in a framework of [BO<SB>3</SB>] triangles, to generate neigbouring [BO<SB>3</SB>]<SP>−</SP> triangles containing one nonbridging oxygen (nBO):</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">For this reaction to proceed, all that is needed is for an electron pair from one of the four B–O bonds in the [BO<SB>4</SB>]<SP>−</SP> group to be transferred entirely to the O atom it shares with the neighbouring [BO<SB>3</SB>] group, and for the structure to relax slightly.</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">This process of chemical isomerisation clearly leads to a localised weakening of the network, and could occur simultaneously (and synergetically) with the arrival of a new cation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reaction above shows how ion hopping might be related to localised relaxation of the network.</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Ion hopping depends on the space being available locally, so cavities of the right size are needed for this reaction to occur.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is noteworthy that a recent molecular dynamics (MD) simulation of lithium borate glasses<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit34">34</REF> points to the importance of nonbridging oxygens (nBOs) in creating sites in glass favourable to Li<SP>+</SP> ion transport.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the concentrations of such nBOs arising from the computer simulations is somewhat higher than that found by NMR.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23 cit24 cit25">23–25</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, we might now postulate that even if these nBOs are produced only transiently in ‘real’ alkali borate glasses, they may still play a vital role in the opening up of sites – either to allow cations to escape from their existing sites or to enter new ones.</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">If this is indeed the process which makes use of free volume cavities in glass, then it provides a logical link between the presence of the cavities detected by PALS and the ion transport mechanism.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">It may also provide the means of reconciling differing viewpoints concerning the numbers of nBOs in borate glasses (compare <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28 cit29 cit30">refs. 28–30</REF> with <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit35">ref. 35</REF>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Clearly, more extended studies are required to establish links between ion transport processes and PALS data, especially if all the additional information can be extracted from the complex temperature dependences reported above.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The authors would like to thank Prof. T. J. Bastow (CSIRO) for experimental assistance, and Dr Kate Nairn and Prof. H. Eckert for helpful discussions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The PALS experiments were carried out with funding from the Australian Research Council within the framework of the ARC Centres of Excellence program through the Centre for Nanostructured Electromaterials.</annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">MDI thanks the Alexander von Humboldt Foundation for a Research Award.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
