<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b301675g" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Reactivity of α,β-unsaturated carbonyl compounds towards nucleophilic addition reaction: a local hard–soft acid–base approach</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">The Fukui function <IT>f</IT><SB>k</SB><SP>+</SP> and local softness <IT>s</IT><SB>k</SB><SP>+</SP> are assigned as reactivity parameters for nucleophilic addition reaction in acrolein, methylacrylate, methylmethacrylate, acryloylchloride, cinnamaldehyde and cinnamoylchloride.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">All calculations were performed at the HF level of theory using 6-31G, 6-31G** and TZV basis sets.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The condensed local softness calculated using a Löwdin population is compared with the local softness calculated from a Mulliken population.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The most probable sites for nucleophilic attack on the α,β-unsaturated carbonyl compounds are determined from local reactivity descriptors: they are quite reliable to predict the reactivity relative to atomic charges.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The chemical reactivity of a molecule is often interpreted in terms of charge distribution of its atoms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Atomic charges are used to indicate the preferred direction for a reagent to approach a substrate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although the chemists have an intuitive feeling for the reactivity based on charge distribution, assigning precise reactivity from atomic charge failed in several cases.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2">1,2</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In recent years, reactivity descriptors<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3 cit4 cit5 cit6 cit7">3–7</REF> such as hardness, softness, Fukui function <IT>etc.</IT> have emerged as powerful tools in predicting the reactive sites of molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">These reactivity descriptors are derived from density functional theory.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Global hardness and global softness<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit9 cit10 cit11 cit12">8–12</REF> represent the reactivity of a molecule as a whole.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the other hand, the Fukui function<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF> defines the reactivity of an atom in a molecule and it is a local property.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fukui function and local softness, which is closely related, are suited to describe the relative reactivity of different substrates.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Pearson's hard–soft acid–base (HSAB) <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12 cit14 cit15 cit16">12,14–16</REF> principle suggested that hard–hard and soft–soft interactions are favorable over hard–soft interactions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17 cit18 cit19">17–19</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Again it has been found that soft–soft interactions are preferred in the site of the maximum Fukui function, <IT>i.e.</IT> frontier control,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20 cit21 cit22">20–22</REF> but on the other hand, hard–hard interactions are preferred in the site of the minimum Fukui function,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23 cit24">23,24</REF><IT>i.e.</IT> charge control.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this paper we have presented the reactivity parameters, the local softness <IT>s</IT><SB>k</SB><SP>+</SP> and <IT>s</IT><SB>k</SB><SP>−</SP> and Fukui functions <IT>f</IT><SB>k</SB><SP>+</SP> and <IT>f</IT><SB>k</SB><SP>−</SP> of α,β-unsaturated carbonyl compounds, namely acrolein (H<SB>2</SB>CCHCHO), methylacrylate (H<SB>2</SB>CCHCOOCH<SB>3</SB>), methylmethacrylate (H<SB>2</SB>CC(CH<SB>3</SB>)COOCH<SB>3</SB>), cinnamaldehyde (C<SB>6</SB>H<SB>5</SB>CHCHCHO), cinnamoylchloride (C<SB>6</SB>H<SB>5</SB>CHCHCOCl) and acryloylchloride (H<SB>2</SB>CCHCOCl), and the most reactive sites of nucleophilic attack were derived.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In these compounds the carbonyl carbon is slightly positive, due to mesomeric and resonance effects.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The β-carbon, which is conjugated with the carbonyl carbon develops partial positive charge.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Experimentally it has been found that a nucleophile attacks at the β-carbon atom of α,β-unsaturated carbonyl compounds.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25">25</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Here we have investigated the reactive sites of these carbonyl compounds towards a nucleophile using a local hard–soft acid–base approach.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Theoretical aspects</HEADER><P><s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Within the framework of density functional theory (DFT) <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF> the global hardness (<IT>η</IT>) <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9 cit10 cit11 cit12">9–12</REF> of an <IT>N</IT> electron system is defined as: where <IT>E</IT>, <IT>N</IT>, <IT>μ</IT> and <IT>v</IT>(<IT>r⃑</IT>) are the energy, number of electrons, chemical potential and external potential, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Again, the inverse of global hardness with a factor of ½ is defined as global softness (<IT>S</IT>),The local property, Fukui function<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF><IT>f</IT>(<IT>r</IT>) is defined as the derivative of electron density, <IT>ρ</IT>(<IT>r⃑</IT>), with respect to the number of electrons at a constant external potential, <IT>v</IT>(<IT>r⃑</IT>).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Similarly local softness, <IT>s</IT>(<IT>r⃑</IT>), is defined as the derivative of electron density, <IT>ρ</IT>(<IT>r⃑</IT>), with respect to the chemical potential, <IT>μ</IT>, at constant external potential,Applying the finite difference approximation, three types of condensed Fukui functions<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF> are found from electronic population analyses<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26">26</REF>.where, <IT>q</IT><SB>k</SB>(<IT>N</IT>), <IT>q</IT><SB>k</SB>(<IT>N</IT> + 1) and <IT>q</IT><SB>k</SB>(<IT>N</IT> − 1) are atomic charges for atom k in the <IT>N</IT>, (<IT>N</IT> + 1) and (<IT>N</IT> − 1)-electron systems.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Fukui functions <IT>f</IT><SB>k</SB><SP>+</SP> and <IT>f</IT><SB>k</SB><SP>−</SP> and local softness <IT>s</IT><SB>k</SB><SP>+</SP> and <IT>s</IT><SB>k</SB><SP>−</SP> are calculated from SCF calculation using 6-31G, 6-31G** and TZV basis sets<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27 cit28">27,28</REF> and all these calculations are performed with the program GAMESS<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29">29</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Results and discussion</HEADER><P><s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The α,β-unsaturated carbonyl compounds contain two reactive sites, the carbonyl group site and the carbon–carbon double bond site.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hence, two types of nucleophilic addition reaction can be assigned as the direct addition reaction and conjugated addition reaction.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, to what extent a given nucleophile undergoes the direct addition and conjugated addition is dependent on the steric and electronic factors.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">If the carbonyl carbon is more sterically congested and weakly electrophilic, the conjugated addition will occur more readily than the direct addition, on the other hand if the β-carbon is more sterically congested the direct addition will take place predominantly.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus the nucleophilic reagents add to the conjugated system in such a way so as to form the most stable intermediate anion.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30">30</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The tendency of the α,β-unsaturated carbonyl compounds to undergo nucleophilic addition is not simply due to the electron withdrawing ability of the carbonyl group, but to the existence of a conjugated system that permits the formation of the resonance stabilized anion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Theoretically atomic charges, Fukui functions and local softness values can be calculated for each atom in the molecule and they provide an insight in directing the incoming nucleophiles for the attack on the carbon atoms of the α,β-unsaturated carbonyl compounds.</annotationART></s></P><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Atomic charges</HEADER><P><s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The atomic charges derived from Mulliken population analysis (MPA) and Löwdin population analysis (LPA) for C<SB>α</SB>, C<SB>β</SB> and C<SB>carbonyl</SB> atoms of α,β-unsaturated carbonyl compounds are given in Table 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is seen from Table 1 that both MPA and LPA derived charges have negative values for C<SB>α</SB> and C<SB>β</SB> atoms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the charges of the C<SB>carbonyl</SB> atoms are positive, a nucleophile should attack at the carbonyl atoms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, experimentally it has been found that in most of the cases the nucleophilic addition takes place at the β-carbon atom.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hence it is difficult to predict the reactive sites of these compounds from atomic charge values.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">In our recent studies,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit31 cit33">31,33</REF> Fukui function and local softness appear to be better reactivity descriptors for studying the acidity and basicity of zeolites.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Roy <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit32">32</REF>. used the reactivity descriptors to study the most preferable protonation sites in aniline and substituted anilines in the gas phase.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, the Fukui function and the local softness are found to be superior to atomic charges in determining the reactive sites in molecules.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Fukui function</HEADER><P><s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Fukui function values for the C<SB>α</SB>, C<SB>β</SB> and C<SB>carbonyl</SB> atoms are presented in Table 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both MPA and LPA derived Fukui functions for the C<SB>β</SB> and C<SB>carbonyl</SB> atoms are positive.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The negative Fukui function is observed for the C<SB>α</SB> atom in acrolein and acryloyl chloride.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The negative values of Fukui functions indicate a very low probability for nucleophilic attack to take place at those sites.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Recently, Hirao and co-workers,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit31 cit32">31,32</REF> suggested that the Fukui function of an atom should be always positive.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">They found that the Fukui function calculated using Hirshfeld population analysis become positive although MPA derived Fukui function for some atoms become negative in the same calculation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In our present study, the LPA derived Fukui functions are found to be positive for all the atoms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">While comparing the Fukui function values calculated using 6-31G, 6-31G** and TZV basis sets, it appears that the β-carbon of each of the molecule has maximum values.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">This indicates that the incoming nucleophile will preferably attack the β-carbon atom which is in agreement with the experimental results.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25">25</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Moreover, the Fukui function values for β-carbon with less bulky groups at α and β positions are more than those of the molecules where more bulky groups are present at α and β positions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">For all the molecules the reactivity of the atoms for nucleophilic attack decreases in the order: C<SB>β</SB> &gt; C<SB>carbonyl</SB> &gt; C<SB>α</SB> while considering the MPA derived Fukui functions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The LPA derived Fukui functions also predict the same trend bearing a disorder in case of methylacrylate.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Local softness</HEADER><P><s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The local softness values of all the molecules calculated with different basis sets such as 6-31G, 6-31G** and TZV are given in Table 3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Like Fukui functions, local softness values predict the similar trend of reactivity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reactivity of the atoms for nucleophilic attack decreases in the order: C<SB>β</SB> &gt; C<SB>carbonyl</SB> &gt; C<SB>α</SB> bearing slight disorder for LPA derived softness values.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac20" novelty="None" advantage="None">From the softness values a reactivity order for molecules could be derived.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">From Table 2 and Table 3 it is seen that Fukui function and local softness values are more at the β-carbon atoms in the molecules with less bulky groups.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hence, β-carbon atoms of α,β-unsaturated carbonyl compounds are more reactive and prone for nucleophilic attacks when less bulky groups are present.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Conclusions</HEADER><P><s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Local reactivity descriptors are shown to be very powerful in predicting the reactivity of α,β-unsaturated compounds.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">From the Fukui functions and local softness values it is concluded that the β-carbon atoms of the α,β-unsaturated carbonyl compounds are more reactive towards a nucleophile.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reactivities of the three types of carbon atoms are found to decrease in the order: C<SB>β</SB> &gt; C<SB>carbonyl</SB> &gt; C<SB>α</SB> in all of the molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The local softness values are dependent on the substituents present at the β-carbon atoms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The local softness values of β-carbon atoms with less bulky groups are greater than those with more bulky groups.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac21" novelty="None" advantage="None">These results provide an insight in comparing the intermolecular reactivities of various α,β-unsaturated carbonyl compounds.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
