<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b305411j" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Intracellular localization of a long alkyl chain tetraphenylporphyrin and chloride channel activation in <IT>Psammobatis extenta</IT> electrocytes</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">The intracellular localization of a tetraphenylporphyrin bearing four long lipophilic alkyl chains in electrocytes from <IT>Psammobatis extenta</IT> (<IT>Rajidae</IT>) is described.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast to what is usually the case, this porphyrin derivative is localized in the electromotor nerves and the nuclear chromatin of the electrocytes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both structures exhibited intense fluorescence, whereas, the mitochondria were only slightly fluorescent.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">These data are discussed in relation to electrocyte death in a weakly electric fish.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Additionally, electron probe X-ray microanalysis suggests a migration of chloride and cationic ions, which might be implicated in chloride and cationic channel activation in the electrocyte.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER /><P><s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The development of new generation photosensitizers to improve the efficiency of photodynamic therapy (PDT) is an area of intensive research.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In PDT, the activation of a photosensitizer by light generates singlet molecular oxygen (<SP>1</SP>O<SB>2</SB>), a highly active form of oxygen that reacts with many biomolecules, including lipids, proteins, and nucleic acids.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The biomolecules are chemically modified by the action of <SP>1</SP>O<SB>2</SB> and, therefore, cannot accomplish their function, which leads to cell death.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">This therapy is applied for treatment of cancer, as well as for bacterial and viral eradication.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2 cit3 cit4 cit5 cit6">2–6</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fluorescence exhibited by photosensitizers means they can also be used for detection of tumors.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The advantages of this method, as compared to other conventional cancer treatment modalities, are its low systemic toxicity and its ability to destroy tumors selectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Nevertheless, the application of PDT remains restricted due to the limited penetration of light into tissues, the photosensitization of normal tissues, and the residual skin photosensitivity that is observed for several weeks following treatment.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The lipophilicity of a particular photosensitizer determines its localization and, therefore, the site and nature of the damage it gives rise to in cells;<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6 cit8 cit9">6,8,9</REF> in general, lipophilic photosensitizers accumulate in the membrane of a cell and its organelles.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the other hand, hydrophilic, as well as aggregated states of photosensitizers, enter the cell by pynocitosis and are localized mainly in lysosomes and endosomes.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">There are many photosensitizers, mostly porphyrin or phthalocyanine derivatives, under clinical study that can be classified as lipophilic or hydrophilic.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, there are a few examples of neutral macrocycles with long alkyl chains which have been studied as potential photosensitizers for PDT.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The efficiency and selectivity of tumor targeting has been shown to increase slightly upon increasing the length of the alkyl groups connected to a Zn(ii)–phthalocyanine complex.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12 cit13">12,13</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this work, we have investigated the uptake and intracellular localization of 5,10,15,20-tetrakis(4-<IT>n</IT>-dodecylphenyl)porphyrin (<XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem1">1</XREF>),<SUP TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" /> and the elemental composition and morphological changes in electrocytes of <IT>Psammobatis extenta</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">This species belongs to the <IT>Rajidae</IT>, one of three groups of weakly electric fish.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">We chose electrocytes for this study because they are large cells with very few organelles.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">This facilitates the study of the intracellular localization of the photosensitizer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, electric ray electrocytes have myoproteins.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14 cit15">14,15</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The electrocytes are highly polarized and multinuclear cells.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">They are semicircular in shape (Fig. 1) and have their concave face receiving innervations (IF) from electromotor neurons of the spinal cord.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The other face, which is convex, is non-innervated (NIF) and shows a system of caveolae.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The nuclei are localized at the posterior region of the cytoplasm.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Electric organ cryostat sections were performed along the antero-posterior axis; sections were incubated with a solution of <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem1">1</XREF> in a mixture of xylene, EtOH, and imidazole buffer<SUP TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn2" /> and observed with an epifluorescence microscope (Fig. 2).</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The phase-contrast micrograph [Fig. 2(a)] shows part of two electrocytes and the fluorescence micrograph [Fig. 2(b)] shows strong fluorescence in the nuclei, but only very slight fluorescence in the mitochondria.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">When the incubation was performed in CHCl<SB>3</SB> solution only, the intracellular localization of <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem1">1</XREF> is the same, but the micrograph shows better contrast (Fig. 3).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The photosensitizer also shows affinity for the terminal nerves (TN).</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The affinity of this lipophilic photosensitizer for the nerves is a result of this tissue being rich in fatty acids.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The nuclei show an intense red fluorescence and the shape of this fluorescence is similar to the semicircular distribution of the chromatin of these cells (Fig. 3), suggesting that <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem1">1</XREF> interacts with DNA.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast, the mitochondria show only slight fluorescence.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">This localization is unusual for other photosensitizers of similar polarity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac20" novelty="None" advantage="None">For example, a lipophilic phthalocyanine has been found to localize on the lysosomes.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Immediately after the penetration of <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem1">1</XREF> (1.2 × 10<SP>–4</SP> M in chloroform) into the electrocytes, they start to swell and the convex faces lose all their invaginations (Fig. 4).</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">In order to understand the reason for the swelling of cells, microanalysis by energy-dispersive X-ray (EDAX) spectroscopy of the same region was carried out.<SUP TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn2" /> After treatment of the electrocyte with <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem1">1</XREF>, the relative semi-quantitative contents [<IT>K</IT><SB>α</SB> (wt%)] of oxygen, sodium, and chloride ions were 39, 17, and 15, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac21" novelty="None" advantage="None">Compared to the negative control, the peak for Na<SP>+</SP> is five times larger, while for oxygen, the variation is not significant.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac22" novelty="None" advantage="None">Additionally, the Ca<SP>2+</SP> peak is twice as large for the treated electrocyte compared to the negative control, but that for K<SP>+</SP> is six times smaller.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The simultaneous increase in the Na<SP>+</SP> and Ca<SP>2+</SP> concentrations and the decrease in the K<SP>+</SP> concentration is good evidence for cationic channel activation by the porphyrin derivative.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the most important change is the appearance of a large new peak corresponding to the Cl<SP>–</SP> anion.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Treatment of electrocytes with systems I and II [(I) 7.8 × 10<SP>–5</SP> M of <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem1">1</XREF> in CHCl<SB>3</SB>–EtOH–imidazole buffer; (II) 3.9 × 10<SP>–4</SP> M of <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem1">1</XREF> in xylene–EtOH–imidazole buffer] produces similar behavior to that observed after treatment with the CHCl<SB>3</SB> solution of <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem1">1</XREF>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">In both cases, the EDAX patterns shows a new peak corresponding to the chloride anion (Fig. 5).</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The <IT>K</IT><SB>α</SB> values for this element are 47 (system I) and 33 wt% (system II), in spite of the higher concentration of <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem1">1</XREF> in system II (5 times higher) compared to system I. These results constitute suggestive evidence for chloride channel activation as a consequence of the penetration of <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem1">1</XREF> into the electrocytes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac23" novelty="None" advantage="None">The massive intracellular accumulation of Cl<SP>–</SP> and, particularly, the influx of Na<SP>+</SP> lead to cell swelling, and eventually a necrotic response from the cells.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17 cit18">17,18</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac24" novelty="None" advantage="None">It should be pointed out that chloride channel activation is not usual for weakly electric fish.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac25" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the presence of a voltage-gated chloride channel was demonstrated in the non-innervated plasma membrane of electrocytes of <IT>Torpedo</IT>, a strongly electric fish.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19">19</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The activation of the chloride channel by <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem1">1</XREF> may constitute an alternative for the treatment of cystic fibrosis, which is related to a dysfunction of chloride ion transport.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac26" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast, the increase in the Ca<SP>2+</SP> concentration in the electrocytes suggests the participation of an apoptotic mechanism.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac27" novelty="None" advantage="None">Moreover, the interaction of <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem1">1</XREF> with DNA, and even the low amount of mitochondrial-bound porphyrin, may contribute to cell death by an apoptotic mechanism after excitation with light.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac28" novelty="None" advantage="None">The photosensitizer used in this work has liquid crystalline properties.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21 cit22">21,22</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac29" novelty="None" advantage="None">It would be very interesting to compare these results with those obtained using another photosensitizer with a similar chemical structure but no mesomorphic properties.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
