<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b310865a" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Vitrification, nucleation and crystallization in phenyl-2-hydroxybenzoate (salol) studied by Differential Scanning Calorimetry (DSC) and Thermally Stimulated Depolarisation Currents (TSDC)</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The behaviour of phenyl-2-hydroxybenzoate (salol) with respect to crystallization and vitrification was studied by Thermally Stimulated Depolarisation Currents (TSDC) and Differential Scanning Calorimetry (DSC).</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">It was found that this compound can be easily supercooled, and vitrified by further cooling.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The degree of supercooling can be high, even for low cooling rates.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fragility index was found to be <IT>m</IT> ≅ 60 by DSC and by TSDC, a value that is lower than the values previously reported.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, glassy salol crystallises on heating (cold crystallisation).</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Two different polymorphs were detected, and the conditions of formation of each of them have been clearly established.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Finally, it was shown that the β-relaxation of salol, that is difficult to observe by Dielectric Relaxation Spectroscopy, was very clearly detected by TSDC.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This mobility, that is believed to assist the occurrence of the nucleation process, was found to be narrowly distributed in activation energy, with a mean value around <IT>E</IT><SB>a</SB> = 46 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The mean characteristic time at the glass transition temperature of these molecular motions was found to be of the order of <IT>τ</IT><SB>β</SB>(<IT>T</IT><SB>g</SB>) ≅ 10<SP>−2</SP> s.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Salol, or phenyl-2-hydroxybenzoate, or phenyl salicylate (see Fig. 1) are three names for an ester with diversified applications, namely as a stabilizer for cellulosic and vinyl plastics, as an ingredient for suntan preparations, and also as an analgesic and antipyretic.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, it is a fragile glass-forming substance and, in this context, it is considered as a model substance for the study of the glass transition and of the molecular mobility in the supercooled liquid state and in the glass.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">It was found, a long time ago, that crystalline salol can exist in, at least, two different crystal structures,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2 cit3 cit4">2–4</REF> one stable that melts at <IT>T</IT><SB>fus</SB> = 41.7° C, and the other, instable, with <IT>T</IT><SB>fus</SB> = 28.5° C.</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, the crystallization behaviour of salol has been the subject of investigation for many years.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3 cit4 cit5 cit6">3–6</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Salol is easily supercooled, that is to say, it has a low tendency to crystallize on cooling and it is relatively easy to vitrify.</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">It was found<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF> that the crystallization due to crystal growth occurs in the temperature interval between 254 and 313 K (between −19 and +40° C) with a maximum at 297 K (26° C).</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">More recently, a different crystallization mechanism was identified by Oguni <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit9">8,9</REF>. in the vicinity of the glass transition temperature (<IT>T</IT><SB>g</SB> = 211 K = −52° C at 10 K min<SP>−1</SP> obtained by DSC), and it was demonstrated that the crystals formed at 220 K and at 300 K have the same crystal structure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is recognised that the homogeneous nucleation rate has a maximum near <IT>T</IT><SB>g</SB> in many cases, given that the development of structured clusters of molecules is enhanced as the temperature decreases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">In particular, this is expected to be the case for fragile liquids, given that they have more opportunities for the development of structured cluster-like configurations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Below <IT>T</IT><SB>g</SB>, however, the motional rearrangement of molecules becomes sluggish, so that the nucleation process should be kinetically reduced.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Despite this general idea, the existence of a slow nucleation mechanism below <IT>T</IT><SB>g</SB> in salol was proposed in a recent paper.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">According to this work, the crystal formed as a consequence of this mechanism is a metastable polymorph that melts at <IT>T</IT><SB>fus</SB> = 300 K = 27° C, and the β-molecular relaxation process is believed to be the motional process that controls the nucleation and growth mechanisms under such conditions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11 cit12">11,12</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In the present work we report some results obtained by Differential Scanning Calorimetry (DSC) that provide us with a better understanding of the thermal behaviour of salol.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this context we will characterise the glass transition of salol, and we will determine the fragility index of this glass-forming system for the heating rate dependence of the onset temperature of the glass transition DSC signal.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The conditions for nucleation, as well as the conditions that enable the crystallization of salol to generate one or the other of the two crystalline polymorphic forms, will be discussed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The technique of Thermally Stimulated Depolarisation Currents (TSDC) will also be used with two purposes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa4" novelty="None" advantage="None">One of them is to monitor the cold crystallization process of salol, the other is to study the β-relaxation process that is believed to assist the nucleation process.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Experimental</HEADER><P><s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Salol (C<SB>13</SB>H<SB>10</SB>O<SB>3</SB>, CAS no.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">118-55-8), was purchased from Aldrich (99% purity).</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">It was purified by sublimation at room temperature under a pressure of 1.3 × 10<SP>−1</SP> Pa.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The calorimetric measurements were performed with a 2920 MDSC system from TA Instruments Inc. Dry high purity He gas with a flow rate of 30 cm<SP>3</SP> min<SP>−1</SP> was purged through the sample.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Cooling was accomplished with the liquid nitrogen cooling accessory (LNCA) which provides automatic and continuous programmed sample cooling down to −150° C.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The baseline was calibrated scanning the temperature domain of the experiments with an empty pan.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The temperature calibration was performed taking the onset of the endothermic melting peak at a heating rate of <IT>q</IT> = 10 K min<SP>−1</SP> of several calibration standards: n-decane (<IT>T</IT><SB>fus</SB> = 243.75 K), n-octadecane (<IT>T</IT><SB>fus</SB> = 301.77 K), hexatriacontane (<IT>T</IT><SB>fus</SB> = 347.30 K), indium (<IT>T</IT><SB>fus</SB> = 430.61 K) and tin (<IT>T</IT><SB>fus</SB> = 506.03 K).</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The organic standards were high purity Fluka products, while the metal standards were supplied by TA Instruments Inc. The correction of the temperature for different heating rates was performed on the basis of results obtained with indium.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The onset temperature of the melting peak of indium, (<IT>T</IT><SB>on</SB>)<SB>fus</SB>, was obtained at several heating rates, <IT>q</IT><SB>h</SB>, and the obtained values were fitted to a third order polynomial, (<IT>T</IT><SB>on</SB>)<SB>fus</SB> = <IT>a</IT> × <IT>q</IT>3h + <IT>b</IT> × <IT>q</IT>2h + <IT>c</IT> × <IT>q</IT><SB>h</SB> + <IT>d</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The temperature correction for each heating rate allows the extrapolation to the melting of indium at infinitely slow rate conditions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this context, the correction for each heating rate, (Δ<IT>T</IT>)<SB>qh</SB> = <IT>a</IT> × <IT>q</IT>3h + <IT>b</IT> × <IT>q</IT>2h + <IT>c</IT> × <IT>q</IT><SB>h</SB>, was subtracted from the experimental values in order to correct the data for the effect of the heating rate on the temperature of the DSC signals.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The enthalpy was also calibrated using indium (melting enthalpy Δ<SB>fus</SB><IT>H</IT> = 28.71 J g<SP>−1</SP>).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thermally Stimulated Depolarisation Current (TSDC) experiments were carried out with a TSC/RMA spectrometer (TherMold, Stamford, CT, USA) covering the range from −170 to +400 °C.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In order to analyse specific regions of the TSDC spectrum, different methods of polarising the sample can be used, namely the so-called TSDC global experiment and the Thermal Sampling (TS) experiment (often called thermal windowing or cleaning, or partial polarisation).</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The TS method, where the polarising field is applied in a narrow temperature interval, enables one to resolve a global peak into its individual relaxation modes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The physical background of the TSDC technique is presented elsewhere.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13 cit14">13,14</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The basic description of the TSDC experiment, and the discussion of the nature of the information it provides, is presented in detail in recent publications<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15 cit16">15,16</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Results and discussion</HEADER><P><s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">As underlined before, an important feature of the thermal behaviour of salol is that the liquid can be cooled down well below the melting temperature without crystallizing.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">This can be the case even for cooling rates as low as 1 K min<SP>−1</SP>, and the supercooling can be as deep as 80° below <IT>T</IT><SB>fus</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is to be underlined that nucleation and crystal growth are somewhat probabilistic events, so that our statements have in this context a considerable statistical or probabilistic signification.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of the behaviour of liquid salol upon cooling, that means that the crystallisation on cooling from the isotropic melt is a relatively infrequent occurrence and that, in most cases, the metastable liquid presents a high stability, enabling an easy handling.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">As will be seen later, crystalline phenyl salicylate presents two polymorphic forms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">One of them has an onset melting temperature at (<IT>T</IT><SB>fus</SB>)<SB>on</SB> = 30° C independent of the heating rate, and a temperature of maximum intensity slightly dependent on the heating rate (<IT>T</IT><SB>fus</SB>)<SB>max</SB> = ∼32° C.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The melting enthalpy of this polymorph was found to be approximately Δ<SB>fus</SB><IT>H</IT> = ∼16.5 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The other polymorph has an onset melting temperature at (<IT>T</IT><SB>fus</SB>)<SB>on</SB> = 41° C which is also independent of the heating rate, and a temperature of maximum intensity slightly dependent on the heating rate (<IT>T</IT><SB>fus</SB>)<SB>max</SB> = ∼43° C.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The melting enthalpy of this polymorph was found to be Δ<SB>fus</SB><IT>H</IT> = 18.6 ± 0.2 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>, in good agreement with the value of 19.2 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> reported in the literature.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF></annotationART></s></P><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>The glass transition</HEADER><P><s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The glass transition temperature was found to be <IT>T</IT><SB>g</SB> = 221 K = −52° C at 10 K min<SP>−1</SP> (onset temperature of the DSC glass transition signal), and the heat capacity jump at the glass transition is Δ<IT>C</IT><SB><IT>p</IT></SB>(<IT>T</IT><SB>g</SB>) = (111 ± 2) J K<SP>−1</SP> mol<SP>−1</SP>, in excellent agreement with the literature values.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The influence of the heating rate on the onset temperature, <IT>T</IT><SB>on</SB>, of the DSC glass transition signal was used to evaluate the activation energy at the glass transition temperature, and the fragility index of this glass-former.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17 cit18">17,18</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The obtained results, after correction of the temperature axis for the different heating rates, are plotted in Fig. 2.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The slope of the regression straight-line is −30.3 (with a confidence interval of ±0.8).</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">From this slope, the value of 252 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> was obtained for the activation energy of the structural relaxation, leading to the value of <IT>m</IT> = 60 for the fragility index of salol, that confirms the fragile character of the compound.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is to be reported that this value is not very far from the value <IT>m</IT> = 63 obtained by Dielectric Relaxation Spectroscopy<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19">19</REF> and from <IT>m</IT> = 68 obtained by Modulated Temperature Differential Scanning Calorimetry,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF> but it is significantly lower than <IT>m</IT> = 76 obtained by Thermally Stimulated Depolarisation Currents,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF> and from the fictive temperatures of differently quenched glasses obtained by DSC.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Given the scattering of these values, we decided to repeat the determination of the fragility index of salol using the technique of Thermally Stimulated Depolarisation Currents (TSDC).</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The sample we used now was from the same batch that was used for DSC measurements, previously purified by sublimation as described in the Experimental.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">From these new TSDC results, that were treated according to the procedures described elsewhere,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF> the value of 255 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> was obtained for the activation energy of the structural relaxation, which corresponds to a value <IT>m</IT> = 61 for the fragility index of salol.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Nucleation and crystallization</HEADER><P><s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Nucleation is believed to be the first step of the crystallization process.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is a stochastic process that depends on a large number of factors, namely size of the sample, type of cell or container used, cooling or heating rate, presence of impurities, <IT>etc</IT>… According to Oguni <IT>et al.</IT>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF> the homogeneous nucleation takes place in many cases above but near <IT>T</IT><SB>g</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac20" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is so because the development of structured clusters of molecules is enhanced as the temperature decreases, and because below <IT>T</IT><SB>g</SB> the motional rearrangement of molecules becomes sluggish, so that the nucleation process should be kinetically reduced.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac21" novelty="None" advantage="None">Heterogeneous nucleation, on the other hand, depends on many factors and can occur in a wide temperature domain.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to characterize, as precisely as possible, the conditions for nucleation in salol, we carried out a series of successive experiments described as follows: 1—the sample melted at 60° C is cooled down at ∼25 K min<SP>−1</SP> to a temperature <IT>T</IT><SB>0</SB>; 2—the sample is heated at constant rate (10 K min<SP>−1</SP>) from <IT>T</IT><SB>0</SB> up to 60° C.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The temperature <IT>T</IT><SB>0</SB> varied from experiment to experiment, from −65° C (well below the glass transition temperature) up to +5° C.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">In all the experiments cold crystallization was observed, indicating that nucleation is not restricted to a narrow temperature interval in the vicinity of the glass transition temperature, but that it takes place in a wide temperature interval above <IT>T</IT><SB>g</SB>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 3 shows the result of different DSC experiments where the sample was heated up from the glassy state at <IT>T</IT> = −90° C up to above the melting temperature, at different heating rates.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Prior to each experiment the sample was vitrified by cooling from the melt (<IT>T</IT> = 60° C) down to <IT>T</IT> = −90° C.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results of these experiments show three essential features: 1—the glass transition signal at <IT>T</IT><SB>g</SB> ≅ −52° C (not shown in Fig. 3); 2—an exothermic signal that corresponds to the cold crystallization (crystallization on heating) and is observed in the temperature interval between <IT>T</IT> = −25° C and the melting peak; 3—and the endothermic melting peak at <IT>T</IT><SB>fus</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">It can be observed that the exothermic signal of the cold crystallization is strongly sensitive, in shape as well as in position, to changes in the heating rate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In fact, for low heating rates the exothermic peak is relatively narrow and well separated from the melting peak.</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The onset temperature of the crystallization process (that we identify with the onset of the exothermic signal at the lowest heating rate of 1 K min<SP>−1</SP>) is (<IT>T</IT><SB>cr</SB>)<SB>on</SB> = −25° C.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast, for higher heating rates, the position of the exothermic signal shifts to higher temperatures and eventually interferes with the melting peak.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Another important conclusion that we can draw from the results shown in Fig. 3 is that, for low heating rates (lower than 6 K min<SP>−1</SP>), the cold crystallization leads to the most stable polymorph, that melts at <IT>T</IT><SB>fus</SB> = 42° C, while for high heating rates (higher than 9 K min<SP>−1</SP>), the cold crystallization tends to form the polymorph that melts at <IT>T</IT><SB>fus</SB> = 32° C.</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac22" novelty="None" advantage="None">The powder X-ray diffraction patterns of the most stable crystalline form of salol have been reported.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac23" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, it was shown that those patterns are identical for the crystal formed by annealing the metastable liquid at 300 K, and for the crystal formed from a long annealing (5 days) at 220 K (very slightly above <IT>T</IT><SB>g</SB>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the latter probably arises from an homogeneous nucleation process,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF> this finding, together with the results shown in Fig. 3 for the lowest heating rates, suggest that the crystallization of the most stable polymorph of salol is initiated by a relatively slow homogeneous nucleation taking place at low temperatures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note also in Fig. 3 that, for intermediate heating rates, a signal is often observed between the exothermic crystallization peak and the endothermic melting peak, as shown on the thermogram at 7 K min<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The signal, that presents an endothermic part followed by an exothermic one, corresponds to the interconversion between the two polymorphs: the lower temperature polymorph crystallized first, begins to melt at 32° C and, as it melts, the stable polymorph crystallizes to melt later at 42° C.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The DSC technique thus shows that the polymorph that melts at <IT>T</IT><SB>fus</SB> = 32° C is unstable, which makes the X-ray analysis of its crystalline structure difficult.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is necessary to emphasize that the behaviour depicted in Fig. 3, and described before, is not always strictly observed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">As pointed out before, nucleation and crystal growth are somewhat probabilistic events, and the consequence is that the experiments are not entirely reproducible.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">For example, we observed that, if the sample crystallizes on cooling, the crystal formed is always the stable form that melts at <IT>T</IT><SB>fus</SB> = 42° C.</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Moreover, if a very tiny portion of the sample crystallizes on cooling, the nucleation and crystal growth processes, that take place in a subsequent heating ramp, will lead also to the stable form, independently of the heating rate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">An important requirement for the behaviour shown in Fig. 3 to be observed is that no crystallization takes place in the process of cooling from the melt that precedes the linear heating ramp.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Temperature dependence of the kinetics of cold crystallization</HEADER><P><s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac24" novelty="None" advantage="None">It was shown before that for low heating rates the onset of the cold crystallization is at ∼−20° C.</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the following we will use the TSDC technique in order to evaluate the stability of the metastable supercooled liquid phase, and to qualitatively analyse the temperature dependence of the rate of the cold crystallization.</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">The TSDC glass transition peak will be used as a probe to quantitatively detect the glassy phase present in the sample.</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 4 shows the results of two TSDC experiments.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp13" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the first one, the sample of salol was cooled quickly from the liquid (50° C) down to the polarisation temperature <IT>T</IT><SB>P</SB> = −57° C, and the experiment was then carried out.</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The final temperature of the linear depolarisation ramp was <IT>T</IT><SB>f</SB> = 38° C, and the heating rate was <IT>q</IT> = 4 K min<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The result of this experiment shows two peaks.</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The first, which appears in the glass transition region, is a component of the glass transition relaxation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The second one shows a maximum intensity at ∼0–5° C.</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Given the big difference between the temperature location of this peak and the polarisation temperature (<IT>T</IT><SB>P</SB> = −57° C), it is not conceivable that it arises from a dipolar polarisation activated by the electric field.</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">This peak at ∼0–5° C is a consequence of a structural modification which occurred in the sample during the constant rate heating process, and that can be ascribed to the crystallisation of salol from the supercooled liquid state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that this peak occurs precisely in the temperature region where the cold crystallisation occurs, beginning close to a temperature of ∼−25° C, in agreement with the DSC results reported previously.</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The second experiment, whose result is shown as a flat dashed line in Fig. 4, was performed immediately after the first: the sample was cooled quickly directly from the final temperature of the heating ramp of the first experiment (<IT>T</IT><SB>f</SB> = 38° C) down to the same polarisation temperature, and it was submitted to the same TS experiment.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The disappearance of the glass transition peak indicates that, at the end of the first experiment, the sample is no more in the glassy state, reinforcing the idea that the peak at 0–5° C was due to cold crystallization.</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Moreover, the absence of any peak in the 0–5° C region in the second heating ramp indicates that the sample is fully crystallized.</annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">The TSDC and DSC data are thus in total agreement.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to obtain more detailed information on the kinetics of this transformation, we performed a series of TSDC global experiments, where the final temperature of the heating ramp, <IT>T</IT><SB>f</SB>, varied from series to series.</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac25" novelty="None" advantage="None">Doing so, the sample was allowed to anneal, for a given period of time, at temperatures in the vicinity of <IT>T</IT><SB>f</SB>, where the transformation of the supercooled liquid into the crystal is more or less effective.</annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 5 shows the results of such a series of global experiments where <IT>T</IT><SB>f</SB> = −21° C.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp15" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the first experiment of the series (higher peak in Fig. 5) the sample was cooled quickly from the liquid state (50° C) down to the polarisation temperature (<IT>T</IT><SB>P</SB> = −57° C), in order to prepare the sample in the glassy state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp16" novelty="None" advantage="None">In all the subsequent experiments, the sample was cooled down to the polarisation temperature from the final temperature of the linear heating ramp of the previous TSDC experiment (<IT>T</IT><SB>f</SB> = −21° C, as reported before, for the experiments shown in Fig. 5).</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">The intensity (or the area) of the glass transition peak probes the quantity of glassy phase present in the sample, so that the decrease of the intensity of the TS peaks observed in Fig. 5 from experiment to experiment is the signature of the progressive crystallisation of salol.</annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 6 shows how the intensity of the TSDC peaks evolves from experiment to experiment, in a different series of experiments with different <IT>T</IT><SB>f</SB>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">It can be concluded from Fig. 6 that the crystallisation from the supercooled liquid is slow at −25° C (in perfect agreement with the DSC results), and that the rate of crystallisation increases with increasing temperature, so that it becomes particularly fast for temperatures higher than −17° C.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results reported in this section illustrate how the TSDC technique can be used in order to detect phase transformations, and to follow their time evolution as a function of temperature, thus providing useful information regarding the respective phase diagrams and the kinetics of phase transformations.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>The β-relaxation of salol</HEADER><P><s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac26" novelty="None" advantage="None">According to the so-called heterogeneous model, a glass and a supercooled liquid are viewed as composed of structured clusters that sink in non-structured or amorphous regions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the context of this model, the α-relaxation is considered to originate from collective motions of the molecules within the structured clusters, while the β-process would arise from local motions in the gap between clusters.</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the β-relaxation time is much shorter than the α-relaxation time near the glass transition temperature, the β-relaxation process is believed to assist the nucleation process.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">One of the techniques most widely used to study the mobility associated with the α and β-processes is Dielectric Relaxation Spectroscopy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="No">However, the use of this experimental technique for the analysis and characterization of the β-process is difficult in the case of salol, given that this process is disguised under the main α-relaxation, and appears as a so-called excess wing in the high frequency side of the dielectric α-peak.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">We recently showed that, in such cases, TSDC appears as an excellent technique to resolve both α and β-relaxational processes, and to enable a clear identification and characterization of the β-rearrangement.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 7 shows the result of a series of TSDC experiments on the secondary β-relaxation of salol.</annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">The peaks in the right-hand side, showing a strongly increasing intensity, indicate the coalescence between α and β motional processes, while the other peaks correspond to molecular motions of the β-process.</annotationART></s> <s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 8 shows the representation of the activation enthalpy, Δ<IT>H</IT><SP>≠</SP>, associated with these TSDC peaks as a function of the respective temperature location (temperature of maximum intensity, <IT>T</IT><SB>m</SB>).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The line shown in Fig. 8 is the so-called zero entropy line.</annotationART></s> <s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">It can be seen that a small number of points in the higher temperature side clearly deviate from the zero entropy line: they correspond to the higher intensity peaks in Fig. 7 and indicate the mergence of the α and β-motions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the other hand, most of the points in the low temperature side show very small deviations from the zero entropy line, indicating that they correspond to localized and non-cooperative molecular motions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">From the data included in Figs. 7 and 8 we can conclude that the TSDC technique provides very clear results on the β-relaxation of salol, allowing a very precise characterisation of the molecular mobility associated with it.</annotationART></s> <s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The β-relaxation shows a narrow distribution in activation energy with a mean value around <IT>E</IT><SB>a</SB> = 46 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The dynamics of this motional process is such that the mean characteristic time at the glass transition temperature is <IT>τ</IT><SB>β</SB>(<IT>T</IT><SB>g</SB>) ≅ 1.6 × 10<SP>−2</SP> s.</annotationART></s> <s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">We want to note that this β-mobility of salol is not present in the TSDC spectrum of the crystallized sample, suggesting that this mobility is a feature of the glassy state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac27" novelty="None" advantage="None">Let us finally note that the results in Fig. 7 were obtained using standard vitrification conditions (cooling rates not higher than −5 to −20 K min<SP>−1</SP>), without need for fast quenching of the liquid<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25">25</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Summary and conclusions</HEADER><P><s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa8" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have investigated phenyl-2-hydroxybenzoate (salol) from the point of view of the molecular mobility, in relation with the problem of phase transformations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The study of the glass transition by DSC (heating rate dependence of the onset temperature of the glass transition signal) provided the value of 252 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> for the activation energy of the structural relaxation, leading to the value of <IT>m</IT> = 60 for the fragility index of salol, that confirms the fragile character of the compound.</annotationART></s> <s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The TSDC results, obtained with the same sample batch used for DSC experiments, lead to similar values, suggesting that those previously reported in the literature are somewhat overestimated.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Two polymorphs of salol were identified.</annotationART></s> <s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">One of them has a melting temperature at (<IT>T</IT><SB>fus</SB>)<SB>max</SB> = ∼32° C and a melting enthalpy of approximately Δ<SB>fus</SB><IT>H</IT> = ∼16.5 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The other polymorph, the most stable, melts at (<IT>T</IT><SB>fus</SB>)<SB>max</SB> = ∼43° C and shows a melting enthalpy of Δ<SB>fus</SB><IT>H</IT> = 18.6 ± 0.2 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">It was demonstrated that the less stable polymorph can be obtained by cold crystallization from a fully amorphous sample in a linear heating ramp with rate higher than ∼9 K min<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">It was shown how the cold crystallization process can be monitored using the dielectric technique of TSDC.</annotationART></s> <s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The TSDC results confirmed those obtained by DSC, and provided qualitative information about the temperature dependence of the cold crystallization kinetics.</annotationART></s> <s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Finally, TSDC was used to study the β-relaxation of salol, that is believed to assist the occurrence of the nucleation process.</annotationART></s> <s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">It was shown that this β-process is detected by TSDC in a very clear way, allowing a very precise characterisation of this mobility.</annotationART></s> <s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The activation energy is narrowly distributed, with a mean value around <IT>E</IT><SB>a</SB> = 46 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="143"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The mean characteristic time at the glass transition temperature was found to be of the order of <IT>τ</IT><SB>β</SB>(<IT>T</IT><SB>g</SB>) ≅ 10<SP>−2</SP> s.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
