<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b314333n" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Phase diagram for an attractive square-well plus a linear tail potential within the van der Waals-like theory</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">The phase equilibrium behavior of a typical colloidal dispersion by the van der Waals-like theory was studied.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this theory, the colloid–colloid potential is split into two parts: a repulsive part modeled by the hard-core potential and an attractive part modeled by the square-well potential corrected by a linear tail.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The theory is numerically elegant since the colloidal free energy is analytic and, physically, the model can be used to study the role played by the <IT>strength</IT> and <IT>range</IT> of interactions on the formation of coexisting phases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The effect of the strength of the interaction can be accounted for by varying the width of the square-well potential (simulated by <IT>γ</IT> parameter) while the range of the interaction—by changing the “slope” of the linear potential (simulated by <IT>λ</IT> parameter).</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this work, we consider three separate cases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="New" advantage="None">First, we fixed the threshold values <IT>γ</IT><SB>th</SB>, being <IT>γ</IT>LLth = 0.221 for liquid–liquid and <IT>γ</IT>SSth = 0.0329 for solid–solid, and increased <IT>λ</IT> to examine the appearance of the liquid–liquid and solid–solid coexistence curves which were both calculated with respect to their liquid–solid counterparts.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="New" advantage="None">Second, we fixed the threshold values <IT>λ</IT><SB>th</SB>, being <IT>λ</IT>LLth = 0.325 for liquid–liquid and <IT>λ</IT>SSth = 0.0456 for solid–solid, and increased <IT>γ</IT> (keeping the <IT>λ</IT>-slope unchanged) to bring in the strength of the interaction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In these two cases, the calculations showed that a switching on of <IT>λ</IT> or <IT>γ</IT> has the consequence of inducing stable liquid–liquid or metastable solid–solid coexisting phases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="New" advantage="None">Finally, we maintained a given <IT>γ</IT> plus <IT>λ</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Here the calculated liquid–liquid and solid–solid phase diagrams can be analyzed in finer details to exhibit the combined influences of the strength and range of interactions.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="1">Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">A long-standing problem in modern condensed matter physics is the understanding of the mechanism of phase separation in both simple and complex liquids.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Recently, several novel experiments were reported to have observed the liquid–liquid phase separation in monatomic liquids,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2">1,2</REF> molecular liquids<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF> as well as in complex liquids.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit5 cit6">4–6</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Stimulated by these laboratory findings, a number of computer-simulation experiments were performed<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7 cit8 cit9 cit10">7–10</REF> and claimed to have successfully reproduced or captured the essential characteristics of some of the above liquid–liquid phase transitions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Perhaps more interesting is that these simulation studies predict in addition an isostructural solid–solid transition for a few simple parametric “model” systems.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10 cit11 cit12">10–12</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Implicit in all of these empirical endeavors is the quest for understanding the link between the role of the <IT>range</IT> and <IT>strength</IT> (in particular, the attractive nature) of inter-particle interactions and the possible mechanisms underlying these complicated phenomena.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13 cit14 cit15">13–15</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this respect, recent experimental and computer simulation results have had a great impact on the theoretical development of liquid–liquid, liquid–solid and solid–solid phase equilibria.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">One of the earlier quantitative works of this kind was that by Victor and Hansen<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF> who, based on the idea of the Week, Chandler and Andersen,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF> worked out a first-order thermodynamic perturbation theory for a charge-stabilized colloidal dispersion induced at high salt concentrations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The theory emphasizes the attraction between charged colloids as arising from the long range van der Waals type and predicts a liquid–liquid phase transition showing features quite similar to those observed by Kotera <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF>. for the polystyrene latex particles and by Hachisu for the gold sol system.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19">19</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The mechanism for the occurrence of the phase transition has been attributed to the existence of a second minimum in the colloid–colloid potential, a characteristic feature simulated in their theoretical studies by an excess salt condition.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Following a somewhat different perturbation theory of Gast <IT>et al.</IT>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF> Kaldasch <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF>. subsequently extended the work of Victor and Hansen<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF> to second order and included in the phase diagram calculations the liquid–liquid phase transition boundary determined with respect to the liquid–solid coexistence curves.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">It should be mentioned moreover that the same first-order theory as Victor and Hansen has been reported also by Lai <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF>. who analyzed and compared in some details the phase separation results between the well-known DLVO model<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF> and a realistic model previously proposed by Belloni.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">A more quantitative second-order thermodynamic perturbation has very recently been reported by Lai and Wu.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25">25</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">This latter work made a detailed comparison of the theory with flocculation scenario observed in charged colloids.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Parallel to these realistic calculations but emerging around 1994 are two theoretical approaches to the study of phase separation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The first approach attempts to understand the phase separation employing the well-known classical density functional theory.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this method, the free energy functional was constructed in terms of the one and two particle density distribution functions, both for the liquid and solid counterparts.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">With the recent development of the inhomogeneous density functional theory for the hard-sphere system in solid state and in conjunction with the liquid state theory already available in the literature, several simple model systems have been investigated.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26 cit27 cit28 cit29">26–29</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">These studies confirm some of the computer-simulation findings and predict generally the occurrence of the isostructural solid–solid phase transition.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30">30</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">On theoretical basis, this approach is rigorous.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The second approach which relies more on simple models follows closely the original ideas of van der Waals to account for the vapor–liquid transition.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Baus and coworkers<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit31">31</REF> are the early main contributors to this approach.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit33">33</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this theory, directed to charged colloidal suspension, the total potential energy of particles is assumed to be composed of an idealized hard-sphere repulsion to which a model attractive part is added.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Gibbs–Bogoliubov inequality is then employed to construct the Helmholtz free energy in terms of a reference system free energy, and a correction consisting of a difference in potential energies of the model and reference systems, with the distribution function of the reference system taken to account for the thermal ensemble average.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">By taking the hard spheres as reference system, and in conjunction with the cell model for liquid and an analogue for solid, these authors succeeded in deriving theoretically self-consistent liquid and solid free-energy expressions in terms of the attractive part of the potential.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Several attractive model potentials were investigated and most show liquid–liquid as well as solid–solid phase transitions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">In view of the mathematical simplicity and the transparency of the underlying theory, we have adopted in the present study of phase separation a model system that has much relevance to real physical systems.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The calculation is both a supplement to the works of Baus and coworkers and an extension of our recent communication.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit32">32</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The model system studied in this paper is the attractive square-well plus a linear tail potential schematically shown in Fig. 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The choice for this potential is twofold.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">First, this potential can be compared unambiguously with the widely studied square-well potential (<IT>λ</IT> = 0 in Fig. 1) to account for the varied strength of the interaction, and by increasing <IT>λ</IT>, it can be used to examine the range of the interaction on the phase transition.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Most importantly, the present model potential mimics closely the embellished form of the colloid–colloid potential function customarily employed in more complicated thermodynamic perturbation theory seeking for an analytical hard sphere reference system (see Fig. 1 in each of <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16 cit22">refs. 16 and 22</REF>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Second, thermodynamic quantities for this potential can be solved also in analytical forms thus permitting an accurate evaluation of the phase diagrams.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac20" novelty="None" advantage="None">The paper is therefore organized as follows.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac20" novelty="None" advantage="None">In Section 2, we describe the van der Waals theory and give the expressions for the thermodynamic functions needed in the phase diagram calculation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac20" novelty="None" advantage="None">Then, in Section 3 we present our numerical results for the three cases showing the role played by <IT>γ</IT> and <IT>λ</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac20" novelty="None" advantage="None">A conclusion that summarizes our present work is given in Section 4.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2">Theory</HEADER><P><s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac21" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this section, main ideas of the van der Waals theory recently advanced by Baus <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit31">31</REF>. were summarized.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac22" novelty="None" advantage="None">We present details of our derived expressions for the attractive square-well plus a linear tail potential.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac22" novelty="None" advantage="None">These equations will be used in the following numerical calculations.</annotationART></s></P><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.1">Van der Waals theory: Gibbs–Bogoliubov inequality</HEADER><P><s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The theoretical framework of the van der Waals theory of Baus <IT>et al.</IT> begins with the well-known Gibbs–Bogoliubov inequality which reads as follows.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Consider a thermodynamic state at temperature <IT>T</IT> and density <IT>ρ</IT> for a physical system whose Helmholtz free energy and Hamiltonian are denoted by <IT>F</IT><SB>t</SB> and <B><IT>H</IT></B><SB>t</SB>, where the subscript t refers to a true system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Suppose at the same <IT>T</IT> and <IT>ρ</IT>, we can find a reference system (symbolized by a subscript <IT>r</IT>) whose <IT>F</IT><SB>r</SB>, <B><IT>H</IT></B><SB>r</SB>, and related quantities such as the structure, thermodynamic functions, <IT>etc.</IT> are known, the inequality gives <IT>F</IT><SB>t</SB> ≤ <IT>F</IT><SB>r</SB> + 〈<B><IT>H</IT></B><SB>t</SB> − <B><IT>H</IT></B><SB>r</SB>〉<SB>r</SB>which states that the true <IT>F</IT><SB>t</SB> of a physical system is bounded above by a reference <IT>F</IT><SB>r</SB> plus a correction term consisting of the difference in Hamiltonians of the true and reference systems.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The 〈…〉<SB>r</SB> in eqn. (1) means an ensemble average taken over the distribution function of the reference system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that the perturbation in eqn. (1) is just the difference in potential energies <IT>V</IT><SB>t</SB> and <IT>V</IT><SB>r</SB> of the true and reference systems, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Next, we write <IT>V</IT><SB>t</SB> = <IT>V</IT>tR + <IT>V</IT>tA splitting the pair potential into a repulsive part and an attractive part and similarly for the reference system, namely, <IT>V</IT>rR and <IT>V</IT>rA.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In accord with the van der Waals theory, we take the reference system to be a system of hard spheres, <IT>V</IT>rR → <IT>V</IT>rHS, which thus implies <IT>V</IT>rA = 0 and approximate the <IT>V</IT>tR to be hard-sphere-like repulsive (R → HS) also.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Setting <IT>V</IT>tR → <IT>V</IT>tHS = <IT>V</IT>rHS, simplifies eqn. (1) to where <IT>ρ</IT><SB>HS</SB>(<B><IT>r</IT></B>) is the one-particle density associated with the reference system <IT>V</IT>rHS.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that in arriving at eqn. (2), we have neglected all two-particle correlations and set the lowest upper bound as a reasonable estimate.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit34">34</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The <IT>F</IT><SB>HS</SB> in eqn. (2) is thus the hard sphere free energy which we will utilize below separately for the liquid and solid phases.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.2">Helmholtz free energies of a liquid and a solid</HEADER><P><s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac23" novelty="None" advantage="None">To emphasize the theoretical consistency in the construction of free energies for the liquid and solid, which is essential for an accurate calculation of the phase diagram, we shall present these equations in parallel, stressing the analogy between them.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since eqn. (2) involves only the attraction, it is convenient to write <IT>V</IT>tA(r) = −<IT>εϕ</IT><SB>A</SB>(r) where <IT>ε</IT> ≥ 0 is an energy parameter measuring the <IT>strength</IT> of attraction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Next, we define where the reduced distance <IT>x</IT> = <IT>r</IT>/<IT>σ</IT>, <IT>σ</IT> being the hard sphere diameter related to the volume fraction <IT>η</IT> by <IT>σ</IT> = (6<IT>η</IT>/π<IT>ρ</IT>)<SP>1/3</SP> and <IT>φ</IT>(<IT>x</IT>) ≥ 0 describing the <IT>range</IT> of interaction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">For a liquid (solid) which is homogeneous (inhomogeneous), the one-particle density function is <IT>ρ</IT> → <IT>ρ</IT><SB>HS</SB>(<B><IT>r</IT></B>) = <IT></IT>, <IT></IT> = <IT>N</IT>/<IT>V</IT> being the uniform number density for the liquid (solid).</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that <IT>ρ</IT><SB>HS</SB>(<B><IT>r</IT></B>) = ∑<IT>N</IT><IT>i</IT> = 1<IT>ψ</IT>(<B><IT>r</IT></B> − <B><IT>R</IT></B><SB><IT>i</IT></SB>) where <IT>ψ</IT>(<B><IT>r</IT></B> − <B><IT>R</IT></B><SB><IT>i</IT></SB>), <B><IT>R</IT></B><SB><IT>i</IT></SB> being Bravais lattice sites in a perfect crystal, is the density profile satisfying the normalized condition ∫d<B><IT>r</IT></B><IT>ψ</IT>(<B><IT>r</IT></B>) = 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Subject to these choices, Δ<IT>F</IT> in eqn. (2) can be written in reduced energy units as Similarly, the hard-sphere reduced free energy <IT>f</IT><SB>HS</SB> = <IT>F</IT><SB>HS</SB>/(<IT>N</IT><IT>ε</IT>) can be cast in the form within the spirit of the free-volume approximation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Here <IT>δ</IT> = <IT></IT>/<IT>ρ</IT><SB>0</SB> (<IT>ρ</IT>/<IT>ρ</IT><SB>cp</SB>) for liquid (solid), <IT>T</IT>* = <IT>k</IT><SB>B</SB><IT>T</IT>/<IT>ε</IT> is the reduced temperature, <IT>ρ</IT><SB>0</SB> (<IT>ρ</IT><SB>cp</SB> = √2/<IT>σ</IT><SP>3</SP>) is the maximum density of liquid (solid at compact crystal structure) for which a liquid (solid) is stable and <IT>Λ</IT> = <IT>h</IT>/(2π<IT>mk</IT><SB>B</SB><IT>T</IT>)<SP>1/2</SP> is the thermal de Broglie wavelength of an hard sphere.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod12" novelty="None" advantage="None">We should stress at this point that, to ensure theoretical consistency in the construction of the free energy <IT>f</IT> = <IT>f</IT><SB>HS</SB> + Δ<IT>f</IT>, the cell model has been applied on ‘equal footing’ to both the liquid and solid phases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod13" novelty="None" advantage="None">For example, we introduce, as is done in eqn. (5), the free volume (free edge) parameter <IT>α</IT> which is the fraction of the total volume <IT>V</IT> that is freely available to hard spheres in a liquid (solid) phase as In this work, we have set <IT>ρ</IT><SB>0</SB> = (6<IT>η</IT><SB>0</SB>/π<IT>σ</IT><SP>3</SP>)<SP>1/3</SP> with an estimated <IT>η</IT><SB>0</SB> following the quantitative analysis of Baus <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit31">31</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Also, for the case of solid, <IT>δ</IT> = 1/<IT>x</IT>31, <IT>x</IT><SB>1</SB> = <IT>r</IT><SB>1</SB>/<IT>σ</IT> being the reduced nearest-neighbor distance for a given crystal structure.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod14" novelty="None" advantage="None">We are now in a position to present our derived expressions for the linear attractive potential shown schematically in Fig. 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod15" novelty="None" advantage="None">First, <IT>Γ</IT> for the liquid phase in eqn. (4) can be written as which reduces to the <IT>Γ</IT> of square-well and linear potentials for <IT>λ</IT> = 0 and <IT>γ</IT> = 0, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod16" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the solid phase, we have where in which In eqn. (10), <IT>n</IT><SB>1</SB> is the number of nearest neighbors and <IT>ζσ</IT><SP>2</SP> is the inverse width of the Gaussian density profile <IT>G</IT>(<IT>a</IT>,<IT>x</IT>) = ∫<IT>x</IT>0d<IT>t</IT><SP><IT>a</IT>−1</SP><IT>e</IT><SP>−<IT>t</IT></SP> is the incomplete gamma function and erf(<IT>x</IT>) = (2/√π)∫<IT>x</IT>0d<IT>t</IT><IT>e</IT><SP>−<IT>t</IT><SP>2</SP></SP> is the error function.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Given eqns. (5), (8) and (9) for <IT>f</IT>, it is straightforward to calculate the pressure <IT>p</IT> = <IT>ερ</IT><SP>2</SP>(∂<IT>f</IT>/∂<IT>ρ</IT>) and chemical potential <IT>μ</IT> = <IT>ε</IT>(∂/∂<IT>ρ</IT>)(<IT>ρf</IT>) from which the corresponding critical points (<IT>η</IT><SB>c</SB>,<IT>T</IT>*c) can be determined by ∂<IT>p</IT>(<IT>ρ</IT><SB>c</SB>,<IT>T</IT>*c)/∂<IT>ρ</IT> = 0 and ∂<SP>2</SP><IT>p</IT>(<IT>ρ</IT><SB>c</SB>,<IT>T</IT>*<SB>c</SB>)/∂<IT>ρ</IT><SP>2</SP> = 0 yielding the critical parameters for the liquid–liquid transition.</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod17" novelty="None" advantage="None">These predictions for the critical points are reminiscent of the celebrated van der Waals theory for the gas–liquid transition; the parameter <IT>Γ</IT> now plays the same role as the attraction parameter while <IT>η</IT><SB>0</SB> simulates the excluded volume factor (see, for example, eqn. (3.49) in .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit35">ref. 35</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod18" novelty="None" advantage="None">In fact one can write down the same van der Waals equation of state if the parameters <IT>a</IT> and <IT>b</IT> appearing in eqn. (3.49) of <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit35">ref. 35</REF> are replaced by <IT>ε</IT><IT>Γ</IT>/<IT>ρ</IT><SB>0</SB> and 1/<IT>ρ</IT><SB>0</SB>, respectively).</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac24" novelty="None" advantage="None">The critical points for the solid–solid phase transition, however, have to be determined numerically.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3">Numerical results and discussion</HEADER><P><s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="New" advantage="None">As pointed out above, the present van der Waals theory needs <IT>ρ</IT><SB>0</SB> and <IT>ρ</IT><SB>cp</SB> as sole input to the calculation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod19" novelty="None" advantage="None">For these estimates, we follow Coussaert and Baus<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit31">31</REF> fixing π<IT>σ</IT><SP>3</SP><IT>ρ</IT><SB>0</SB>/6 = 0.4952 and <IT>ρ</IT><SB>cp</SB> = √2/<IT>σ</IT><SP>3</SP>; these choices are based on: (a) the exact virial expansion of the hard-sphere free energy up to the second virial coefficient; and (b) the criterion of maximum density for a stable liquid or crystalline phase to exist.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the following we assume the face-centered cubic (fcc) crystalline structure for the solid phase.</annotationART></s></P><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.1">Liquid–liquid <IT>versus</IT> liquid–solid phase transitions: fixed <IT>λ</IT> or <IT>γ</IT></HEADER><P><s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="New" advantage="None">We have applied eqns. (5), (8) and (9) to study the occurrence of the liquid–liquid and solid–solid coexisting phases calculated first at their threshold values <IT>γ</IT>LLth = 0.221 and <IT>γ</IT>SSth = 0.0329, respectively.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit32">32</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">By increasing the <IT>range</IT> of the interaction <IT>λ</IT> from 0 (dashed curves), which corresponds to the threshold conditions for the square-well potential, to 0.01 (dotted curves) and then 0.05 (solid curves), we see from Fig. 2 that the stable liquid–liquid phases progressively evolve with the critical <IT>T</IT>*c increases from the threshold <IT>T</IT>*th = 0.481 to <IT>T</IT>*c = 0.495 and then to 0.549.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">These results are in reverse order for the solid–solid transition, shown in Fig. 3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Here, <IT>γ</IT>SSth = 0.0329 (and <IT>λ</IT> = 0) is the threshold value marking a stable solid–solid transition just about to appear.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">When <IT>λ</IT> is increased, which implies extending a wider range of the interaction, the coexistence of solid–solid phases becomes metastable with respect to their stable liquid–solid counterparts.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac25" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is interesting to compare these results with cases in which we fix the range of the interaction at the threshold values <IT>λ</IT>LLth = 0.325 and <IT>λ</IT>SSth = 0..0456<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit32">32</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="New" advantage="None">We again start with the threshold range of the interaction (the triangular potential, <IT>γ</IT> = 0) at which values the stable liquid–liquid and solid–solid branches are just about to develop.</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod20" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the liquid–liquid case, increasing <IT>γ</IT>, which corresponds to adding to the system the strength of the interaction but at the same time extending the range (since the “slope” <IT>λ</IT> is kept unchanged), favors the occurrence of a stable liquid–liquid.</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This trend differs from the solid–solid case where the metastable coexisting phases are induced due to weakening of the interaction between particles brought about by the extended range <IT>λ</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">These features are clearly seen in Figs. 4 and 5.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac26" novelty="None" advantage="None">We should comment further on the physical implication of the scenarios discussed above.</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Let us first depict in Fig. 6 the typical two-body colloid–colloid potential.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac26" novelty="None" advantage="None">In our previous thermodynamic perturbation theory, the two-body colloid–colloid potential is split into a repulsive and an attractive part.</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod21" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the repulsive interaction between colloidal particles is generally strong due to the huge amount of charge carried by the particles, the repulsive part of the potential is quite often modeled by a hard-sphere potential.</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod21" novelty="None" advantage="None">An effective hard-sphere diameter at <IT>x</IT> = S, denoted by the dotted curve, is substituted for the steep rising repulsion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod22" novelty="None" advantage="None">Next, the “plateau”, from S to the second minimum, and the tail are treated as an attractive perturbation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Apart from the tail, the structure of the perturbation closely resembles that shown in Fig. 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Now it is seen that the increase or decrease of the basin is a reflection of the softness of the repulsion; a softer repulsive part will yield a larger basin and hence a larger <IT>γ</IT>, and <IT>vice versa</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The behavior of the liquid–liquid transition as presented here is in qualitative agreement with the general trend obtained here, namely, an increase of <IT>γ</IT> enhances the occurrence of a stable liquid–liquid transition.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">As discussed in our preceding work,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25">25</REF> the mechanism is attributed to the appearance of a second minimum.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.2">Liquid–liquid <IT>versus</IT> liquid–solid phase transitions: fixed <IT>λ</IT> plus <IT>γ</IT></HEADER><P><s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod23" novelty="None" advantage="None">We turn to examining the phase diagrams for cases in which the strength and range of interactions are simultaneously operating but their sum is kept unchanged at a prescribed value <IT>ξ</IT> = <IT>λ</IT> + <IT>γ</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">To this end, we first recall Fig. 3 for the solid–solid threshold value <IT>γ</IT>SSth = 0.0329 that characterizes the square-well potential (<IT>λ</IT> = 0).</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In Fig. 7, we fix <IT>ξ</IT> = 0.0329 and consider the combination <IT>γ</IT> = 0.01 and <IT>λ</IT> = 0.0229.</annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod24" novelty="None" advantage="None">The situation describes an extremely narrow region with the same attractive strength of interaction and is corrected by a rapidly decaying linear tail.</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Compared with our recent work for the square-well potential (Fig. 3 in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit32">ref. 32</REF>) at <IT>γ</IT> = 0.01, there we see a stable lower density fcc solid coexisting with a stable higher density fcc solid; the solid–solid transition occurs at a <IT>lower</IT> critical temperature <IT>T</IT>*c.</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The extended range of the interaction <IT>λ</IT> ≠ 0 has resulted in lowering <IT>T</IT>*c for the appearance of stable solid–solid phases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the other hand, Fig. 5 shows that, at the same <IT>γ</IT> = 0.01 (dotted curves), when the range of the interaction is longer, <IT>i.e.</IT><IT>λ</IT> = 0.0456, the solid–solid separation is driven to metastable phases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">It thus implies that there exists for the given <IT>γ</IT> = 0.01 a threshold <IT>λ</IT><SB>th</SB> at which value the solid–solid transition is just about to occur.</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">By varying <IT>λ</IT> between 0.0229 and 0.0456, we find that this threshold value is <IT>λ</IT>SSth = 0.0346 for <IT>γ</IT> = 0.01.</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Similarly, we determine the threshold <IT>λ</IT>SSth = 0.0216 for <IT>γ</IT> = 0.02.</annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">These latter results are depicted in Fig. 8.</annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The set of threshold values <IT>γ</IT> and <IT>λ</IT>, together with those of the threshold values <IT>γ</IT>SSth and <IT>λ</IT>SSth for the square-well and linear potentials, respectively, define a phase boundary demarcating the metastable solid–solid transition from the stable solid–solid counterpart.</annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">This scenario is shown in Fig. 9.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4">Conclusion</HEADER><P><s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The classic theory of van der Waals previously applied to understanding the gas–liquid separation has been extended to study the phase diagrams of the liquid–liquid and solid–solid coexisting phases calculated with respect to the liquid–solid counterparts.</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">By appealing to the cell model approximation aimed at treating the liquid and the solid on an equal footing, we follow Baus <IT>et al.</IT> and construct theoretically the self-consistent Helmholtz free energies separately for a liquid and a solid.</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="New" advantage="None">Analytical expressions for the pressures and chemical potentials of the latter phases then permit a straightforward calculation of the coexistence curves.</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Employing this extended van der Waals theory, we investigate the square-well plus a linear tail attractive potential added to a repulsive hard-sphere system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac27" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our studies of the phase diagrams suggest the following:</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">(a) Given the threshold strength of interactions <IT>γ</IT>LLth and <IT>γ</IT>SSth, an increase in <IT>λ</IT> results in progressive development of the stable liquid–liquid phases whereas for the solid–solid coexisting phases, metastability results.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">(b) In analogy with (a), we fixed the threshold range of interactions <IT>λ</IT>LLth and <IT>λ</IT>SSth and increased the interaction strength, <IT>γ</IT>; the same trend is observed, namely, the stable liquid–liquid phases evolve progressively whereas for the solid–solid phases, metastability results.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">(c) The <IT>range</IT> of interaction, <IT>λ</IT>, plays a non-negligible role in lowering the critical <IT>T</IT>*c for the stable coexisting solid<IT>-</IT>solid phases.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
