<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b314172a" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Pressure perturbation calorimetic studies of the solvation properties and the thermal unfolding of staphylococcal nuclease</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">A rather new technique, pressure perturbation calorimetry (PPC), was applied to study volumetric and solvation properties of <IT>staphylococcal nuclease</IT> (Snase) in its native and unfolded state with high precision.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, the effects of various chaotropic and cosmotropic co-solvents on the solvation and unfolding behaviour of Snase was investigated in detail.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In PPC, the apparent coefficient of thermal expansion of the protein is deduced from the heat consumed or produced after small isothermal pressure jumps, which strongly depends on the interaction of the protein with the solvent at the protein–solvent interface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the native state, the protein shows a very strong thermal expansion of 1.0 × 10<SP>−3</SP> K−1 at 10 °C, which decreases steeply to 0.65 × 10<SP>−3</SP> K<SP>−1</SP> at 40 °C.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa3" novelty="None" advantage="None">This behaviour is discussed in terms of a continuous release of condensed water from the protein surface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Upon unfolding, the volume decreases by about 19 mL × mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Solutions of the cosmotropic and chaotropic compounds glycerol, sorbitol, K<SB>2</SB>SO<SB>4</SB> and urea, respectively, show characteristic deviations from the thermal expansion and volumetric properties of the pure buffer solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The solvent contribution to the apparent coefficient of thermal expansion of the protein, <IT>α</IT>, is enhanced considerably when the protein is immersed in a solvent known to be more structured than H<SB>2</SB>O (even the more structured D<SB>2</SB>O has a drastic effect) and nearly eliminated in a solvent in which “normal” water is largely absent (<IT>e.g.</IT>, in 1.5 M urea).</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Similarly to D<SB>2</SB>O, a continuous increase in solvation was observed with increase in glycerol or sorbitol content in the buffer, which leads to an increase in protein stability, as is verified by the increasing <IT>T</IT><SB>m</SB> and Δ<IT>H</IT> values obtained by microcalorimetric measurements (DSC).</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this regard, sorbitol is the more efficient agent.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reduction of Δ<IT>V</IT> in the presence of these stabilisers can in part be attributed to the formation of a partial unfolded state of the protein, in part it is due to the temperature dependence of Δ<IT>V</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The preferential binding of urea reduces the hydration level, also in the native state, causing the protein to approach a more disordered state at high urea concentration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The increase in Δ<IT>V</IT> and the decrease in Δ<IT>H</IT> with increasing urea concentration support these conclusions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">A stabilising effect, even though there is a reduction in solvation around the protein is observed for 0.5 M K<SB>2</SB>SO<SB>4</SB> as co-solvent.</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this case, surprisingly, Δ<IT>V</IT> is found to be positive which is an indication of the formation of a swollen, molten globule kind of unfolded state at the transition.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Finally, Δ<IT>V</IT> values for the temperature-induced unfolding are compared with corresponding data for the pressure-induced unfolding of Snase.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="1.">Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The in depth knowledge of various thermodynamical properties of proteins in solution has been drawing attention of many researchers, as these form the basis for understanding their physiological functions, but also their use in drug design and formulations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The stability of globular proteins depends on temperature,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2 cit3 cit4">1–4</REF> solvent properties,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6 cit7 cit8">5–8</REF> and its hydration capacity.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9 cit10">9,10</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Another important factor contributing to the stability of proteins is their relative affinity towards a particular reagent (in the present context, a co-solvent) in comparison to water or buffer solution.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The use of co-solvents such as glycerol and sucrose have been used widely, primarily because of their ability to stabilize the folded proteins through a mechanism that does not involve direct contact, but rather their preferential exclusion from the protein surface.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Brandts<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF> and Pohl<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13 cit14">13,14</REF> proposed that the driving force for stabilizing the protein folded conformation is a non-specific solvation effect in which the preferential exclusion of the co-solvents from the protein surface arises from enhanced water ordering (structure makers).</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast, when denaturating co-solvents bind to proteins, water–protein and water–co-solvent interactions, that occur in the unbound state, are replaced by relatively stronger co-solvent–protein interactions in the bound state with concomitant release of water molecules into the bulk phase.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, these compounds tend to reduce the solvent ordering (structure breakers).</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Such ligand interactions can be studied based on determining the solvent accessible surface area (SASA).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15 cit16">15,16</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The structure-making and structure-breaking tendencies of these compounds on protein-bound water have been studied extensively by Lin <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Their results indicate that when hydrophilic groups, such as charged or polar side chains of proteins, are exposed or come in contact with the surrounding water, they show a pattern characteristic of structure breakers, with a large positive apparent expansion coefficient of the protein, in particular at low temperature, which decreases drastically with increasing temperature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the contrary, apolar, hydrophobic amino acid side groups act in the reverse manner, as structure makers, by enhancing the space consuming hydrogen-bonded network structure of water, particularly at low temperature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is accompanied by a decrease in solvent density around the hydrophobic groups.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Aliphatic side chains, for example, are known to have even negative apparent thermal expansion coefficients, <IT>α</IT>, at low temperatures (near 0 °C) with a large positive temperature coefficient.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Increasing thermal energy, however, allows the water molecules to free themselves from this expanded ordered solvation state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hence, in general, for proteins in dilute aqueous solutions, the temperature dependent thermal expansion coefficient at the protein–solvent interface is dominated by protein–water interactions, which arise mainly from interactions between the protein groups with the surrounding hydration layer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Irrespective of whether co-solvents directly interact with or are preferentially excluded from the protein surface, they induce definite changes in the quantity of bound water and its associated properties, such as hydrogen-bonded structure, and chemical potential.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18 cit19 cit20 cit21 cit22">18–22</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Densimetric studies are often not of sufficient sensitivity to reveal these changes in solvation properties or volume changes upon unfolding of proteins.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22 cit23 cit24 cit25">22–25</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the present paper, we examine these perturbations in the hydration layer around a protein caused by addition of co-solvents using a relatively new and efficient technique called pressure perturbation calorimetry (PPC).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17 cit26 cit27 cit28">17,26–28</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">Applying this method, determination of the thermal expansion coefficient and relative volume changes, Δ<IT>V</IT>/<IT>V</IT>, upon unfolding of proteins in solution has advantages over densimetric measurements since its sensitivity is higher by more than one order of magnitude.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17 cit29 cit30 cit31">17,29–31</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">This high sensitivity is a prerequisite for such studies, as the expansivity and the volume change upon unfolding, which can be either positive of negative, are usually very small (Δ<IT>V</IT>/<IT>V</IT> &lt; 0.3%).</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="New" advantage="None">The observed volume and expansivity changes are correlated with further thermodynamic properties obtained from differential scanning calorimetry (DSC).</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Taken together, these data lead to a deeper understanding of the solvation process of proteins in different co-solvents in their native and unfolded states.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">We have chosen to study the solvation properties and stability of a well characterized monomeric protein, staphylococcal nuclease (Snase), in H<SB>2</SB>O and D<SB>2</SB>O buffer solutions, as well as in the presence of various types of co-solvents, such as glycerol, sorbitol, urea and potassium sulfate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">Their influence on the expansivity as well as the denaturation temperature, relative volume and enthalpy changes upon unfolding were obtained with high accuracy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Snase is a small protein of about 17.5 kDa containing 149 amino acid residues and no disulfide bonds.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">It has an extraordinarily high fraction of ionisable groups.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The X-ray diffraction pattern of native crystalline Snase<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit32">32</REF> reveals that in the crystalline state the protein contains 26.2% helices, 24.8% β-sheets (barrel), 7.4% extended chains, 24.8% turns and loops, and 8.7% unordered chains, and the remaining 8.1% is uncertain.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Volume and expansivity changes of Snase upon pressure and acid induced denaturation were given elsewhere<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit33 cit34 cit35 cit36 cit37">33–37</REF> and are compared with these data.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The present study aims to obtain more insight into the basic thermodynamic properties of protein solvation and volume effects accompanying unfolding scenarios on one hand, and on the other hand, to initiate further potential applications of pressure perturbation calorimetry in studies of biomolecular systems in general.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.">Materials and methods</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.1">Protein preparation</HEADER><P><s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Recombinant Snase with the sequence of nuclease A from the V8 strain of <IT>Staphylococcus aureus</IT> was obtained using the λ expression system in the <IT>Escherichia coli</IT> strain Arλ9 as described by Shortle and Lin.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit38">38</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The cells were grown according to the procedure described by Shortle <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit39">39</REF>. except that SB rather than MOPS media was employed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The protein purification was carried out according to the method described by Shortle and Meeker<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit40">40</REF> with modifications described by Frye <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit41">41</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Potassium sulfate (K<SB>2</SB>SO<SB>4</SB>), deuterium oxide (D<SB>2</SB>O) were obtained from Aldrich, urea and D-sorbitol from Fluka, and glycerol from Merck.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The chemicals were used without further purification.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">10 mM of phosphate buffer (di-sodium hydrogen phosphate, anhydrous, from Merck) was used for all experiments.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.2">Differential scanning and pressure perturbation calorimetry (PPC)</HEADER><P><s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The thermal unfolding of Snase was measured by means of a high precision VP DSC micro-calorimeter from MicroCal, Northamption, MA, USA.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The cell volume is 0.51 mL.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reference cell was filled with matching buffer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both buffer and protein solutions were degassed before being injected into the respective cells.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Degassing was performed at a slightly reduced atmospheric pressure and for a short time only, so that no concentration changes occurred.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The instrument was operated in the high gain mode at a rate of 40 °C h<SP>−1</SP> for all experiments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The instrument is also equipped with a pressuring cap that allows application of <IT>ca</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">1.8 bar to the cells in order to avoid air bubbles at elevated temperatures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Sample concentration of Snase in 10 mM phosphate buffer was 0.2 wt% with a known quantity of co-solvent.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Baseline subtraction (pure buffer) and normalization with respect to protein concentration were performed by the instrument software, yielding the temperature-dependent apparent molar heat capacity of the protein, <IT>C</IT><SB>p</SB>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The pressure perturbation (PPC) experiments were performed in the DSC calorimeter using the MicroCal PPC accessory.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reference and sample cell volume are identical (0.51 mL) and they open to a common pressure chamber containing a sensor.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp10" novelty="None" advantage="None">An equal pressure of 5 bar was applied to both cells in a programmed manner using nitrogen gas.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The pressure effect on the sample volume is negligibly small (0.02%).</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The protein concentration used for the PPC studies was <IT>ca</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp11" novelty="None" advantage="None">4 mg mL<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Each pressure jump starts with equilibration at 5 bar pressure of the calorimeter in the isothermal high gain and low noise modes at the desired temperature with 0.02 °C tolerance.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="New" advantage="None">The software then initiates a pressure release to ambient pressure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="New" advantage="None">The temperature of the cell is kept constant by active compensation of the heat change caused by the pressure jump.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="New" advantage="None">The compensation power returns to the baseline typically within one minute and integration of the supplied power <IT>vs.</IT> time yields the heat consumed or released by the sample.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="New" advantage="None">After complete equilibration, automatically checked by an adjustable slope criterion, an upward pressure jump is applied when the PPC controller reconnects the PPC cells with nitrogen gas.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="New" advantage="None">The heat peak of compressed and decompressed pressures should agree in absolute values; they are of opposite sign, however.</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="New" advantage="None">For both compression and decompression experiments, temperature, pressure, and heat flow are recorded as a function of time.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="New" advantage="None">The calorimeter is then automatically heated or cooled to the next desired temperature and the next two pressure jumps are applied.</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Various pH variation studies from 2 to 9 on Snase using DSC indicated that it is most stable at pH 5.5 in 10 mM phosphate buffer.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">As the technique has been introduced quite recently only,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17 cit26 cit27 cit28 cit31">17,26–28,31</REF> we briefly summarize the thermodynamics on which it is based.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">From the second law of thermodynamics we know that an entropy change for a reversible process carried out at temperature <IT>T</IT>, whose heat change is d<IT>Q</IT><SB>rev</SB>, can be written as d<IT>S</IT> = d<IT>Q</IT><SB>rev</SB>/<IT>T</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Differentiation with respect to pressure, at constant <IT>T</IT>, gives (∂<IT>Q</IT><SB>rev</SB>/∂<IT>p</IT>)<SB><IT>T</IT></SB> = <IT>T</IT> (∂<IT>S</IT>/∂<IT>p</IT>)<SB><IT>T</IT></SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Using the Maxwell relation (∂<IT>S</IT>/∂<IT>p</IT>)<SB><IT>T</IT></SB> = −(∂<IT>V</IT>/∂<IT>T</IT>)<SB><IT>p</IT></SB>, we obtain eqn. (1): where <IT>V</IT> is the volume and <IT>α</IT> is the coefficient of thermal expansion, (1/<IT>V</IT>)(∂<IT>V</IT>/∂<IT>T</IT>)<SB><IT>p</IT></SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Here it is assumed that <IT>V</IT> and <IT>α</IT> are nearly invariant within small pressure changes (here 5 bar), which is a very good approximation for all liquids.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Integration of eqn. (1), at constant temperature, over a small pressure range, Δ<IT>p</IT>, gives the working equation for calculating <IT>α</IT> The coefficient of thermal expansion, <IT>α</IT>, can thus be determined from an isothermal measurement of the heat consumed or released upon small pressure changes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Here, Δ<IT>Q</IT><SB>rev</SB> is the heat difference between the sample cell that contains the dissolved sample, and the reference cell, which contains the same solvent, upon the pressure changes Δ<IT>p</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Moreover, the relative volume changes Δ<IT>V</IT>/<IT>V</IT> at the unfolding transition, taking place in the temperature range from <IT>T</IT><SB>o</SB> to <IT>T</IT><SB>e</SB>, can be obtained by eqn. (3): </annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In extending eqn. (2) to protein solute (in buffer solvent) and solvent (buffer only) binary component systems, we obtain eqn. (4): where <IT>α</IT> and <IT>α</IT><SB>solv</SB> are the thermal expansion coefficients of the protein and solvent, respectively, and <IT>V</IT><SB>cell</SB> is the active cell volume.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17 cit26">17,26</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The experiment thus yields the difference in expansivity between the protein solution (sample cell) and the buffer (reference cell).</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The apparent expansion coefficient of the protein is measured, which includes changes in hydrational properties at the protein surface with regard to the pure solvent system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The uncertainties in <IT>α</IT> determined from at least three measurements using different sample preparations is ±0.05 × 10<SP>−3</SP> K<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.">Results and discussion</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.1">Pure solvents</HEADER><P><s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The values of the expansion coefficients of the solvents, <IT>α</IT><SB>solv</SB>, measured for the phosphate buffer containing 0.5 M co-solvents are shown in Fig. 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The solutions with 0.5 M glycerol, sorbitol, urea, and K<SB>2</SB>SO<SB>4</SB> exhibit a greater thermal expansion compared to pure water (shown for comparison), in particular at low temperature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of K<SB>2</SB>SO<SB>4</SB>, above 80 °C, however, its expansivity becomes smaller than that of pure water, which is likely due to the “structure making” effect of the salt.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.2">Snase–H<SB>2</SB>O</HEADER><P><s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 2a represents PPC curves of the apparent expansion coefficient, <IT>α</IT>(<IT>T</IT>), of 0.4 wt% Snase dissolved in 10 mM phosphate buffer at pH 5.5, from which <IT>α</IT> at different temperatures, the midpoint of thermal unfolding (<IT>T</IT><SB>m</SB>) and the relative volume change upon unfolding, Δ<IT>V</IT>/<IT>V</IT>, are obtained.</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None"><IT>T</IT><SB>m</SB> and the enthalpy change of the transition (Δ<IT>H</IT>) are obtained from the DSC experiments (Fig. 2b).</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The protein begins to unfold (onset temperature) at <IT>ca</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">43 °C and the temperature of the unfolding midpoint, <IT>T</IT><SB>m</SB>, was found to be 51.5 °C.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The enthalpy change obtained by integration over the DSC peak amounts to 178 ± 5 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">We find an increase in <IT>C</IT><SB>p</SB> of 5.7 ± 0.2 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> K<SP>−1</SP> between the unfolded and native state.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Between 10 and 40 °C, the apparent thermal expansion coefficient of the protein, <IT>α</IT>, decreases almost linearly from 1.0 × 10<SP>−3</SP> K<SP>−1</SP> to a value near 0.65 × 10<SP>−3</SP> K<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">At approximately 51.7 °C, where the DSC curve <IT>C</IT><SB>p</SB>(<IT>T</IT>) exhibits its maximum, a distinct dip is observed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Above that temperature, <IT>α</IT> increases again to a relatively constant level in the post-transition temperature range.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Above 70 °C, <IT>α</IT> then decreases again.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">High <IT>α</IT> values at lower temperatures (1.0 × 10<SP>−3</SP> K<SP>−1</SP> at 10 °C) and their steep decrease up to 40 °C (d<IT>α</IT>/d<IT>T</IT>)<SB>10–40</SB> = −1.17 × 10<SP>−5</SP> K<SP>−2</SP>) are indicative of the presence of a large number of structure-breaking hydrophilic side chains on the surface of Snase.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">As the temperature increases, water molecules are released from the surface and the value of the thermal expansivity is reduced.</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since Snase has an extraordinarily large number of ionisable residues (39%), it exhibits very large values of <IT>α</IT> and |(d<IT>α</IT>/d<IT>T</IT>)<SB>10–40</SB>|.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="New" advantage="None">The relative volume change upon unfolding, Δ<IT>V</IT>/<IT>V</IT>, as obtained from the area under the transitional peak, is calculated by integrating the <IT>α</IT>(<IT>T</IT>) transition curve (after baseline subtraction); Δ<IT>V</IT>/<IT>V</IT> = −1.5 × 10<SP>−3</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The absolute volume change upon unfolding, Δ<IT>V</IT>, can be calculated from Δ<IT>V</IT>/<IT>V</IT> using the molar mass of Snase (16 812 Da) and its partial specific volume (0.754 mL g<SP>−1</SP>)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit33">33</REF> which yields Δ<IT>V</IT> = −19 mL mol<SP>−1</SP>, which is of the order of −0.15% of the whole system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">In agreement with the DSC data, the transition has been found to be reversible up to temperatures of 80 °C.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.3">Snase–H<SB>2</SB>O, D<SB>2</SB>O</HEADER><P><s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The effect of solvation strength on the temperature dependence of <IT>α</IT>, which is largely controlled by protein–solvent interactions, should be expected to change significantly upon replacing H<SB>2</SB>O for D<SB>2</SB>O as solvent.</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 3a shows PPC results of Snase in dilute buffer prepared from D<SB>2</SB>O (Snase – D<SB>2</SB>O) in comparison to those of Snase in H<SB>2</SB>O (Snase – H<SB>2</SB>O).</annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">From this figure it is clear that in the lower temperature region, the negative slope of <IT>α</IT>(<IT>T</IT>) is considerably enhanced in D<SB>2</SB>O: (d<IT>α</IT>/d<IT>T</IT>)<SB>10–40</SB> = −2.2 × 10<SP>−5</SP> K<SP>−2</SP> in Snase–D<SB>2</SB>O, whereas (d<IT>α</IT>/d<IT>T</IT>)<SB>10–40</SB> = −1.17 × 10<SP>−5</SP> K<SP>−2</SP> for Snase in dilute buffer prepared from H<SB>2</SB>O. The larger absolute (d<IT>α</IT>/d<IT>T</IT>)<SB>10–40</SB> value in the case of Snase–D<SB>2</SB>O points to a higher degree of solvation than in the Snase–H<SB>2</SB>O system.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">D<SB>2</SB>O has a stronger structuring tendency which, in contact with structure-breaking protein groups results in a relatively larger solvation layer around the protein surface.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The decrease in thermal expansivity with temperature is indeed largely controlled by the net structure-breaking tendencies of the polar protein groups interacting with water.</annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is not to say that the intrinsic expansivity of the protein is negligible, but simply that the protein interior does not appear to contribute significantly to the decrease in expansivity with increasing temperature (see below).</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The <IT>T</IT><SB>m</SB> value shifts from 51.5 °C in H<SB>2</SB>O to 56 °C in D<SB>2</SB>O. Furthermore, there is a <IT>ca</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">33% reduction in Δ<IT>V</IT> (Δ<IT>V</IT> = −12.7 mL mol<SP>−1</SP> for Snase–D<SB>2</SB>O).</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">All the results are listed in Table 1.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Concerning <IT>T</IT><SB>m</SB> values, similar results as from PPC were obtained from the DSC traces of Snase in D<SB>2</SB>O and H<SB>2</SB>O, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">From Fig. 3b it is clear that there is a shift in <IT>T</IT><SB>m</SB> from 51.7 °C in H<SB>2</SB>O to 56.3 °C in D<SB>2</SB>O. We observe also a considerable increase in the enthalpy of unfolding in D<SB>2</SB>O. The transition enthalpy change of the system Snase–D<SB>2</SB>O (Δ<IT>H</IT> ≈ 227 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>) is <IT>ca</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None">25% greater than that of the system Snase–H<SB>2</SB>O (Δ<IT>H</IT> ≈ 178 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>), which is, again, an indication that the protein is more stable in D<SB>2</SB>O. Such an enhancement of the structure of a solvation layer contributing to the protein stability was also reported elsewhere<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit43 cit44">43,44</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.4">Snase–H<SB>2</SB>O–glycerol</HEADER><P><s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Glycerol and other polyolic co-solvents have been shown to lead to a “preferential hydration” of the protein, <IT>i.e.</IT> the exclusion of the co-solvent molecules from the protein surface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hence, in their presence proteins are preferentially hydrated.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18 cit45 cit46 cit47 cit48 cit49 cit50 cit51">18,45–51</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">For sugars (<IT>e.g.</IT>, sucrose), glycerol and polyhydric alcohols (<IT>e.g.</IT>, ethylene glycerol, sorbitol), the preferential hydration was found to induce also protein stabilization.</annotationART></s> <s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Glycerol, being a strongly hydrophilic co-solvent, interacts strongly with H<SB>2</SB>O and has a weaker affinity for the polar residues on the protein surface, thus leading to preferential hydration of the protein.</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, the steric exclusion principle should make the distance of closest approach of a co-solvent with a larger molecular volume greater than that of water.</annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac20" novelty="None" advantage="None">As a result, the volume fraction occupied by the co-solvent at the surface of the protein should be less than that in the bulk solvent.</annotationART></s> <s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac20" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thermodynamically, this thus also manifests itself as preferential hydration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac21" novelty="None" advantage="None">Upon denaturation, the surface of the protein increases, which results in an enhanced preferential hydration of the denatured protein relative to the native protein.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit51 cit52">51,52</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The PPC results of Snase dissolved at various molar concentrations of glycerol in 10 mM phosphate buffer at pH 5.5 are shown in Fig. 4a.</annotationART></s> <s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The glycerol concentration in the buffer was varied from 0.5 M (<IT>ca</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp14" novelty="None" advantage="None">5 wt%) to 3.5 M (<IT>ca</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp14" novelty="None" advantage="None">32 wt%).</annotationART></s> <s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">From the figure it can be clearly seen that there is a continuous increase in <IT>α</IT>, |(d<IT>α</IT>/d<IT>T</IT>)<SB>10–40</SB>|, and <IT>T</IT><SB>m</SB> values with increasing glycerol concentration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The increase in <IT>T</IT><SB>m</SB> value is clearly an evidence of the stabilization of the folded state, arising from the energetically unfavourable increase in preferential hydration due to the increase in exposed surface area upon unfolding.</annotationART></s> <s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Similar results were obtained for the Snase–D<SB>2</SB>O system (data not shown).</annotationART></s> <s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The increase in glycerol concentration leads to a drastic increase of the thermal expansivity at 10 °C due to the preferential hydration, even though the total amount of water in the system is reduced with increasing glycerol concentration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The comparison of the (d<IT>α</IT>/d<IT>T</IT>)<SB>10–40</SB> value of Snase–3.5 M glycerol (−2.4 × 10<SP>−5</SP> K<SP>−2</SP>) with that of Snase–H<SB>2</SB>O (−1.17 × 10<SP>−5</SP> K<SP>−2</SP>) in buffer solution indicates that the addition of glycerol contributes to a <IT>ca</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">100% increase in solvation, assuming that (d<IT>α</IT>/d<IT>T</IT>)<SB>10–40</SB> is proportional to the degree of solvation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The possibility of extensive glycerol binding to the protein, even at high glycerol concentration, might be ruled out because in such a case part of the water should be expelled from the protein surface to accommodate glycerol which would lead to a decrease in <IT>α</IT> and hence |(d<IT>α</IT>/d<IT>T</IT>)<SB>10–40</SB>|.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The values of <IT>T</IT><SB>m</SB> from DSC (Fig. 4b) and PPC are in good agreement.</annotationART></s> <s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The steady increment of <IT>T</IT><SB>m</SB> and Δ<IT>H</IT> in the glycerol containing buffer solutions, up to 56 °C and Δ<IT>H</IT> ≈ ∼260 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> for the 3.5 M glycerol containing solution (Table 1), confirms the continuous increase in protein stability with increasing glycerol concentration.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The volume change of unfolding is drastically reduced for the glycerol solvent systems (<IT>e.g.</IT>, <IT>ca</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="143"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">100% for the 3.5 M glycerol solution), which might be due to a less disordered unfolded state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="144"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" advantage="None">This would be in agreement with the smaller Δ<IT>C</IT><SB>p</SB> values as obtained by DSC (Table 1).</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.5">Snase–H<SB>2</SB>O–sorbitol</HEADER><P><s sid="145"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Several reports state that stabilisation of proteins in the presence of sorbitol, which is about twice as large as glycerol, is also mainly due to it being excluded from the surface of the protein,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit47 cit51">47,51</REF><IT>i.e.</IT>, in their presence, proteins are preferentially hydrated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="146"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa6" novelty="None" advantage="None">To quantify the relative hydration changes, PPC experiments were also conducted using 0.5 M (<IT>ca</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="147"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa6" novelty="None" advantage="None">9 wt%) and 1.5 M (<IT>ca</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="148"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa6" novelty="None" advantage="None">27 wt%) sorbitol as co-solvents in 10 mM phosphate buffer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="149"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The PPC results are shown in Fig. 5a and indicate that the hydration changes and stabilisation due to sorbitol are even higher than those for the corresponding concentrations of glycerol (Table 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="150"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The comparison of (d<IT>α</IT>/d<IT>T</IT>)<SB>10–40</SB> values of Snase–1.5 M sorbitol (−1.7 × 10<SP>−5</SP> K<SP>−2</SP>) and Snase–1.5 M glycerol (−1.5 × 10<SP>−5</SP> K<SP>−2</SP>) indicates that there is an <IT>ca</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="151"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">12% increase in solvation of the native protein in the sorbitol containing solvent, which also acts as a more effective stabilising agent.</annotationART></s> <s sid="152"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The shift in <IT>T</IT><SB>m</SB> value, <IT>e.g.</IT>, from 51.5 to 58.6 °C in 1.5 M sorbitol (53.7 °C in 1.5 M glycerol) indicates the more effective stabilising effect of sorbitol compared to glycerol.</annotationART></s> <s sid="153"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The volume change upon unfolding is much smaller, −5 mL mol<SP>−1</SP> in 1.5 M sorbitol as compared to −16 mL mol<SP>−1</SP> in 1.5 M glycerol and −19 mL mol<SP>−1</SP> in the pure phosphate buffer system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="154"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs20" novelty="None" advantage="None">The high Δ<IT>H</IT> (<IT>ca</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="155"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs20" novelty="None" advantage="None">208 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>) and <IT>T</IT><SB>m</SB> (59 °C) values obtained from the DSC data, which are shown in Fig. 5b, are in good agreement with the conclusions drawn from the PPC results.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.6">Snase–H<SB>2</SB>O–urea</HEADER><P><s sid="156"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is well known that the destabilising nature of the chaotropic agent urea on protein stability is caused by binding efficiently to the unfolded state of the protein, compared to the folded state, due to exposure of more binding sites upon unfolding.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit52 cit53">52,53</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="157"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The PPC and DSC results on Snase–urea solutions displayed in Fig. 6 are in agreement with these general findings.</annotationART></s> <s sid="158"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs21" novelty="None" advantage="None">As expected, the <IT>T</IT><SB>m</SB> value decreases with increasing urea concentration, for example <IT>T</IT><SB>m</SB>(1.5 M urea) = 39.1 °C, <IT>T</IT><SB>m</SB>(2.5 M urea) = 32.5 °C (Table 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="159"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs22" novelty="None" advantage="None">The <IT>α</IT> values at low temperature are much smaller than those of the pure Snase–H<SB>2</SB>O system, and the absolute value of d<IT>α</IT>/d<IT>T</IT>, taken between 10 °C and the onset temperature of the denaturation peak, also decreases with increasing urea concentration (Fig. 6a).</annotationART></s> <s sid="160"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac22" novelty="None" advantage="None">These effects are related to specific binding of urea to the polypeptide, thereby replacing water molecules and releasing them into the bulk phase, such that the hydration of the protein is largely diminished in the presence of urea, prior to denaturation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="161"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs23" novelty="None" advantage="None">Interestingly, the Δ<IT>V</IT> values of Snase–0.5 M urea and Snase–1.5 M urea buffer solutions with −32 and −56 mL mol<SP>−1</SP>, respectively, are much greater than those of Snase in the pure buffer solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="162"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Beyond a concentration of 1.5 M of urea, it is not possible to calculate Δ<IT>V</IT> accurately as the protein does not denaturate in a cooperative manner anymore.</annotationART></s> <s sid="163"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs24" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is supported by the reduction in the enthalpy values of denaturation, Δ<IT>H</IT>, as calculated from the DSC data, which are shown in Fig. 6b.</annotationART></s> <s sid="164"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Δ<IT>H</IT> values are 168 and 108 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> for the 0.5 and 1.5 M urea containing solutions, <IT>i.e.</IT>, they decreased by <IT>ca</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="165"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">6% and <IT>ca</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="166"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">39%, respectively, when compared to Snase–H<SB>2</SB>O (buffer).</annotationART></s> <s sid="167"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">The <IT>T</IT><SB>m</SB> values as obtained by DSC also decrease with increasing urea concentration and are in good agreement with the values obtained by the PPC method.</annotationART></s> <s sid="168"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs25" novelty="None" advantage="None">Above a concentration of 2.5 M urea, no clear transition can be observed anymore.</annotationART></s> <s sid="169"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac23" novelty="None" advantage="None">All experimental data are again listed in Table 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="170"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of urea, an increase in absolute Δ<IT>V</IT> values is observed at the unfolding transition, which is an indication that the protein tends to form a rather extended structure, and the solvation properties at the protein surface are probably largely determined by binding of urea.</annotationART></s> <s sid="171"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">As a consequence, the <IT>α</IT> values in the denatured state are rather small.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.7">Snase–H<SB>2</SB>O–K<SB>2</SB>SO<SB>4</SB></HEADER><P><s sid="172"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac24" novelty="None" advantage="None">Some specific anions are known to induce the formation of molten globule forms in proteins, for example from acid-unfolded proteins.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit54">54</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="173"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac24" novelty="None" advantage="None">The mechanism of stabilisation by anions is due to a reduction of the net positive charge on the protein through anion binding.</annotationART></s> <s sid="174"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac24" novelty="None" advantage="None">Stabilisation of proteins due to the presence of such salts are thus more effective at lower pH than at neutral pH.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit55">55</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="175"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac25" novelty="None" advantage="None">At reduced protein surface charge and at higher anion concentrations, the Hofmeister effects<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit46 cit55">46,55</REF> prevail, however.</annotationART></s> <s sid="176"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac25" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hofmeister anions interact favourably with the peptide groups whereas they interact unfavourably with the nonpolar peptide side chains.</annotationART></s> <s sid="177"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac26" novelty="None" advantage="None">Sulfate, for example, is known to be a good protein stabilizer, because sulfate strongly salts out nonpolar compounds and only weakly interacts with and thus salts in the peptide group.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit55">55</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="178"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Here, we looked at the role of the cosmotropic salt K<SB>2</SB>SO<SB>4</SB> in a solvent environment where the net charge of the protein is still small.</annotationART></s> <s sid="179"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac27" novelty="None" advantage="None">Under these conditions, the K<SB>2</SB>SO<SB>4</SB> specific binding tendency is reduced.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="180"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs26" novelty="None" advantage="None">The PPC and DSC results for Snase dissolved in 0.5 M K<SB>2</SB>SO<SB>4</SB> buffer solution are presented in Figs. 7a and 7b, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="181"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">From the PPC experiments it is clear that the shift in the <IT>T</IT><SB>m</SB> value from 51.5 to 59.5 °C is an indication that the salt acts as a strong stabilising agent.</annotationART></s> <s sid="182"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast to the osmolytes glycerol and sorbitol, the apparent expansion coefficient of the protein in the native state is smaller than that of the protein in pure buffer solution, however.</annotationART></s> <s sid="183"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">The value of (d<IT>α</IT>/d<IT>T</IT>)<SB>10–40</SB> = −0.77 × 10<SP>−5</SP> K<SP>−2</SP> obtained for the K<SB>2</SB>SO<SB>4</SB> system is <IT>ca</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="184"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">30% less than that of the Snase–H<SB>2</SB>O (buffer) system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="185"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the present case, even though there is a net reduction in solvation, similar to urea, the K<SB>2</SB>SO<SB>4</SB>–buffer system increases the stability of the protein.</annotationART></s> <s sid="186"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">The high Δ<IT>H</IT> value of <IT>ca</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="187"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">295 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> obtained from the DSC results indicates the drastically increased stability of the protein in the K<SB>2</SB>SO<SB>4</SB> buffer solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="188"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">Surprisingly, in this and only in this case, Δ<IT>V</IT> becomes positive (Δ<IT>V</IT> = 19 mL mol<SP>−1</SP>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="189"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None">This volume increase at the unfolding transition could be due to the formation of a protein conformation which is not fully unfolded but rather achieves a flexible, expanded state only, which might be a molten globule kind of structure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="190"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs27" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the unfolded state at <IT>ca</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="191"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs27" novelty="None" advantage="None">80 °C, <IT>α</IT> is similar to that of the pure buffer system, again.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.8">The thermal unfolding scenario</HEADER><P><s sid="192"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The interpretation of the present results must be made in the context of previously published work on the volumetric properties of Snase (and proteins in general) as a function of temperature and pressure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="193"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac28" novelty="None" advantage="None">Direct densimetric measurements on Snase as a function of temperature and pressure<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit36">36</REF> revealed that below the unfolding transition temperature at atmospheric pressure, the slope of the change in specific volume with temperature exhibits a distinct downward curvature, indicating that the apparent thermal expansivity of the native state of the solvated protein decreases with increasing temperature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="194"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" advantage="None">The present more accurate studies are in good agreement with these earlier observations, as they demonstrate a marked decrease in <IT>α</IT> between 4 and 40 °C, below the transition temperature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="195"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac29" novelty="None" advantage="None">At higher temperatures, between 55 and 65 °C, our earlier studies show that the increase in specific volume with temperature was nearly linear, <IT>i.e.</IT> the thermal expansivity appeared nearly constant over this temperature range.</annotationART></s> <s sid="196"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the present study, it is seen that this temperature range corresponds to the tail end of the transition, and thus to the region of rollover in which d<IT>α</IT>/d<IT>T</IT> ≈ 0 before changing sign.</annotationART></s> <s sid="197"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, the present determination of <IT>α</IT> as a function of temperature using PPC is in good agreement with the previous observations based on a determination of the specific volume by densimetry, which had to be carried out at a much higher (20×) protein concentration, however.</annotationART></s> <s sid="198"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res29" novelty="None" advantage="None">The estimation, based on the present PPC results, of the change in <IT>α</IT> upon unfolding, Δ<IT>α</IT>, at the transition temperature yields a positive value of about 1 × 10<SP>−4</SP> K<SP>−1</SP>, and is in the range (0.5–1.5 × 10<SP>−4</SP> K<SP>−1</SP>) of the values obtained by Lin <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF>. on a number of proteins.</annotationART></s> <s sid="199"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac30" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our earlier densimetric measurements also revealed an increase in the apparent value of the expansivity between 45 and 65 °C, consistent with a positive value for Δ<IT>α</IT>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="200"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac31" novelty="None" advantage="None">Intrinsic protein volume, including the effects of protonation and deprotonation of amino acids upon unfolding, volume changes due to thermal motions and changes in water structure at the protein surface are the three major factors contributing to the apparent thermal expansivity of a protein.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit42 cit56">42,56</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="201"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac32" novelty="None" advantage="None">The thermal volume at the protein solvent interface and the intrinsic volume of the protein increase with temperature leading to a positive contribution to <IT>α</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="202"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac33" novelty="None" advantage="None">The thermal expansivity of the protein interior has been measured over a limited temperature range, essentially using fluorescence and X-ray diffraction (on single crystals),<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit57 cit58 cit59 cit60">57–60</REF> and the changes observed are rather small.</annotationART></s> <s sid="203"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac34" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is in accord with our SAXS measurements of the radius of gyration, <IT>R</IT><SB>g</SB>, of Snase in solution; within the accuracy of our data (±1–2 Å), the <IT>R</IT><SB>g</SB>value is unchanged up to <IT>ca</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="204"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac34" novelty="None" advantage="None">40 °C.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit34 cit61">34,61</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="205"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac35" novelty="None" advantage="None">The solvation effect also represents a positive contribution to the thermal expansivity, but is expected to decrease with increasing temperature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="206"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac35" novelty="None" advantage="None">This behaviour is due to the fact that the protein surface binds adjacent water.</annotationART></s> <s sid="207"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac35" novelty="None" advantage="None">Vicinal water molecules may be oriented to the surface charges leading to a more or less layered structure.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17 cit62 cit63">17,62,63</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="208"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac36" novelty="None" advantage="None">This layering is probably substantial at low temperature, and thermal activation leads to a continuous release of this “condensed” water from the protein surface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="209"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac36" novelty="None" advantage="None">Once the water is released, it no longer contributes to the partial volume of the protein and hence to <IT>α</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="210"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac36" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus at low temperatures, the solvation effect (in particular, of the polar/charged peptide groups) leads to large positive contributions to <IT>α</IT> and will decrease steeply with increasing temperature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="211"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac37" novelty="None" advantage="None">Lin <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF>. proposed that the d<IT>α</IT>/d<IT>T</IT> value of a protein in its native state is a direct measure of the solvation contribution to the volume expansivity.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="212"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac38" novelty="None" advantage="None">The volume change that accompanies the unfolding transition of a protein (in this case Snase) clearly will depend upon the temperature at which the transition occurs.</annotationART></s> <s sid="213"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res30" novelty="None" advantage="None">The value of Δ<IT>V</IT> at the transition temperature of 51.5 °C obtained in this study (−19 mL mol<SP>−1</SP>) is smaller than those reported in denaturation studies by pressure<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit36">36</REF> or acid induced<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit33">33</REF> denaturation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="214"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac39" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the acid denaturation studies may include significant electrostriction effects.</annotationART></s> <s sid="215"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac40" novelty="None" advantage="None">More to the point, the pressure-induced unfolding was carried out over a temperature range of 4 to 45 °C, below the unfolding transition temperature.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit34">34</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="216"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac40" novelty="None" advantage="None">These pressure studies demonstrated that the absolute value of the volume change upon unfolding was strongly temperature dependent, decreasing significantly in magnitude with increasing temperature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="217"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac40" novelty="None" advantage="None">At 40 °C, the Δ<IT>V</IT> was near −65 ± 10 mL mol<SP>−1</SP>, whereas at 45 °C it had decreased in absolute value to −37 mL mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="218"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac41" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our previous data were not of high enough quality to determine whether this temperature dependence of Δ<IT>V</IT> was linear or non-linear.</annotationART></s> <s sid="219"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, one can assume that at 52.5 °C it would have decreased to at least −25 mL mol<SP>−1</SP>, a value within experimental error of that determined in the present studies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="220"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac42" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is possible, however, that differences in Δ<IT>V</IT> values may also arise from differences in the structure of the denatured states at high temperature as compared to high pressure.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="221"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac43" novelty="None" advantage="None">Studies involving the application of hydrostatic pressure to solutions of native proteins have demonstrated that at temperatures below that corresponding to the unfolding transition, the volume change upon unfolding of proteins is negative, <IT>i.e.</IT> the partial specific volume of the unfolded state is smaller than that of the folded state and therefore pressure induces unfolding.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit64 cit65">64,65</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="222"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac44" novelty="None" advantage="None">Early work on metmyoglobin<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit66">66</REF> and ribonuclease<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit67">67</REF> and later on Snase as noted above<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit34">34</REF> has also shown that the pressure effect decreases in magnitude with increasing temperature, and may even change sign, <IT>i.e.</IT>, the partial specific volume of the unfolded state becomes larger than that of the folded state at high temperature and pressure can induce folding, rather than unfolding under these conditions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="223"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac45" novelty="None" advantage="None">Moreover, even though it is negative at low temperatures, the absolute value of the volume change upon unfolding is quite small.</annotationART></s> <s sid="224"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac46" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, clearly the value and sign of the volume change upon unfolding at higher temperature will depend upon how the thermal expansivities of folded and unfolded states change with temperature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="225"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac46" novelty="None" advantage="None">Unfortunately, the temperature dependence of the thermal expansivity of the unfolded state cannot be determined at temperatures below the transition temperature, while that of the folded state cannot be determined at temperatures above the transition temperature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="226"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res32" novelty="None" advantage="None">Nonetheless, since Δ<IT>α</IT> is positive at the transition temperature, the expansivity of the unfolded state is higher than that of the folded state at the transition.</annotationART></s> <s sid="227"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res32" novelty="None" advantage="None">As the temperature is lowered, it is likely that <IT>α</IT> of the unfolded state increases, but probably to a lesser degree than that of the folded state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="228"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac47" novelty="None" advantage="None">This might be due to the fact that relatively more aliphatic side chains of the protein are exposed to the solvent in the unfolded state, and the temperature dependence of the thermal expansivity of aliphatic side chains is opposite to that of the polar side chains and peptide bonds, given the fact that the aliphatic groups tend to promote a higher degree of structure in the water of solvation than exists in bulk water.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="229"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac47" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, as temperature is lowered this ordering significantly reduces the expansivity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="230"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac48" novelty="None" advantage="None">Aromatic groups as well are exposed to the solvent in the unfolded state, whereas they are significantly less exposed in the folded state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="231"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs28" novelty="None" advantage="None">The temperature dependence of the thermal expansivity of these groups is very small.</annotationART></s> <s sid="232"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac49" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus overall, while the thermal expansivity of the unfolded state is likely to be higher than that of the folded state (at least near the transition temperature), its temperature dependence is probably reduced in comparison.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="233"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res33" novelty="None" advantage="None">Given that the specific volume of the unfolded state is smaller at low temperature than that of the folded state, the temperature evolution of the specific volume of the two states may be similar to that schematized in Fig. 8.</annotationART></s> <s sid="234"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs29" novelty="None" advantage="None">Such a scheme of the individual contributing factors to the volume change upon unfolding changes as a function of temperature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="235"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None">At low temperature, the volume change upon unfolding, Δ<IT>V</IT>, is negative because elimination of internal cavities and electrostrictive effects around exposed polar groups upon unfolding offset the positive contributions of exposure of hydrophobic groups and the larger thermal volume of the unfolded state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="236"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None">At higher temperature, the decreased solvation effect can no longer offset the larger thermal volume of the unfolded state compared to the unfolded state, and the Δ<IT>V</IT> changes sign.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="237"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs30" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Δ<IT>α</IT> and Δ<IT>C</IT><SB>p</SB> values for Snase in phosphate buffer solution at pH 5.5 are 0.12 × 10<SP>−3</SP> K<SP>−1</SP> and 5.7 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> K<SP>−1</SP>, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="238"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac50" novelty="None" advantage="None">These values are taken as a reference to compare relative SASAs in the presence of the various co-solvents.</annotationART></s> <s sid="239"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res34" novelty="None" advantage="None">The larger absolute (d<IT>α</IT>/d<IT>T</IT>)<SB>10–40</SB> value in the case of Snase–D<SB>2</SB>O points to a higher solvation than that of the Snase–H<SB>2</SB>O system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="240"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con15" novelty="None" advantage="None">D<SB>2</SB>O has a stronger structuring tendency which, in contact with structure-breaking protein groups results in a relatively larger solvation layer around the protein surface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="241"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con16" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the Snase in glycerol, the changes in expansivity and heat capacity upon unfolding indicate a decrease compared to those measured in pure buffer, indicating a compaction of the unfolded state as the glycerol concentration increases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="242"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con16" novelty="None" advantage="None">This would be in agreement with the reduced Δ<IT>V</IT> values observed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="243"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac51" novelty="None" advantage="None">Indeed, glycerol has been found to decrease the specific volume and the adiabatic compressibility of the protein interior, suggesting that the mechanism involves the collapse of voids in the protein core following a glycerol-induced elimination of flexibility-associated (“lubricant”) water.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit45">45</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="244"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac52" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, in pressure unfolding experiments on Snase at 21 °C as a function of increasing osmolyte concentration (in that case xylose up to <IT>ca</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="245"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac52" novelty="None" advantage="None">0.5 M), we observed that while the apparent free energy of unfolding increased with increasing xylose concentration as would be expected, the volume change of unfolding remained essentially constant.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit68">68</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="246"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con17" novelty="None" advantage="None">One explanation for this discrepancy between previous studies and the present can be found in the temperature dependence of the volume change, which is quite large.</annotationART></s> <s sid="247"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac53" novelty="None" advantage="None">Indeed, addition of osmolyte stabilizes the folded state, such that the <IT>T</IT><SB>m</SB> (the temperature at which Δ<IT>V</IT> is measured in the present experiments) increases with increasing glycerol concentration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="248"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the volume change of unfolding decreases strongly with increasing temperature, we can conclude that at least part of the observed effect of glycerol on the Δ<IT>V</IT> is due to the increase in temperature.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="249"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac54" novelty="None" advantage="None">A similar but inverse explanation may also hold for the observed increase in the absolute value of Δ<IT>V</IT> as a function of increasing urea concentration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="250"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac54" novelty="None" advantage="None">Indeed, urea destabilizes the folded state of the protein leading to a decrease in the <IT>T</IT><SB>m</SB> as a function of increasing urea concentration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="251"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the Δ<IT>V</IT> is of larger absolute value as the temperature decreases, increasing urea concentration results automatically in a larger absolute value of Δ<IT>V</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="252"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Another contribution may be that increasing urea concentration leads to a more completely unfolded state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="253"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res35" novelty="None" advantage="None">We observed that there is a continuous decrease in Δ<IT>α</IT> which finally approaches zero with increasing urea concentration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="254"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac55" novelty="None" advantage="None">This could arise from significant binding of urea to the protein in the pre- and post-transitional temperature range.</annotationART></s> <s sid="255"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac55" novelty="None" advantage="None">The excess area available after protein denaturation would be occupied by the remaining free urea molecules, such that electrostatic or hydrophobic hydration effects could be largely reduced.</annotationART></s> <s sid="256"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac56" novelty="None" advantage="None">We note in contrast to this explanation, that another effective denaturant, guanidinium hydrochloride, had no effect on the value of the volume change of unfolding obtained in the pressure-induced unfolding of Snase at 21 °C,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit69">69</REF> indicating that such solvation effects do not play a role in the value of the volume change under those high pressure conditions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="257"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac56" novelty="None" advantage="None">Moreover, the radius of gyration observed for urea denatured Snase (35 Å)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit70 cit71">70,71</REF> is smaller than that which we observed by temperature denaturation (45 Å),<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit34">34</REF> indicating that, on the contrary, urea leads to a more ordered unfolded state than does temperature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="258"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con19" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, it is altogether possible that the combination of both temperature and urea significantly destabilizes residual interactions in the unfolded state compared to either perturbation alone.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="259"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac57" novelty="None" advantage="None">Very interesting observations are made when the protein is stabilised in the presence of the salt K<SB>2</SB>SO<SB>4</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="260"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con20" novelty="None" advantage="None">Firstly, Δ<IT>V</IT> being positive is probably an indication of the dominance of the thermal volume expansion due to an increase in the dynamics of backbone and side chains of the protein over the internal dead volume being exposed during denaturation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="261"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con20" novelty="None" advantage="None">The state might be characterized by a swollen, molten globule kind of state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="262"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con21" novelty="None" advantage="None">The experimental Δ<IT>α</IT> and Δ<IT>C</IT><SB>p</SB> values of −0.03 × 10<SP>−3</SP> K<SP>−1</SP> and <IT>ca</IT>. −9.5 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> K<SP>−1</SP> (Table 1), respectively, point to no drastic increase in SASA in the denatured state, again indicative of a less unfolded and hence less hydrophobically hydrated structure in the denatured state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="263"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con21" novelty="None" advantage="None">This state can be achieved only, if K<SB>2</SB>SO<SB>4</SB>–H<SB>2</SB>O interactions dominate over Snase–K<SB>2</SB>SO<SB>4</SB>–H<SB>2</SB>O interactions and specific anion binding is largely missing.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.">Concluding remarks</HEADER><P><s sid="264"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con22" novelty="None" advantage="None">Pressure perturbation calorimetry has been found to be an effective tool for measuring the thermal expansion coefficient and volume changes of biomolecular systems with very high precision.</annotationART></s> <s sid="265"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">Accurate information related to solvent binding, ligand binding and volume changes during unfolding and denaturation of proteins can be obtained by this technique.</annotationART></s> <s sid="266"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The observed thermodynamic data obtained drastically depend on the interfacial solvent conditions, which drastically influence the structural and dynamic behaviour of the biomolecular system.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="267"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">We clearly demonstrate that solvation properties contribute extensively towards the stability of proteins.</annotationART></s> <s sid="268"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con23" novelty="None" advantage="None">The apparent expansion coefficient of the protein, <IT>α</IT>, is strongly dependent on the type and concentration of co-solvent and its interactions with functional groups of the polypeptide.</annotationART></s> <s sid="269"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This effect is already clearly observed when the thermodynamic data obtained using water as solvent are compared with those of a chemically structurally similar solvent, D<SB>2</SB>O. The increase in thermal stability of the protein in the presence of D<SB>2</SB>O can be understood to be due to an increase in solvation around the protein as indicated by the much larger <IT>α</IT> value in the native state of the protein.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="270"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con24" novelty="None" advantage="None">The solvation effects leading to the strong temperature dependence of <IT>α</IT> are controlled by two contributions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="271"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac58" novelty="None" advantage="None">Firstly, as shown in the seminal paper by Lin <IT>et al.</IT>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF> hydrophobic groups known to act as structure-makers in water have a large positive slope and a negative curvature in <IT>α</IT>(<IT>T</IT>) plots, while structure-breaking hydrophilic groups show the opposite behaviour.</annotationART></s> <s sid="272"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac58" novelty="None" advantage="None">For charged and polar groups, <IT>α</IT>(<IT>T</IT>) curves exhibit a large negative slope and a positive curvature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="273"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac58" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the solvation effects of a protein are dominated by hydrophilic groups, both the native and unfolded protein exhibit a net structure-breaking profile for <IT>α</IT>(<IT>T</IT>).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="274"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con25" novelty="None" advantage="None">Upon unfolding of the Snase, the internal dead volume becomes accessible to water (leading to a decrease in system volume) and the dynamics of the protein backbone, and amino acid side chains increases thus leading to an increase of the thermal volume.</annotationART></s> <s sid="275"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con25" novelty="None" advantage="None">Moreover, the water-accessible surface area becomes larger upon unfolding, thus increasing the number of water molecules being affected.</annotationART></s> <s sid="276"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con25" novelty="None" advantage="None">The surface term may reflect two contributions: Firstly, since charged or polar surface-affected water is supposed to be condensed, this will give rise to a negative contribution to Δ<IT>V</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="277"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con25" novelty="None" advantage="None">Secondly, upon unfolding of the surface, the protein becomes more hydrophobic because the native structure tends to bury more of the hydrophobic side chains in the interior.</annotationART></s> <s sid="278"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con25" novelty="None" advantage="None">It can be supposed that this effect counteracts the first one to some extent.</annotationART></s> <s sid="279"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con26" novelty="None" advantage="None">The negative volume change upon unfolding observed under most conditions implies that at the transition temperature, the opening of void volume and the increase in accessible surface area with more charged and polar groups upon unfolding overcompensate the positive effects of thermal volume and the decrease in the hydrophilic to hydrophobic balance of the surface area.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="280"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res36" novelty="None" advantage="None">Similarly to D<SB>2</SB>O, a continuous increase in solvation was observed with increase in glycerol or sorbitol content in the buffer, hence indicating that they act as protein stabilisers, as is indeed verified by the increasing <IT>T</IT><SB>m</SB> and Δ<IT>H</IT> values.</annotationART></s> <s sid="281"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res37" novelty="None" advantage="None">The values of Δ<IT>V</IT> and Δ<IT>C</IT><SB>p</SB> are also smaller for these co-solvents.</annotationART></s> <s sid="282"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con27" novelty="None" advantage="None">The observed reduction in absolute value of Δ<IT>V</IT> in the presence of these stabilisers may be in part attributed to the formation of a partially unfolded state of the protein (which is consistent with a smaller change in heat capacity upon unfolding) and in part directly due to the temperature dependence of Δ<IT>V</IT>; as <IT>T</IT><SB>m</SB> increases, Δ<IT>V</IT> decreases (in absolute value).</annotationART></s> <s sid="283"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con28" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the contrary, the chaotropic agent urea destabilizes the protein by direct ligand binding and restricts direct water contact with the protein surface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="284"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con28" novelty="None" advantage="None">This preferential binding of urea to the protein reduces the hydration level causing the protein to approach a disordered, random coil-like state at high urea concentration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="285"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con29" novelty="None" advantage="None">The increase in Δ<IT>V</IT> and the decrease in Δ<IT>H</IT> with increasing urea concentration support these conclusions, although a significant contribution to the increase in Δ<IT>V</IT> arises as well from its temperature dependence; as <IT>T</IT><SB>m</SB> decreases Δ<IT>V</IT> increases in absolute value.</annotationART></s> <s sid="286"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con30" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Δ<IT>α</IT> and Δ<IT>C</IT><SB>p</SB> values are less affected by changes in hydrophilic and hydrophobic hydration, which is attributed to the strong ligand binding of urea with the protein.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="287"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">A stabilising effect, even though there is a reduction in solvation around the protein (|Δ<IT>α</IT>/Δ<IT>T</IT><SB>10–40</SB>| is <IT>ca</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="288"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">30% lower compared to the pure buffer system) is also observed for 0.5 M K<SB>2</SB>SO<SB>4</SB> as co-solvent.</annotationART></s> <s sid="289"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac59" novelty="None" advantage="None">Near pH 5.5, K<SB>2</SB>SO<SB>4</SB> is still left with little chance to bind strongly to the protein.</annotationART></s> <s sid="290"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac59" novelty="None" advantage="None">Yet, the sulfate anions are still able to decrease the hydration layer around the protein.</annotationART></s> <s sid="291"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con20" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this case, Δ<IT>V</IT> is found to be positive which is an indication of the formation of a swollen, molten globule kind of unfolded state at the transition.</annotationART></s> <s sid="292"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con21" novelty="None" advantage="None">Indeed, the negative values for Δ<IT>α</IT> and Δ<IT>C</IT><SB>p</SB> in presence of this salt point to no marked increase in SASA upon unfolding.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="293"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con31" novelty="None" advantage="None">These results for the various chaotropic and cosmotropic co-solvents clearly show that the co-solvent not only markedly changes the stability of Snase, but also its solvation, and perhaps also the structures of the denatured state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="294"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con32" novelty="None" advantage="None">More generally, the present results on Snase combined with the few previously reported studies on other small globular proteins<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF> demonstrate that the PPC technique provides an exquisitely sensitive handle on the hydration properties of proteins in solution, the understanding of which is prerequisite to a global comprehension of protein stability and dynamics.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
