<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b315777f" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Comparison of photochemical properties of brookite and anatase TiO<SB>2</SB> films</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The photocatalytic oxidation activity and photoinduced hydrophilicity of brookite-rich TiO<SB>2</SB> film were compared to those of anatase TiO<SB>2</SB> film under ultraviolet (UV) light irradiation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">The photocatalytic oxidation activities were evaluated by the initial photodegradation rates of methylene blue and <IT>cis</IT>-9-octadecenoic acid.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rates for the methylene blue bleaching were nearly identical (−2.2 × 10<SP>−3</SP> Abs min<SP>−1</SP>) for the brookite-rich and anatase films, and the rate for <IT>cis</IT>-9-octadecenoic acid decomposition on the brookite-rich film was slightly less than that on the anatase one (−0.08 ± 0.01 μg cm<SP>−2</SP> min<SP>−1</SP> and −0.10 ± 0.01 μg cm<SP>−2</SP> min<SP>−1</SP>, respectively).</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the rate constants for photoinduced hydrophilicity, which were evaluated by the changes in water contact angles (<IT>θ</IT>) under rather weak UV light irradiation (5 μW cm<SP>−2</SP>), were better for the brookite surface than the anatase one.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Moreover, the brookite-rich film became more hydrophilic (<IT>θ</IT> = 10°) than the anatase one (<IT>θ</IT> = 18°) after long time exposure to weak UV light irradiation, and showed a good ability for the photoinduced hydrophilicity.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In recent years, numerous researchers have investigated the photocatalytic activities of TiO<SB>2</SB> due to the strong oxidation power of its photogenerated holes under ultraviolet (UV) light irradiation,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF> as well as its chemical inertness and nontoxicity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition to the strong oxidation power, we reported that UV light irradiation causes the TiO<SB>2</SB> surface to become highly hydrophilic.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">2</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">These useful properties have been applied to commercial products, such as anti-fogging mirrors, self-cleaning ceramic tiles, <IT>etc.</IT> At normal pressure, TiO<SB>2</SB> has three different crystal structures, rutile, anatase and brookite.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">As photocatalysts, both rutile and anatase phases have been widely investigated, and it is well known that the photocatalytic activities of the anatase phase are mostly superior to those of the rutile one.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast, there are a limited number of reports on brookite phase TiO<SB>2</SB><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3 cit4 cit5 cit6 cit7 cit8 cit9 cit10 cit11 cit12 cit13 cit14">3–14</REF> and most of these papers are simply on its preparation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">There are a few reports on its photocatalytic and electrochemical properties,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10 cit12 cit13 cit14">10,12–14</REF> but none on photoinduced hydrophilicity of brookite films.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Here, the photocatalytic oxidation activity and the photoinduced hydrophilic property of a brookite-rich film are compared with those of an anatase film.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Experimental</HEADER><P><s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">TiO<SB>2</SB> films with a thickness around 270–280 nm were prepared on SiO<SB>2</SB>-coated glass plates by a spin-coating method of TiO<SB>2</SB> sols (1500 rpm for 10 s), followed by a calcination at 500 °C for 30 min.</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Two types of films were prepared: film A was from NTB-01 (brookite type TiO<SB>2</SB> sol: SHOWA DENKO K. K., Japan) and film B was from STS-01 (anatase sol: Ishihara Sangyo Kaisha, Ltd., Japan).</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">For comparison, corresponding powders A and B were prepared by desiccating the NTB-01 and STS-01 sols at 500 °C for 30 min, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The crystal phases of the films were identified by glancing incidence X-ray diffraction (RINT-2100, Rigaku Denki Ltd., Japan) at a constant incident angle of 0.8° using Cu-Kα radiation operated at 40 kV–30 mA.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Conventional <IT>θ</IT>–2<IT>θ</IT> scanning was used in the powder XRD measurements.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The optical absorption spectra were recorded on a UV-VIS-NIR scanning spectrophotometer (UV-3100PC, Shimadzu Co., Japan).</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The microstructures of these films were observed by atomic force microscopy (AFM, SPA300, Seiko Instruments Inc., Japan) and scanning electron microscopy (SEM, S-4200, Hitachi Co., Japan).</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The morphologies of the powders were observed using a transmission electron microscope (TEM, JEM-2010, JEOL, Japan).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Degradation of Methylene Blue (MB) was measured to evaluate the photocatalytic oxidation activity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">MB is a brightly coloured, blue cationic thiazine dye with <IT>λ</IT><SB>max</SB> between 550 and 600 nm, and is not photoblenched by UV light irradiation in the absence of TiO<SB>2</SB> under the present experimental conditions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp9" novelty="None" advantage="None">MB was applied on the TiO<SB>2</SB> films by dipping the films in 1 mmol l<SP>−1</SP> methylene blue solution for 30 min.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">The change of the absorbance peak in the visible region was measured by the spectrophotometer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is known that reduction of MB leads to colorless leucoMB, which can be reoxidized to MB by oxygen.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">To exclude the contribution of this bleaching reduction process, the irradiated TiO<SB>2</SB> samples were stored in the dark until the absorption remained constant before the measurement.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">The photocatalytic oxidation activity of the TiO<SB>2</SB> films was also measured by the weight change of <IT>cis</IT>-9-octadecenoic acid under UV light irradiation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Approximately 10 mg of <IT>cis</IT>-9-octadecenoic acid was first applied onto the 6.25 cm<SP>2</SP> samples and their weight changes were measured by an electronic balance (AG285, Mettler Toledo, Switzerland, 10 μg precision).</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">The weight was determined averaging 5 different measurements from the same sample.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Details have been given elsewhere.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Because <IT>cis</IT>-9-octadecenoic acid on a glass substrate was stable when irradiating with UV light, we concluded that the weight changes were not due to the evaporation of <IT>cis</IT>-9-octadecenoic acid but from the photooxidization by the TiO<SB>2</SB> films.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The photoinduced hydrophilic property was evaluated by measuring the water contact angle (<IT>θ</IT>) of the TiO<SB>2</SB> film's surfaces by the sessile drop method with a commercial water contact meter (CA-X, Kyowa Interface Science, Japan).</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The droplet size used for the measurements was 0.7 μL.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">The value of the contact angle was determined averaging at least 5 different measurements from the same sample.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp13" novelty="None" advantage="None">All the above UV light irradiation experiments were done using a cylindrical black-light lamp as a light source.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The UV intensity was measured by a UV radiometer (UVR-2, TOPCON, Japan).</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Results and discussion</HEADER><P><s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 1 shows the XRD patterns of Films A, B and Powders A, B. Although Film B and Powder B showed only anatase peaks, Film A and Powder A displayed characteristic peaks for brookite (JCPDS #29-1360) in addition to weak anatase ones.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to estimate the ratio (<IT>R</IT>) of brookite for Powder A, the following equation was used.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that the equation was obtained from the literature by excluding the contribution of the rutile peak.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">(<IT>k</IT><SB>anatase</SB> = 0.886, <IT>k</IT><SB>brookite</SB> = 2.721)</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Here <IT>I</IT>anatase101 and <IT>I</IT>brookite121 represent the integrated intensities of the anatase (101) peak and the brookite (121) peak, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The anatase (101) peak and the brookite (120) and (111) peaks were separated using a numerical deconvolution method.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The <IT>R</IT> value was estimated to be about 0.75 from Fig. 1 pattern (c), indicating that Powder A consists of mostly brookite phase with some anatase one.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The estimated value agrees well with the previously reported value for the NTB-01 sol,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF> suggesting that crystal phases did not change by the thermal treatment at 500 °C for 30 min.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Because Film A was prepared under the same thermal conditions with Powder A, it is reasonably expected that the film also consists of mostly brookite phase with some anatase one.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hereafter, Film A, Film B, Powder A and Powder B are referred to brookite-rich film, anatase film, brookite-rich powder and anatase powder, respectively.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The SEM and AFM measurements showed that the surface roughnesses of the brookite-rich and anatase films were nearly identical.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The average roughnesses (<IT>Ra</IT>), which indicate surface roughness estimated from AFM measurements, were 5.2 nm and 4.3 nm for the brookite-rich and anatase films, respectively, with the same grain size around 10–20 nm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">These films were transparent between 400–800 nm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The UV-VIS spectra showed that the main absorption edges for the brookite-rich and anatase films were located around 380 nm, which corresponds to the photoelectrochemically determined band gap energy values <IT>E</IT> = 3.26 eV for brookite and <IT>E</IT> = 3.20 eV for anatase (not shown here).</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 2 is the TEM image of the brookite-rich powders, showing the characteristic crystal shape, a plate-like aspect with a square plane.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Electron diffraction patterns identified the indices of the square surface as brookite (010) and (210).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Now, let us evaluate the photocatalytic oxidation activities of the brookite-rich and anatase films.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 3 shows the change in the absorbance of the MB peak in visible region under 1 mW cm<SP>−2</SP> UV light irradiation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The continuous UV light irradiation caused the adsorbed MB absorption to decrease.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Here we estimated the degradation rate (<IT>k</IT>) for MB from the initial slope to be <IT>k</IT><SB>brookite</SB> = <IT>k</IT><SB>anatase</SB> = −2.2 × 10<SP>−3</SP> Abs min<SP>−1</SP> under the assumption of a pseudo-zero-order kinetics.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 4 shows the weight change of the applied <IT>cis</IT>-9-octadecenoic acid adsorbed on the TiO<SB>2</SB> films.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The weight immediately started decreasing upon UV light irradiation accompanied by CO<SB>2</SB> production.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Continuous UV light irradiation decomposed almost all the reactants.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The initial decomposition rates (<IT>k</IT>′) for the brookite-rich film and the anatase one were estimated to be <IT>k</IT>′<SB>brookite</SB> = −0.08 ± 0.01 μg cm<SP>−2</SP> min<SP>−1</SP> and <IT>k</IT>′<SB>anatase</SB> = −0.10 ± 0.01 μg cm<SP>−2</SP> min<SP>−1</SP>, respectively.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Irradiating with UV light generates electrons and holes in the bulk TiO<SB>2</SB> that diffuse to the surface and then react with organic materials adsorbed on the surface directly or <IT>via</IT> various active oxygen species, such as ˙OH and ˙HO<SB>2</SB>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18 cit19 cit20 cit21">18–21</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">These organic compounds eventually decompose into CO<SB>2</SB> and H<SB>2</SB>O, due to the strong oxidation power of the generated radicals and holes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since these two films have almost identical surface roughness, the difference in the photocatalytic decomposition activities is attributed to that in the amounts of the active species produced by UV light irradiation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ratio of the total absorbed photon numbers for the present brookite-rich to anatase films was calculated to be 1.26.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, the present results suggest that the photocatalytic oxidation activity of the anatase film is roughly the same or rather greater than that of the brookite-rich film.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Ohtani <IT>et al.</IT> reported that the brookite-type TiO<SB>2</SB> showed almost the same activity for photocatalytic oxidation reaction (photocatalytic mineralization of acetic acid) as that of anatase-type TiO<SB>2</SB>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF> which coincides with our present results.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Next, let us examine the photoinduced hydrophilicity of these films.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 5 shows the changes in the water contact angle for the brookite-rich and anatase films under the irradiation with sufficient UV light (1 mW cm<SP>−2</SP>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Before irradiation, the contact angles of these two TiO<SB>2</SB> films were around 30°.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although a small difference was initially observed between the two films in Fig. 5, the hydrophilicizing behaviors were very similar after 30 min and lead to a decent hydrophilic conversion when <IT>θ</IT> = approximately 5°.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast, Fig. 6 demonstrates the changes when irradiating with a rather weak UV light (5 μW cm<SP>−2</SP>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Under this condition, not enough photons were produced to fully create hydrophilic surfaces and both films were partially hydrophilic, reflecting the sensitivity for the hydrophilicizing reaction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">We previously reported that plots of the reciprocal of the water contact angles <IT>versus</IT> irradiation time have a linear relationship and its slope can be regarded as the hydrophilicizing rate constant.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22 cit23">22,23</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" advantage="None">From the inset of Fig. 6, it is estimated that the rate constants of the brookite-rich and anatase films for hydrophilic conversion were 7.2 × 10<SP>−5</SP> degree<SP>−1</SP> min<SP>−1</SP> and 2.7 × 10<SP>−5</SP> degree<SP>−1</SP> min<SP>−1</SP>, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs19" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, the contact angle of the brookite-rich film became to 10°, although that of the anatase one was only ∼18° after long time exposure to the weak UV light irradiation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The contact angle of the heterogeneous surface is determined by well-known Cassie equation.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of brookite-rich film, the contact angle is given bycos<IT>θ</IT> = <IT>f</IT><SB>a</SB> cos<IT>θ</IT><SB>a</SB> + <IT>f</IT><SB>b</SB>cos<IT>θ</IT><SB>b</SB>where <IT>f</IT><SB>a</SB>, <IT>f</IT><SB>b</SB> are the fractions of anatase and brookite, and <IT>θ</IT><SB>a</SB>, <IT>θ</IT><SB>b</SB>, <IT>θ</IT> are the contact angles of anatase, brookite and the mixed surface, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the brookite-rich surface showed lower contact angle than that of the pure anatase film under UV light irradiation, it is reasonable to consider that the brookite phase exhibits a better ability for the photoinduced hydrophilicity than the anatase one.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is important to note that the brookite-rich film showing the better hydrophilic conversion property is not superior in oxidation ability to the anatase one.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">We previously reported that SrTiO<SB>3</SB> film having a good oxidation property did not become highly hydrophilic under UV light irradiation.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25">25</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">These results indicate that photoinduced hydrophilicity is not simply induced by the oxidation of adsorbed organic impurities on the surface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">In fact, nearly zero degrees of water contact angle on the UV light irradiated TiO<SB>2</SB> surface increases to about 10 degrees when the TiO<SB>2</SB> is sonicated in ultra-pure water.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26">26</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Such a deterioration of the wettability is also observed when the highly hydrophilic TiO<SB>2</SB> is stored in high vacuum chamber.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27">27</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">We proposed that the highly hydrophilic state is due to the formation of unstable OH group on TiO<SB>2</SB> surface<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF> and the surface with bridging site oxygen may give a better change for the formation of unstable OH species.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28">28</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs20" novelty="None" advantage="None">The (010) face of brookite, which is considered to be one of the main faces of the present brookite particles, has such a two-fold oxygen atoms with rather high surface concentration (7.1 × 10<SP>14</SP> site cm<SP>−2</SP>) as shown in Fig. 7.</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">This might be one of the reasons for a good hydrophilic property of the present brookite-rich film.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The photoinduced hydrophilicity of TiO<SB>2</SB> (mostly anatase) has been already used commercially in various materials.</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, highly hydrophilicity can be obtained only under rather strong UV light irradiation, above 100 μW cm<SP>−2</SP>, and thus its application field is almost limited in outdoor use.</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The present results show that the brookite-rich TiO<SB>2</SB> film is more sensitive in hydrophilicity than anatase one especially under weak UV light irradiation, indicating that the application field potentially expanded by using the brookite film.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Conclusion</HEADER><P><s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This study compared the photocatalytic oxidation and photoinduced hydrophilicity of brookite-rich TiO<SB>2</SB> to the anatase one.</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is noteworthy that the activity for the photoinduced hydrophilic reaction of the brookite was more sensitive than that of anatase, while the photocatalytic oxidation activities of these two phases were nearly identical or rather lower.</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">These results showed that the photoinduced hydrophilic conversion was not simply explained by the degradation of organic impurities, and supported the existence of alternative mechanism for it.</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Moreover, the current work reveals a high potential for brookite type TiO<SB>2</SB> as a coating material.</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">It suggests that the hydrophilicity may be improved by using the brookite type TiO<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
