<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b316185d" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">The dipeptide cyclic(glycyltryptophanyl) in the gas phase: A concerted action of density functional calculations, S<SB>0</SB>–S<SB>1</SB> two-photon ionization, spectral UV/UV hole burning and laser photoelectron spectroscopy</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">The S<SB>0</SB>–S<SB>1</SB> spectrum of the dipeptide cyclic(glycyltryptophanyl) (cGW) has been recorded by two-photon ionization (R2PI) spectroscopy of thermally evaporated, jet-cooled molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The R2PI spectrum contains several vibronic transitions with relatively small spacing.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Density functional theory predicts more than 8 conformers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Applying spectral UV/UV hole burning spectroscopy we found that the strongest S<SB>0</SB>–S<SB>1</SB> transitions belong to a single conformer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The transition at 35 058 cm<SP>−1</SP> is attributed to the S<SB>1</SB> origin and the other transitions to inter-ring modes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">To obtain further information on the conformer structure, resonant two-colour two-photon ionization photoelectron spectroscopy (R(1 + 1′)PI PES) has been performed <IT>via</IT> the two most intense S<SB>0</SB>–S<SB>1</SB> transitions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">To our knowledge these are the first PE spectra of a dipeptide.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The spectra are broad with a smooth onset.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The lowest ionization onset lies at 7.709 eV, but is assumed to be not the adiabatic IE.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Theoretical calculations with the B3LYP/6-311++G** theory predict that in the most stable neutral conformer an N–H group of the dipeptide ring binds to the indole π system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This structure has the highest IE of all conformers investigated and shows a strong geometry change upon ionization.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fact that the IE of the experimentally observed cGW conformer is higher than that of 3-methylindole is taken as a signature of a repulsion between the two rings in the cation: This could be explained by the N–H group of the peptide ring now interacting with the positively charged indole π system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The conformational assignment by R(1 + 1′)PI PES is tentative, because all of the lowest-energetic neutral conformers are expected to behave similarly in regard to ionization energies.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="I">Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The advantage of gas phase measurements is the applicability of spectroscopy methods such as resonant two-photon ionization (R2PI) spectroscopy combined with mass-selective detection, spectral UV/UV or IR/UV hole burning (UV/UV SHB or IR/UV SHB) spectroscopy and resonant two-colour two-photon ionization photoelectron spectroscopy (R(1 + 1′)PI PES).</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Further advantages of gas phase investigations are usually sharp spectra which reveal detailed structural information.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Most importantly, however, gas phase data can be directly compared to theory.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">For reviews on biological molecules in the gas phase see .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2 cit3 cit4">ref. 1–4</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Levy and co-workers were the first to perform spectroscopy of di- and tripeptides in the gas phase by using laser desorption with R2PI and mass-selective detection.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6">5,6</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">For tryptophan-containing peptides they obtained sharp spectra with distinct lines despite the many vibrational degrees of freedom and the many possible conformers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The spectroscopy of laser-desorbed small peptides was later improved by using double resonance methods.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7 cit8">7,8</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Neutral laser desorption and R2P ionization and laser fragmentation was also introduced as a new species selective inlet system into mass spectrometry.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9 cit10 cit11">9–11</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thermal evaporation of natural unprotected peptides is impossible.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12 cit13">12,13</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Up to now only for some modified peptides in which the polar functional groups have been protected by methyl groups a thermal evaporation of intact molecules is reported.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14 cit15">14,15</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Cyclic dipeptides have no polar N or C terminal and hence, as we show here, can be vaporized intact by heating.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">To our knowledge up to now no investigation of cyclic peptides in the gas phase has been performed.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">UV/UV or IR/UV double resonance methods are widely used in spectroscopy of floppy molecules and clusters.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">2</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The strategy to obtain structural information by using zero kinetic energy electron PES (ZEKE<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF>), mass analyzed threshold ionization (MATI<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF>) or high resolution conventional laser PES<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF> is not new.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18 cit19 cit20 cit21 cit22 cit23 cit24 cit15">18–25</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">In these publications model systems, such as extended molecules with a chromophore and a flexible side chain, have been investigated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Whereas for non-polar side groups sharp PE spectra are observed exclusively<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18 cit19 cit20">18–20</REF> for polar groups sharp spectra are only expected for conformers where the interaction of the charge site and the polar group are minimized, <IT>i.e.</IT> unfolded, linear structures.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">In folded structures the polar group solvates the charge strongly and structural changes upon ionization become so large that it is impossible to reach the origin of the cation ground state and obtain vibrationally resolved spectra.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Nevertheless, the IE shift together with theory may provide useful information to allow an identification of the neutral conformation.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Only in one case of an aromatic molecule with a polar side chain, both folded and unfolded conformers showed sharp vibrationally resolved spectra.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24 cit25">24,25</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">In this paper we report on spectroscopy of the cyclic(glycyltryptophanyl) (cGW) in the gas phase.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">R2PI spectroscopy with mass selection has been used to record the S<SB>0</SB>–S<SB>1</SB> spectrum.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">UV/UV SHB was applied to analyze the number of conformers present in the molecular beam.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">To obtain further information on the conformer structure, R(1 + 1′)PI PES was performed for the two most intense S<SB>0</SB>–S<SB>1</SB> transitions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Density functional theory (DFT) calculations on the B3LYP/6-311++G** level are used to interpret the number and structure of observed conformers, IEs and geometry shifts upon ionization.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">A tentative conformer identification is given on the basis of a comparison between experiment and theory.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="II">Experimental</HEADER><P><s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The cyclic peptide cGW was purchased from Bachem.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">It has been synthesized from pure L-tryptophan (W) and hence cGW has also L chirality.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The apparatus is described in detail elsewhere.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Briefly it consists (Fig. 1) of a supersonic jet chamber (a), a field-free time-of-flight PE spectrometer (b) and a pulsed linear time-of-flight mass spectrometer (c).</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="New" advantage="None">A modified pulsed nozzle (General Valve, orifice diameter 300 μm) was heated to achieve a suitable sample vapor pressure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="New" advantage="None">The indole sample has been added to a sample container above the nozzle and heated to 325 K. The cGW sample, crystalline at room temperature, is placed directly in the nozzle head and heated to 525 K. Ar was used as carrier gas with a backpressure of 5 bar.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The jet passed the skimmer (1.5 mm orifice) and crossed the laser beam at right angles in the middle of the PE spectrometer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The time-of-flight PE spectrometer is 900 mm long, μ-metal shielded and covered inside by graphite.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Only photoelectrons emitted into the small acceptance angle of the two-stage micro channel plate (MCP) detector were detected and their time measured with high precision in a start–stop logic.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="New" advantage="None">Note that for photoelectron spectroscopy no ion extraction plates have been used within the PE spectrometer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">After ionization, the ions drift downwards with their supersonic jet velocity into a pulsed linear time-of-flight (linTOF) mass spectrometer (mass resolution <IT>m</IT>/Δ<IT>m</IT> × 100).</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hence R2PI mass spectra, mass-analyzed R2PI spectra and R(1 + 1′)PI PE spectra with simultaneous mass control can be recorded in the same apparatus.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Only for UV/UV SHB experiments three deflection plates were introduced at the ionization site in the PE spectrometer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this case the ions were formed in an electric field and deflected into the former electron detector.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The laser system consisted of two Nd:YAG laser-pumped and frequency-doubled tunable dye lasers (5–7 ns pulse width) and an additional excimer-pumped frequency-doubled dye laser which can be arbitrarily shifted in time with respect to the Nd:YAG-pumped dye lasers.</annotationART></s></P><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>R2PI spectroscopy</HEADER><P><s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">For recording the R2PI spectrum ions were formed in the PE spectrometer and, after drifting down, mass-analyzed in the pulsed linear TOF mass spectrometer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The S<SB>0</SB>–S<SB>1</SB> spectrum was recorded by tuning the laser wavelength and recording the parent cations with a gated integrator.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">For this purpose we used the Nd:YAG-pumped frequency doubled dye laser (resolution in the UV: &lt; 1 cm<SP>−1</SP>, 100 μJ pulse<SP>−1</SP>, 1000 mm lens out of focus).</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">We found that the cooling efficiency of the supersonic jet very much depended on the expansion gas and improved with increasing mass of the carrier gas.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>UV/UV SHB</HEADER><P><s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the SHB a three-plate ion optics (repeller plate, intermediate plate, grounded exit plate) was mounted in the PE spectrometer which deflected and accelerated the ions to the electron detector of the PE spectrometer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">By changing the MCP voltages suitable for ion detection mass and UV/UV SHB spectra have been measured.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The mass resolution <IT>m</IT>/Δ<IT>m</IT> of this linTOF is 1500.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">This setup is needed to deflect the ions formed by the hole burning laser by using a pulsed electric field scheme.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The hole burning laser performed ground state depletion by R2PI 4 μs before the probe laser ionizes the remaining neutrals.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">For ion discrimination coming from different lasers, ions stemming from the hole burning laser were for 4 μs accelerated backwards (+500 V at the second plate, repeller plate grounded) and neutralized on the repeller plate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="New" advantage="None">A suitable pulsed voltage (750 V) was then applied to the repeller shortly after new ions had been formed by the probe laser.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="New" advantage="None">The SHB spectrum was recorded by scanning the hole burning laser while the probe laser was set to the S<SB>0</SB>–S<SB>1</SB> origin transition of cGW.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="New" advantage="None">Each time when the neutral ground state of the cGW conformer was depopulated a dip appeared in the probe laser signal.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that in this mode the dip depth directly correlates with the transition moment of the transition.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="New" advantage="None">Also a reversed scheme has been used to test the percentage of depletion for each transition of interest.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>(R(1 + 1′)PI) PE spectroscopy</HEADER><P><s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">For R(1 + 1′)PI PE spectroscopy ionization was performed by two frequency-doubled dye lasers pumped by the same Nd:YAG laser.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ionizing laser (laser 2) was time-delayed by 3 ns against laser 1 which performed the S<SB>0</SB>–S<SB>1</SB> excitation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The photon energy of laser 2 was not sufficient for a two-photon ionization.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The one-photon signal of laser 1 was lower than 5% of the total two-color ion signal.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="New" advantage="None">Typical laser pulse energies were 10 μJ for laser 1 and 20 μJ for laser 2 (1000 mm lens, out of focus).</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="New" advantage="None">To optimize the electron energy resolution, the photon energy of laser 2 was chosen to keep the maximum photon excess energy below 200 meV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">For indole we achieved a PE energy resolution Δ<IT>E</IT> = 1 meV and an absolute accuracy of ±2 meV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The accuracy for cGW was ±3 meV due to the smooth onset at the ionization onset.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="III">Theoretical results</HEADER><P><s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our motivation to perform calculations on cGW was (i) to obtain the relative energies of the neutral and cation conformers, (ii) to calculate the vibrational frequencies for the lowest conformers, (iii) to calculate the vertical IEs and (iv) to explore the structural differences between the neutral and cation for the most stable conformers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="New" advantage="None">For conformer assignment we use the comparison of the experimental to calculated data, such as relative neutral conformer energies, vertical IEs and neutral to cation geometry shifts.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">So far no <IT>ab initio</IT> or DFT calculations of a cyclic peptide are reported.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">We used the density functional B3LYP<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26">26</REF> because according to our experience<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF> it seems to better describe flexible molecules with polar groups than other methods.</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="New" advantage="No">It is well known that B3LYP systematically underestimates intermolecular electron correlation forces as present in folded molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">There could be several explanations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">One would be an accidental error compensation, another that electrostatic forces dominate the binding.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">The greatest advantage of DFT methods is that they are fast enough to allow the use of big basis sets even for large molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">This is very important for folded molecules because it minimizes the basis set superposition error usually favoring folded molecules energetically.</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">DFT calculations have been performed with the Gaussian 98 program.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27">27</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The basis sets 3-21G, 6-31+G* and 6-311++G** were used.</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The large basis set 6-311++G** was applied for neutral cGW to especially account for diffuse electron distributions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">By increasing the basis set from 3-21G to 6-31+G* we observe big changes in the relative conformer energies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">A saturation effect occurs when increasing the basis set from 6-31+G* to 6-311++G** (Table 1) which might be due to accidental error compensation for the smaller basis set.</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="New" advantage="None">We also calculated vibrational frequencies (B3LYP/6-31+G*) for the neutral conformers 1, 2 and 3 which are needed for calculating the Gibbs free energy and also used for a tentative vibrational assignment in section IV.2.</annotationART></s></P><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>The conformers of neutral cGW</HEADER><P><s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa4" novelty="None" advantage="None">To find the local minima the conformational landscape of cGW has been explored using the program Tinker.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28">28</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">It performs a general conformational search for the entire potential energy surface by using a hopping algorithm<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29">29</REF> which is able to overcome barriers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The program Tinker also minimizes each conformer after its generation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">The chosen MM3 force field<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30">30</REF> is known to be quite successful in reproducing molecular IR spectra.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="New" advantage="None">In order to make sure we do not miss a conformer, in addition also a potential energy surface scan was performed using the OPLS all atom force field.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit31">31</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="New" advantage="None">The results from the both scans were collected and the conformers processed with B3LYP by stepwise increasing the basis set size.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">For discussions of the type of conformers of cGW in Fig. 2a the relevant rotational axes and the resultant structural possibilities are shown.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The conformers of cGW can be classified as follows: The peptide ring can be moved into three positions when rotating about the C<SB>1</SB>–C<SB>2</SB> axis (Fig. 2a, right side, see also atomic numbering C<SB>0</SB>–C<SB>2</SB>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">For each of these conformers the indole ring then can be switched into six positions by rotation around the C<SB>0</SB>–C<SB>1</SB> axis (Fig. 2b, left side).</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">This gives theoretically 18 conformers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The most stable conformers are formed by rotating the C<SB>1</SB>–C<SB>2</SB> axis into the plane which is perpendicular to the indole ring (perpendicular conformer class).</annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The other tilted conformers are sterically unfavoured or unstable.</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">By our calculations 8 stable conformers have been found for neutral cGW.</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The calculated relative energies with respect to the lowest conformer are presented in Table 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">A full geometry optimization of the neutral conformers was performed by using the B3LYP/6-311++G** method.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The calculations show that the peptide ring (cyclic(glycylglycyl) or 2,5-piperazinedione) is not planar resulting in a double well potential (see Fig. 2b).</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the unperturbed cyclic(glycylglycyl) the minima are equal in energy and the barrier is expected to be low because of the high flexibility between the amide groups described in biochemical text books.</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In cGW this double well is superimposed with a ring-to-ring interaction potential (schematic drawing in Fig. 2b).</annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Depending on the size and steepness of this ring-to-ring interaction potential, for each of the above-mentioned conformers either two sub-conformers a and b (this is the case for conformers 1 and 3), or only one conformer (a or b for conformers 2, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8) exist.</annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The peptide-ring sub-conformers are very similar in energy (energy difference 41 cm<SP>−1</SP> for conformers 1a and 1b, and 18 cm<SP>−1</SP> for conformers 3a and 3b, see Table 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The calculated isomerization barrier (B3LYP/6-31+G*) from conformer 1b to conformer 1a is 2 cm<SP>−1</SP> and already the zero point vibration would be above the barrier.</annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The same is expected for conformers 3a and 3b for which the energetic difference is even smaller.</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The accuracy of the reaction barrier calculation is not known.</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, even if the isomerization barrier between the a and the b forms would be larger than 2 cm<SP>−1</SP> but lower than 300 cm<SP>−1</SP>, the more unstable form would be converted to the lower conformer in the supersonic expansion.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit32">32</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the following we assume that conformers 1b and 3b are experimentally not observable.</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is evident, however, that the resulting broad and anharmonic potential strongly reduces the vibrational frequencies in this coordinate, increases the vibrational density and by this favors these conformers on the Gibbs free energy landscape.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">In Table 1 the results of the B3LYP density functional calculations of the 8 stable neutral conformers of the dipeptide cGW (see also a and b conformers) using the 3-21G, 6-31+G* and 6-311++G** basis sets are presented.</annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Relative conformer energies are given in cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The four lowest structures are shown in Fig. 3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None">With the increase of the basis set from 3-21G to 6-31+G* the energetic order of some conformers changes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None">When increasing the basis set from 6-31+G* to 6-311++G** the conformer order is conserved and the changes in the relative conformer energies become small, which might be due to an error compensation for the smaller basis set.</annotationART></s> <s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">As discussed above, structures 1b and 3b are not stable by zero point vibration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Conformer 2 which is characterized by a C–H⋯π interaction has a relative energy of 194 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Conformer 3a which is similar to conformer 1a but with the indole ring switched by 180° lies 355 cm<SP>−1</SP> above 1a.</annotationART></s> <s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs20" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this conformer the N–H group seems to have better access to the indole π system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fact that it is less stable than conformer 1a is attributed to a positive partial charge on the carbon in position 4.</annotationART></s> <s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Only conformers with relative energies well below 365 cm<SP>−1</SP> (∼ <IT>kT</IT> at 525 K) are expected to have measurable populations in the beam.</annotationART></s> <s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This also holds for conformer 2 but not for conformer 3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">To calculate the exact thermal population beside the energy difference of the electronic energies also the vibrational zero point energy and the vibrational density of states has to be considered.</annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Assuming harmonic potentials all this would be included in the Gibbs free energy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs21" novelty="None" advantage="None">For a temperature of 300 K it shows an increase of the energetic spacing between conformer 1 and 2 from 355 cm<SP>−1</SP> to 675 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">This energy difference is expected to further increase when the strong anharmonicity of the inversion coordinate in conformer 1 would be taken into account.</annotationART></s> <s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hence from theory we predict that a great entropy effect is forcing the dipeptide population into conformer 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The high energy of conformer 3 (355 cm<SP>−1</SP>) above conformer 1 should result in a marginal or vanishing population of conformer 3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac20" novelty="None" advantage="None">Comparing conformer 1 and 3 the entropy argument is not helpful because also conformer 3 has a broad double minimum in the peptide ring inversion coordinate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac21" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is well known that barriers lower than 300 cm<SP>−1</SP> can be overcome during the supersonic jet expansion.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit32">32</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac22" novelty="None" advantage="None">To compare theoretical data to the experimental data it would be important to calculate the barrier heights between conformers 2 and 1 as well as 3 and 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="New" advantage="No">Unfortunately, because of the complexity of the coordinates and the size of the system, it is impossible to calculate such isomerization barriers.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>The cGW cation</HEADER><P><s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">We calculated vertical (6-311++G** basis set) and adiabatic (3-21G and 6-31+G* basis sets) IEs for comparison with the PE results in the hope to be able to assign the structure of the observed conformer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The cation geometry optimization was performed with the 3-21G basis set for all 8 conformers, and with the 6-31+G* basis set for seven conformers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="143"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The B3LYP/6-31+G* calculation for conformer 7 did not converge presumably because the potential surface is very flat.</annotationART></s> <s sid="144"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs22" novelty="None" advantage="None">We checked the dependence of the cation structural changes on the basis set, but found that the 3-21G structures are very similar to the structures found with the 6-31+G* basis set.</annotationART></s> <s sid="145"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs22" novelty="None" advantage="None">The calculated data are collected in Table 2 and the comparison of neutral and cation structures is shown in Fig. 4.</annotationART></s> <s sid="146"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac23" novelty="None" advantage="None">We also calculated the vertical IEs of the b conformers of structures 1 and 3, although it is clear that they are not populated due to their low isomerization barriers (see above).</annotationART></s> <s sid="147"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs23" novelty="None" advantage="None">The differences between the vertical IEs of conformers a and b nevertheless give hints as to how steep the ion ground state potential at the vertical geometry might be.</annotationART></s> <s sid="148"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">When optimizing the geometry in the cation ground state the sub-conformers a and b formed by the peptide ring inversion converge for conformers 1a and 1b as well as 3a and 3b to a single minimum.</annotationART></s> <s sid="149"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is explained by a large repulsive peptide ring-to-indole ring interaction in the cation which forces the system into one minimum.</annotationART></s> <s sid="150"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">A calculation of the geometrical average of the changes of all atomic coordinates between neutral and cation (termed RMS value in Table 2) shows that, except one conformer, all conformers undergo large structural changes upon ionization.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="151"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs24" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 4 shows the neutral-to-cation geometry changes of conformers 1, 2 and 6.</annotationART></s> <s sid="152"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">For this the neutral and the cation structure are overlaid with the indole ring and conformational changes indicated by arrows and lines.</annotationART></s> <s sid="153"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">In all cases the structural changes are so large that it might be difficult to reach the adiabatic IE.</annotationART></s> <s sid="154"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">For conformers 1, 2 (Fig. 4a,b) and 3 (not shown) the large geometry change is explained by the difference between the attractive (neutral) <IT>versus</IT> the repulsive (cation) N–H⋯π (conformers 1 and 3) or C–H⋯π (conformer 2) interaction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="155"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs25" novelty="None" advantage="None">In Fig. 4c the neutral and the cationic structures of conformer 6, the most stable cation conformer, are compared.</annotationART></s> <s sid="156"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs25" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this conformer the CO group (note the negative partial charge on O) has access to the indole chromophore.</annotationART></s> <s sid="157"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Whereas conformer 6 is rather unstable in the neutral due to the repulsive CO⋯π interaction it becomes the most stable conformer when the π system is positively charged.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="IV">Experimental results and discussion</HEADER><P><s sid="158"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac24" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the following we present R2PI mass, R2PI S<SB>0</SB>–S<SB>1</SB>, UV/UV SHB and R(1 + 1′)PI PE spectra of the dipeptide cGW.</annotationART></s></P><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="IV.1">The R2PI mass spectrum</HEADER><P><s sid="159"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">For recording the R2PI mass spectrum of cGW (Fig. 5) the second harmonic of a Nd:YAG laser-pumped dye laser was tuned to the S<SB>0</SB>–S<SB>1</SB> origin transition.</annotationART></s> <s sid="160"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The mass spectrum was recorded by using the PE spectrometer as flight tube for the linTOF.</annotationART></s> <s sid="161"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs26" novelty="None" advantage="None">Mass 234 Da corresponds to the parent radical cation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="162"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs26" novelty="None" advantage="None">Two fragments with masses 131 Da and 117 Da are observed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="163"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">These masses correspond to the neutral fragments 3-methylindole (131 Da) and indole (117 Da) which are then ionized by the laser pulse.</annotationART></s> <s sid="164"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of a cationic fragmentation of tryptophan instead of mass 117 Da mass 130 Da would be expected as the most intense fragment.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit33">33</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="165"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs27" novelty="None" advantage="None">Measurements with different laser intensities and wavelengths confirm that both masses are neutral fragments containing the indole chromophore.</annotationART></s> <s sid="166"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ionization of the neutral fragments is a minor contribution in the mass spectrum at low photon energies but increases when coming closer to the indole S<SB>0</SB>–S<SB>1</SB> resonance.</annotationART></s> <s sid="167"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Because of the mass selection there should be no influence of the fragment ionization on the R2PI spectrum of cGW.</annotationART></s> <s sid="168"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs28" novelty="None" advantage="None">Nevertheless we find a small peak in the cGW spectrum at exactly the energy of the S<SB>0</SB>–S<SB>1</SB> origin transition of indole which does not show the usual a<SP>1</SP> and b<SP>1</SP> progressions of cGW transitions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="169"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None">We believe that this peak is due to an intermolecular charge transfer (CT) effect where after ionization the charge hops from indole to the cGW which has the lower IE.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="IV.2">Mass selective R2PI spectroscopy: the S<SB>0</SB>–S<SB>1</SB> transition</HEADER><P><s sid="170"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">To record the R2PI spectrum of cGW the second harmonic of a Nd:YAG laser-pumped dye laser was tuned and the intensity of the parent ion monitored as a function of the wavelength.</annotationART></s> <s sid="171"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs29" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the R2PI spectrum shown in Fig. 6 an intense first transition is followed by several transitions which have decreasing intensities with increasing energy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="172"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The spacing is not regular which may be a hint for the presence of several conformers in the beam.</annotationART></s> <s sid="173"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">UV/UV SHB spectroscopy proves (see section III.3) that this is not the case: All intense transitions correspond to one single conformer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="174"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac25" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the following we make use of this information and assign transitions a<SP>1</SP>, b<SP>1</SP>, c<SP>1</SP>, d<SP>1</SP> and presumably Y to vibrations of this conformer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="175"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac26" novelty="None" advantage="None">A tentative conformer identification has been made in section IV.4.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="176"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The R2PI spectrum of cGW shown in Fig. 6 covers 450 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="177"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs30" novelty="None" advantage="None">No transitions were observed below 35 000 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="178"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Above 35 300 cm<SP>−1</SP> the indole vibrations and their many combination bands with vibrations a, b, c and d are expected.</annotationART></s> <s sid="179"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The justification to confine our investigation to a range of 450 cm<SP>−1</SP> is, that the four most stable calculated conformers have an attractive peptide ring-to-indole ring interaction and therefore should have similar S<SB>0</SB>–S<SB>1</SB> origin energies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="180"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs31" novelty="None" advantage="None">The S<SB>0</SB>–S<SB>1</SB> origin transition of cGW is situated at 35 058 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="181"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac27" novelty="None" advantage="None">It lies 180 cm<SP>−1</SP> below the S<SB>0</SB>–S<SB>1</SB> transition of indole<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit34">34</REF> and 178 cm<SP>−1</SP> above the S<SB>0</SB>–S<SB>1</SB> transition of 3-methylindole.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit35">35</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="182"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The S<SB>1</SB> energy in cGW is expected to be influenced by three parameters: (i) The electronic effect caused by the increase of the side chain of indole from 3-methylindole to cGW, (ii) the solvation of indole by the dipeptide ring and (iii) vibrational zero point energy effects.</annotationART></s> <s sid="183"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Concerning (i) we expect in analogy to the alkylbenzene series (relative shift with respect to methylbenzene: +110 cm<SP>−1</SP> for ethylbenzene, +105 cm<SP>−1</SP> for propylbenzene, +99 cm<SP>−1</SP> for butylbenzene<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit36">36</REF>) a blue shift in comparison to 3-methylindole when increasing the chain size.</annotationART></s> <s sid="184"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Concerning (ii): In a structure where the N–H group can interact with the indole π system (see most stable conformer 1 in Fig. 2a), a red shift of the S<SB>0</SB>–S<SB>1</SB> transition is expected when the π system is excited, <IT>i.e.</IT> enlarged,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF> because the N–H⋯π interaction is stabilized further.</annotationART></s> <s sid="185"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp9" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, (iii) this shift may be partially compensated by a change in the zero point vibrational energy if some vibrations increase strongly with the excitation to S<SB>1</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="186"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac28" novelty="None" advantage="None">Interestingly the origin of S<SB>1</SB> in cGW lies 353 cm<SP>−1</SP> above the S<SB>1</SB> of the lowest and 163 cm<SP>−1</SP> above the second conformer of linear NH<SB>2</SB>–G–W–COOH.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6 cit8">5,6,8</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="187"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fact that our red-shift is not as strong as in linear peptides may be interpreted as follows: The peptide ring formation forces the functional groups CO and N–H of the peptide backbone into positions which do not allow ideal solvation of the indole ring.</annotationART></s> <s sid="188"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac29" novelty="None" advantage="None">This lengthy discussion shows how difficult it is to interpret the tryptophan S<SB>0</SB>–S<SB>1</SB> absorption in peptides with regard to structural changes of the environment.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="189"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The relatively intense transitions to one quantum of the low-frequency modes a<SP>1</SP> (30 cm<SP>−1</SP>) and b<SP>1</SP> (52 cm<SP>−1</SP>) indicate some S<SB>0</SB>–S<SB>1</SB> geometry change in the corresponding coordinates.</annotationART></s> <s sid="190"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs32" novelty="None" advantage="None">Interestingly the transition a<SP>2</SP> is not observed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="191"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs32" novelty="None" advantage="None">Only the combination band a<SP>1</SP>b<SP>1</SP> and tentatively a small transition b<SP>2</SP> is observed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="192"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Because the intense indole vibrations lie above 300 cm<SP>−1</SP>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit34">34</REF> the vibrations a, b, c (108 cm<SP>−1</SP>) and d (174 cm<SP>−1</SP>) are attributed to vibrations involving a relative motion between the two rings.</annotationART></s> <s sid="193"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs33" novelty="None" advantage="None">For conformer 1a the frequency calculation of the neutral ground state gives the following vibrations below 90 cm<SP>−1</SP>: 21 cm<SP>−1</SP> (global ring–ring bending), 39 cm<SP>−1</SP> (ring–ring torsion along C<SB>1</SB>–C<SB>2</SB>), 51 cm<SP>−1</SP> (boat to inverse boat motion in the peptide ring) and 59 cm<SP>−1</SP> (higher order bending of the peptide ring, the angle at C<SB>0</SB>–C<SB>1</SB>–C<SB>2</SB> and the indole ring).</annotationART></s> <s sid="194"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The frequency of 51 cm<SP>−1</SP> for the ring inversion mode is an artefact of the harmonic potential approximation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="195"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Because of the small energy difference of 41 cm<SP>−1</SP> between conformers 1a and 1b, at the energy of the first vibrational quantum the real potential width is much broader as assumed by the harmonic approximation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="196"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">This should lead to a very low experimental frequency.</annotationART></s> <s sid="197"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Excitation of this motion would, however, only be expected if the peptide ring would have a strong coupling to the indole ring, which is not expected.</annotationART></s> <s sid="198"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac30" novelty="None" advantage="None">For a tentative assignment of the vibration in S<SB>1</SB> we therefore only take the global ring–ring vibrations into account.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="199"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac30" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ring–ring interaction in the lowest-energetic conformer 1 is attractive.</annotationART></s> <s sid="200"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp12" novelty="None" advantage="None">One can expect that this attraction increases in the S<SB>1</SB> state due to the increase of the size of the π system upon excitation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="201"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp12" novelty="None" advantage="None">As a consequence the frequencies of the ring–ring motions would increase.</annotationART></s> <s sid="202"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hence the S<SB>0</SB> vibrations with the energy 21 cm<SP>−1</SP> and 39 cm<SP>−1</SP> might correspond to the S<SB>1</SB> vibrations a<SP>1</SP> and b<SP>1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="203"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The type of these vibrational motions also agrees with the concept that the N–H⋯π interaction changes when exciting from S<SB>0</SB> to S<SB>1</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="204"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac31" novelty="None" advantage="None">The S<SB>1</SB> vibrations observed in the S<SB>0</SB>–S<SB>1</SB> spectra of linear NH<SB>2</SB>–G–W–COOH are 24 cm<SP>−1</SP> and 38 cm<SP>−1</SP> and not too far off our values although the structures are very different.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6 cit8">5,6,8</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="205"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp14" novelty="None" advantage="None">This indicates that the first two or three low-frequency vibrations of all similar-sized chromophore–tail molecules lie in the range of 20–50 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="206"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs34" novelty="None" advantage="None">For conformer 2 for example the first three calculated S<SB>0</SB> vibrational frequencies are with 26 cm<SP>−1</SP>, 41 cm<SP>−1</SP> and 56 cm<SP>−1</SP> very similar to those of conformer 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="207"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hence the S<SB>0</SB> frequencies provide no arguments for conformer assignment.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="208"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The S<SB>0</SB>–S<SB>1</SB> R2PI spectrum was recorded with 5 bar Ar nozzle backpressure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="209"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs35" novelty="None" advantage="None">Experiments with He and Ne as carrier gas resulted in less perfect vibrationally cooling.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="IV.3">Spectral UV/UV hole burning spectroscopy (UV/UV SHB)</HEADER><P><s sid="210"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa5" novelty="None" advantage="None">To clarify the number of conformers in our molecular beam, we used R2PI UV/UV SHB.</annotationART></s> <s sid="211"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="New" advantage="None">As mentioned in the experimental section, for the SHB a three-plate ion optics was mounted and the PE spectrometer used as a linTOF mass spectrometer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="212"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac32" novelty="None" advantage="None">This setup was needed in order to remove and neutralize the prompt ions formed by the hole burning laser by applying a pulsed electric field.</annotationART></s> <s sid="213"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="New" advantage="None">The spectrum was recorded by scanning the hole burning laser while the probe laser was set to the S<SB>0</SB>–S<SB>1</SB> origin transition.</annotationART></s> <s sid="214"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs36" novelty="None" advantage="None">Each time when the neutral ground state of the cGW conformer was depopulated by the hole burning laser a dip appeared in the probe laser parent ion signal.</annotationART></s> <s sid="215"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="New" advantage="None">Note that with this scheme the transition moments of the individual peaks determine the depth of the SHB dip.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="216"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs37" novelty="None" advantage="None">In Fig. 7a the UV/UV SHB spectrum of cGW and in (b) for comparison the R2PI spectrum are shown.</annotationART></s> <s sid="217"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp15" novelty="None" advantage="None">We confined our investigation on the low-energetic section of the R2PI spectrum of cGW because (i) it contains the most intense transitions and (ii) the lowest-energetic four conformers are expected to lie in this range because of their similar peptide ring-to-indole ring interaction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="218"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">In Fig. 7a all transitions except E show a strong hole burning effect and hence correspond to one conformer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="219"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa6" novelty="None" advantage="None">To investigate the hole burning for transition E in detail, but also to probe accidental overlap of conformer transitions, we carefully checked the degree of hole burning for each transition.</annotationART></s> <s sid="220"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs38" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 8 shows the degree of depletion of the probe signal by the hole burning laser for the first six transitions of the R2PI spectrum.</annotationART></s> <s sid="221"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="New" advantage="None">The conditions have been the same as for Fig. 7a, except that now the hole burning laser is kept fix at transition A and the probe laser is scanned to the individual transitions A-F.</annotationART></s> <s sid="222"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac33" novelty="None" advantage="None">With this scheme the depletion percentage should be the same for all transitions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="223"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="New" advantage="None">The transition intensities recorded with the probe laser have been measured with the hole burning laser “off” (left trace) and “on” (right trace).</annotationART></s> <s sid="224"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="New" advantage="None">For each “off” and “on” sequence of each transition 15 measurements (each averaged over 20 laser shots) are displayed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="225"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs39" novelty="None" advantage="None">The hole burning reduces the probe signal by 50% for all transitions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="226"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">This shows that no origin transition of a minor conformer component is accidentally covered by a vibronic transition of the most stable conformer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="227"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac34" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that theoretically more than 50% of the neutral ground state levels can be depopulated<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit37">37</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="IV.4">Photoelectron spectroscopy</HEADER><P><s sid="228"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Photoelectron spectroscopy is in principle a double-resonance spectroscopy which is able to provide conformer- and state-selective radical cation spectra.</annotationART></s> <s sid="229"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The initial hope was that we could sort out and assign the different conformers of cGW by PE spectroscopy alone.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="230"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac35" novelty="None" advantage="None">To achieve a resolution of 1 meV it is necessary to keep the electron kinetic energy below 200 meV.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit38">38</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="231"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">To fulfil this condition a second frequency-doubled dye laser which is pumped by the second harmonic of the same Nd:YAG laser was used for ionization of excited S<SB>1</SB> cGW.</annotationART></s> <s sid="232"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs40" novelty="None" advantage="None">The R2PI PE spectra of cGW ionized <IT>via</IT> the vibrationless origin transition of S<SB>1</SB> and the transition S<SB>1</SB> a<SP>1</SP> are shown in Fig. 9a and b.</annotationART></s> <s sid="233"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs40" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both spectra show a broad ionization onset with no vibrational structure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="234"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None">According to the calculations of the neutral and cation structures which show a great geometry change upon ionization (Fig. 4a) we believe that we do not observe the origin transition to the cation ground state, but excite to a dense higher excited vibrational manifold.</annotationART></s> <s sid="235"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac36" novelty="None" advantage="None">Due to the smooth onset the IE can only be determined with an accuracy of ±3 meV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="236"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fact that the ionization onset <IT>via</IT> the S<SB>1</SB>a<SP>1</SP> state is 6 cm<SP>−1</SP> lower than when ionized <IT>via</IT> the S<SB>1</SB> 000 state (7.715 eV ±3 meV) is attributed to a better Franck–Condon factor to lower vibrational quantum numbers in the cation ground state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="237"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">The PE spectrum of indole (Fig. 9c) taken in the same machine shows that we could resolve vibrational structures if their spacing were larger than 10 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="238"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac37" novelty="None" advantage="None">The vibrations of the indole cation ground state have been recently investigated in detail by ZEKE spectroscopy<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit39">39</REF> and are not discussed here.</annotationART></s> <s sid="239"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="New" advantage="None">The IE value of indole determined by ZEKE spectroscopy allows us to calibrate our indole and cGW PE spectra with an accuracy of ±2 meV.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="240"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs41" novelty="None" advantage="None">Unfortunately there is a background in the peptide PE spectra which stems from ionization of neutral fragments, preferentially indole, which is wavelength-dependent.</annotationART></s> <s sid="241"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs41" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is small for the wavelength range of the first two S<SB>1</SB> transitions of cGW, but increases as the closer the wavelength comes to the indole S<SB>0</SB>–S<SB>1</SB> origin.</annotationART></s> <s sid="242"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Without coincidence techniques it is in principle impossible to distinguish between fragment and peptide photoelectrons.</annotationART></s> <s sid="243"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="New" advantage="None">We therefore confined our PE measurements to the first two S<SB>0</SB>–S<SB>1</SB> transitions.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="244"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs42" novelty="None" advantage="None">In Fig. 9 the IE of 3-methylindole (7.514 eV<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit40">40</REF>) is also marked.</annotationART></s> <s sid="245"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac38" novelty="None" advantage="None">The IEs of substituted indoles should monotonically decrease with chain length (alkylbenzene<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit41">41</REF>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="246"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fact that with respect to 3-methylindole the IE of cGW is blue-shifted and the smooth onset indicates a relatively strong repulsive interaction between the two rings in the cation, as predicted by theory.</annotationART></s> <s sid="247"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">Unfortunately the calculation of absolute IEs is relatively inaccurate and the measured IE corresponds neither directly to the calculated adiabatic IE nor the vertical IE.</annotationART></s> <s sid="248"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fact that conformer 1 has the highest IE of all conformers agrees well with the observed blue shift with respect to 3-methylindole.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="V">Conclusion and tentative conformer assignment</HEADER><P><s sid="249"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">DFT predicts that one conformer (conformer 1) is predominantly stable and further favoured by entropy due to a low-energy peptide ring inversion mode.</annotationART></s> <s sid="250"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is qualitatively in agreement with our R2PI and R2PI SHB spectra in which we attribute the most intense transition in the spectra to one conformer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="251"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">In conformer 1 the N–H group of the dipeptide ring interacts with the π system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="252"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp18" novelty="None" advantage="None">This interaction is attractive and is expected to increase with S<SB>1</SB> excitation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="253"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is qualitatively confirmed by comparison to the calculated low-frequency S<SB>0</SB> vibrations.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="254"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fact that the experimentally observed conformer has an IE which is 195 meV higher than 3-methylindole shows that the solvation of the charge in the indole by the peptide ring is repulsive.</annotationART></s> <s sid="255"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The most stable neutral conformer has the highest vertical IE of all 8 conformers and shows a very strong geometry change upon ionization.</annotationART></s> <s sid="256"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hence conformer 1 fulfils all experimental findings.</annotationART></s> <s sid="257"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac39" novelty="None" advantage="None">We admit that also conformer 2 and 3 follow the pattern of a attractive ring–ring interaction in the neutral cGW and a repulsive ring–ring interaction in the cationic cGW and that our arguments for the conformer assignment are very weak.</annotationART></s> <s sid="258"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac40" novelty="None" advantage="None">For a confident conformer assignment it would be helpful to have several conformers in the molecular beam and be able to compare their IEs.</annotationART></s> <s sid="259"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac40" novelty="None" advantage="None">Because the relative energies of calculated IEs are more accurate this would allow a more confident assignment.</annotationART></s> <s sid="260"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In conclusion, we propose that conformer 1 is the cGW conformer we observe in our molecular beam.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="261"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our work shows that R2PI and the R(1 + 1′)PI PE spectra predominantly provide information about the structural changes in the nearest environment of the chromophore.</annotationART></s> <s sid="262"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con16" novelty="None" advantage="None">In cGW, however, the structural changes upon ionization are so great that with conventional high resolution PES a resolution of vibrational structures in the PE spectrum is impossible.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="263"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con17" novelty="None" advantage="None">In general a similar neutral-to-cation Franck–Condon problem might exist for peptides or amino acids which have polar groups near the chromophore.</annotationART></s> <s sid="264"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The IR/UV double resonance technique may provide additional clues for conformer identification and especially allow us to distinguish between conformers 1 (N–H⋯π interaction) and 2 (C–H⋯π interaction).</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
