<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b400243a" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Temperature-dependent kinetics study of the reactions of O(<SP>1</SP>D<SB>2</SB>) with N<SB>2</SB> and O<SB>2</SB></annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">A laser flash photolysis–resonance fluorescence technique has been employed to investigate the kinetics of the reactions of electronically excited oxygen atoms, O(<SP>1</SP>D<SB>2</SB>), with N<SB>2</SB> (<IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB>) and O<SB>2</SB> (<IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB>) as a function of temperature (197–427 K) in helium buffer gas at pressures of 11–40 Torr.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results are well-described by the following Arrhenius expressions (units are 10<SP>−11</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>): <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB>(<IT>T</IT>) = (1.99 ± 0.06) exp{(145 ± 9)/T} and <IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB>(<IT>T</IT>) = (3.39 ± 0.03) exp{(63 ± 3)/T}.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Uncertainties in the Arrhenius parameters are 2<IT>σ</IT> and represent precision only; estimated accuracies of reported <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB>(<IT>T</IT>) and <IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB>(<IT>T</IT>) values at the 95% confidence level are ±10% around room temperature and ±15% at the temperature extremes of the study.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The O(<SP>1</SP>D<SB>2</SB>) + O<SB>2</SB> kinetic data reported in this study are in very good agreement with available literature values.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the kinetic data reported in this study (and two other new studies reported in this issue) suggest that the O(<SP>1</SP>D<SB>2</SB>) + N<SB>2</SB> reaction is significantly faster than previously thought, a finding that has important implications regarding production rates of tropospheric HO<SB><IT>x</IT></SB> radicals as well as stratospheric HO<SB><IT>x</IT></SB> and NO<SB><IT>x</IT></SB> radicals calculated in atmospheric models.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Atomic oxygen in its lowest-energy excited electronic state, O(<SP>1</SP>D<SB>2</SB>), is an important reactive intermediate in atmospheric chemistry.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Production of O(<SP>1</SP>D<SB>2</SB>) in the atmosphere occurs primarily <IT>via</IT> ultraviolet photodissociation of ozone,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">2</REF> and O(<SP>1</SP>D<SB>2</SB>) is rapidly destroyed <IT>via</IT> reaction with N<SB>2</SB> and O<SB>2</SB>, the two most abundant atmospheric constituents: O(<SP>1</SP>D<SB>2</SB>) + N<SB>2</SB> → O(<SP>3</SP>P<SB><IT>J</IT></SB>) + N<SB>2</SB>O(<SP>1</SP>D<SB>2</SB>) + O<SB>2</SB> → O(<SP>3</SP>P<SB><IT>J</IT></SB>) + O<SB>2</SB> In competition with reactions (1) and (2), a small fraction of atmospheric O(<SP>1</SP>D<SB>2</SB>) atoms are destroyed <IT>via</IT> interaction with atmospheric trace gases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Of particular importance are the following chemical reactions: O(<SP>1</SP>D<SB>2</SB>) + H<SB>2</SB>O → 2 OHO(<SP>1</SP>D<SB>2</SB>) + N<SB>2</SB>O → 2 NOO(<SP>1</SP>D<SB>2</SB>) + N<SB>2</SB>O → N<SB>2</SB> + O<SB>2</SB>Reaction (3) is the single most important primary source of HO<SB><IT>x</IT></SB> radicals in the troposphere while reaction (4a) is the dominant primary source of NO<SB><IT>x</IT></SB> radicals in the stratosphere.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Assuming that atmospheric destruction of O(<SP>1</SP>D<SB>2</SB>) is completely dominated by reactions (1) and (2) (reaction (3) can actually make a small but significant contribution under humid lower tropospheric conditions), eqns. (I) and (II) can be readily derived to represent the production rates of tropospheric HO<SB><IT>x</IT></SB> and stratospheric NO<SB><IT>x</IT></SB>, respectively: d[HO<SB><IT>x</IT></SB>]/d<IT>t</IT> = 2<IT>J</IT>[O<SB>3</SB>]<IT>k</IT><SB>3</SB>[H<SB>2</SB>O]/(<IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB>[N<SB>2</SB>] + <IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB>[O<SB>2</SB>])d[NO<SB><IT>x</IT></SB>]/d<IT>t</IT> = 2<IT>J</IT>[O<SB>3</SB>]<IT>k</IT><SB>4a</SB>[N<SB>2</SB>O]/(<IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB>[N<SB>2</SB>] + <IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB>[O<SB>2</SB>])In the above equations, <IT>J</IT> represents the first order rate coefficient for production of atmospheric O(<SP>1</SP>D<SB>2</SB>) <IT>via</IT> O<SB>3</SB> photodissociation, <IT>i.e.</IT>, d[O(<SP>1</SP>D<SB>2</SB>)]/d<IT>t</IT> = <IT>J</IT>[O<SB>3</SB>].</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Clearly, accurate evaluation of the above production rates requires accurate rate coefficients for reactions (1) and (2) over the range of temperatures encountered in the troposphere and stratosphere.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Arrhenius parameters for <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB>(<IT>T</IT>) and <IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB>(<IT>T</IT>) used in models of atmospheric chemistry are those recommended by the NASA<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF> and IUPAC<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF> panels for chemical kinetic and photochemical data evaluation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In units of 10<SP>−11</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>, the Arrhenius expressions currently recommended by the NASA panel are <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB>(<IT>T</IT>) = 1.8 exp(110/T) and <IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB>(<IT>T</IT>) = 3.2 exp(70/T) while the expressions recommended by the IUPAC panel are <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB>(<IT>T</IT>) = 1.8 exp(107/T) and <IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB>(<IT>T</IT>) = 3.2 exp(67/T).</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The recommended room temperature rate coefficients are based almost entirely on experimental work carried out more than twenty years ago,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6 cit7 cit8">5–8</REF> and the recommended activation energies are based on a single temperature dependent study.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">While the earlier experimental work was at the state-of-the-art for its time, the accuracy of reported results was somewhat limited by available technology and, as a result, uncertainties in the recommended rate coefficients are undesirably high, <IT>i.e.</IT>, about 20% at 298 K and over 40% at 200 K at the 67% confidence level.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3 cit4">3,4</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Over the years, the ability of the atmospheric field measurement community to accurately determine the concentrations of reactive free radicals has evolved to the point where detailed comparisons of field data with photochemical models is limited by the accuracy of rate coefficients for key reactions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">For this reason, new kinetics studies of important atmospheric processes (like reactions (1) and (2)) that focus on high accuracy are needed.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">While studying a variety of O(<SP>1</SP>D<SB>2</SB>) reactions of atmospheric interest, three respected gas kinetics research groups have independently reinvestigated the temperature dependence of <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results of the three studies are in quite good agreement with each other, but suggest that <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB>(<IT>T</IT>) is significantly faster than suggested by previously available kinetic data.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3 cit4 cit5 cit6 cit7 cit8">3–8</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">To disseminate this important new result to the atmospheric chemistry community as rapidly as possible, a joint communication was recently published<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF> where the results of all three groups are summarized and recommendations concerning values for <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB>(<IT>T</IT>) that should be used in atmospheric models are presented.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this paper and two companion papers,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11 cit12">11,12</REF> each of the three individual studies is presented in detail.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Also, presented in this paper are the results of a temperature dependent kinetics study of reaction (2).</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Experimental technique</HEADER><P><s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The experimental approach is similar to one we have employed in several previous studies of O(<SP>1</SP>D<SB>2</SB>) reactions of atmospheric interest,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7 cit13 cit14 cit15 cit16 cit17 cit18">7,13–18</REF> although the data acquisition and analysis methods are improved over those employed in all but the most recent studies.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17 cit18">17,18</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The experiments involve time-resolved detection of ground state atomic oxygen, O(<SP>3</SP>P<SB><IT>J</IT></SB>), by atomic resonance fluorescence spectroscopy following laser flash photolysis of O<SB>3</SB>/N<SB>2</SB>/O<SB>2</SB>/He mixtures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The O(<SP>3</SP>P<SB><IT>J</IT></SB>) atoms are produced with a small quantum yield <IT>via</IT> O<SB>3</SB> photodissociation,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13 cit20">13,20</REF> and with a large yield as a product of O(<SP>1</SP>D<SB>2</SB>) deactivation by the gases in the reaction mixture.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3 cit4">3,4</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">An apparatus diagram is published elsewhere.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19">19</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Some experimental details that are particularly relevant to this study are given below.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">A jacketed, Pyrex reaction cell with an internal volume of approximately 160 cm<SP>3</SP> was used in all experiments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The cell was maintained at a constant temperature (±2 K at the temperature extremes of the study) by circulating either ethylene glycol (for <IT>T</IT> &gt; 298 K) or 1∶1 ethanol-methanol (for <IT>T</IT> &lt; 298 K) through the outer jacket.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">O(<SP>1</SP>D<SB>2</SB>) atoms were produced by 248 nm or 266 nm laser flash photolysis of O<SB>3</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The source of 248 nm photons was a Lambda Physik model Compex 102 excimer laser operating with a KrF gas fill; the laser pulsewidth was ∼25 ns and the range of fluences employed was 24–32 mJ cm<SP>−2</SP> pulse<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The source of 266 nm photons was fourth harmonic radiation from a Quanta Ray Model DCR-2A Nd:YAG laser; the pulsewidth of this laser was ∼6 ns and the range of fluences employed was 12–32 mJ cm<SP>−2</SP> pulse<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">An atomic resonance lamp, situated perpendicular to the photolysis laser, excited ground state O(<SP>3</SP>P<SB><IT>J</IT></SB>) atoms in the reaction cell.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Radiation was coupled out of the lamp through a MgF<SB>2</SB> window and into the reaction cell through a MgF<SB>2</SB> lens.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Fluorescence was collected by a CaF<SB>2</SB> lens on the axis normal to both the photolysis laser beam and the resonance lamp beam and imaged onto the photocathode of a solar blind photomultiplier; the CaF<SB>2</SB> lens prevented impurity lamp emission of Lyman-α radiation from reaching the detector.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The regions between the resonance lamp and reactor and between the reactor and photomultiplier were purged with N<SB>2</SB> to prevent absorption of the atomic oxygen resonance radiation (130–131 nm) by atmospheric compounds such as O<SB>2</SB> and H<SB>2</SB>O. Signals were processed using photon-counting techniques in conjunction with multichannel scaling.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The multichannel scaler sweep was pre-triggered in order to allow a pre-flash baseline to be obtained.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">All experiments were carried out under “slow flow” conditions with a linear flow rate through the reactor of about 25 cm s<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the laser repetition rate was 10 Hz, the gas mixture within the detection volume was replenished between laser pulses.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Ozone, O<SB>2</SB>, N<SB>2</SB> (in most experiments), and zero air (low hydrocarbon impurity levels) were allowed to flow into the reaction cell from 12-L Pyrex bulbs containing dilute mixtures in helium buffer gas while helium was allowed to flow directly from its high-pressure storage tank.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In a few of the experiments designed to measure <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB>, the N<SB>2</SB> source was a high pressure cylinder containing a certified 3.15% UHP N<SB>2</SB> in UHP He mixture.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The concentrations of each component in the reaction mixture were determined from measurements of the appropriate mass flow rates and the total pressure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The mole fraction of ozone in its storage bulbs was checked frequently by UV photometry.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The monitoring wavelength for the photometric measurements was 253.7 nm (Hg line) and the room temperature O<SB>3</SB> absorption cross section that is needed to convert the measured absorbance to an O<SB>3</SB> concentration was taken to be 1.144 × 10<SP>−17</SP> cm<SP>2</SP>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20 cit21 cit22 cit23 cit24 cit25">20–25</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Research grade helium (&gt;99.9999% purity) was used as the buffer gas (the total pressure was 20 Torr in most experiments) and in the preparation of all gas mixtures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The stated minimum purities of the other gases were: N<SB>2</SB>, 99.999% and O<SB>2</SB>, 99.997%; these gases were used as supplied, although in some experiments the O<SB>2</SB>/He or N<SB>2</SB>/He mixture was passed through a glass-bead-filled liquid nitrogen trap during transit from the storage bulb to the reactor.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The zero air had a stated minimum purity of 99.997% and stated upper limit total hydrocarbon mole fraction of 0.001% it was used as supplied.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Ozone was prepared by passing O<SB>2</SB> through a commercial ozonizer; the O<SB>3</SB> was trapped on silica gel at 196 K and excess O<SB>2</SB> was removed by pumping.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Results and discussion</HEADER><P><s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">All experiments were carried out under pseudo-first-order conditions with O<SB>3</SB>, N<SB>2</SB>, O<SB>2</SB>, zero air, and of course, helium buffer gas in excess over oxygen atoms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In reaction mixtures containing, for example, O<SB>3</SB>, N<SB>2</SB>, and He, the processes that control the temporal evolution of O(<SP>3</SP>P<SB><IT>J</IT></SB>) are the following: O<SB>3</SB> + <IT>hν</IT> → O(<SP>3</SP>P<SB><IT>J</IT></SB>) + O<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> + <IT>hν</IT> → O(<SP>1</SP>D<SB>2</SB>) + O<SB>2</SB>O(<SP>1</SP>D<SB>2</SB>) + O<SB>3</SB> → O(<SP>3</SP>P<SB><IT>J</IT></SB>) + O<SB>3</SB>O(<SP>1</SP>D<SB>2</SB>) + O<SB>3</SB> → 2 O(<SP>3</SP>P<SB><IT>J</IT></SB>) + O<SB>2</SB>O(<SP>1</SP>D<SB>2</SB>) + O<SB>3</SB> → 2 O<SB>2</SB>O(<SP>1</SP>D<SB>2</SB>) + N<SB>2</SB> → O(<SP>3</SP>P<SB><IT>J</IT></SB>) + N<SB>2</SB> In the presence of O<SB>2</SB>, production of O(<SP>3</SP>P<SB><IT>J</IT></SB>) can also occur <IT>via</IT> the following (exothermic) processes:O(<SP>1</SP>D<SB>2</SB>) + O<SB>2</SB> → O(<SP>3</SP>P<SB><IT>J</IT></SB>) + O<SB>2</SB>(X <SP>3</SP>Σ<SB>g</SB><SP>−</SP>)O(<SP>1</SP>D<SB>2</SB>) + O<SB>2</SB> → O(<SP>3</SP>P<SB><IT>J</IT></SB>) + O<SB>2</SB>(a <SP>1</SP>Δ<SB>g</SB>)O(<SP>1</SP>D<SB>2</SB>) + O<SB>2</SB> → O(<SP>3</SP>P<SB><IT>J</IT></SB>) + O<SB>2</SB>(b <SP>1</SP>Σ+g)</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is well-established that the dominant pathway for reaction (1) is channel (1a).</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">At a pressure of one atmosphere the yield of N<SB>2</SB>O from reaction (1) is only ∼10<SP>−6</SP> while under the conditions of a majority of our experiments (20 Torr He buffer gas) the branching ratio for channel (1b) is less than 10<SP>−7</SP>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26">26</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Published studies of the mechanism of reaction (2) suggest that the branching ratio for channel (2c) is high (∼0.8)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27 cit28 cit29 cit30">27–30</REF> and the branching ratio for channel (2b) is low (≤0.05).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit31">31</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The temporal profile of the O(<SP>3</SP>P<SB><IT>J</IT></SB>) fluorescence following the laser flash is described by the following expression:<IT>S</IT><SB><IT>t</IT></SB> = {<IT>k</IT><SB>a</SB>/(<IT>k</IT><SB>d</SB> − <IT>k</IT><SB>a</SB>)}<IT>A</IT>{exp(−<IT>k</IT><SB>a</SB><IT>t</IT>) − exp(−<IT>k</IT><SB>d</SB><IT>t</IT>)} + <IT>B</IT>exp(−<IT>k</IT><SB>d</SB><IT>t</IT>)</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In eqn. (I), <IT>S</IT><SB><IT>t</IT></SB> is the fluorescence signal at time t after the laser flash, <IT>k</IT><SB>a</SB> is the pseudo-first order rate coefficient for O(<SP>3</SP>P<SB><IT>J</IT></SB>) appearance, <IT>k</IT><SB>d</SB> is the rate coefficient for O(<SP>3</SP>P<SB><IT>J</IT></SB>) decay (assumed to be first order), and the parameters <IT>A</IT> and <IT>B</IT> are related to the concentrations of O(<SP>1</SP>D<SB>2</SB>) and O(<SP>3</SP>P<SB><IT>J</IT></SB>) produced by the laser flash: <IT>A</IT> = <IT>CΦ</IT>[O(<SP>1</SP>D<SB>2</SB>)]<SB>0</SB><IT>B</IT> = <IT>C</IT>[O(<SP>3</SP>P<SB><IT>J</IT></SB>)]<SB>0</SB>In eqns. (II) and (III), <IT>C</IT> is a proportionality constant that relates the resonance fluorescence signal to the O(<SP>3</SP>P<SB><IT>J</IT></SB>) concentration and <IT>Φ</IT> is the number of O(<SP>3</SP>P<SB><IT>J</IT></SB>) produced per O(<SP>1</SP>D<SB>2</SB>) destroyed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">If (for example) the reaction mixture contains O<SB>3</SB>, He, and N<SB>2</SB>, then in eqn. (IV), <IT>k</IT>0a is the pseudo-first-order rate coefficient for O(<SP>3</SP>P<SB><IT>J</IT></SB>) appearance in the absence of N<SB>2</SB>.<IT>k</IT><SB>a</SB> = <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB>[N<SB>2</SB>] + <IT>k</IT>0aGround state oxygen atoms are unreactive toward He and N<SB>2</SB>, and react very slowly with O<SB>3</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hence, under the experimental conditions employed in this study, <IT>k</IT><SB>a</SB> ≫ <IT>k</IT><SB>d</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">As a result, the assumption that <IT>k</IT><SB>d</SB> is a first order rate coefficient, while not strictly correct, does not compromise the accuracy with which <IT>k</IT><SB>a</SB>, the parameter of interest, can be determined.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Some typical O(<SP>3</SP>P<SB><IT>J</IT></SB>) temporal profiles observed following laser flash photolysis of O<SB>3</SB>/N<SB>2</SB>/He mixtures are shown in Fig. 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="New" advantage="None">Bimolecular rate coefficients for the collisional removal of O(<SP>1</SP>D<SB>2</SB>) by N<SB>2</SB>, <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB>(<IT>T</IT>), are obtained from the variation of <IT>k</IT><SB>a</SB> with [N<SB>2</SB>] at constant concentrations of O<SB>3</SB> and He.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Typical data are shown in Fig. 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Similarly, values for <IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB>(<IT>T</IT>) are obtained from the variation of <IT>k</IT><SB>a</SB> with [O<SB>2</SB>] in experiments with [N<SB>2</SB>] = 0 and constant concentrations of O<SB>3</SB> and He.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results of all experiments carried out to evaluate <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB>(<IT>T</IT>) are summarized in Table 1 and the results of all experiments carried out to evaluate <IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB>(<IT>T</IT>) are summarized in Table 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Arrhenius plots for reactions (1) and (2) are shown in Fig. 3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The following Arrhenius expressions are derived from the data (units are cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>): <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB>(<IT>T</IT>) = (1.99 ± 0.06) × 10<SP>−11</SP> exp{(145 ± 9)/<IT>T</IT>}<IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB>(<IT>T</IT>) = (3.39 ± 0.03) × 10<SP>−11</SP> exp{(63 ± 3)/<IT>T</IT>}Uncertainties in the above expressions are 2<IT>σ</IT> and represent precision only.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">A discussion of possible systematic errors along with an estimate of the accuracy of reported rate coefficients is given below.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">One potentially important source of systematic error in elementary reaction kinetics studies is the occurrence of secondary reactions that are not accounted for properly in the data analysis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The photochemical system employed to study reaction (1) seems to be devoid of possible secondary reactions that could destroy or regenerate oxygen atoms on the time scale for O(<SP>3</SP>P<SB><IT>J</IT></SB>) production <IT>via</IT> reaction (1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, in the case of reaction (2), oxygen atoms can be regenerated <IT>via</IT> the reaction of the major molecular product, O<SB>2</SB>(b<SP>1</SP>Σ+g), with O<SB>3</SB>: O<SB>2</SB>(b<SP>1</SP>Σ+g) + O<SB>3</SB> → O(<SP>3</SP>P<SB><IT>J</IT></SB>) + 2 O<SB>2</SB>O<SB>2</SB>(b<SP>1</SP>Σ+g) + O<SB>3</SB> → other products</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is well-established that <IT>k</IT><SB>7</SB> ∼ 2.2 × 10<SP>−11</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7 cit8 cit29 cit32 cit33 cit34 cit35 cit36 cit37">7,8,29,32–37</REF> with little or no temperature dependence,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit36">36</REF> and that <IT>k</IT><SB>6a</SB>/<IT>k</IT><SB>6</SB> ≈ 0..7<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit33 cit34">33,34</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Because very low O<SB>3</SB> concentrations were employed in our study of reaction (2) (Table 2), the pseudo-first-order rate coefficient for O(<SP>3</SP>P<SB><IT>J</IT></SB>) formation (<IT>via</IT> reaction (2)) exceeded the pseudo-first-order rate coefficient for O(<SP>3</SP>P<SB><IT>J</IT></SB>) regeneration (<IT>via</IT> reaction (7)) by factors of 50–700 in all experiments where O<SB>2</SB> was present in the reaction mixture.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">As a result, the occurrence of reaction (7) had a negligible effect on observed O(<SP>3</SP>P<SB><IT>J</IT></SB>) appearance rates.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Side reactions of oxygen atoms with background impurities in the reactant samples is usually not a problem when the rate coefficients of interest are more than 10% of the gas kinetic collision rate coefficient.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, given the extreme level of reactivity of O(<SP>1</SP>D<SB>2</SB>) and the fact that the values for <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB>(<IT>T</IT>) measured in this study are somewhat faster than nearly all previously reported values, a number of experimental checks were carried out to verify that impurity reactions were unimportant.</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In most experiments, the N<SB>2</SB> source was a certified 3.15% N<SB>2</SB> in He mixture obtained from Matheson.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">However, in other experiments, the N<SB>2</SB>/He mixtures were prepared manometrically by the investigators using two different He cylinders and two different N<SB>2</SB> cylinders.</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">As seen from the results reported in Table 1, excellent precision in room temperature rate coefficients was obtained even though multiple sources of N<SB>2</SB>/He reactant mixtures were employed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">In some of the <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB>(<IT>T</IT>) experiments, the N<SB>2</SB>/He mixture was allowed to flow through a glass-bead-filled liquid nitrogen trap.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">Back-to-back experiments where the N<SB>2</SB>/He mixture (a) was allowed to flow through the trap and (b) by-passed the trap gave essentially identical results.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">In most experiments, the N<SB>2</SB>/He reaction mixture was transported to the reaction cell through Teflon tubing.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">However, in some room temperature experiments, the Teflon tubing was replaced with stainless steel tubing that was heated and purged with helium for several hours before being used in kinetics experiments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">As in the case of the other variations described above, the measured rate coefficient was found to be independent of whether the reactant line tubing was Teflon or stainless steel.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Finally, to test for possible mixing problems, about half of the room temperature experiments were done using a 1/4″ stainless steel cross to mix the O<SB>3</SB>/He and reactant/He mixtures with additional He, while about half of the experiments employed a 200 cm<SP>3</SP> Pyrex “mixing chamber” in place of the stainless steel cross; the measured rate coefficient was independent of this variation in apparatus configuration.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">As a final test of the internal consistency of the reported values of <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB>(<IT>T</IT>) and <IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB>(<IT>T</IT>), the deactivation of O(<SP>1</SP>D<SB>2</SB>) by zero air was investigated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The data are summarized in Table 3 and an Arrhenius plot of the ln <IT>k</IT><IT>vs</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None"><IT>T</IT><SP>−1</SP> data is shown in Fig. 4.</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The solid line in Fig. 4 is the best linear fit of the ln <IT>k</IT><IT>vs</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None"><IT>T</IT><SP>−1</SP> data; the best fit Arrhenius expression is k(<IT>T</IT>) = (2.11 ± 0.17) × 10<SP>−11</SP> exp{(140 ± 21)/T} cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The dashed line in Fig. 4 is obtained from the expression k(<IT>T</IT>) = 0.79 <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB>(<IT>T</IT>) + 0.21 <IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB>(<IT>T</IT>) where <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB>(<IT>T</IT>) and <IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB>(<IT>T</IT>) are evaluated using the Arrhenius expressions obtained in this study.</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Clearly, the O(<SP>1</SP>D<SB>2</SB>) + zero air results are consistent with the O(<SP>1</SP>D<SB>2</SB>) + N<SB>2</SB> and O(<SP>1</SP>D<SB>2</SB>) + O<SB>2</SB> results.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="No">Since secondary chemistry and impurity reactions appear to be very minor sources of error in this study (see above), the largest source of systematic error is probably the measurement of the reactant concentration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">Flow meter calibrations were checked frequently over the course of the study, and are believed to be accurate to within a few percent.</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">We conservatively estimate the overall uncertainty in the reported room temperature rate coefficients to be ±10% at the 95% confidence level.</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">At the temperature extremes of the study, the overall uncertainty increases a little because (a) precision is not as good as at room temperature and (b) uncertainty of ±2 deg in the temperature leads to additional uncertainty in the reactant concentration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">We estimate the overall uncertainty in the rate coefficients measured at the temperature extremes of the study to be ±15% at the 95% confidence level.</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The NASA panel for chemical kinetics and photochemical data evaluation parameterizes temperature-dependent uncertainty factors in second order rate coefficients using the following relationship:<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF><IT>f</IT>(<IT>T</IT>) = <IT>f</IT>(298)exp{|(Δ<IT>E</IT>/<IT>RT</IT>)(<IT>T</IT><SP>−1</SP> − 298<SP>−1</SP>)|} At the 67% confidence level (used by the NASA panel), the values of the parameters f(298) and (Δ<IT>E</IT>/<IT>R</IT>) that are consistent with the above error estimates are <IT>f</IT><SB>1</SB>(298) = <IT>f</IT><SB>2</SB>(298) = 1.05 and (Δ<IT>E</IT>/<IT>R</IT>)<SB>1</SB> ∼ Δ(<IT>E</IT>/<IT>R</IT>)<SB>2</SB> ∼ 15 K, where the subscripts refer to the reaction number.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The kinetic data obtained in this study are compared with other published rate coefficients in Tables 4 (<IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB>) and 5 (<IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the sake of clarity, only results published since 1973 are included in the Tables.</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results summarized in the Tables include all studies where absolute rate coefficients are reported<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6 cit7 cit11 cit12 cit38 cit39">5–7,11,12,38,39</REF> as well as one recent relative rate study,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF> but do not include a number of relative rate studies published during the 1960s and early 1970s.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27 cit28 cit40 cit41 cit42 cit43 cit44 cit45 cit46 cit47 cit48 cit49">27,28,40–49</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">None of the early relative rate data are used to derive current recommendations of <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB>(<IT>T</IT>) and <IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB>(<IT>T</IT>) for use in atmospheric models.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3 cit4">3,4</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Uncertainties in room temperature rate coefficients are not quoted in Tables 4 and 5 because it is very difficult to obtain a consistent set of uncertainty estimates from the published information.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">It appears that reasonable uncertainty estimates for previously published absolute room temperature values of <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB> and <IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB> are typically around ±20% at the 95% confidence level.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac20" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rate coefficients reported by Husain and coworkers<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit38 cit39">38,39</REF> are significantly faster than all others summarized in Tables 4 and 5; this trend also holds for a number of other O(<SP>1</SP>D<SB>2</SB>) reactions,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3 cit4">3,4</REF> and is widely believed to result from a problem with the experimental determination of the modified Beer–Lambert law parameter γ that is needed to relate the O(<SP>1</SP>D<SB>2</SB>) absorbance to its concentration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac21" novelty="None" advantage="None">A theoretical treatment<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit50">50</REF> suggests that <IT>γ</IT> should be near unity under the experimental conditions employed by Husain and coworkers, while the experimental value used to obtain the rate coefficients given in Tables 4 and 5 is <IT>γ</IT> = 0.41.</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac22" novelty="None" advantage="None">Assuming <IT>γ</IT> = 1 would decrease the measured rate coefficients by more than a factor of two.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit39">39</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac23" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results of Husain and coworkers are not included in the data set used by the NASA<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF> and IUPAC<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF> panels to arrive at recommendations of O(<SP>1</SP>D<SB>2</SB>) rate coefficients for use in atmospheric models.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac24" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Arrhenius parameters for the O(<SP>1</SP>D<SB>2</SB>) + O<SB>2</SB> reaction that are reported in this study are in very good agreement with current panel recommendations<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3 cit4">3,4</REF> (which are based on the room temperature study of Amimoto <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF>. and the temperature-dependent study of Streit <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF>.), and also agree well with results reported in the two very recent studies of Dunlea and Ravishankara<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF> and Blitz <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the other hand, the values of <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB>(<IT>T</IT>) reported in this study are among the fastest of any listed in Table 4, although our results agree quite well with those reported in the two other very recent studies.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11 cit12">11,12</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The room temperature rate coefficient reported in this paper is 25% faster than the currently recommended value,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3 cit4">3,4</REF> which is based on the absolute studies of Streit <IT>et al.</IT>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF> Amimoto <IT>et al.</IT>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF> and Wine and Ravishankara,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF> as well as the competitive kinetics study of Shi and Barker.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac25" novelty="None" advantage="None">The 1981 study of Wine and Ravishankara<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF> employed the same experimental approach as this study and another recent study by Dunlea and Ravishankara.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac26" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the precision and accuracy of the recent studies is believed to be superior to the 1981 study because of improved instrumentation for data collection and analysis, which allows higher quality data to be obtained and more experimental tests for systematic errors to be performed in a workable time frame.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac27" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is well established that photodissociation of O<SB>3</SB> at 248–266 nm generates translationally hot O(<SP>1</SP>D<SB>2</SB>).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit51 cit52 cit53 cit54 cit55 cit56">51–56</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac28" novelty="None" advantage="None">Matsumi and coworkers have investigated the competition between translational relaxation and electronic quenching in collisions of O(<SP>1</SP>D<SB>2</SB>) with N<SB>2</SB><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit55">55</REF> and O<SB>2</SB>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit54">54</REF> and find that, in pure N<SB>2</SB> or pure O<SB>2</SB>, electronic quenching occurs before translational deactivation is complete, <IT>i.e.</IT>, the translational energy distribution of the O(<SP>1</SP>D<SB>2</SB>) atoms undergoing electronic quenching is superthermal.</annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac29" novelty="None" advantage="None">The cross section for reaction (2) appears to depend only weakly on the relative translational energy of the reactants,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit54 cit57">54,57</REF> but both experimental<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit55">55</REF> and theoretical<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit58 cit59 cit60">58–60</REF> results suggest that the cross section for reaction (1) decreases sharply with increasing reactant translational energy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac30" novelty="None" advantage="None">All absolute kinetics studies of reactions (1) and (2) have employed reaction mixtures where the reactant (N<SB>2</SB> or O<SB>2</SB>) is diluted in helium, thus ensuring thermalization of the O(<SP>1</SP>D<SB>2</SB>) translational degrees of freedom.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6 cit7 cit11 cit12 cit38 cit39">5–7,11,12,38,39</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the results discussed above<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit55 cit58 cit59 cit60">55,58–60</REF> suggest that if O(<SP>1</SP>D<SB>2</SB>) is generated in the atmosphere with significant translational excitation, its effective rate coefficient for deactivation by N<SB>2</SB> could differ from the thermal rate coefficient measured in this study and in all other absolute kinetics studies summarized in Table 4.</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac31" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the troposphere and lower stratosphere, O(<SP>1</SP>D<SB>2</SB>) is generated <IT>via</IT> O<SB>3</SB> photolysis at wavelengths longer than 300 nm, <IT>i.e.</IT>, near the thermodynamic threshold for the spin-allowed O(<SP>1</SP>D<SB>2</SB>) + O<SB>2</SB>(a <SP>1</SP>Δ<SB>g</SB>) channel which accounts for well over 90% of O(<SP>1</SP>D<SB>2</SB>) production at the relevant wavelengths.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">2</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hence, it appears that the thermal rate coefficient <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB>(<IT>T</IT>) can be employed in simulations of atmospheric chemistry without introducing significant error.</annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, in the upper stratosphere and above, where significant O(<SP>1</SP>D<SB>2</SB>) production occurs <IT>via</IT> short wavelength photodissociation of O<SB>2</SB> and O<SB>3</SB>, use of thermal rate coefficients in simulations could result in systematic errors in evaluation of HO<SB><IT>x</IT></SB> and NO<SB><IT>x</IT></SB> production rates.</annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac32" novelty="None" advantage="None">Arguing against this idea is a study by Greenblatt and Ravishankara,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit61">61</REF> who have measured the yield of NO resulting from reaction of O(<SP>1</SP>D<SB>2</SB>) with gas mixtures containing N<SB>2</SB>O, N<SB>2</SB>, O<SB>2</SB>, and He under a variety of experimental conditions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac33" novelty="None" advantage="None">Within the combined uncertainties, the NO yields measured by Greenblatt and Ravishankara agreed quite well with yields calculated from values for <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB>, <IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB>, and k<SB>4a</SB> that were accepted at the time of their study (1990).</annotationART></s> <s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac34" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, NO yields were found to be independent of (a) O(<SP>1</SP>D<SB>2</SB>) source, <IT>i.e.</IT>, 193 nm photolysis of N<SB>2</SB>O <IT>versus</IT> 248 nm photolysis of O<SB>3</SB>, and (b) whether or not helium was present in the reaction mixture, suggesting that the stratospheric N<SB>2</SB>O production rate can be evaluated with good accuracy using thermal rate coefficient data.</annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac35" novelty="None" advantage="None">Reanalysis of the Greenblatt and Ravishankara data using the new faster value for <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB> reported in this study and two other new studies<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11 cit12">11,12</REF> improves the agreement between NO yields measured in their “integrated study” and yields calculated from the individual thermal rate coefficients.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">For reasons discussed in the introduction, the higher rate coefficient for the O(<SP>1</SP>D<SB>2</SB>) + N<SB>2</SB> reaction that is reported in this study has important implications for model calculations of the production rates of tropospheric HO<SB><IT>x</IT></SB> as well as stratospheric HO<SB><IT>x</IT></SB> and NO<SB><IT>x</IT></SB> radicals.</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">For example, in the marine lower troposphere, where water vapor concentrations are relatively high but concentrations of other potential OH precursors are relatively low, using the Arrhenius expression for <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB>(<IT>T</IT>) reported in this study would lead to a calculated OH production rate that is ∼18% smaller than the production rate that is calculated using the currently recommended<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3 cit4">3,4</REF> Arrhenius expression.</annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the upper troposphere, however, where H<SB>2</SB>O levels are very low and, as a result, the O(<SP>1</SP>D<SB>2</SB>) + H<SB>2</SB>O reaction is a less important OH source, use of the expression for <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB>(<IT>T</IT>) reported in this study would reduce the calculated OH production rate by only ∼5%<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit62">62</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
