<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b402202e" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Specific deuterium isotope effects on the intramolecular charge-transfer dynamics of 4-(dimethylamino)benzonitrile</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">The photoinduced charge-transfer (CT) dynamics of 4-(dimethylamino)benzonitrile (DMABN) are studied for methyl-deuterated isotopomers DMABN-<IT>d</IT><SB>6</SB> (with two CD<SB>3</SB> groups) and DMABN-<IT>h</IT><SB>3</SB><IT>d</IT><SB>3</SB> (with one CH<SB>3</SB> and one CD<SB>3</SB> group) by steady-state and time-resolved fluorescence spectroscopy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The asymmetrically deuterated species DMABN-<IT>h</IT><SB>3</SB><IT>d</IT><SB>3</SB> is found to exhibit less CT fluorescence in sufficiently polar solvents than the symmetric isotopomers of DMABN-<IT>h</IT><SB>6</SB> and DMABN-<IT>d</IT><SB>6</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results of fluorescence decay measurements are also reported, which suggest that the rate of backward electron transfer is increased upon asymmetric substitution of the dimethylamino group.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="I">Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The photoinduced charge-transfer (CT) reaction of DMABN in polar solvents has been the subject of extensive experimental and theoretical investigations.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2">1,2</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This process is usually considered as a twisting motion of the dimethylamino (DMA) group with respect to the benzonitrile group to produce an emissive transient species called twisted intramolecular charge-transfer (TICT) state.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">After finding similar behavior in many other molecules containing electron donor and acceptor groups, the rotamerism accompanying charge separation is most widely accepted.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">A wide variety of model compounds have been studied to explain the motion leading to the CT state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The so-called <IT>pretwisted</IT> compounds, such as sterically hindered <IT>ortho</IT>-methyl-derivatives of DMABN, are known to emit preferentially or only CT fluorescence in a medium polarity solvent.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3 cit4">3,4</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The CT fluorescence is also observed in the static vapor<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF> and under supersonic jet conditions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the DMA group in these compounds is already twisted in the ground-state structure, direct excitation of the CT state becomes possible.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Other derivatives of DMABN, in which the amino group is rigid with respect the twist around the N<SB>amino</SB>–C<SB>ring</SB> bond, reveal only locally excited (LE) fluorescence.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3 cit4">3,4</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">These results are considered as evidence of the TICT scenario.</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the other hand, neither the <IT>meta</IT> nor the <IT>ortho</IT> isomer of DMABN shows dual fluorescence even in strongly polar solvents.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The specific ring-substitution behavior has been ascribed to the large energy gap between the S<SB>1</SB> and S<SB>2</SB> states as compared to that of <IT>para</IT>-DMABN, leading to suggest a planar CT state.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Nonetheless, the nature of the structural change is not well characterized yet and under controversial discussion.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Recently, we have measured S<SB>1</SB>–S<SB>0</SB> spectra of methyl-deuterated isotopomers of DMABN (DMABN-<IT>d</IT><SB>6</SB> and DMABN-<IT>h</IT><SB>3</SB><IT>d</IT><SB>3</SB>) in supersonic jets using resonant two-photon ionization (R2PI) spectroscopy.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The spectra of the deuterated isotopomers reveal low-frequency progression due to the torsional motion of the DMA group in the S<SB>1</SB> state, essentially analogous to the protonated species DMABN-<IT>h</IT><SB>6</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Analysis shows that in all isotopomers the DMA group is twisted by ≈26° with respect to the ring plane under the isolated molecular condition.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the DMABN-<IT>h</IT><SB>3</SB><IT>d</IT><SB>3</SB> spectrum exhibits additional bands with a less regular pattern, suggesting that the asymmetric deuteration of the DMA group induces extensive mixing of its torsional motion and other low-frequency motions in S<SB>1</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Possible candidates for these motions are predicted to be torsion of the methyl groups and pyramidarization at the amino nitrogen.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is therefore interesting to compare the CT dynamics of the symmetric and asymmetric rotors in polar solvents.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Several examples of deuterium isotope effects on electron-transfer reactions have been reported, especially for those in the Marcus inverted region.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9 cit10 cit11">9–11</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">It has been shown that in intermolecular complexes between methyl-substituted benzene donors and cyanoanthracene acceptors, the backward electron transfer rate decreases substantially when the methyl hydrogens of the donor are deuterated.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, no or insignificant isotope effect is observed upon ring deuteration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">An asymmetric substitution effect has been suggested for intramolecular electron transfer reactions in bianthryls.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12 cit13">12,13</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this case, the so-called symmetry breaking is believed to be an important step for CT.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac20" novelty="None" advantage="None">Likewise, such symmetry reduction can be achieved upon complexation of bianthryl with other solvent molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac21" novelty="None" advantage="None">It has been shown that the 1:1 complex with acetone formed in a supersonic jet reveals a red-shifted emission assignable to the CT fluorescence.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac22" novelty="None" advantage="None">The complex is likely to have the solvent molecule sticking to one of the anthracene moieties, undergoing symmetry breaking and charge separation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac23" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the other hand, no CT formation occurs for the 1:2 complex, which is explained by invoking a symmetric structure.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this paper we report the results of the systematic study of the effect of deuterium substitution on the dual fluorescence behavior of DMABN in solvents of different polarity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The asymmetric isotopomer DMABN-<IT>h</IT><SB>3</SB><IT>d</IT><SB>3</SB> is found to reveal less CT fluorescence in moderately polar solvents than the symmetric ones (DMABN-<IT>h</IT><SB>6</SB> and DMABN-<IT>d</IT><SB>6</SB>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In less polar solvents (<IT>e.g.</IT>, 1,4-dioxane), on the other hand, the fully protonated compound gives rise to red-shifted fluorescence with higher efficiency than the deuterated isotopomers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa3" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have also employed a time-resolved spectroscopic technique to investigate the origin of the specific deuteration effects.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results suggest that the backward electron transfer is facilitated upon asymmetric deuteration of the DMA group.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">These observations are interpreted within the framework of the TICT model.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="II">Experimental</HEADER><P><s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Commercial DMABN (DMABN-<IT>h</IT><SB>6</SB>) was obtained from Aldrich and purified by vacuum sublimation before use.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The methods of preparing the deuterium-substituted DMABN samples, (CD<SB>3</SB>)<SB>2</SB>N-C<SB>6</SB>H<SB>4</SB>-CN (DMABN-<IT>d</IT><SB>6</SB>), and (CH<SB>3</SB>)(CD<SB>3</SB>)N-C<SB>6</SB>H<SB>4</SB>-CN (DMABN-<IT>h</IT><SB>3</SB><IT>d</IT><SB>3</SB>) have been described elsewhere.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The isotope content (&gt;99%) was confirmed by NMR and mass spectroscopy analysis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The DMABN-<IT>h</IT><SB>3</SB><IT>d</IT><SB>3</SB> sample showed traces (≈0.17%) of monomethylated impurities [<IT>e.g.</IT>, (CD<SB>3</SB>)HN-C<SB>6</SB>H<SB>4</SB>-CN].</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">A series of solvents of different polarities [cyclohexane, tetrahydrofuran (THF), 1,4-dioxane, <IT>n</IT>-butyronitrile, acetonitrile, 1-butanol, 1-propanol, 2-propanol, ethanol, methanol, and water] were purchased from Kanto Chemical Co. These solvents were of spectroscopic grade and used as received.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The sample concentration was 1 × 10<SP>−4</SP> M.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">A Hitachi F-2000 spectrofluorometer was used for the steady-state fluorescence measurements.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The time-resolved fluorescence measurements were carried out by exciting the samples with the frequency-tripled output of a femtosecond laser (Spectra Physics Tsunami/Spitfire) at 266 nm and by recording the fluorescence with a streak camera (Hamamatsu Photonics).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The system response function was found to be ≈30 ps.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the samples exhibit dual fluorescence, each fluorescence emission was collected separately through a monochromator.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fluorescence decays were fitted with exponential functions by taking account of the response function of the streak camera.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="III">Results</HEADER><P><s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The steady-state fluorescence spectra of three isotopomers of DMABN in 1,4-dioxane, ethanol, and acetonitrile at 25 °C are shown in Fig. 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In each solvent, the absorption and fluorescence excitation spectra are essentially identical for the three isotopomers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fluorescence spectra of the fully protonated species (Fig. 1) are in good agreement with previous measurements.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit17">4,17</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of weakly polar dioxane (dielectric constant <IT>ε</IT> = 2.2 at 25 °C), the relative LE fluorescence intensity is strongest for DMABN-<IT>d</IT><SB>6</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">With increasing the solvent polarity (ethanol and acetonitrile), the ratio for the asymmetric isotopomer DMABN-<IT>h</IT><SB>3</SB><IT>d</IT><SB>3</SB> becomes larger than those for -<IT>h</IT><SB>6</SB> and -<IT>d</IT><SB>6</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The symmetric species give nearly the same intensity ratios.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac24" novelty="None" advantage="None">This behavior cannot be ascribed to the monomethylated impurity described in the Experimental section, which is known to exhibit only LE fluorescence.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fluorescence spectra of the three isotopomers in cyclohexane (not shown) appear to be identical.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">In all polar solvents studied, the relative intensity of the LE and CT fluorescence is found to be different for the three isotopomers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac25" novelty="None" advantage="None">Ratios of the CT and LE fluorescence yields (<IT>Φ</IT><SB>CT</SB>/<IT>Φ</IT><SB>LE</SB>) can be obtained by separating the respective emission bands.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The <IT>Φ</IT><SB>CT</SB>/<IT>Φ</IT><SB>LE</SB> ratios plotted against the dielectric constant of the solvent are shown in Fig. 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">It can be seen that in 1-butanol (<IT>ε</IT> = 17.1) or more polar solvents the ratio for the -<IT>h</IT><SB>3</SB><IT>d</IT><SB>3</SB> isotopomer is considerably lower than for the symmetric isotopomers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, the ratios in protic solvents (propanols, 1-butanol, methanol, and ethanol) appear to increase monotonically with the polarity, but differ noticeably from those obtained with aprotic solvents of similar polarity [<IT>e.g.</IT>, 1-propanol (<IT>ε</IT> = 20.1) and <IT>n</IT>-butyronitrile (<IT>ε</IT> = 20.4)].</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac26" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fluorescence yield ratios have also been obtained for the three isotopomers with an excitation wavelength of 306 nm (not shown).</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The symmetry dependent behavior is essentially the same for the two different excitation wavelengths.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="New" advantage="None">Time profiles of the LE and CT fluorescence emissions have been measured separately for three DMABN isotopomers in each solvent.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="New" advantage="None">The selected spectral range chosen to follow the LE fluorescence kinetics is centered at 350 nm in dioxane and 355 nm in more polar solvents, whereas the CT fluorescence was measured with the observation window centered at 450 nm for dioxane and 490 nm for the other solvents.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Each time-resolved fluorescence intensity appears to consist of two components, with a picosecond decay followed by a nanosecond decay for the LE emission and a picosecond rise followed by a nanosecond decay for the CT emission.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, the time-resolve fluorescence intensity can be described by the following equationswhere <IT>I</IT>(<IT>t</IT>)<SB>LE</SB> is the LE fluorescence intensity with the fast and slow decay lifetimes <IT>τ</IT><SB>fast</SB> and <IT>τ</IT><SB>slow</SB>, and the amplitudes <IT>A</IT><SB>fast</SB> and <IT>A</IT><SB>slow</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None"><IT>I</IT>(<IT>t</IT>)<SB>CT</SB> is the CT fluorescence intensity with the risetime <IT>τ</IT><SB>rise</SB> and decay lifetime <IT>τ</IT><SB>decay</SB>, and the amplitudes <IT>A</IT><SB>rise</SB> and <IT>A</IT><SB>decay</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The decay profiles of the LE fluorescence obtained for dioxane, ethanol and acetonitrile are compared in Fig. 3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">In each solvent, the profiles of the CT fluorescence are nearly identical for the three isotopomers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fluorescence decay lifetimes and preexponential factors calculated by fitting the data to eqns. (1) and (2) are summarized in Table 1.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">As shown in Fig. 3, a small isotope effect is observed for the decay curves in dioxane.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fast decay lifetime of the LE fluorescence <IT>τ</IT><SB>fast</SB> increases slightly upon deuterium substitution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The value of 25 ps for the -<IT>h</IT><SB>6</SB> species is in good agreement with that reported by Schuddeboom <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Pronounced isotope effects occur in the case of ethanol and acetonitrile.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The asymmetric deuteration leads to an increase in the magnitude of the slow decay component of the LE fluorescence.</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ratio of the amplitudes of the fast and slow decay components (<IT>A</IT><SB>fast</SB>/<IT>A</IT><SB>slow</SB>) for -<IT>h</IT><SB>3</SB><IT>d</IT><SB>3</SB> is calculated to be 6.3 for ethanol and 22.2 for acetonitrile.</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The corresponding values for the symmetric isotopomers are much larger (28.6 and 34.5 for -<IT>h</IT><SB>6</SB> and 76.9 and 83.3 for -<IT>d</IT><SB>6</SB>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">As listed in Table 1, the lifetimes of the fast and slow decay components of the LE fluorescence (<IT>τ</IT><SB>fast</SB> and <IT>τ</IT><SB>slow</SB>) are not significantly influenced by the isotope substitution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The result obtained for -<IT>h</IT><SB>6</SB> is in qualitative agreement with that reported by Changenet <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">In all cases, the amplitude ratio of the rise and decay components of the CT fluorescence <IT>A</IT><SB>rise</SB>/<IT>A</IT><SB>decay</SB> is nearly equal to –1, which implies that the CT state is formed through the LE state decay.</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Isotope dependent behavior obtained with methanol is very similar to the case of ethanol, except that the fast components <IT>τ</IT><SB>fast</SB> and <IT>τ</IT><SB>rise</SB> are much shorter than in ethanol.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs20" novelty="None" advantage="None">For all isotopomers in the protic solvents (<IT>i.e.</IT>, ethanol and methanol), the CT fluorescence risetime <IT>τ</IT><SB>rise</SB> is found to vary with the emission wavelength: it increases as the observation window is shifted to a longer wavelength region.</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">This implies that the CT fluorescence intensity distribution redshifts with time, which has been recognized previously<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18 cit19">18,19</REF> and explained as a result of the longer solvent reorganization time in these solvents.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs21" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this case, the risetime of the CT fluorescence <IT>τ</IT><SB>rise</SB> does not match the fast decay lifetime of the LE fluorescence <IT>τ</IT><SB>fast</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the other hand, rapid equilibrium between the LE and CT states can be reached upon excitation in aprotic solvents, and thus <IT>τ</IT><SB>rise</SB> and <IT>τ</IT><SB>decay</SB> of the CT fluorescence are nearly equal to the decay lifetimes <IT>τ</IT><SB>fast</SB> and <IT>τ</IT><SB>slow</SB> of the LE fluorescence, respectively.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="IV">Discussion</HEADER><P><s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs22" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have observed that in solvents of moderate and high polarity, the intensity ratio of the CT to LE fluorescence (<IT>Φ</IT><SB>CT</SB>/<IT>Φ</IT><SB>LE</SB>) of DMABN decreases upon deuteration of one of the methyl groups.</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">This symmetry effect is contrasted with the case of the weakly polar solvent dioxane where the fully methyl-deuterated isotopomer gives the lowest <IT>Φ</IT><SB>CT</SB>/<IT>Φ</IT><SB>LE</SB> fluorescence ratio.</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Moreover, the time-resolved fluorescence measurements reveal that the asymmetric substitution leads to a substantial decrease in the ratio of the fast to slow decay component of the LE fluorescence (<IT>A</IT><SB>fast</SB>/<IT>A</IT><SB>slow</SB>) in polar solvents.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Here, we employ the kinetic scheme (Scheme 1) proposed by Grabowski <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF>. to rationalize these observations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, the TICT model is invoked in which the CT stabilization occurs as a consequence of the torsional motion of the DMA group.</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac27" novelty="None" advantage="None">For DMABN in polar aprotic solvents, the excited-state equilibrium can be fully established within the lifetime, <IT>i.e.</IT>, <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB>, <IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB> ≫ <IT>k</IT><SB>LE</SB>, <IT>k</IT><SB>CT</SB>, where <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB> and <IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB> are the forward and backward reaction rate constants, respectively, and <IT>k</IT><SB>LE</SB> and <IT>k</IT><SB>CT</SB> are the decay rate constants of the respective excited states.</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this high-temperature regime, the ratio of the LE fluorescence components <IT>A</IT><SB>fast</SB>/<IT>A</IT><SB>slow</SB> can be associated with the ratio of the reaction rate constants <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB>/<IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reciprocal of the short decay lifetime <IT>τ</IT><SB>fast</SB> corresponds to the sum of the forward and backward reaction rate constants <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB> + <IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac28" novelty="None" advantage="None">For DMABN in protic solvents, the risetime of the CT fluorescence is determined by the solvent reorganization time as described above.</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac28" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this case, the reaction kinetics can be deduced from the LE state decays.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs23" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rate constants <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB> and <IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB> for the two aprotic solvents (dioxane and acetonitrile) derived based on the high-temperature approximation are listed in Table 2.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Comparison of the kinetic data in Table 2 suggests that the backward reaction rate constant <IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB> increases upon asymmetric deuteration, whereas the change in <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB> is minor.</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs24" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is also important to note that the emission maxima of the LE and CT fluorescence are identical for all isotopomers (Fig. 1), supporting that the energies of the LE and CT states are not shifted by the symmetry reduction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, we conclude that the activation barrier for CT changes upon deuteration of one of the methyl groups.</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs25" novelty="None" advantage="None">For DMABN-<IT>h</IT><SB>6</SB> in polar solvents, the activation energy of the backward reaction <IT>E</IT><SB>2</SB> is much larger than that of the forward reaction <IT>E</IT><SB>1</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, the ratios of <IT>Φ</IT><SB>CT</SB>/<IT>Φ</IT><SB>LE</SB> and <IT>A</IT><SB>fast</SB>/<IT>A</IT><SB>slow</SB> increase by lowering the temperature in the so-called high-temperature region.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The activation energies <IT>E</IT><SB>1</SB> and <IT>E</IT><SB>2</SB> have been obtained separately from Arrhenius-type plots of the decay rate constants.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">In both protic and aprotic solvents, the observed Arrhenius activation energy <IT>E</IT><SB>1</SB> appears to be similar to the activation energy for the solvent mobility <IT>E</IT><SB><IT>η</IT></SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">This implies the absence of intrinsic potential barrier for the forward reaction.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs26" novelty="None" advantage="None">For example, the activation energy <IT>E</IT><SB>1</SB> in butyronitrile is obtained to be 10.5 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>, which is comparable to <IT>E</IT><SB><IT>η</IT></SB> (9.2 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the other hand, the activation energy of the backward reaction <IT>E</IT><SB>2</SB> (15.9 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> in butyronitrile) is substantially larger than <IT>E</IT><SB><IT>η</IT></SB>, and a significant intrinsic barrier exists for this process.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the basis of the barrierless reaction model, we propose that the pronounced asymmetric substitution effect on the CT dynamics in sufficiently polar solvents is due to vibrational coupling between the primary reactive mode, namely the twisting motion around the N<SB>amino</SB>–C<SB>ring</SB> bond, and other low-frequency motions (<IT>e.g.</IT>, pyramidalization at the DMA group and torsion of the methyl groups).</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac29" novelty="None" advantage="None">Among these <IT>nonreactive</IT> motions, pyramidalization is believed to be important in determining the CT dynamics of DMABN.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit22">4,22</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac30" novelty="None" advantage="None">With very low pyramidalization, the activation energy for the CT reaction is lowered, leading to a barrierless reaction coordinate, as discussed above.</annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, asymmetric substitution of the DMA group exerts a minor influence on the forward reaction process.</annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast, vibrational coupling with <IT>nonreactive</IT> modes will increase the density of states for the back CT reaction, thus lowering its barrier height.</annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The above interpretation is consistent with the absence of noticeable symmetry effect in dioxane.</annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs27" novelty="None" advantage="None">As shown in Fig. 1, the protonated species DMABN-<IT>h</IT><SB>6</SB> reveals the largest <IT>Φ</IT><SB>CT</SB>/<IT>Φ</IT><SB>LE</SB> value among all isotopomers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the weakly polar solvent, the forward reaction may also have an intrinsic barrier.</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this case, deuterium isotope effects prevail.</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac31" novelty="None" advantage="None">The slower CT reaction rate for the deuterated species can be explained in terms of the torsional frequency of the DMA group, which decreases by ≈10% in going from -<IT>h</IT><SB>6</SB> to -<IT>d</IT><SB>6</SB>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac32" novelty="None" advantage="None">While DMABN is known to be pyramidal in the ground state,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF> increased conjugation upon excitation would be expected to lead to a more planar (with respect to inversion) conformation in S<SB>1</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac33" novelty="None" advantage="None">It has been suggested that its S<SB>1</SB> inversion potential is very flat-bottomed.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac34" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the other hand, the torsional geometry is planar in S<SB>0</SB>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF> while twisted in S<SB>1</SB> by about 26° with a small barrier to planarity.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac35" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this case, vibrational coupling between the torsion and inversion of the DMA group is expected to occur extensively upon excitation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac35" novelty="None" advantage="None">Evidence in support of such coupling can be obtained from vibrational analysis of the S<SB>1</SB> ← S<SB>0</SB> spectra of three isotopomers.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac35" novelty="None" advantage="None">Each spectrum, obtained in a supersonic jet, consists of a prominent low-frequency progression due to the DMA torsion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs28" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition to this, bands assignable to the inversion and its combination bands with the DMA torsion are apparent in the spectrum of the asymmetric isotopomer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs29" novelty="None" advantage="None">The -<IT>h</IT><SB>3</SB><IT>d</IT><SB>3</SB> spectrum also reveals bands involving torsion of each methyl group (CH<SB>3</SB> and CD<SB>3</SB>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The increased coupling of the <IT>reactive</IT> DMA torsion with these <IT>nonreactive</IT> modes upon asymmetric substitution is expected to reduce the activation energy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is also possible to ascribe the observed symmetry effect to an increase of the preexponential (frequency) factor due to such mode coupling.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In conclusion, it is demonstrated that the fluorescence intensity ratio of the CT and LE emissions of DMABN decreases substantially upon deuteration of one of the methyl groups.</annotationART></s> <s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">This asymmetric substitution effect can be observed only in polar solvents of medium and high polarity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The time-resolved fluorescence measurement reveals that the reverse electron transfer is facilitated in the asymmetric isotopomer, whereas no significant change occurs for the forward reaction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">This behavior is explained by mode coupling of the torsional motion of the DMA group with other low-frequency motions, which occurs strongly upon asymmetry reduction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac36" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, more accurate decay data would be essential to determine unequivocally the origin of the asymmetric substitution effect.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
