<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b406569g" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Oxidation potentials and electron donation to photosystem II of manganese complexes containing bicarbonate and carboxylate ligands</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The oxidation potentials of Mn<SP>II</SP> in aqueous solutions of bicarbonate, formate, acetate and oxalate are reported as a function of concentration and compared to the rate of photooxidation of these solutions by the Mn-depleted water-oxidizing complex of photosystem II (apo-WOC-PSII) from peas.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although all the carboxylate species lower considerably the oxidation potential of Mn<SP>II</SP>, only bicarbonate stimulates the electron transfer from Mn<SP>II</SP> to apo-WOC-PSII.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the basis of the electrochemical data it is proposed that the unique capability of Mn-bicarbonate complexes to be photooxidized by PSII could be due to four possible reasons: (i) significantly larger decrease in the oxidation potential of Mn<SP>II</SP> (down to 0.52 V); (ii) electroneutrality of the functional electron transfer complex; (iii) the more favorable energetics reflected in the two p<IT>K</IT><SB>a</SB> values for H<SB>2</SB>CO<SB>3</SB>/HCO<SB>3</SB><SP>−</SP> and HCO<SB>3</SB><SP>−</SP>/CO<SB>3</SB><SP>2−</SP> and greater number of proton transfer sites; and (iv) multiple composition possibilities for the Mn<SP>III</SP> photo-product as Mn<SP>III</SP>(HCO<SB>3</SB><SP>−</SP>)<SB>3</SB>, Mn<SP>III</SP>(HCO<SB>3</SB><SP>−</SP>)(CO<SB>3</SB><SP>2−</SP>) and Mn<SP>III</SP>(HCO<SB>3</SB><SP>−</SP>)<SB>2</SB>(OH<SP>−</SP>) (due to the high Lewis acidity of Mn<SP>III</SP> (p<IT>K</IT> &lt; 1).</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Photosynthetic water oxidation produces molecular oxygen in photosystem II (PSII) of green plants and cyanobacteria.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Absorption of light in PSII antenna and reaction center (RC) of PSII induces charge separation between molecules of excited chlorophylls (P680) and pheophytin (free-base chlorophyll), with subsequent electron transfer steps to the first quinone acceptor Q<SB>A</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The electron vacancy arising in P680<SP>+</SP> is filled up by an electron donated ultimately by a water molecule (the terminal reductant of PSII).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2">1,2</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Substrate water is bound to an enzymatic water-oxidizing complex (WOC) comprised of Mn<SB>4</SB>Ca<SB>1</SB>Cl<SB>x</SB>, redox-active tyrosine (Y<SB>z</SB>) and possibly bicarbonate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The WOC serves the purpose of a redox catalyst (electron/proton reservoir) to deliver electrons one at a time to P680<SP>+</SP> until four electron vacancies are accumulated resulting in oxidation of two H<SB>2</SB>O molecules to O<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is known that bicarbonate (HCO<SB>3</SB><SP>−</SP>) ions are needed for maximum activity of PSII (for recent reviews, see <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3 cit4 cit5 cit6">refs. 3–6</REF> and references therein).</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The stimulating effect of HCO<SB>3</SB><SP>−</SP> on PSII was primarily ascribed to the processes taking place on the donor side of PSII<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF> and a model including bicarbonate as a mediator for photosynthetic water oxidation has been given<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7 cit8">7,8</REF> which, however, was in contradiction with the results of isotopic experiments.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, strong evidence is known for the action of bicarbonate on the electron acceptor side of PSII, where it promotes efficient re-oxidation of Q<SB>A</SB><SP>−</SP>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">This role was supported by a number of compelling data, including evidence for binding of bicarbonate directly to the non-heme Fe located between Q<SB>A</SB> and Q<SB>B</SB><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11 cit12">11,12</REF> where it accelerates electron transfer between the quinones and may also serve as proton donor to the reduced Q<SB>B</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Further, Xiong <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF>. have suggested involvement of R-257 on D-1 protein in bicarbonate/formate binding through their site-directed mutagenesis studies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">These studies have led to a widely accepted model (for review, see <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">ref. 4</REF>).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Recent data have shown a role for bicarbonate on the donor side, with specific evidence indicating a function in assembling the inorganic cofactors within apo-WOC (WOC-depleted of Mn, Ca and Cl cofactors), but also for sustaining oxygen-evolution activity.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14 cit15 cit16 cit17 cit18 cit19 cit20 cit21 cit22">14–22</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">It was shown that after removal of all four manganese ions from subchloroplast PSII preparations, an effective reactivation of electron transfer<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14 cit15 cit17 cit18 cit19 cit20">14,15,17–20</REF> and oxygen evolution<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18 cit22 cit23">18,22,23</REF> was observed only if a nearly stoichiometric amount of Mn<SP>II</SP> (2–4 atoms of Mn<SP>II</SP> per PSII reaction center) was added together with bicarbonate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Bicarbonate also specifically restores electron transport on the donor side of PSII containing Mn-sufficient, intact, WOC that has been modified with formate<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14 cit15 cit16 cit17 cit18">14–18</REF> or by removal of bicarbonate from the medium.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14 cit15 cit17 cit18 cit19 cit20 cit21">14,15,17–21</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">From comparison of the light-induced FT-IR spectra originating from the donor side of O<SB>2</SB>-evolving PS II and measured in the presence of (<SP>12</SP>C)NaHCO<SB>3</SB> or (<SP>13</SP>C) NaHCO<SB>3</SB><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF> with the FT-IR spectrum ascribed to the S<SB>1</SB>/S<SB>2</SB> – transition<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF> it has been postulated that bicarbonate acts as a bridging ligand between the redox-active Mn and Ca<SP>2+</SP> within the WOC.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">It has been shown<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25">25</REF> that formate modifies the S<SB>1</SB>-state of the WOC by reduction to the S<SB>0</SB>-state.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">All these facts suggest that HCO<SB>3</SB><SP>−</SP> ion not only involved in the PS II acceptor side, but is also a necessary component for optimal functioning of the WOC.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although it is chemically reasonable and consistent with available data to suggest that bicarbonate binds as a ligand to either Mn or Ca, we do not yet know where HCO<SB>3</SB><SP>−</SP> binds within the WOC, nor how it functions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Recent X-ray diffraction data at 3.5 Å resolution of a PSII complex isolated from a cyanobacterium have postulated<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26">26</REF> suitable binding sites for (bi)carbonate on both the acceptor and donor sides of PSII.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The authors have suggested (in accordance with an earlier assumption)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF> that on the donor side (bi)carbonate binds to the high affinity Mn site and also to Ca based on the absence of sufficient protein ligands,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26">26</REF> though they have no direct support of this.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">It was shown in a previous work<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27">27</REF> that upon addition of NaHCO<SB>3</SB> to an aqueous solution of Mn<SP>II</SP> the potential for oxidation of Mn<SP>II</SP> to Mn<SP>III</SP> was shifted from 1.19 to 0.63 V at fixed pH 8.3 as a result of formation of (bi)carbonate complexes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">These data provided a basis for suggesting a role for bicarbonate in promoting oxidation of Mn in the WOC.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, there is contradictory information in the literature about the chemical composition of Mn-bicarbonate complexes in solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Lesht and Bauman reported a stability constant for [Mn<SP>II</SP>(HCO<SB>3</SB><SP>−</SP>)]<SP>+</SP> (<IT>K</IT><SB>1</SB> = 18.6 at 298 K) using a thermodynamic method.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28">28</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac20" novelty="None" advantage="None">Smith and Martel summarized literature data for <IT>K</IT><SB>1</SB> equal to 63 and 2.8 at ionic strengths of solutions equal to 3.0 and 0.0 (298 K), respectively.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29">29</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac21" novelty="None" advantage="None">Sychev and co-workers<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30 cit31">30,31</REF> summarized the prior literature and proposed successive formation of [Mn<SP>II</SP>(HCO<SB>3</SB><SP>−</SP>)]<SP>+</SP> and Mn<SP>II</SP>(HCO<SB>3</SB><SP>−</SP>)<SB>2</SB> complexes and reported their stability constants (<IT>K</IT><SB>1</SB> = 11 and <IT>K</IT><SB>2</SB> = 3.7) using an indirect assay method based solely on the HCO<SB>3</SB><SP>−</SP> concentration dependence of the rate of Mn-dependent dismutation of exogenous hydrogen peroxide (at pH 7.0).</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac22" novelty="None" advantage="None">Using the same assay method, Stadtman <IT>et al</IT>. confirmed that HCO<SB>3</SB><SP>−</SP> is required for catalytic dismutation of H<SB>2</SB>O<SB>2</SB> by Mn<SP>II</SP> and showed that three equivalents of HCO<SB>3</SB><SP>−</SP> are required to create the catalyst that is active in the dismutation reaction that forms O<SB>2</SB> and water.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit32">32</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac23" novelty="None" advantage="None">The values of the stability constants for the bicarbonate complexes with Mn<SP>III</SP> and Mn<SP>IV</SP> and their composition are not known, presumably owing to their instability.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is clear that more detailed knowledge of the complexation of Mn<SP>II</SP> and Mn<SP>III</SP> with bicarbonate is required for understanding the thermodynamics consequences.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The aim of the present work is to determine the electrochemical potentials for the oxidation of Mn-complexes of bicarbonate, acetate and formate and correlate them with their capability to donate electrons to Mn-depleted PSII (apo-WOC-PSII).</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Methods and materials</HEADER><P><s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Subchloroplast membrane fragments enriched in PSII (BBY-particles) and containing 200–220 chlorophyll molecules per PSII reaction center were prepared from pea (<IT>Pisum sativum L</IT>.) chloroplasts, as described previously.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit33">33</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">A complete (&gt;95%) removal of Mn from the membrane fragments was carried out using the treatment with 1 M Tris-HCl (pH 8.0) plus 0.5 M MgCl<SB>2</SB>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit34">34</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The preparations were stored in liquid nitrogen or at −80 °C at a Chl concentration of 2 mg ml<SP>−1</SP> after the addition of 10% glycerol.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">A partial removal of bicarbonate from BBY preparations was achieved, as described earlier<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF> by a 200-fold dilution of concentrated (2 mg ml<SP>−1</SP>) PSII preparations into the medium (100 mM MES-NaOH buffer, pH 6.2, 35 mM NaCl) depleted of endogenous bicarbonate by means of 60 min flushing with air (which was freed from CO<SB>2</SB> by passage through a solution of 50% NaOH and 20 cm layer of ascarite) and subsequent 10-min incubation at 20 °C.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The kinetics of the photoinduced change of chlorophyll fluorescence yield (Δ<IT>F</IT>) (<IT>λ</IT> &gt; 660 nm) related to photoreduction of the primary quinone electron acceptor of PSII, Q<SB>A</SB>, were measured in a tightly closed 10-mm cuvette at 20 °C using a phosphoroscopic set-up.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit34">34</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Voltammetry curves for Mn<SP>II</SP> oxidation were recorded with a standard potentiostat (polarographic analyzer model PA-3; LP, Praha) using a three-electrode cell, as described earlier.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27">27</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">A hemispheric Pt electrode with visible surface of 0.01 cm<SP>2</SP>, and soldered in glass, was used as the working electrode.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">A Pt plate (1 × 1 cm) was used as counter-electrode.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">All potentials were measured against the saturated calomel electrode and then were recalculated <IT>versus</IT> the normal hydrogen electrode.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The accuracy of the potential measurements was equal to 10 mV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">A solution of 0.1 M LiClO<SB>4</SB> in water was used as the background.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Oxygen was not removed during the measurements.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">Adsorption of the oxidized products accompanied by the appearance of a new anodic wave at 0.68 V (that increased with the number of scans), was a characteristic feature of the measurements of Mn<SP>II</SP> oxidation curves.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">Therefore, recordings of the voltage–current curves for Mn<SP>II</SP> on Pt were carried out only upon the first scan.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Pt working electrode was cleaned with filter paper after each scanning into the anodic region.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Reagent grade NaHCO<SB>3</SB>, NaHCO<SB>2</SB>, CH<SB>3</SB>COONa and LiClO<SB>4</SB> were used in this work using doubly-distilled water with initial pH 6.5.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Addition of acetate (NaCH<SB>3</SB>COO), formate (NaHCO<SB>2</SB>) or oxalate (Na<SB>2</SB>(COO)<SB>2</SB>) to water led to gradual alkalization of the solution up to pH 8.5.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Dissolving of bicarbonate (NaHCO<SB>3</SB>) in the range of concentrations used in this study produces solutions having a constant pH equal to pH 8.3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">Accordingly, the dominant species in solution is the bicarbonate anion (p<IT>K</IT><SB>a1</SB> = 6.3, p<IT>K</IT><SB>a2</SB> = 10.3).</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Control measurements to examine the influence of pH were performed with MnSO<SB>4</SB> in unbuffered water by addition of HCl or KOH.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The potential–current curves for oxidation of Mn<SP>II</SP> were found to be independent of pH in the 5.0 to 8.5 range (less than 10 mV change for the whole region).</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, above pH 9 the oxidation potential begins to shift due to complex formation with hydroxide.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This shift is in agreement with the onset of formation of [Mn(OH)]<SP>+</SP> (p<IT>K</IT><SB>a</SB> for Mn<SP>2+</SP><SB>aq</SB> is 10.5).</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, in the present experiments at pH lower than 8.35, Mn<SP>2+</SP><SB>aq,</SB> and not [Mn(OH)]<SP>+</SP>, is the predominant Mn<SP>II</SP> species detected electrochemically in equilibrium with exogenous anions.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Results</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="I.">Effect of bicarbonate and other carboxylates on reactivation of electron transport from Mn<SP>2+</SP> to PSII reaction centers</HEADER><P><s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac24" novelty="None" advantage="None">It has been shown earlier that complete removal of Mn from PSII membrane fragments results in a 15–20-fold decrease of the photoinduced changes of chlorophyll fluorescence yield (Δ<IT>F</IT>) (due to loss of electron transfer from the WOC to PSII reaction centers) that can be restored by Mn<SP>2+</SP> added at a catalytic (0.1–0.2 μM) concentration.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit34">34</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac25" novelty="None" advantage="None">The capability of added Mn<SP>2+</SP> to restore photoinduced Δ<IT>F</IT> in Mn-depleted PSII preparations considerably increases upon the addition of bicarbonate.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15 cit16">15,16</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 1 shows that (in accordance with the previous publications) the photoinduced Δ<IT>F</IT> lost due to removal of Mn from BBY preparations (curve 1) is efficiently reactivated if 0.2 μM MnCl<SB>2</SB> (which corresponds to 4 Mn atoms per one PSII reaction center) is added together with 5 mM NaHCO<SB>3</SB> (curve 4), while 0.2 μM MnCl<SB>2</SB> added alone induces a very low reactivation (curve 3).</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">This activation by bicarbonate in the presence of 0.2 μM MnCl<SB>2</SB> (curve 4) saturates at 1–2 mM bicarbonate and 50% saturation occurs at 100–200 μM NaHCO<SB>3</SB> (data not shown).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">By contrast, formate does not facilitate the restoration of Δ<IT>F</IT> (curve 5); on the other hand, bicarbonate added to the sample containing 0.2 μM MnCl<SB>2</SB> and 5 mM formate causes a considerable restoration of Δ<IT>F</IT> (curve 6), similar to that observed upon the addition of bicarbonate in the absence of formate (curve 4).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Similar effects are seen for acetate: no reactivation of Δ<IT>F</IT> upon its addition together with MnCl<SB>2</SB> (curve 7) and subsequent reactivation with bicarbonate (curve 8).</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The effects are shown for 5 mM concentration of formate and acetate but they are similar over a wide range of concentrations (10 μM–10 mM) of these carboxylates.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="II.">Voltammetry of Mn<SP>III</SP> complexes</HEADER><P><s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">The formation of Mn<SP>III</SP> complexes with different ligands was measured under electrochemical oxidation of Mn<SP>II</SP> to Mn<SP>III</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">If the electrode reaction is reversible, and the amount of a ligand is so great that its concentration near the surface of the electrode is equal to that in bulk solution, then recording the dependence of the oxidation potential on the logarithm of concentration of the ligand [eqn.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">(I)], it is possible to determine the composition of the complex and the equilibrium stability constant for reaction:<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit35 cit36">35,36</REF> Mn<SP>II</SP> − <IT>e</IT> + <IT>p</IT>X<SP>−</SP> ⇔ Mn<SP>III</SP>X<SB><IT>p</IT></SB>where <IT>E</IT><SB>1/2me</SB> and <IT>E</IT><SB>1/2com</SB> are the half-wave oxidation potentials for Mn<SP>II</SP> and its complex with ligand X, respectively; <IT>K</IT><SB>st</SB> is the stability constant of the complex; <IT>C</IT><SB>X</SB> is the concentration of ligand X in solution, <IT>q</IT> and <IT>p</IT> is the number of ligands in complexes of Mn<SP>II</SP> and Mn<SP>III</SP>, respectively; <IT>n</IT> is the number of electrons involved in the redox reaction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of prior complex formation with Mn<SP>II</SP> the oxidation process is: Mn<SP>II</SP> X<SB><IT>q</IT></SB> − <IT>e</IT> + (<IT>p</IT> − <IT>q</IT>) X<SP>−</SP> ⇔ Mn<SP>III</SP>X<SB><IT>p</IT></SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this case, the shift of the oxidation potential of Mn<SP>II</SP> depends on the ratio of the stability constants for oxidized (<IT>K</IT><SB>ox</SB>) and the reduced (<IT>K</IT><SB>red</SB>) forms, as well as on the concentration of the ligand as given by eqn. (II):<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit35 cit36">35,36</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac26" novelty="None" advantage="None">In both cases, the number of ligands in the complex can be determined from the slope of the dependence of the oxidation potential on log <IT>C</IT><SB>X</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">By extrapolation of the curve to log <IT>C</IT><SB>X</SB> = 0, the standard reduction potential <IT>E</IT><SP>0</SP> of the complex and its stability constant can be determined:</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The voltage–current curves obtained by voltammetry method on the Pt-electrode are seen as a wave with a peak characterized by the value of the peak potential, <IT>E</IT><SB>p</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac27" novelty="None" advantage="None">For reversible one- or two-electron processes, the difference between <IT>E</IT><SB>p</SB> and <IT>E</IT><SB>1/2</SB> is equal to 28 and 14 mV, respectively.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit37">37</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">We used the experimental <IT>E</IT><SB>p</SB> values instead of <IT>E</IT><SB>1/2</SB> for plotting of eqns. (1) and (2).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The first stage of Mn<SP>II</SP> oxidation in acidic (pH &lt; 1) solutions is a reversible reaction given by eqn. (1):Mn<SP>II</SP>(H<SB>2</SB>O)<SB>6</SB> − e<SP>−</SP> ⇔ Mn<SP>III</SP>(H<SB>2</SB>O)<SB>6</SB>which is characterized by <IT>E</IT><SP>0</SP> = 1.51 V.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit38 cit39">38,39</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac28" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the hydrolysis constant (p<IT>K</IT><SB>a</SB>) for Mn<SP>III</SP> is close to 0, the hydrolysis reaction of Mn<SP>III</SP> with the formation of [Mn<SP>III</SP>(OH)<SP>2+</SP>] takes place at pH &gt; .0<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit38">38</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">This reaction is followed by further hydrolysis to form Mn<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3(aq)</SB> which is a precursor to forming the insoluble solid, Mn<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3(s)</SB>, as summarized in the following equations:2Mn<SP>II</SP> − 2e<SP>−</SP> + 2H<SB>2</SB>O ⇔ 2Mn<SP>III</SP>(OH)<SP>2+</SP> + 2H<SP>+</SP>2Mn<SP>III</SP>(OH)<SP>2+</SP> + 2H<SB>2</SB>O ⇒ Mn<SP>IV</SP>(OH)<SB>4</SB> + Mn<SP>II</SP> + 2H<SP>+</SP>Mn<SP>II</SP> + Mn<SP>IV</SP>(OH)<SB>4</SB> ⇒ Mn<SP>II</SP>Mn<SP>IV</SP>O<SB>3</SB> + H<SB>2</SB>O + 2H<SP>+</SP>2Mn<SP>II</SP> − 2e<SP>−</SP> + 3H<SB>2</SB>O ⇒ Mn<SP>II</SP>Mn<SP>IV</SP>O<SB>3</SB> + 6H<SP>+</SP></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Due to these hydrolysis reactions the wave for Mn<SP>II</SP> oxidation at pH &gt; 0 in the absence of ligands corresponds increasingly to eqns. (1)–(5).</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The hydrolysis reactions are responsible for the irreversibility of reactions (2)–(4).</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, in the presence of ligands (X) that bind to Mn<SP>III</SP> more strongly than water the hydrolysis reactions of Mn<SP>III</SP> are suppressed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, in the presence of the ligands, oxidation of Mn<SP>II</SP> occurs in accordance with reaction (1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The potential for oxidation is no longer equal to 1.51 V, but shifts to lower potentials.</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 2 shows the cyclic voltage–current curve of MnSO<SB>4</SB> (5 × 10<SP>−4</SP> M) oxidation (curve 1) on the background of 0.1 M LiClO<SB>4</SB> in water (curve 0).</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The oxidation wave of Mn<SP>II</SP> aqua-cations with the maximum at 1.18 V is clearly seen on the anode branch of the curve (in good agreement with previous measurements of the potential of Mn<SP>II</SP> oxidation in water solutions).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27">27</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">A small cathode wave at 1.12 V and additional two peaks at 0.96 and 0.28 V are observed upon the return scan, reflecting the presence of all the reactions, <IT>e.g.</IT>, (1–5) of Mn<SP>II</SP> oxidation in water.</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The anode peak of Mn<SP>II</SP> oxidation is shifted to lower potentials (0.82 instead of 1.18 V) upon the addition of <IT>ca</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">100 mM acetate, and the cathode peaks at 0.76 V and at 0.59 V are observed upon the return scan in this case.</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The difference between the anode (E<SB>p</SB><SP>a</SP>) and the first cathode (<IT>E</IT><SB>p</SB><SP>k</SP>) peaks for Mn<SP>II</SP> is equal to 60 mV, both in the presence and absence of acetate thus indicating a reversible transfer of one electron per Mn<SP>II</SP> during the oxidation step.</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The peak current of the cathode peak is much lower than the anode peak current, which indicates that a subsequent transformation of the oxidation product into another product takes place.</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">This oxidation product (the peak at 0.59 V) is attributed to the disproportionation reaction eqn. (3).</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The same picture is observed in the case of formate, oxalate and bicarbonate complexes of Mn<SP>III</SP> (not shown).</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reversibility of the electron transfer was further confirmed by the data on independence of the peak potential difference between <IT>E</IT><SB>p</SB><SP>a</SP> and <IT>E</IT><SB>p</SB><SP>k</SP> on the scan rate in the region from 10 mV s<SP>−1</SP> to 50 mV s<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">These considerations allow us to consider the Mn<SP>II</SP> oxidation process in the presence of ligands as reversible and thus we used eqns. (I) or (II) to determine the composition, the stability constant and standard potential <IT>E</IT><SP>0</SP> for the complexes from the dependence of <IT>E</IT><SB>p</SB> on log <IT>C</IT><SB>X</SB> taking into account that for the free aqua complex of Mn<SP>II</SP>, <IT>E</IT><SP>0</SP><SB>me</SB> = 1.51 V.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit38">38</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the value of the stability constants is well known for Mn<SP>II</SP>-oxalate and Mn<SP>III</SP>-oxalate complexes,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit40">40</REF> we started first by considering the effects of the oxalate (Ox<SP>2−</SP>) on the oxidation of Mn<SP>II</SP> in order to check the validity of using eqns. (I) and (II) to estimate these values.</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Upon addition of sodium oxalate the wave of Mn<SB>aq</SB><SP>II</SP> oxidation (1.18 V in 0.1 M LiClO<SB>4</SB>) is shifted to negative potentials.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the concentration region from 2.15 × 10<SP>−3</SP> M to 7.11 × 10<SP>−3</SP> M (Fig. 3, curve 1) the dependence of the peak potential on log <IT>C</IT><SB>X</SB> is linear and the slope of this dependence (Δ<IT>E</IT>/Δlog <IT>C</IT><SB>X</SB>) is equal to 58 mV, indicating participation of just one ligand in the electrode reaction:Mn<SP>II</SP>− <IT>e</IT><SP>−</SP> + Ox<SP>2−</SP> ⇔ [Mn<SP>III</SP>(Ox<SP>2−</SP>)]<SP>+</SP>.Extrapolation of this linear part of the dependence to log <IT>C</IT><SB>X</SB> = 0 gives the value for <IT>E</IT><SP>0</SP>, equal to 0.92 V. Using eqn. (I), the logarithm of the stability constant of the Mn<SP>III</SP>-oxalate complex is equal to 10 ± 0.01 which is in agreement with the literature data for log <IT>K</IT><SB>st</SB> of [Mn<SP>III</SP>(C<SB>2</SB>O<SB>4</SB><SP>2−</SP>)]<SP>+</SP> equal to 9..98<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit40">40</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">At oxalate concentrations above 7.11 × 10<SP>−3</SP> M, a new linear section with a slope of 126 mV is observed (Fig. 3, curve 1) that reveals an additional electrode process.</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The slope of this section reveals participation of two ligands in the electrode reaction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Extrapolation of the linear dependence of <IT>E</IT><SB>p</SB> to log <IT>C</IT><SB>X</SB> = 0 gives the <IT>E</IT><SP>0</SP> value equal to 0.77 V. The same value is obtained using eqn. (II) and in the available literature data, as follows.</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac29" novelty="None" advantage="None">The dissociation constant of Mn complexes with Ox<SP>2−</SP> are 1.5 × 10<SP>−4</SP> for Mn<SP>II</SP>(Ox<SP>2−</SP>) and 2.72 × 10<SP>−17</SP> for Mn<SP>III</SP>[(Ox<SP>2−</SP>)<SB>2</SB>]<SP>−</SP>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit40">40</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Then the logarithm of <IT>K</IT><SB>ox</SB>/<IT>K</IT><SB>red</SB> will be equal to 12.75 that [according to eqn. (II)] gives Δ<IT>E</IT><SP>0</SP> equal to 0.75 V and <IT>E</IT><SP>0</SP><SB>com</SB> equal to 0.76 V. This (calculated) value agrees with the value of <IT>E</IT><SP>0</SP> obtained from our experimental work (0.77 V).</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">We conclude that the electrode reaction consists in this case of two steps:Mn<SP>II</SP> + Ox<SP>2−</SP> ⇔ Mn<SP>II</SP>(Ox<SP>2−</SP>)Mn<SP>II</SP>(Ox<SP>2−</SP>) − e<SP>−</SP> + Ox<SP>2−</SP> ⇔ [Mn<SP>III</SP>(Ox<SP>2−</SP>)<SB>2</SB>]<SP>−</SP>The agreement with the literature data, as well as the strict linear dependence of <IT>E</IT><SB>P</SB> on log <IT>C</IT><SB>X</SB>, demonstrates the accuracy of our measurements and confirms the suitability of using the eqns. (I) and (II).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Upon the addition of acetate ions (Fig. 2, curve 2), the oxidation peak is also shifted to lower potentials.</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">A linear dependence of the potential <IT>versus</IT> the logarithm of CH<SB>3</SB>COONa concentration is observed over the whole range of acetate concentration from 1 × 10<SP>−3</SP> M to 0.15 M (Fig. 3, curve 2).</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The slope is equal to 120 mV which by eqn. (I), gives <IT>p</IT> = 2 for <IT>n</IT> = 1 and thus corresponds to a 1∶2 ratio of Mn∶acetate, formulated as [Mn<SP>III</SP>(CH<SB>3</SB>COO<SP>−</SP>)<SB>2</SB>]<SP>+</SP>:Mn<SP>II</SP> − <IT>e</IT><SP>−</SP> + 2CH<SB>3</SB>COO<SP>−</SP> → [Mn<SP>III</SP>(CH<SB>3</SB>COO<SP>−</SP>)<SB>2</SB>]<SP>+</SP>.Extrapolation of the potential dependence to log <IT>C</IT><SB>X</SB> = 0 gives <IT>E</IT><SP>0</SP> = 0.69 V for this process and enables calculation of the stability constant for acetate binding, <IT>K</IT><SB>st</SB> = 7.91 × 10<SP>13</SP> at <IT>T</IT> = 21.5 °C.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Essentially identical behaviour is seen for oxidation of Mn<SP>II</SP> in the presence of formate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this case, the shift of <IT>E</IT><SB>P</SB> is characterized by a linear dependence on the logarithm of the formate concentration between 3 × 10<SP>−3</SP> and 1.6 × 10<SP>−1</SP> M, as shown in Fig. 3 (curve 3).</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The slope is equal to 131 ± 5 mV, which according to eqn. (I) gives <IT>p</IT> ≅ 2 at <IT>n</IT> = 1, corresponding to a reaction stoichiometry of 1∶2:Mn<SP>II</SP> − <IT>e</IT><SP>−</SP> + 2HCO<SB>2</SB><SP>−</SP> → [Mn<SP>III</SP>(HCO<SB>2</SB><SP>−</SP>)<SB>2</SB>]<SP>+</SP>.Extrapolation of the data to log <IT>C</IT><SB>X</SB> = 0 gives <IT>E</IT><SP>0</SP> = 0.775 V for Mn<SP>III</SP>(HCO<SB>2</SB><SP>−</SP>)<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP> and a corresponding stability constant <IT>K</IT><SB>st</SB> equal to 2.86 × 10<SP>12</SP>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None">A different behaviour is seen for the dependence of the voltage–current curves for Mn<SP>II</SP> oxidation in the presence of NaHCO<SB>3</SB> (Fig. 4).</annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None">At first (at concentration of NaHCO<SB>3</SB> higher than 6 × 10<SP>−3</SP> M) the peak of Mn<SP>II</SP> oxidation is shifted to lower potentials (Fig. 4, curves 2–4), which is analogous to the data obtained with acetate and formate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, at NaHCO<SB>3</SB> concentrations higher than 2 × 10<SP>−2</SP> M a new Mn<SP>II</SP> oxidation wave appears around 0.70 V. It begins to emerge as a shoulder above 3 × 10<SP>−2</SP> M and becomes the only peak observed at bicarbonate concentration of 8.3 × 10<SP>−2</SP> M (Fig. 4, curves 4–8).</annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Upon further increase of NaHCO<SB>3</SB> (0.1 M and higher) the shift of the oxidation potential of Mn<SP>II</SP> is still observed, however, the height of the oxidation wave begins to decrease progressively due to the precipitation of a white suspension of MnCO<SB>3</SB>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs20" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 3 (curves 4 and 5) shows the dependence of the Mn<SP>II</SP> oxidation potential on the logarithm of bicarbonate (BC) concentration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The dependence reveals three linear components with different slopes reflecting participation of as many as three precursors in the oxidation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac30" novelty="None" advantage="None">We discuss these in sequence.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">(i) The linear dependence of the Mn<SP>II</SP> oxidation potential on log <IT>C</IT><SB>X</SB> at concentration higher than 3 × 10<SP>−3</SP> M, NaHCO<SB>3</SB> (Fig. 3, curve 4) reflects the oxidation of free aqua Mn<SP>II</SP> (in analogy with the other anions) since it extrapolates back to the free Mn<SP>II</SP> potential.</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The slope of this dependence is equal to 173 ± 5 mV, in contrast to the slope for oxalate, acetate and formate, and thus by eqn. (I) corresponds most closely to <IT>p</IT> ≅ 3 for <IT>n</IT> = 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">This ratio suggests participation of three HCO<SB>3</SB><SP>−</SP> anions in this electrode reaction:Mn<SP>II</SP> − e<SP>−</SP> + 3HCO<SB>3</SB><SP>−</SP> ⇔ Mn<SP>III</SP>(HCO<SB>3</SB><SP>−</SP>)<SB>3</SB><IT>E</IT><SP>0</SP> is equal to 0.67 V for this reaction (determined by extrapolation to log <IT>C</IT> = 0).</annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">This value gives a stability constant for Mn<SP>III</SP>(HCO<SB>3</SB><SP>−</SP>)<SB>3</SB><IT>K</IT><SB>st</SB> = 1.73 × 10<SP>14</SP> [<IT>T</IT> = 21 °C].</annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is clearly seen (Fig. 3, curve 4) that the plot of the dependence of Mn<SP>II</SP> oxidation potential on log <IT>C</IT><SB>X</SB> is free of any breaks, thus indicating that a single species is detected, formulated as the electro-neutral species Mn<SP>III</SP>(HCO<SB>3</SB><SP>−</SP>)<SB>3</SB>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">(ii) The voltage–current curves in Fig. 4 show that a second precursor is revealed (as a “new” wave of oxidation) at increasing bicarbonate concentrations that is more easily oxidized (appears at less positive potential) than the previous species.</annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The experimental dependence of the oxidation potential of this new wave on log <IT>C</IT><SB>X</SB> (from −1.4 to −1.08) reveals a linear region with slope equal to 60 ± 2 mV (Fig. 3, curve 5), suggesting the involvement of one additional bicarbonate ion per electron in the oxidation of this new complex.</annotationART></s> <s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Extrapolation of the data in Fig. 3 (curve 5) to log <IT>C</IT><SB>X</SB> = 0 gives the <IT>E</IT><SP>0</SP> = 0.61 V (complex I).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">(iii) Upon further increase of the NaHCO<SB>3</SB> concentration (to 0.1 M and higher) there is a break in the dependence of <IT>E</IT><SB>P</SB> on log <IT>C</IT><SB>X</SB> (Fig. 3, curve 5) with a linear slope equal to 120 ± 10 mV, suggesting the involvement of two additional bicarbonate ions per electron in the oxidation of this new complex.</annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this case, the slope extrapolates to <IT>E</IT><SP>0</SP> = 0.52 V at log <IT>C</IT><SB>X</SB> = 0.</annotationART></s> <s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The appearance of this new section is evidently related to oxidation of another Mn<SP>II</SP>-BC complex (complex II).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac30" novelty="None" advantage="None">Analysis of the dependence of oxidation <IT>E</IT><SB>P</SB> on log <IT>C</IT><SB>X</SB> for both Mn<SP>II</SP>-BC complexes (using eqn. (II)) is complicated since it requires knowledge of the stability constants of the initial Mn<SP>II</SP> complexes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac31" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the literature the values represented for the stability constant, <IT>K</IT><SB>st</SB>, of complex Mn<SP>II</SP>(HCO<SB>3</SB><SP>−</SP>)<SP>+</SP> are different: 186<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28">28</REF>. and 63..1<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29">29</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac32" novelty="None" advantage="None">Sychev <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30 cit31">30,31</REF>. reported the formation of two complexes, Mn<SP>II</SP>(HCO<SB>3</SB><SP>−</SP>)<SP>+</SP> and Mn<SP>II</SP>(HCO<SB>3</SB><SP>−</SP>)<SB>2</SB> having stability constants equal to 11 and 40.7, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac32" novelty="None" advantage="None">This considerable uncertainty in the values of <IT>K</IT><SB>st</SB> requires further work.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs21" novelty="None" advantage="None">A similar dependence of <IT>E</IT><SB>P</SB> on log <IT>C</IT><SB>X</SB> is observed, if the titration is performed at a constant concentration of bicarbonate while changing the Mn<SP>II</SP> concentration (Fig. 5).</annotationART></s> <s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs22" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this case at fixed bicarbonate concentration, the wave associated with complexes I and II appears first followed by formation of the Mn<SB>aq</SB><SP>II</SP> oxidation wave at higher Mn<SP>II</SP> concentration, <IT>e.g.</IT>, in reverse sequence to that observed in Fig 4.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">After recording the background curve (Fig. 5, curve 0), 0.05 M NaHCO<SB>3</SB> was added and the background in the presence of NaHCO<SB>3</SB> was again measured (curve 0<SP>1</SP>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">The titration shows the step-by-step addition of MnSO<SB>4</SB> (from 55 μM to 1 mM).</annotationART></s> <s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs23" novelty="None" advantage="None">Under these experimental conditions, the wave of the most stable Mn–bicarbonate complex at <IT>E</IT><SB>P</SB> = 0.56 V appears first (curve 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs23" novelty="None" advantage="None">The amplitude of this wave is linearly increased upon the increase of the Mn<SP>II</SP> concentration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs24" novelty="None" advantage="None">Analysis of the <IT>E</IT><SB>P</SB> shift for curves 1–6 yields a linear slope Δ<IT>E</IT>/Δlog <IT>C</IT><SB>Mn</SB> of 120 mV, followed by (curves 7–9) a shallower slope, Δ<IT>E</IT>/Δlog <IT>C</IT><SB>Mn</SB> approximately equal to <IT>ca</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs24" novelty="None" advantage="None">60 mV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs25" novelty="None" advantage="None">At this concentration, one sees that a new current wave also appears at a potential of <IT>ca</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs26" novelty="None" advantage="None">0.9 V. This peak shifts to more positive potentials with increasing concentrations of Mn<SP>II</SP> (curves 7–12) with a slope Δ<IT>E</IT>/Δlog <IT>C</IT> equal to 180 mV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this region (curves 7–12) Mn<SB>ag</SB><SP>II</SP> is oxidized by the reaction:Mn<SP>II</SP> − e<SP>−</SP> + 3HCO<SB>3</SB><SP>−</SP> ⇒ Mn<SP>III</SP>(HCO<SB>3</SB><SP>−</SP>)<SB>3</SB>.The observed equilibria are the same as found in Fig. 4.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Discussion</HEADER><P><s sid="143"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The data presented herein show that only bicarbonate but not carboxylate ligands (acetate, formate) is capable of stimulating the photooxidation rate of Mn<SB>aq</SB><SP>II</SP> by Mn-depleted apo-WOC-PSII.</annotationART></s> <s sid="144"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">This stimulation occurs using Mn<SP>II</SP> concentrations equal to the native stoichiometry of 4 Mn/PSII and over a 1000-fold range in ligand concentrations.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="145"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac33" novelty="None" advantage="None">The electrochemical characteristics of Mn<SP>II</SP> oxidation offer a possible explanation for the stimulation of the photooxidation rate and its selectivity for bicarbonate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="146"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The oxidation potential for Mn<SP>III</SP>/Mn<SP>II</SP> decreases from 1.18 V for Mn<SB>aq</SB><SP>II</SP> (in 0.1 M LiClO<SB>4</SB>, pH independent in the region pH 5.0–pH 8.5) to less positive values upon formation of Mn<SP>III</SP> complexes with acetate, formate, oxalate and bicarbonate, respectively:Mn<SP>II</SP> − <IT>e</IT><SP>−</SP> + 2CH<SB>3</SB>COO<SP>−</SP> ⇔ [Mn<SP>III</SP>(CH<SB>3</SB>COO<SP>−</SP>)<SB>2</SB>]<SP>+</SP><IT>E</IT><SP>0</SP> = 0.69 V, (<IT>K</IT><SB>st</SB> = 7.9 × 10<SP>13</SP>)Mn<SP>II</SP> − <IT>e</IT><SP>−</SP> + 2HCO<SB>2</SB><SP>−</SP> ⇔ [Mn<SP>III</SP>(HCO<SB>2</SB><SP>−</SP>)<SB>2</SB>]<SP>+</SP><IT>E</IT><SP>0</SP> = 0.775 V, (<IT>K</IT><SB>st</SB> = 2.9 × 10<SP>12</SP>)Mn<SP>II</SP> − <IT>e</IT><SP>−</SP> + Ox<SP>2−</SP> ⇔ [Mn<SP>III</SP>(Ox<SP>2−</SP>)]<SP>+</SP><IT>E</IT><SP>0</SP> = 0.92 V, (<IT>K</IT><SB>st</SB> = 1.0 × 10<SP>10</SP>)Mn<SP>II</SP> − <IT>e</IT><SP>−</SP> + 3HCO<SB>3</SB><SP>−</SP> ⇔ Mn<SP>III</SP>(HCO<SB>3</SB><SP>−</SP>)<SB>3</SB><IT>E</IT><SP>0</SP> = 0.67 V, (<IT>K</IT><SB>st</SB> = 1.7 × 10<SP>14</SP>)In the bicarbonate stimulated oxidation process the stoichiometry of 3 bicarbonates reflects the total number of bicarbonate molecules involved in the process and thus includes several potential Mn<SP>III</SP> species differing in both ligation and deprotonation of bicarbonate and hydroxide.</annotationART></s> <s sid="147"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Only bicarbonate exhibits two additional electrochemical processes corresponding to two more easily oxidizable Mn<SP>II</SP>-BC complexes (denoted complexes I and II):Mn<SP>II</SP> − BC<SB>complex I</SB> − <IT>e</IT><SP>−</SP> + HCO<SB>3</SB><SP>−</SP> ⇔ Mn<SP>III</SP>(HCO<SB>3</SB><SP>−</SP>)<SB>3</SB><IT>E</IT><SP>0</SP> = 0.61 VMn<SP>II</SP> − BC<SB>complex II</SB> − <IT>e</IT><SP>−</SP> + 2HCO<SB>3</SB><SP>−</SP> ⇔ Mn<SP>III</SP>(HCO<SB>3</SB><SP>−</SP>)<SB>3</SB><IT>E</IT><SP>0</SP> = 0.52 VThe formation of these Mn<SP>II</SP> complexes with bicarbonate results in a maximum decrease of the oxidation potential of Mn<SP>II</SP> that is probably important for their redox interaction with apo-WOC-PSII.</annotationART></s> <s sid="148"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">These complexes form at bicarbonate concentrations above 0.025 M, which is close to the upper concentration region, we could explore, owing to the onset of precipitation of MnCO<SB>3</SB> at 0.1 M. It is possible that these Mn<SP>II</SP>–BC complexes represent oligomeric Mn<SB><IT>n</IT></SB>(BC)<SB><IT>m</IT></SB> clusters.</annotationART></s> <s sid="149"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac34" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the instability of the solutions to precipitation did not allow a wider study of the dependence on Mn and bicarbonate concentrations.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="150"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">In case of acetate and formate, a positively charged complex, Mn<SP>III</SP>L<SB>2</SB>, forms upon oxidation of Mn<SB>aq</SB><SP>II</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="151"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Only for bicarbonate does the neutral complex Mn<SP>III</SP>(HCO<SB>3</SB><SP>−</SP>)<SB>3</SB> form upon oxidation of Mn<SB>aq</SB><SP>II</SP><SB>.</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="152"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The absence of breaks in the plot of <IT>E</IT><SB>P</SB><IT>vs.</IT> log of the concentration of acetate and formate shows that, in spite of the possibility of formation of Mn<SP>II</SP>-complexes with the added ligands (log <IT>K</IT><SB>st</SB> for the Mn<SP>II</SP>–(CH<SB>3</SB>COO<SP>−</SP>)<SP>+</SP> is equal to 1.2),<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit40">40</REF> there is no additional wave related to the oxidation of the Mn<SP>II</SP>L complexes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="153"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">These results suggest that these complexes are either not electroactive or are not stable in solution at the surface of the positively charged electrode.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="154"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac35" novelty="None" advantage="None">For Mn<SP>II</SP>-complexes with acetate, formate and bicarbonate the value of the stability constant is known to be <IT>ca</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="155"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac35" novelty="None" advantage="None">10<SP>1</SP>–10<SP>2</SP>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27 cit28 cit40">27,28,40</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="156"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The large difference in the stability constants for Mn<SP>II</SP><IT>vs.</IT> Mn<SP>III</SP> complexes is a clear indicator of large differences in the kinetics of binding/dissociation and thus will be of importance for understanding the dynamics of Mn photooxidation by the WOC.</annotationART></s> <s sid="157"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">This difference may explain the considerable variations in the bicarbonate concentration (from μM to mM) measured for optimal reconstitution of electron transfer rates from Mn<SP>II</SP> to apo-WOC-PSII.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14 cit15 cit16 cit17 cit18 cit19 cit20 cit21 cit22">14–22</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="158"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">These variations could reflect changes in the average oxidation state of manganese ions as they assemble to form the Mn<SB>4</SB> cluster or upon the S-state transitions of the WOC.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="159"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac36" novelty="None" advantage="None">The electrochemical data allow us to answer why the Y<SB>Z</SB>˙ radical in PSII is capable of oxidizing Mn<SP>II</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="160"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The <IT>E</IT><SP>0</SP> value for Mn<SB>aq</SB><SP>II</SP> is equal to 1.18 V, which is higher than the oxidation potential of the Y<SB>Z</SB>˙ radical estimated to 0.95–1.0 V.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit41">41</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="161"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None">We may conclude that Mn<SP>II</SP> can be efficiently oxidized by Y<SB>Z</SB>˙ only in the presence of ligands capable of shifting the Mn<SP>II</SP> oxidation potential to a lower value and thus stabilizing the Mn<SP>III</SP> oxidation state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="162"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Nevertheless, the effect of these anions on electron transfer from Mn<SP>II</SP> to apo-WOC-PSII is quite different.</annotationART></s> <s sid="163"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">Acetate and formate are not active in stimulation of electron transfer from Mn<SP>II</SP> to apo-WOC-PSII, although both anions considerably lower the reduction potential of Mn<SP>III</SP>/Mn<SP>II</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="164"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">Bicarbonate efficiently stimulates the process of Mn<SP>II</SP>-dependent electron transfer to apo-WOC-PSII, and is also known to reverse the formate-induced inhibition of electron transport from Mn<SP>II</SP> and O<SB>2</SB> evolution of functionally active PSII with high specificity.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14 cit15 cit16 cit17 cit18">14–18</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="165"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, bicarbonate is special and presumably binds together with Mn<SP>II</SP> to apo-WOC-PSII forming a ternary complex that is capable of efficient photooxidation of additional Mn<SP>II</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="166"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None">This ternary complex may form starting either with Mn<SB>aq</SB><SP>II</SP> or the Mn<SP>II</SP>-BC complexes I and II as precursors.</annotationART></s> <s sid="167"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the current results have not identified which one or all of these precursors is involved, nor the structure of these complexes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="168"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac37" novelty="None" advantage="None">One may consider the following differences as possible reasons for the advantage of bicarbonate <IT>vs.</IT> carboxylate anions in stimulating the photooxidation rate of Mn<SP>II</SP> by apo-WOC-PSII:</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="169"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None">(i) Only bicarbonate forms an electro-neutral complex Mn<SP>III</SP>(HCO<SB>3</SB><SP>−</SP>)<SB>3</SB>, while the other ligands form charged complexes: [Mn<SP>III</SP>(HCO<SB>2</SB><SP>−</SP>)<SB>2</SB>]<SP>+</SP>, [Mn<SP>III</SP>(CH<SB>3</SB>COO<SP>−</SP>)<SB>2</SB>]<SP>+</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="170"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac38" novelty="None" advantage="None">Net charge exerts influence on the local concentration of the Mn<SP>II</SP> precursor near PSII.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit42">42</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="171"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None">(ii) Since photooxidation of Mn<SP>II</SP> with Y<SB>Z</SB>˙ in apo-WOC-PSII releases a proton on the first and subsequent steps,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit42 cit43">42,43</REF> ligands such as acetate, formate or oxalate, which have a low p<IT>K</IT> 2–4, may not be suitable for exchanging H<SP>+</SP> with the medium at pH 6.5 (used in the PSII experiments), <IT>versus</IT> the higher proton affinity of bicarbonate (p<IT>K</IT><SB>a</SB> = 6.4).</annotationART></s> <s sid="172"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac39" novelty="None" advantage="None">Bicarbonate is also amphoteric having both acidic and basic properties (carbonate p<IT>K</IT><SB>a</SB> = 10.3).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="173"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None">(iii) On the basis of our electrochemical results, the bicarbonate stoichiometry is 3 for the formation of the Mn<SP>III</SP>-bicarbonate complex.</annotationART></s> <s sid="174"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac40" novelty="None" advantage="None">The high Lewis acidity of Mn<SP>III</SP> (p<IT>K</IT><SB>a</SB> ≈ 1)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit39">39</REF> requires that Mn<SP>III</SP>(HCO<SB>3</SB><SP>−</SP>)<SB>3</SB> will ionize one or more HCO<SB>3</SB><SP>−</SP> ligands to form Mn<SP>III</SP>(HCO<SB>3</SB><SP>−</SP>)<SB>2</SB>(OH<SP>−</SP>)<SB>1</SB> + CO<SB>2</SB> or Mn<SP>III</SP>(HCO<SB>3</SB><SP>−</SP>)(CO<SB>3</SB><SP>2−</SP>) + CO<SB>2</SB> at pH 8.3 used in the present studies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="175"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Formation of these complexes may stimulate both the kinetics of incorporation of Mn<SP>II</SP> into the apo-WOC and the subsequent assembly of other Mn<SP>II</SP> ions during reconstitution of the Mn<SB>4</SB>O<SB><IT>x</IT></SB> core of the WOC.</annotationART></s> <s sid="176"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thermodynamic data also confirm this proposal.</annotationART></s> <s sid="177"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac41" novelty="None" advantage="None">The energy required to dissociate OH<SP>−</SP> from bicarbonate is considerably smaller (8.9 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>) than the energy for dissociation of OH<SP>−</SP> from water (21.4 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit44">44</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="178"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac42" novelty="None" advantage="None">(iv) The maximum decrease of the potential of Mn<SP>II</SP> oxidation (down to 0.52 V) is observed for Mn<SP>II</SP>–BC complex II, which forms at the highest bicarbonate concentration studied (&gt;0.1 M).</annotationART></s> <s sid="179"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac43" novelty="None" advantage="None">We previously suggested that Mn<SP>II</SP>–BC complexes were similar to the major Mn<SP>II</SP> species in the oceans of the Archean period (&gt;2.2 BYA), where estimates of the bicarbonate concentration are considerably higher than for the contemporary ocean (10–10<SP>4</SP> mM).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit44">44</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="180"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac44" novelty="None" advantage="None">The electrochemical potentials of Mn<SP>II</SP>–BC complexes I and II (0.61 and 0.52 V) indicate that they are thermodynamically capable of serving as electron donors to reaction centers of both green and purple photoautotrophic bacteria (<IT>E</IT><SP>0</SP> ∼ 0.26–0.55 V).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit45">45</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="181"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac45" novelty="None" advantage="None">Recently, it has been shown that Mn–bicarbonate complexes can serve as electron donor to bacterial reaction centers genetically modified to shift the redox potential of the primary electron donor to more positive potentials<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit46">46</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
