<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b407316a" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Preliminary structural characterisation of the 33 kDa protein (PsbO) in solution studied by site-directed mutagenesis and NMR spectroscopy<XREF TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" /></annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Site-directed mutagenesis experiments combined with 1D and 2D NMR spectra provide a preliminary insight into the structure and dynamics of the 33 kDa protein (PsbO) from <IT>T. elongatus</IT> free in solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The NMR spectra suggest that PsbO rather than forming a ‘molten globule’ state or being ‘natively unfolded’, contains both a well folded core and highly flexible regions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This core shows remarkable stability over a broad range of temperatures and pH values.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Additional experiments with Cys residues introduced at different positions indicate sites of increased accessibility/flexibility which may be important for the docking to the PS2 core complex.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Photosystem 2 (PS2) is part of the thylakoid membrane of chloroplasts and cyanobacteria and performs one of the key reactions on our planet: the light-driven oxidation of water.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2">1,2</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">It consists of more than 20 polypeptides, most of them with no function identified yet.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Especially, the role of the numerous small membrane spanning peptides is still unclear.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The primary electron transfer reaction occurs at the heterodimeric core of PS2 formed by the subunits D1 and D2, which bind most of the redox active cofactors.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Water oxidation to molecular oxygen is catalysed <IT>via</IT> the sequence of four one-electron oxidation steps (S-states) by the manganese containing water-oxidising complex (WOC).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Recent advances in X-ray structure analysis of PS2 crystals<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6">5,6</REF> provide a detailed view of the structure and organisation of the WOC.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">At the lumen side of PS2, the WOC is shielded by several extrinsic proteins.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">One of them, the 33 kDa protein (PsbO), is of special interest because it is ubiquitous in all photosynthetic organisms performing water-splitting and its extraction results in a strong decrease of the oxygen evolving activity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, it is often referred to as manganese stabilizing protein (MSP).</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, it is obvious from the recently published PS2 X-ray structure<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF> that the PsbO subunit is not directly involved in binding of manganese as part of the WOC.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Several lines of experiments using different kinds of spectroscopic techniques or biochemical and theoretical analyses have made suggestions about the PsbO structure and its behaviour free in solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">It was concluded from Fourier transform infrared (FTIR) spectroscopy<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit9 cit10">8–10</REF> and circular dichroism (CD) spectroscopy<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11 cit12">11,12</REF> that the PsbO subunit in solution consists of a high content of β-sheet (30%) and random/loop structure (60%) whereas <IT>α</IT>-helical parts are only present in small amounts (10%).</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">These results were consistent with secondary structure prediction methods and folding models of the 33 kDa protein.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13 cit14 cit15">13–15</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Some authors suggested an unusual folding behaviour for PsbO in solution and therefore postulated an ‘intrinsically disordered’, ‘natively unfolded’ or ‘molten globule’ protein structure.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10 cit16">10,16</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Experiments with focus on the dynamic properties of the PsbO subunit led to the observation of pH-dependent and cofactor-induced structural changes in solution.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11 cit17 cit18">11,17,18</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Recently, it was reported that reconstitution of the PS2-complex with PsbO is accompanied by changes of its secondary structure.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19">19</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Indeed, there are hints for structural changes of the bound PsbO subunit depending on the oxidation state of the manganese cluster.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20 cit21">20,21</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Here we report preliminary results from NMR-spectroscopy on PsbO from <IT>Thermosynechococcus elongatus</IT> (<IT>T. elongatus</IT>) describing its structural and dynamic properties.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The 1D and 2D NMR spectra suggest that PsbO free in solution adopts a defined structured core.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The spectra also indicate that the PsbO from <IT>T. elongatus</IT> in solution contains a considerable amount of flexible regions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The PsbO protein shows a remarkable temperature, pH, and long term stability beeing stable for at least four weeks under the conditions tested in this study.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Due to this extraordinary stability of PsbO, we characterised four cysteine mutants serving as local probes for structural and dynamic properties of PsbO.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Materials and methods</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Sample preparation</HEADER><P><s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The recombinant 33 kDa protein was expressed in <IT>E. coli</IT> from an expression plasmid containing the full-length sequence of the <IT>T. elongatus psbO</IT> gene resulting in the export of PsbO into the periplasmic space.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Point mutations were constructed by oligonucleotide-directed mutagenesis.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The periplasmic cell-fraction highly enriched with 33 kDa protein was isolated,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF> dialysed against 20 mM Tris pH 8.0, 0.5 M mannitol, and loaded onto a ResourceQ column (Amersham-Pharmacia).</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The protein was eluted with a linear gradient from 0 to 0.5 M NaCl.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">By this method, we obtained highly purified PsbO (up to 20 mg L<SP>−1</SP> culture).</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The <SP>15</SP>N-labeled samples were prepared from minimal medium with <SP>15</SP>N NH<SB>4</SB>Cl as the nitrogen source.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25">25</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Unless otherwise stated, PsbO protein samples for NMR experiments were prepared in 20 mM Na-phosphate buffer, pH 3.6, supplemented with 10% D<SB>2</SB>O.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">To prove the integrity of the recombinant protein, reconstitution experiments were performed with PS2 particles prepared according to .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26">ref. 26</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">These particles were washed with 1 M CaCl<SB>2</SB> to remove the extrinsic proteins before adding the recombinant PsbO protein<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27">27</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>NMR spectroscopy</HEADER><P><s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">NMR experiments were carried out at different pH and at different temperatures on a Bruker DRX600 spectrometer equipped with a 5 mm BBI probe and a <IT>z</IT>-axis gradient unit.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Water suppression for 1D and 2D experiments was achieved by the watergate pulse scheme.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28">28</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="New" advantage="None">The 1D <SP>1</SP>H NMR spectrum was recorded with a time domain of 32 k complex points and a sweep width of 12376.24 Hz.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="New" advantage="None">The 2D <SP>1</SP>H-<SP>15</SP>N HSQC spectrum was recorded with a time domain of 2 k complex data points with 256 complex increments collected, and a sweep width of 12019.23 Hz in the <SP>1</SP>H and 2128.68 Hz in the <SP>15</SP>N dimension.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Modified versions of the experiment proposed previously were used to determine <SP>15</SP>N{<SP>1</SP>H}-NOE at 600.13 MHz proton frequency.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29 cit30 cit31 cit32 cit33 cit34 cit35 cit36">29–36</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="New" advantage="None">The <SP>15</SP>N{<SP>1</SP>H}-NOE experiment was recorded using a 4.9 s saturation period and an additional recycle delay of 5 s.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="New" advantage="None">The <SP>15</SP>N{<SP>1</SP>H}-NOE was recorded in an interleaved manner to reduce influences from possible instabilities under the chosen experimental conditions.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Data analysis</HEADER><P><s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">NMR spectra were processed and analysed with XWINNMR (Bruker, Rheinstetten, Germany), NMRPipe, NMRDraw, and NMRView.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit37">37</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">NOE values were calculated from the ratio of the peak heights in the experiment with and without proton saturation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Uncertainties for NOE values were determined from triple recording of the whole relaxation experiment.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Albeit no assignments are available, the NOE values were quantified based on the fraction of resolved peaks with NOE values less than 0.5 <IT>versus</IT> the total number of resolved resonances observed in the experiment.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Results and discussion</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Recombinant wild-type PsbO (WT-PsbO)</HEADER><P><s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this report, we have used NMR-spectroscopy to elucidate preliminary structural and dynamic properties of the 33 kDa protein from the donor side of PS2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to investigate functional aspects of this protein, we have also carried out site-directed mutagenesis experiments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="New" advantage="None">The PsbO protein from the thermophilic cyanobacterium <IT>T. elongatus</IT> was overexpressed in <IT>E. coli.</IT> Its ability to restore the water splitting activity of CaCl<SB>2</SB>-washed PS2 was shown by reconstitution experiments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Routinely, about 50% of the original oxygen-evolving activity was obtained with the reconstituted PS2 (data not shown).</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 1 shows the 1D <SP>1</SP>H NMR spectrum of wild-type PsbO free in solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The dispersion of aliphatic and amide proton resonances clearly indicates that the protein is, at least in part, comprised of a well folded core domain.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to test the influence of different experimental conditions on the stability of WT-PsbO we recorded several 1D <SP>1</SP>H NMR spectra at different pH values and at different temperatures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">No significant changes in the 1D <SP>1</SP>H NMR spectra were observed for spectra recorded at pH 3.6, 6.5, and 8.0.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Obviously, PsbO retains its fold and is not denatured by lowering the pH from 6.5 to 3.6.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="New" advantage="None">Therefore, we recorded several 1D NMR spectra at 298 K, 310 K, 313 K, and 318 K with a buffer pH adjusted to 3.6.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The line width of these 1D spectra did not change dramatically suggesting that PsbO structure is stable at higher temperatures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In conclusion, the free thermophilic PsbO in solution is stable at pH 3.6 and 310 K as judged from the signal dispersion in the NMR spectra.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">No significant protein degradation was observed even after four weeks.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 2 shows a 2D <SP>1</SP>H-<SP>15</SP>N HSQC spectrum of PsbO isotopically enriched with <SP>15</SP>N at pH 3.6 and 310 K. The 2D <SP>1</SP>H-<SP>15</SP>N HSQC spectrum is characterised by a substantial amount of well dipersed resonances indicative for secondary structure elements (especially <IT>β</IT>-sheet) present in PsbO.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit38 cit39 cit40">38–40</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the 1D <SP>1</SP>H NMR and the 2D <SP>1</SP>H-<SP>15</SP>N HSQC spectra also show intense signals at 1–2 ppm and at 8.5 ppm characteristic for unstructured polypeptide chains.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is consistent with the X-ray structure of PsbO that contains 30% β-sheet and 5% α-helix with several loops involved in binding to the PS2-complex.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Remarkably, 65% of PsbO do not show any secondary structure elements in the X-ray structure of the PS2 complex.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is further corroborated by the <SP>15</SP>N{<SP>1</SP>H} NOE of wild-type PsbO.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Out of 109 resolved and dispersed resonances in the <SP>15</SP>N{<SP>1</SP>H} NOE experiment, approximately 29 show values less than 0.5 suggesting that these residues are part of unstructured elements of PsbO (data not shown).</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="New" advantage="None">Peaks that cluster around 8.5 ppm have been omitted in this preliminary analysis due to spectral overlap.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Based on the <SP>15</SP>N{<SP>1</SP>H} NOE, at least an estimated 30% to 40% of all residues of WT-PsbO show increased flexibility on the ps to ns time scale (data not shown).</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Nevertheless, this is only in part consistent with the analysis of the B-factors obtained from the X-ray structure where the loops do not show elevated values compared to the core of PsbO.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">From this preliminary comparison, it appears that flexible regions of free PsbO are motional restricted when bound to the PS2 complex.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Overall, the 2D <SP>1</SP>H-<SP>15</SP>N HSQC spectrum of wild-type PsbO is characteristic for a folded protein which also contains a considerable amount of unstructured parts.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the presence of a considerable amount of flexible regions in the free form of PsbO does not explain why PsbO from <IT>T. elongatus</IT> exhibits a higher thermostability than PsbO from spinach, especially as the content of Pro residues is virtually indentical in both organisms (5.6% for spinach compared to 5.3% for <IT>T. elongatus</IT>).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit43">43</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">In conclusion, the structured core should be one of the major reasons for the thermostability of the thermophilic 33 kDa protein where a variety of factors may contribute to this stability as shown for other thermophilic proteins<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit41">41</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Site-directed mutagenesis of PsbO</HEADER><P><s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to investigate the accessibility and mobility of surface-exposed structural protein elements, we created four mutants containing an additional cystein each at a different position in the amino acid chain of PsbO.</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="New" advantage="None">These mutants were analysed by SDS-PAGE in the presence and absence of DTT.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 3 shows that two of them, N58C and E180C, form dimers whereas T94C and Q196C are monomeric under oxidizing conditions.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac20" novelty="None" advantage="None">The mutations T94C and Q196C are located in the folded <IT>β</IT>-barrel core of PsbO while the mutations E180C and N58C are part of the extended loops.</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac21" novelty="None" advantage="None">Obviously, the folded core region sterically prevents the formation of a dimer while the Cys residues in the loops are easily accessible for interaction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None">From these results we conclude, that the regions around residues Asn58 and Glu180 of PsbO are either flexible and/or solvent exposed to allow the formation of a disulfide bond between two PsbO molecules.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 4 shows 1D <SP>1</SP>H NMR spectra of the oxidised and the reduced form of mutant N58C and E180C.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Interestingly, in our experiments the signal dispersion and the line width in the 1D NMR spectra of the reduced mutant proteins does not dramatically differ from the spectra recorded in the absence of DTT.</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Typically, the line width for several selected aliphatic resonances is approximately 24–27 Hz for WT-PsbO, 28–29 Hz for oxidised N58C and 21–22 Hz for reduced N58C, and approximately 24 Hz for oxidised E180C as well as for reduced E180C.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">These values indicate that the line width does not significantly change upon reduction of the oxidised mutants of PsbO as a more dramatic change would be expected from the decrease in molecular weight (52 kDa compared to 26 kDa).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None">This suggests that both PsbO domains of the disulfide linked dimer are folded and tumble, at least to a significant extent, independently free in solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None">From this we conclude that the loops carrying the point mutation exhibit an increased degree of flexibility in the apo-form of PsbO.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Especially, the reduced and the oxidised form of the PsbO E180C mutant show a signal dispersion and line widths in the 1D NMR spectrum that are virtually identical and comparable to the spectra of WT-PsbO.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac22" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is interesting to note that especially the longer loop (carrying the mutation E180C) which is composed of 40 residues does not show any secondary structure elements in the X-ray structure of the PS2 complex from <IT>T. elongatus</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac23" novelty="None" advantage="None">This loop does not show elevated B-factors in comparison to the core of the protein which could be explained by its various contacts to other subunits of the PS2 complex, such as D2, CP47, and the 12 kDa-Protein (PsbU).</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Comparing the preliminary results presented in this study with the B-factors for loop regions and the core of PsbO from the X-ray structure, we propose that originally flexible loops of free PsbO, <IT>e.g.</IT> the longer loop, are structurally better defined after complexation with PS2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, our analysis of the cysteine mutants indicates that the presence of the disulfide bond C19–C44 in PsbO from <IT>T. elongatus</IT> might not be critical for a stable fold.</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is also in accordance with the observation that removal of the cysteins of PsbO by mutagenesis neither impaired its binding to PS2 nor influenced its water-splitting activity.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit42">42</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Further, Fig. 1 shows that the line width of the 1D <SP>1</SP>H NMR spectrum of WT-PsbO is characteristic for a monomeric state of the protein in solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is corroborated by the results from HPLC size exclusion experiments that show a monodispersed peak corresponding to an approximate molecular weight of 20 kDa for the recombinant PsbO (data not shown).</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con15" novelty="None" advantage="None">This suggests that WT-PsbO is monomeric in solution.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con16" novelty="None" advantage="None">In summary, we have shown by NMR-spectroscopy that apo-PsbO contains folded structural elements as concluded from the signal dispersion of 1D and 2D NMR spectra.</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our data suggest that PsbO, rather than forming a ‘molten globule’ state or being ‘natively unfolded’, contains both a well folded core and highly flexible regions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, the <SP>15</SP>N{<SP>1</SP>H}-NOE experiment provides evidence for a significant number of residues that show a higher degree of flexibility (approx.</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">30–40%).</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Spectra of the oxidised and reduced forms of PsbO N58C and PsbO E180C suggest that loops responsible for the interaction with the PS2 complex are flexible and/or solvent exposed when free in solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Comparing our preliminary results with the B-factors for loop regions and the core of PsbO from the X-ray structure, there is evidence for the compelling hypothesis that originally flexible loops of free PsbO get motional restricted upon binding to PS2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is further corroborated by the changes of apparent hyperfine splitting and line width of EPR spectra recorded with spin labeled PsbO E180C free in solution and after reconstitution of the PS2 complex (Nowaczyk, unpublished data).</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Based on these results we propose that changes in the flexibility between the free and bound form of PsbO, particularly of the loop regions, are responsible for an efficient binding of PsbO to the PS2 core and might play a crucial role in modulating the binding affinity.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
