<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b411356j" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Microchip-based enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (microELISA) system with thermal lens detection</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">A microchip-based enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (microELISA) system was developed and interferon-γ was successfully determined.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">The system was composed of a microchip with a Y-shaped microchannel and a dam structure, polystyrene microbeads, and a thermal lens microscope (TLM).</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">All reactions required for the immunoassay were done in the microchannel by successive introduction of a sample and regents.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">The enzyme reaction product, in a liquid phase, was detected downstream in the channel using the TLM as substrate solution was injected.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">The antigen-antibody reaction time was shortened by the microchip integration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The limit of the determination was improved by adopting the enzyme label.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Moreover, detection procedures were greatly simplified and required time for the detection was significantly cut.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The system has good potential to be developed as a small and automated high throughput analyzer.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Immunoassay, represented by enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA), is a well-known and important analytical method in the life sciences.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">It is an indispensable technique in biochemistry and clinical diagnosis fields because of its extremely high specificity and sensitivity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="No">The conventional heterogeneous immunoassay, however, has a relatively long assay time, and involves troublesome liquid-handling procedures and many expensive antibody reagents.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="No">Moreover, automated assay systems used for clinical diagnoses require rather large apparatuses.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">A microchip-based system is potentially an effective way to realize a highly sensitive analysis system which overcomes these drawbacks.</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Integration of analytical systems into a microchip should bring about enhanced reaction efficiency, simplified procedures, shortened assay time, and lowered consumption of samples, reagents, and energy.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Some papers have reported on miniaturization of ELISA or immunosorbent assay systems, in which antigen and antibodies are fixed on a solid surface in a microchip.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2 cit3 cit4 cit5 cit6 cit7 cit8 cit9 cit10 cit11">1–11</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Most were preliminary reports that only mentioned the possibility of immunosorbent assay or an antigen-antibody reaction in a microfabricated device, however, we described a microchip-based immunosorbent assay system for determinations of some proteins with high sensitivity.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">2</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">In that paper, we showed the reaction time necessary for an antigen-antibody reaction was reduced to 1/90 in the integrated system, because of size effects of the liquid microspace.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Moreover, we applied this system to a clinical diagnosis system, which is based on a determination of a major tumor marker for colon cancer known as human carcinoembryonic antigen (CEA).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">The system provided rapid and sensitive determination and showed a high correlation with the conventional assay in practical measurements of patients' sera.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, we succeeded in doing a simultaneous assay of multiple samples with a microchip which had branching parallel multichannels.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The high sensitivity of our microchip-based immunoassay system was attributable to the combination of a good labeling material, <IT>i.e.</IT> colloidal gold nanoparticles, and an ultra high sensitive detector, a thermal lens microscope (TLM).</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In the system, colloidal gold fixed on the surface of microbeads <IT>via</IT> an antigen-antibody complex was detected by focused laser beams.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="No">Although the method had high sensitivity, the precision was poor because of the difficulty in focusing the laser onto the top of spherical surface and the heterogeneity of the protein adsorption and antigen-antibody reaction on the small areas of the beads.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Therefore, for determination of one sample, 5–10 beads had to be measured with the TLM while the laser was successively focused on the top of each bead and then the average was taken.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hence, the procedures for detection were very troublesome and time-consuming and good instrumental skills were necessary.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Whereas, the reaction time required for the antigen-antibody reaction was sharply cut by microchip integration, reduction of the total assay time was limited because of the troublesome detection procedures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Improvement of the detection scheme is effective to realize higher throughput and more precise assay.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">In this paper, an ELISA system was integrated into a microchip, in which peroxidase was used as a labeling material instead of colloidal gold and an enzyme reaction product was detected in a microchannel with the TLM.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Detecting the reaction product in a solution was much easier to do than making surface measurements and determination limit was improved by adoption of the enzyme label due to amplification of the signals derived by the enzyme reaction.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Materials and methods</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Assay scheme</HEADER><P><s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Schematic illustrations of our bead-bed microELISA system are shown in Fig. 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Polystyrene beads pre-coated with a capture antibody were put into the reaction channel of the ELISA microchip (Fig. 1-1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Next, a sample containing an antigen (Fig. 1-2), a biotinylated second antibody (Fig. 1-3), and streptavidin-peroxidase conjugate (Fig. 1-4) were introduced into the channel, successively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Finally enzyme reaction substrate solutions were continuously pumped into the channel (Fig. 1-5), while monitoring the reaction product with the TLM positioned downstream (Fig. 1-6).</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Microchip fabrication</HEADER><P><s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">A dam structure is necessary to pack a definite amount of the microbeads in the microchip.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In our previous paper, we reported a two-step fabrication method, <IT>i.e.</IT> the combination of laser abrasion for microchannel formation and dry etching by a fast atom beam for dam structure formation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="No">This method, however, was troublesome and time-consuming and required expensive large equipment.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">For easy and rapid fabrication of the chip, we developed a one-step or two-step wet etching method in which the chip was fabricated by simply combining standard photolithography and wet chemical etching techniques.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The basic etching procedures were described previously.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In the one-step method, the microchannel and dam were fabricated simultaneously.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the dam structure, a photomask with a gapped channel pattern was used (Fig. 2A).</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">After photolithography, the gapped narrow window was opened on a Pyrex glass surface, and then the glass substrate was etched isotropically with HF solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Two separate narrow channels appeared at first; these became wider and deeper and then came to connect to one channel with a neck as etching proceeded.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">By this method, microchannels and dam were simultaneously created only with a simple one-step etching.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The structure image of the dam region is shown in Fig. 2B.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Two channels with curved surface were connected slightly at the center of the image.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Beads can be retained one side of the dam region.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">For the two-step method, the microchannel and dam were fabricated individually by using a different photomask for each.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The former mask had a wider gap than that of the one-step method for dam region.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The first wet etching was terminated before the two channels were connected.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Next, photoresists that remained on the dam area were removed by the second photolithography and then the appeared glass substrate was etched to become the dam structure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Using this method, the microchannel and the dam were individually fabricated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The etched substrate was laminated with a cover plate, which had reagent inlet and outlet holes using a thermal fusion bonding method as described previously<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Reagents</HEADER><P><s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Phosphate buffer (PB; 1/15 M, pH 7.4) was prepared from phosphate buffer powder (Wako Pure Chemical, Osaka, Japan) and ultra pure water, and the buffer was filtered through a 0.2 µm membrane filter prior to use.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Polystyrene bead (Polybead polystyrene microspheres, 15 µm, 20 µm, and 25 µm in diameter with 1% CV) suspensions were obtained from Polysciences (Warrington, PA).</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The beads were washed with PB prior to use.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Recombinant human interferon-γ (IFN) was obtained from R&amp;D Systems Inc. (Minneapolis, MN).</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">For capture antibody, chromatographically purified mouse anti-recombinant human interferon-γ monoclonal antibody (R&amp;D Systems Inc.) was used.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the second antibodies, biotinylated anti-recombinant interferon-γ polyclonal antibody from goats (R&amp;D Systems Inc.) was used.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">All antibodies and the antigen were diluted with PB and used without further purification.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Anti-IFN coated beads were prepared in a 500 µL microtube.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The monoclonal anti-IFN solution (100 µL, 50 µg mL<SP>−1</SP>) was added to the polystyrene beads (10 µL solid), and the suspension was stirred gently at room temperature for 1 h, followed by overnight incubation at 4 °C.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The coated beads were washed with PB and blocked with 0.2% casein solution for 1 h at room temperature and then washed with PB and stored at 4 °C.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Streptavidin-horseradish peroxidase (HRP) conjugate was purchased from Sigma-Aldrich (St. Louis, MO).</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp12" novelty="None" advantage="None">4-aminoantipyrine (AA) and H<SB>2</SB>O<SB>2</SB> solution were obtained from Wako Pure Chemical and <IT>N</IT>-ethyl-<IT>N</IT>-(2-hydroxy-3-sulfopropyl)-3-methylaniline, sodium salt (TOOS) was from Dojindo Laboratories (Kumamoto, Japan).</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp13" novelty="None" advantage="None">AA, H<SB>2</SB>O<SB>2</SB> and TOOS are reacted by catalysis of HRP to produce red-colored product.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Because the product has strong absorption at ∼530 nm, it is suitable for TLM detection using aYAG laser.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp15" novelty="None" advantage="None">To prevent nonspecific binding of proteins to the microchannel and capillary tubes, 0.2% casein (Merck, biochemistry grade) in PB, 1% bovine serum albumin (Sigma-Aldrich) in PB, or BlockAce (Dainippon Pharmaceutical, Osaka, Japan) was used as a blocking reagent.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Apparatus</HEADER><P><s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">To determine very small amounts of the enzyme reaction product in a microchannel, a highly sensitive detection method with high space resolution is indispensable.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">We have developed a laser-induced thermal lens microscope (TLM), which is especially useful for ultra sensitive determination in a microspace.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13 cit14">13,14</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">The TLM was comprised of a microscope with two laser-oscillation apparatuses and other optical devices.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The excitation beam was the 532 nm emission line of a YAG laser (CrystaLaser, Reno, NV, model GCL-100-S) with output power of 76 mW, and its intensity was modulated by a mechanical chopper with a modulation frequency at 1.03 kHz.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp17" novelty="None" advantage="None">A He–Ne laser (Melles Griot, Carlsbad, CA, model 05LHP171, 15 mW) with an emission line of 632.8 nm was used for the probe beam.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The two beams were made coaxial by a dichroic mirror, and tightly focused by an objective lens (Nikon, CF IC EPI Plan 20×, N.A.</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp18" novelty="None" advantage="None">0.46).</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">The transmitted beams were collected by a condenser lens and filtered.</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Only the probe beam intensity was monitored with a photodiode.</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The pre-amplified signal from the photodiode was synchronously amplified with a lock-in amplifier LI-575 (NF Corp., Yokohama, Japan).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp20" novelty="None" advantage="None">The liquid flow was controlled with a microsyringe pump (KD Scientific, Boston, MA) and Hamilton gastight syringes with untreated fused silica capillary tubing and capillary column connectors (GL Science, Tokyo, Japan).</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Fused silica capillaries were connected to inlet and outlet holes of the microchip.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">The capillaries for reagent introduction were connected to syringes, and the outlet capillary was connected to a syringe for suction or to a waste reservoir.</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp21" novelty="None" advantage="None">Before the assay, the inner walls of the capillaries and the microchannel were blocked with the blocking reagent for 1 h, and then this was replaced with PB.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">A change of supplied reagents could be achieved simply by changing syringes.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp22" novelty="None" advantage="None">During the enzyme reaction, the microchip temperature was controlled with a PE120 Peltier Heating and Freezing Stage (Linkam Scientific Instruments, Surrey, UK) which was mounted on the TLM.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Analytical procedures</HEADER><P><s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">To introduce the beads pre-coated with anti-IFN into the microchip, an aliquot of the bead suspension was placed in one inlet hole of the microchip, and then the beads were moved to the dam region by suction from the outlet hole while the other inlet was kept closed (Fig. 3).</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp23" novelty="None" advantage="None">This procedure was repeated until the packed bead channel (1 cm in length) was completely filled.</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Excess beads were washed out by flushing PB from one inlet to the other inlet.</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp24" novelty="None" advantage="None">Then, sample solution containing IFN was introduced from one inlet into the packed bead channel at 1 µL min<SP>−1</SP> for 10 min for the first antigen-antibody reaction.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Next, PB, biotinylated anti-IFN, PB, and streptavidin-peroxidase conjugate were injected into the microchannel successively from the inlet (Fig. 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp25" novelty="None" advantage="None">Solution flow rates were adjusted to 100 µL min<SP>−1</SP> for PB washing and for solution exchange, and they were 1 µL min<SP>−1</SP> for the other reagents during the reaction.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">After the reaction, the solution in the microchannel was replaced with PB, and then substrate solutions were introduced from inlet holes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">A mixture of TOOS and H<SB>2</SB>O<SB>2</SB> was introduced from one inlet and AA was introduced from the other, all at the same flow rate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">The resulting product was continuously detected using the TLM downstream.</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Signal intensity was recorded after reaching a plateau.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp26" novelty="None" advantage="None">After the measurement, the beads were removed from the microchip by a reverse flow of PB and the microchannel was washed with 0.1 M NaOH solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Thus, the microchip could be used repeatedly.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Microchip-based immunosorbent assay using colloidal gold as a labeling material was performed as described previously<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Results and discussion</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>ELISA microchip</HEADER><P><s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">A glass microchip suitable for ELISA was designed and fabricated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The chip had two inlet holes, a Y-shaped channel, a dam, a detection area, and an outlet hole (Fig. 3).</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Injection of a reagent or a sample solution was from an inlet using the syringe pump.</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Because premixing of the three substrates might bring about some undesirable progression of the reaction outside of the chip without the enzyme, substrates were introduced from two inlets separately; one solution was a mixture of TOOS and H<SB>2</SB>O<SB>2</SB>, and the other was AA.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">The two solutions were mixed in the packed bead area (1 cm long) which was from the mixing point of the Y-shaped channel to the dam.</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Y-shaped channel was suitable not only for mixing of the substrate solutions, but also for packing a definite amount of beads in the microchannel easily.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The dam structure was fabricated by the one-step or two-step wet etching method.</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Any dimensions of the microchannel and dam could be altered by changing the gap width of the photomask and etching time.</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The one-step method required only one photomask, one photolithography and one etching process to fabricate both a microchannel and dam.</annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, accurate control of the channel depth of the dam was technically difficult for a narrow neck especially at depth of less than 10 µm because of unstable etching rate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore this method was suitable for beads with a diameter greater than 20 µm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">For smaller beads, the two-step method was suitable, because the second etching process for the dam was fully controllable.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The microchannel was 200 µm and 90 µm in width and depth, respectively, whereas the depth of the dam region was dependent on each experiment.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Diameter of the beads</HEADER><P><s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">In our previous paper, we used microbeads with 45 µm diameter for the microchip immunoassay using colloidal gold as a labeling material, because it is very difficult to focus a laser beam on the top of small beads.</annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the microELISA system, however, specific interface area (<IT>S</IT>/<IT>V</IT>), which is defined as surface area of the beads to liquid phase volume ratio, is very important for enzyme reaction rate, because <IT>S</IT>/<IT>V</IT> is directly proportional to the amount of the enzyme fixed in the chip.</annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore a large <IT>S</IT>/<IT>V</IT> is favorable for high amplification rate of the enzyme reaction, which means high signal intensity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although bead diameter is apparently inversely proportional to <IT>S</IT>/<IT>V</IT>, smaller beads often led to problems in the assay.</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The most critical problem was a considerable increase of backpressure at the solution introduction procedure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Moreover, removal of air bubbles, which accidentally contaminated the packed bead region, was also very difficult in the case of smaller beads.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">After detailed studies, we concluded that the optimum bead diameter was 25 µm in our system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">By using 25 µm beads, a strong signal could be obtained without any problems.</annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore microchips made by both one-step and two-step methods could be used for the assays.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Antigen-antibody and biotin-avidin reactions</HEADER><P><s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reaction time required for the antigen-antibody reaction was remarkably cut in the bead-bed microchip-based immunoassay system as described previously.</annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the present microELISA system, the time to achieve equilibrium for the antigen-antibody reaction or the biotin-avidin reaction was also 10 min (data not shown).</annotationART></s> <s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp27" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, in this study, every reaction time was fixed at 10 min.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the best reproducible results, reagent concentration was set at 1 µg mL<SP>−1</SP> or 10 µg mL<SP>−1</SP> for the biotinylated second antibody or the streptavidin-peroxidase conjugate, respectively.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Flow rate in the enzyme reaction</HEADER><P><s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">In the last step of the microELISA, the reaction of the HRP with TOOS, AA, and H<SB>2</SB>O<SB>2</SB> was carried out in the packed bead area of the microchip.</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The enzyme reaction could be performed in both continuous flow and stopped flow modes.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the stopped flow mode, after the microchannel including the packed bead area was completely filled with the substrate solutions, the enzyme reaction proceeded for an appropriate time with the liquid flow stopped.</annotationART></s> <s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">The resulting product, dissolved in the solution, was pushed downstream by the syringe pump and detected with the TLM.</annotationART></s> <s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">We expected that the optimum amplification could be easily obtained by changing the reaction time with minimum consumption of reagents.</annotationART></s> <s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Reproducible results, however, could not be obtained due to significant molecular diffusion of the product and difficulty of completely stopping the liquid flow.</annotationART></s> <s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, we concluded the stopped flow method was not suitable for the current assay system.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">In the continuous flow mode, two substrate solutions, a mixture of TOOS and H<SB>2</SB>O<SB>2</SB>, and an AA solution, were introduced from two inlets with the same flow rate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">In our microELISA system, the enzyme reaction time was inversely proportional to the flow rate because the volume of the reaction area was fixed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Clearly, a slower flow rate brought a longer reaction time and higher signal intensity (Fig. 4).</annotationART></s> <s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is, however, very difficult to realize a constant stable flow at low flow rate, typically slower than 0.01 µL min<SP>−1</SP> for each solution, because of poor performance of the microsyringe pump.</annotationART></s> <s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore we concluded that the best flow rate of each solution was 0.02 µL min<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Enzyme reaction temperature</HEADER><P><s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Turnover of the enzyme reaction is strongly dependent on the reaction temperature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Precise control to the optimum temperature is recommended for reliable and highly sensitive determination.</annotationART></s> <s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">We monitored the signal intensity of the enzyme reaction product at various temperatures to get the temperature dependency of the reaction rate (Fig. 5).</annotationART></s> <s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Not only the reaction rate, but the thermal lens signal was also affected by the solution temperature; higher temperatures led to the higher signals.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Maximum signal intensity was obtained at 55 °C.</annotationART></s> <s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the plotted temperatures were surface temperatures of the temperature control stage of the microscope, actual solution temperature might be lower.</annotationART></s> <s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">From this result, we concluded that the optimum temperature of the stage during the enzyme reaction was 55 °C.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Determination by MicroELISA</HEADER><P><s sid="143"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">IFN was determined with the developed microELSA system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="144"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp28" novelty="None" advantage="None">The antigen-antibody reactions and the biotin-avidin reaction were done with a 10 min injection of sample solution, the biotinylated second antibody solution, and the streptavidin-peroxidase conjugate solution, respectively, with a flow rate of 1 µL min<SP>−1</SP>, followed by 30 s washing with PB at 100 µL min<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="145"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp29" novelty="None" advantage="None">The enzymatic reaction was performed at 55 °C with a flow rate of 0.02 µL min<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="146"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The calibration curves of IFN are shown in Fig. 6.</annotationART></s> <s sid="147"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The sample containing 0.1 ng mL<SP>−1</SP> (6 pM) IFN had a clear TLM signal, whereas the determination limit by the microchip immunoassay using colloidal gold as a labeling material was 1 ng mL<SP>−1</SP> (60 pM).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="148"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the colloidal gold method, measurements of 5–10 beads and averaging were necessary for one assay, because signal intensity obtained from each bead varied greatly.</annotationART></s> <s sid="149"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore 10–60 min were required for detection of one sample, and the required time was dependent on the packing conditions of the beads and instrument operator's skill.</annotationART></s> <s sid="150"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, because obtained data were rather dispersed, improvement of the lower limit of determination was very difficult.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="151"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the contrary, in the microELISA system proposed in this paper, the measured signal was derived from all the beads, and then there was very little variation during the measurement.</annotationART></s> <s sid="152"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hence, only 10 s was required for measurement of one sample, though a 2–3 min wait was required for the signal to reach a plateau.</annotationART></s> <s sid="153"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">In total, 35 min were required for the microELISA including three reactions and detection, while several hours or one day would be required in the conventional bulk-scale ELISA or 40–90 min in the colloidal gold-based microchip immunoassay.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="154"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Moreover, detection of the enzyme reaction product in the liquid phase with the TLM was much easier than detection of the colloidal gold fixed on the surface of the beads, and no special instrumental operating skills were necessary.</annotationART></s> <s sid="155"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, by adoption of the enzyme, the work burden was greatly reduced.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Conclusion</HEADER><P><s sid="156"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">With the microELISA system, a rapid and sensitive assay of a protein could be realized.</annotationART></s> <s sid="157"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">By using an enzyme as a labeling material, laborious detection tasks were eliminated, and assay time and data error were reduced.</annotationART></s> <s sid="158"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Additionally no special skills were needed for the assay.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="159"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Though the microELISA was demonstrated here to be useful in a single channel assay, its merits will be fully exploited in a parallel multichannel system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="160"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the previous colloidal gold method, the multichannel system could realize high throughput assays due to simultaneous reactions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="161"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, improvement of the total throughput of the assay was limited because of difficulties with the detection.</annotationART></s> <s sid="162"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None">By adopting the ELISA in the multichannel system, measurements can be made in a lot of channels laid in parallel, simultaneously or successively in a very short time.</annotationART></s> <s sid="163"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, throughput of the detection will be much improved.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="164"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">If the detection operations become easier and no special skills are required for the determination, an automated detector becomes possible.</annotationART></s> <s sid="165"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">We expect an automated multichannel analyzer can be realized on the basis of the microELISA system in the near future.</annotationART></s> <s sid="166"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">This automated microELISA system will be a small, high throughput, and high sensitivity system and it will be suitable for ubiquitous assays including point-of care testing.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
