<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b310850c" hasDoc="yes" version="1168" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Structure of the FeFe-cofactor of the iron-only nitrogenase and possible mechanism for dinitrogen reduction<XREF TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" /></annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">We use density functional calculations to model the FeFe-cofactor of the iron-only nitrogenase.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None">We determine the ground state geometical and magnetic structure and show that our results are in agreement with experimental observations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="New" advantage="None">We model the reactivity of the FeFeco towards hydrogen and nitrogen and compare to the FeMoco.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our results for the difference in reactivity can be linked to experimental observations.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="1">Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The enzyme nitrogenase catalyzes the conversion of atmospheric nitrogen to ammonia.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although nitrogen is abundant in the air, it has to be converted to a biologically accessible form, in this case NH<SB>3</SB>, in order to be used by plants.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In nature, the conversion of N<SB>2</SB> to NH<SB>3</SB> can only be performed by a small group of diazotrophic microorganisms that contain the enzyme nitrogenase.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Nitrogenase catalyzes the following reaction:<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF> N<SB>2</SB> + 8H<SP>+</SP> + 8e<SP>−</SP> + 16ATP → 2NH<SB>3</SB> + H<SB>2</SB> + 16ADP + 16P<SB><IT>i</IT></SB>The most common form of nitrogenase contains an FeMo-cofactor (FeMoco), a cluster of the stoichiometry MoFe<SB>7</SB>S<SB>9</SB>, where the reduction of N<SB>2</SB> most probably takes place.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">2</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">When Mo is absent, some organisms can form alternative nitrogenases, where Mo is substituted by V or Fe.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In most cases, the activity of alternative nitrogenases decreases with the sequence Mo &gt; V &gt; Fe.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Fe-only nitrogenase thus has the lowest activity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The active center of this nitrogenase is an FeFe-cofactor (FeFeco), which consists exclusively of iron and sulfur atoms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition to the low activity for nitrogen fixation, the Fe-only nitrogenase catalyzes an unusually high hydrogen evolution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">These differences are not yet understood in terms of molecular structure, <IT>i.e.</IT> whether they arise from the replacement of Mo with Fe or from other differences in the enzyme structure.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj5" novelty="New" advantage="None">In the present paper, we present a detailed investigation of the FeFe-cofactor and compare it to the FeMoco.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj6" novelty="New" advantage="None">We study the FeFe-cofactor by means of extensive density functional theory (DFT) calculations and outline a possible path of nitrogen fixation at the FeFe-cofactor.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj7" novelty="New" advantage="None">Comparing the energetics of this path to a tentative one for the FeMo-cofactor<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF> leads us to suggest reasons for the differences in activity.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The paper is organized as follows.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj8" novelty="New" advantage="None">We briefly review the experimental and theoretical knowledge that has been assembled about the structure and function of the Fe-only nitrogenase.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj9" novelty="New" advantage="None">Then we introduce our computational method and explain how we model the FeFe-cofactor.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj10" novelty="New" advantage="None">The results section starts with a description of the magnetic ground state of the FeFe-cofactor.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj11" novelty="New" advantage="None">Then we present results for N<SB>2</SB> and H<SB>2</SB> adsorption on the FeFeco and for the subsequent hydrogenation of adsorbed N<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj12" novelty="New" advantage="None">We compare these results to results for the FeMoco.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The X-ray structure of the conventional Mo-containing nitrogenase has been determined by X-ray diffraction for different bacteria and with different resolutions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6 cit7">5–7</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">From these studies and from EXAFS-studies<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF> it is known that nitrogenase consists of two proteins, the Fe protein and the MoFe protein.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Fe protein contains a ferredoxin, <IT>i.e.</IT> an Fe<SB>4</SB>S<SB>4</SB> cluster, and transfers electrons to the FeMo protein along with the hydrolysis of Mg-bound ATP.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The FeMo protein contains a P-cluster (Fe<SB>8</SB>S<SB>7</SB>) and a FeMo cofactor (MoFe<SB>7</SB>S<SB>9</SB>, FeMoco).</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The P-cluster presumably transfers the electrons which come from the ferredoxin, on to the FeMoco, where the reduction of N<SB>2</SB> most probably takes place.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">2</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The protons required for the reduction come from solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">A very recent X-ray study of the MoFe-protein revealed that the FeMoco has a central ligand in the cavity, which could be either nitrogen, oxygen or carbon.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Subsequent theoretical studies by us<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF> and other researchers<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10 cit11">10,11</REF> have presented strong support for the central ligand to be nitrogen.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">It has been shown by ENDOR and ESEEM spectroscopy that the central nitrogen ligand does not exchange during turnover.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the Fe-nitrogenase, there is no crystal structure available, and thus it is not yet known, whether a central N ligand is present in the cavity as well, but this seems well possible.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac20" novelty="None" advantage="None">A recent EXAFS and Mössbauer study by Krahn <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF>. shows that the iron and sulfur atoms most probably assume the same prismatic geometry as in the FeMo cofactor.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have carried out this study for the FeMoco structure without the central ligand and with an equivalent FeFeco structure where the Mo atom is substituted by Fe.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac21" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is clear that for both the FeMoco and the FeFeco there will be changes in structure and mechanics due to an inclusion of the central ligand.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac22" novelty="None" advantage="None">The central ligand only changes the catalytic properties of the FeMoco slightly.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac23" novelty="None" advantage="None">Dinitrogen adsorption and reduction on the triangular Fe atoms as suggested by<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF> is still possible with energies similar to those for the FeMoco without a central ligand.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj13" novelty="New" advantage="None">We concentrate on the <IT>difference</IT> between the FeMoco and FeFeco.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This means that whereas a central ligand may change the chemical properties somewhat, this should only be a second order effect on the properties we are studying here.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2">Previous studies</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.1">Experimental studies</HEADER><P><s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac24" novelty="None" advantage="None">It had long been assumed that the ability to fix N<SB>2</SB> depends on the presence of Mo in the enzyme.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac25" novelty="None" advantage="None">This assumption had to be revised when in 1980, the first evidence for alternative nitrogenases in the bacteria <IT>A. vinelandii</IT> was presented.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac26" novelty="None" advantage="None">It came as a surprise when in 1988 the Fe-only nitrogenase was purified from <IT>A. vinelandii</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF> and was proved to neither contain Mo nor V. Apart from <IT>A. vinelandii</IT>, the Fe-only nitrogenase has been purified and characterized from <IT>R. capsulatus</IT>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17 cit18 cit19 cit20">17–20</REF> and it has been purified from <IT>R. rubrum.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21 cit22">21,22</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac27" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Fe-only nitrogenase is only formed if both Mo and V are absent, otherwise the conventional Mo-nitrogenase or the V-nitrogenase are expressed.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23 cit24">23,24</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac28" novelty="None" advantage="None">Contrary to the Mo nitrogenase, there are no X-ray studies of the structure of the Fe-only nitrogenase.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac29" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, until very recently it was mainly because of genetic evidence and the conservation of important amino acids that the cofactors of the different nitrogenases were assumed to be similar.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac30" novelty="None" advantage="None">Genetic studies<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25 cit26 cit27">25–27</REF> showed that the important genes for nitrogen fixation in Mo-nitrogenase are also present in Fe-nitrogenase.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac31" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, it was shown for <IT>R. capsulatus</IT> that the amino acids in Mo-nitrogenase which link the functional clusters to the peptide chains, are conserved in the sequence of Fe-nitrogenase, although the two sequences only show an overall agreement of 26%.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28">28</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac32" novelty="None" advantage="None">Another indication of the similarity between the Mo-nitrogenase and the Fe-nitrogenase is that hybrid enzymes, which <IT>e.g.</IT> consist of the protein of the FeFe nitrogenase, but with a FeMo cofactor, could be produced.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22 cit24 cit29 cit30 cit31">22,24,29–31</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac32" novelty="None" advantage="None">Those enzymes were able to fix N<SB>2</SB>, but with a much lower activity.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac33" novelty="None" advantage="None">Electron paramagnetic resonance (EPR) spectroscopy has shown that the spin ground state of the dithionite-reduced FeFe-cofactor is integer, probably <IT>S</IT> = .0<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17 cit18 cit19 cit20">17–20</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac34" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is in contrast to the FeMoco, for which it is known from electron paramagnetic resonance (EPR) that the spin state of the FeMoco is <IT>S</IT> = 3/2 in the resting state.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit32 cit33">32,33</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac35" novelty="None" advantage="None">In a very recent study, Krahn <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF>. investigate the Fe-only nitrogenase from <IT>R. capsulatus</IT> using EXAFS and Mössbauer spectroscopy and obtain for the first time direct information about the structure and the coordination of the FeFe-cofactor.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac36" novelty="None" advantage="None">The study confirms by Mössbauer spectroscopy that the dithionite-reduced FeFe-cofactor is diamagnetic and therefore has an integer spin state, probably <IT>S</IT> = 0.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac37" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, the Mössbauer spectroscopy results show that the FeFe-cofactor contains eight iron atoms and thus has a stoichiometry of Fe<SB>8</SB>S<SB>9</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac38" novelty="None" advantage="None">By means of EXAFS, Krahn <IT>et al.</IT> obtain information about how the iron atoms are coordinated within the cluster.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac38" novelty="None" advantage="None">They find that the only possible arrangement of the iron atoms which is consistent with the EXAFS spectra is the trigonal prismatic arrangement of the FeMo cofactor.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac39" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, they conclude that the structure of the FeFe-cofactor probably is very similar to the one of the FeMo cofactor with the Mo atom exchanged for Fe.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac40" novelty="None" advantage="None">The kinetics of the Mo-nitrogenase have been studied extensively and the results are reviewed in refs. <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2 cit34">2 and 34</REF> The most comprehensive model for the reactivity of nitrogenase and the kinetics of nitrogen fixation is the Thorneley–Lowe model.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit35">35</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac41" novelty="None" advantage="None">This model also incorporates the observation that at least one H<SB>2</SB> is produced per N<SB>2</SB> fixated, even for very high N<SB>2</SB> pressures up to 50 bar.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit36">36</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac42" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is the reason for the stoichiometry of eqn. (1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac43" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the Fe-nitrogenase, however, there are only few studies of the reactivity and no model comparable to the Thorneley-Lowe model exists.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac44" novelty="None" advantage="None">There are several measurements of the activity of the Fe-only nitrogenase towards different substrates.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3 cit16 cit19 cit20 cit37">3,16,19,20,37</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac45" novelty="None" advantage="None">The most recent study is the one by Schneider <IT>et al.</IT> in 1997<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF> and investigates both the Mo-nitrogenase and the Fe-nitrogenase of <IT>R. capsulatus</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac46" novelty="None" advantage="None">In agreement with previous studies they find that the H<SB>2</SB>-producing activity of the Fe-nitrogenase is extraordinarily high.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac47" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, the H<SB>2</SB> production of the Fe-nitrogenase is much less inhibited by N<SB>2</SB>, as the H<SB>2</SB> production of the Mo-nitrogenase.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac48" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the Mo-nitrogenase it is found that under very high N<SB>2</SB> pressure, the limiting ratio of produced H<SB>2</SB> and fixated N<SB>2</SB> is H<SB>2</SB>/N<SB>2</SB> = 1, in accordance with the Thorneley–Lowe scheme.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac49" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the Fe-nitrogenase, this ratio is found to be H<SB>2</SB>/N<SB>2</SB> = 7.5, which means that the reduction of N<SB>2</SB> competes much worse with hydrogen production than for the Mo-nitrogenase.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This outstanding feature of hydrogen production might make the Fe-nitrogenase useful for technical applications in connection with hydrogen production<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit38">38</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.2">Theoretical studies</HEADER><P><s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac50" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the crystal structure of the FeMoco was first published in 1992 there have been a number of theoretical studies of both the structure and the reactivity of the FeMoco.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit9 cit10 cit11 cit39 cit40 cit41 cit42 cit43 cit44 cit45 cit46 cit47 cit48 cit49 cit50 cit51 cit52 cit53">4,9–11,39–53</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac51" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the Fe-only nitrogenase, there are only few theoretical studies, a study by Plass from 1994<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit40">40</REF> and a recent study by Lovell <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit54">54</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac52" novelty="None" advantage="None">Plass<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit40">40</REF> studied the cofactors of the Mo-, V- and Fe-nitrogenase using the Extended Hückel method.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac53" novelty="None" advantage="None">By analyzing the frontier orbitals, he showed that the Mo and V atoms do not contribute to the respective frontier orbitals of the FeMoco and FeVco and that for the FeFeco the Fe atom at the Mo position does not contribute either.</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac54" novelty="None" advantage="None">This lead Plass to suggest that the atom at the Mo position is not directly involved in the N<SB>2</SB> binding, but rather fine-tunes the activity of the cluster.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac55" novelty="None" advantage="None">Assuming that N<SB>2</SB> binds to one of the six threefold-coordinate iron atoms, Plass showed that the reduction of the N<SB>2</SB>-binding FeFeco is much more energy-demanding than the reduction of the N<SB>2</SB>-binding FeMoco or FeVco.</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac56" novelty="None" advantage="None">Lovell <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit54">54</REF>. recently presented density functional theory calculations on the FeVco and on the FeFeco.</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac57" novelty="None" advantage="None">They investigated the geometrical and the magnetic structure of the FeFeco and suggested a spin structure for the magnetic ground state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac58" novelty="None" advantage="None">They also presented results for isomer shifts.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj14" novelty="New" advantage="None">In the following we compare to these results whenever possible.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.3">Model for ammonia synthesis and hydrogen release</HEADER><P><s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac59" novelty="None" advantage="None">As a starting point for our study we take the results of Rod and Nørskov,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF> who investigated both hydrogen evolution and ammonia production on the FeMoco.</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Their model for H<SB>2</SB> evolution is shown in Fig. 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac60" novelty="None" advantage="None">The coupled addition of protons and electrons to the FeMoco is modeled by the addition of hydrogen atoms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac61" novelty="None" advantage="None">The first three hydrogen atoms adsorb on the <IT>μ</IT><SB>2</SB>S-atoms and these adsorptions are exothermic.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac62" novelty="None" advantage="None">The most energy-demanding step is the adsorption of the fourth H on one of the triangular Fe atoms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac63" novelty="None" advantage="None">Once this is accomplished, the next step is the transfer of one H atom from the <IT>μ</IT><SB>2</SB>S atom to the Fe atom, which is exothermic.</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac64" novelty="None" advantage="None">The subsequent desorption of H<SB>2</SB> is exothermic as well.</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj15" novelty="New" advantage="None">In the following we use this model in order to investigate the reactivity differences of the FeMoco and the FeFeco.</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The two deciding energies for this process are the adsorption energy of H on the <IT>μ</IT><SB>2</SB>S atoms (which has to be exothermic for the process to function) and the adsorption energy of H on a triangular Fe atom, which dominates the process.</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac65" novelty="None" advantage="None">The adsorption energy of H on a triangular Fe atom depends only weakly on the number of H atoms adsorbed on the <IT>μ</IT><SB>2</SB>S atoms.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, by calculating the adsorption energies for one H atom on the different possible positions on the FeFeco, we can judge the feasibility of H<SB>2</SB> production on the FeFeco.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The model for ammonia synthesis is shown in Fig. 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac66" novelty="None" advantage="None">The adsorption of N<SB>2</SB> on one of the triangular Fe atoms is thermoneutral.</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac67" novelty="None" advantage="None">Dissociation of N<SB>2</SB> on the cluster is highly unfavorable and thus the N<SB>2</SB> gets hydrogenated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac68" novelty="None" advantage="None">The first hydrogenation step is highly endothermic and the most energy-demanding step in the whole cycle.</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac69" novelty="None" advantage="None">The subsequent hydrogenations and the release of the first NH<SB>3</SB> molecule are exothermic.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac70" novelty="None" advantage="None">The only endothermic step is the release of the second NH<SB>3</SB> molecule and one can speculate that this step is much easier in solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac71" novelty="None" advantage="None">One should note that an intermediate in this cycle is hydrazine (N<SB>2</SB>H<SB>4</SB>), which has indeed been shown to be an intermediate in the enzyme turnover.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">2</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The two most important energies, which determine the reactivity of the FeMoco, are the adsorption energy for N<SB>2</SB> on a triangular Fe atom, and the energy of the first hydrogenation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj16" novelty="New" advantage="None">Thus we concentrate on calculating those two energies for the FeMoco and the FeFeco in the following.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, the model for ammonia synthesis for the FeMoco from <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">ref. 4</REF> yields that the most energy-demanding step is the first hydrogenation of adsorbed N<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is to be expected, as in the first hydrogenation step from N<SB>2</SB> to NNH, the nitrogen triple bond is broken, and this is the bond containing most energy.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit55">55</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac72" novelty="None" advantage="None">This holds also for the hydrogenation of N<SB>2</SB> in the gas phase<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit45 cit56">45,56</REF> and on a Ru metal surface.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit47">47</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, for all processes where N<SB>2</SB> is hydrogenated directly without dissociating, it is to be expected that the first hydrogenation step from N<SB>2</SB> to NNH is the most energy-demanding step.</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Using this general result, we choose to focus on calculating the first two steps, the binding of N<SB>2</SB> and the first reduction to NNH, as these steps determine the entire process.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj17" novelty="New" advantage="None">We note explicitly that we only address the thermodynamics of the processes of dihidrogen and ammonia formation and do not calculate any activation barriers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac73" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the other hand, there are indications that the transfer of protons to the adsorbed N<SB>2</SB> is not associated with significant energy barriers.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit57 cit58">4,57,58</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac74" novelty="None" advantage="None">For example, in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">ref. 4</REF> proton transfer was modeled with the very simple proton donors NH<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP> and H<SB>3</SB>O<SP>+</SP>, and it was found that in this setup there is no barrier for proton transfer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj18" novelty="New" advantage="None">Although the question of activation barriers certainly has to be addressed in future studies, we limit ourselves to thermodynamical considerations at present.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3">Methods</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.1">Model of the Fe-only cofactor</HEADER><P><s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac75" novelty="None" advantage="None">The FeMoco with its ligands from the most recent crystal structure 1M1N<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF> is depicted in Fig. 3a (general pdb references given in ref. <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit59">59</REF>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">We model the FeMoco by truncating all ligands after the first ligating atom.</annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus we stubstitute Cys by SH, His by NH<SB>3</SB> and homocitrate by two OH groups.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our model structure of the FeMoco with a central N ligand, which we have investigated in ref. <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF> is shown in Fig. 3b.</annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The model structure for the FeMoco without a central ligand is shown in Fig. 3c.</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Structure 3b is much more symmetric and resembles the experimental structure 3a more than structure 3c.</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is due to the higher coordination of the Fe atoms in structure 3b, which are therefore kept in a more symmetical position.</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">One consequence of the higher coordination is that the structure 3b is much constrained than structure 3c and cannot distort in the same way.</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac76" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, this has only a very small effect on the ability of the triangular Fe atoms to bind and reduce N<SB>2</SB>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod12" novelty="None" advantage="None">As discussed in Section 1, we perform all calculations with the FeMoco model of Fig. 3c, where there is no central ligand.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac77" novelty="None" advantage="None">As discussed before, there is no X-ray crystal structure of the FeFeco of the iron-only nitrogenase, however, the recent EXAFS study<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF> shows that the FeFeco most probably has the same geometry as the FeMoco with Mo substituted by Fe.</annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac78" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, the His442 and the Cys275 residues, which link the FeMoco to the peptide chain, are conserved in the Fe-only nitrogenase and the gene encoding a homocitrate synthase is also present.</annotationART></s> <s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, it is reasonable to assume that the FeFeco is coordinated to Cys, His, and homocitrate in the same way as the FeMoco.</annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, we model the FeFeco in an analogous way as the FeMoco and the model is depicted in Fig. 3d.</annotationART></s> <s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, when minimizing the FeFeco model of Fig. 3d, in some cases one of the OH groups was unstable and tended to move closer to one of the Fe atoms on the triangle.</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This rises the question, whether the homocitrate ring might be opened at the FeFeco and only form a monodentate coordination instead of a bidentate coordination which is present in the FeMoco.</annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac79" novelty="None" advantage="None">There are hints in the literature that opening of the homocitrate ring indeed is possible.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit48 cit49 cit71 cit72">48,49,71,72</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod14" novelty="None" advantage="None">We investigate this by considering a second model for the FeFeco, where the lower Fe atom only is coordinated to NH<SB>3</SB> and to one OH group.</annotationART></s> <s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod15" novelty="None" advantage="None">This model is shown in Fig. 3e.</annotationART></s> <s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac80" novelty="None" advantage="None">All calculations are carried out on both models in the following.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod16" novelty="None" advantage="None">We emphasize that we model a charge neutral cluster and unit cell in all cases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod16" novelty="None" advantage="None">We consider this the most natural choice, as a net charge would introduce long-range Coulomb forces.</annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, a large negative charge on the cluster without proper shielding from the surroundings seems problematic.</annotationART></s> <s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In terms of formal oxidation states, the model with one OH group (Fig. 3e) corresponds to the oxidation states [4Fe<SP>2+</SP>4Fe<SP>3+</SP>9S<SP>2−</SP>], which agrees with the oxidation state assignment from the isomer shift measured in ref. .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our model with two OH groups corresponds to the oxidation states [3Fe<SP>2+</SP>5Fe<SP>3+</SP>9S<SP>2−</SP>].</annotationART></s> <s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod17" novelty="None" advantage="None">One should be aware of that in ref. <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF> the average oxidation state of the Fe sites was measured to be 2.5 and that the oxidation state assignment of 4Fe<SP>2+</SP> and 4Fe<SP>3+</SP> sites therefore is a purely formal one.</annotationART></s> <s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">From the iron-iron interactions and the net spin density on the Fe sites one can infer that the electrons are delocalized and that the average oxidation state is a more appropriate picture.</annotationART></s> <s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac81" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this context we remark that in<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit54">54</REF> the FeFeco with the oxidation state assignments [6Fe<SP>2+</SP>2Fe<SP>3+</SP>9S<SP>2−</SP>] and [4Fe<SP>2+</SP>4Fe<SP>3+</SP>9S<SP>2−</SP>] have been modeled.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 3 as well as Figs. 5, 6, 7 and 8 are prepared with Molscript<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit60">60</REF> and Raster3D<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit61">61</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.2">Calculational details</HEADER><P><s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod19" novelty="None" advantage="None">All calculations are carried out with the program <IT>dacapo</IT>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit62">62</REF> which uses a plane-wave expansion of the Kohn–Sham wavefunctions and the generalized gradient approximation for the exchange-correlation terms.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit63">63</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod20" novelty="None" advantage="None">Due to the plane-wave expansion, we have to choose systems which are periodic in all three dimensions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod21" novelty="None" advantage="None">Here we accomplish this by repeating a <IT>supercell</IT> containing the cluster periodically in all three dimensions including enough vacuum around the cluster for the interactions between the supercells to be neglegible.</annotationART></s> <s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod22" novelty="None" advantage="None">We use a triclinic supercell with the axes <IT>a</IT> = <IT>b</IT> = 11 Å and <IT>c</IT> = 15.4 Å and the angles <IT>α</IT> = 90°, <IT>β</IT> = 69° and <IT>γ</IT> = 120°.</annotationART></s> <s sid="143"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod23" novelty="None" advantage="None">In all calculations, we include plane waves with energies up to 25 Ry.</annotationART></s> <s sid="144"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod24" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to describe the core parts of the ions, we use ultrasoft pseudopotentials,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit64">64</REF> except for sulfur, where we use a soft pseudopotential.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit65">65</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="145"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod25" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the <IT>k</IT>-point sampling of the Brillouin zone, <IT>Γ</IT>-point sampling has been used.</annotationART></s> <s sid="146"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod26" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Fermi population of the Kohn–Sham orbitals is set to <IT>k</IT><SB>B</SB><IT>T</IT> = 1 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> and Pulay mixing is applied to the resulting density.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit66 cit67">66,67</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="147"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod27" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have tested that the calculations are converged with respect to the plane-wave cutoff, the size of the supercell and the number of <IT>k</IT>-points within a few kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="148"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod28" novelty="None" advantage="None">All calculations have been carried out spin-polarized.</annotationART></s> <s sid="149"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod29" novelty="None" advantage="None">The magnitude of the spin density on the Fe atoms is independent of the chosen (non-zero) initial spin density.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="150"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod30" novelty="None" advantage="None">As exchange-correlation functional, we use the spin-dependent revised Perdew–Enzerhoff–Burke (RPBE) functional.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit68">68</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="151"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac82" novelty="None" advantage="None">For N<SB>2</SB> adsorption on Fe surfaces, where there is experimental data available for comparison, this functional describes the adsorption energies and the activation energies very well.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit69">69</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="152"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod31" novelty="None" advantage="None">As initial guess for the electron densities, sums of atomic densities or the densities of previously calculated structures are used.</annotationART></s> <s sid="153"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod32" novelty="None" advantage="None">As starting structure, the coordinates of the crystal structure 3MIN<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF> are used and reasonable guesses are made for the ligands.</annotationART></s> <s sid="154"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod33" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the structures without adsorbates, all degrees of freedom, that means all atoms, are relaxed, except for the Mo atom (or the Fe atom at the Mo position), which is kept fixed in order to avoid translational motion of the whole cluster.</annotationART></s> <s sid="155"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod34" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the structures with adsorbates, the ligands and the Mo atom are kept fixed in the positions found for the respective structures without adsorbates, and all other atoms are allowed to relax.</annotationART></s> <s sid="156"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod35" novelty="None" advantage="None">An exception is made for the adsorption of N<SB>2</SB> on the Mo atom (or on the Fe atom in the Mo position), where the adjacent ligands are also allowed to relax.</annotationART></s> <s sid="157"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac83" novelty="None" advantage="None">This will be discussed at the appropriate place in the results section.</annotationART></s> <s sid="158"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod36" novelty="None" advantage="None">All energy minimizations of ionic degrees of freedom take place according to a conjugate-gradient algorithm.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit70">70</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="159"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod37" novelty="None" advantage="None">The convergence criterion for the absolute force is 0.1 eV Å<SP>−1</SP> for the structures without adsorbates and 0.2 eV Å<SP>−1</SP> for the structures with adsorbates.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4">Results</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.1">Spin ground state and geometry</HEADER><P><s sid="160"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj19" novelty="New" advantage="None">As a starting point for determining the spin magnetic ground state of the FeFeco, we briefly look at the FeMoco.</annotationART></s> <s sid="161"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac84" novelty="None" advantage="None">The magnetic ground state of the FeMoco has a total spin of <IT>S</IT> = 3/2 and the Fe atoms are antiferromagnetically coupled.</annotationART></s> <s sid="162"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac85" novelty="None" advantage="None">The magnetic configuration with the lowest energy has for example been determined by Rod and Nørskov<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF> and by Lovell <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit50">50</REF>. and is depicted in Fig. 4a.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="163"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac86" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the FeFeco it is known from experiments that the spin ground state has antiferromagnetic couplings and an integer total spin, probably <IT>S</IT> = 0.</annotationART></s> <s sid="164"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj20" novelty="New" advantage="None">We have investigated numerous spin configurations both with ferromagnetic and with antiferromagnetic couplings.</annotationART></s> <s sid="165"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">We find that two antiferromagnetic configurations lie lowest in energy and are very similar in energy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="166"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">These two spin states A1 and A2 are shown in Fig. 4b and c.</annotationART></s> <s sid="167"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">All other spin states which we have examined, lie significantly higher in energy (&gt;30 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>) for both the model with one OH group and the model with two OH groups.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="168"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Taking the spin state A1 as the energy zero, the energy difference to the spin state A2 <IT>E</IT><SB>A2</SB> − <IT>E</IT><SB>A1</SB> is −4 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> for the model with two OH groups and 1 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> for the model with one OH group.</annotationART></s> <s sid="169"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">These energy differences between the two lowest spin states A1 and A2 are much too small to be decisive for their stability.</annotationART></s> <s sid="170"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, for both models we observe that the spin states A1 and A2 are significantly more stable than all other examined spin states.</annotationART></s> <s sid="171"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, their stability seems to be independent of the details of our model, in this case independent of whether there are one or two OH groups.</annotationART></s> <s sid="172"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj21" novelty="New" advantage="None">For the spin states A1, we also considered the spin isomers, <IT>i.e.</IT> those spin structures where the spin state is rotated around the C<SB>3</SB> axis, which is present for the cluster if one disregards the ligands.</annotationART></s> <s sid="173"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">We find that the spin isomers are very similar in energy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="174"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the spin state A2 there are no spin isomers due to its C<SB>3</SB> symmetry.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="175"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The net spin densities on the Fe atoms lie in the range of 1.7–2.9 for the FeFeco with two OH groups and 2.0–2.9 for the FeFeco with one OH group.</annotationART></s> <s sid="176"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">These spin densities are independent of the magnitude of the chosen initial (nonzero) spin densities.</annotationART></s> <s sid="177"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The main difference between the two models is that the bottom Fe atom, which is coordinated to NH<SB>3</SB> and to the OH groups has a net spin density of 1.7 in case of two OH groups and 2.0 in case of one OH group.</annotationART></s> <s sid="178"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">This difference gives rise to the different total spins.</annotationART></s> <s sid="179"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the FeMoco, the net spin density on the Mo atom is close to zero.</annotationART></s> <s sid="180"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">As we cannot conclude from our calculations whether A1 or A2 is the ground state spin structure (it might be possible that they indeed are both present) we carry out all further calculations and analyses on both spin structures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="181"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj22" novelty="New" advantage="None">This gives the advantage that we can examine the effect of the detailed spin structure on the geometries and adsorption energies.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="182"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The bond lengths and angles of the FeFeco for the two models and spin states are listed in Table 1, where they can be compared to the values from the recent EXAFS study.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="183"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The values for the FeMoco are also listed for comparison.</annotationART></s> <s sid="184"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod38" novelty="None" advantage="None">As the experimental values are from an EXAFS study, it makes most sense to compare the averages of all bonds of the same type (Fe–S, Fe–Fe, Fe–Fe diagonal) to the EXAFS value, since the same averaging is inherent in EXAFS.</annotationART></s> <s sid="185"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Generally, our geometries agree very well with the experimental values.</annotationART></s> <s sid="186"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs20" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Fe–S bond lengths only vary relatively little and the average is only slightly smaller than the EXAFS value.</annotationART></s> <s sid="187"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs21" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the Fe–Fe bond lengths the variations are larger and the averages are somewhat larger than the EXAFS values.</annotationART></s> <s sid="188"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs22" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Fe–Fe distances over the face diagonals in our models have particularly high standard deviations, but the averages are only somewhat larger than the EXAFS values.</annotationART></s> <s sid="189"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs23" novelty="None" advantage="None">The high standard deviations may well be consistent with the EXAFS data, as the peak associated with this distance looks relatively broad.</annotationART></s> <s sid="190"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs24" novelty="None" advantage="None">The total height of the FeFeco (distance top Fe–bottom Fe) is about 0.2–0.4 Å larger than the EXAFS value of 6.9 Å, except for the model with one OH group and spin state A1 with a value of 7.0 Å.</annotationART></s> <s sid="191"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">In summary, the geometry the model with one OH group and spin state A1 agrees best with the EXAFS results.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="192"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs25" novelty="None" advantage="None">In our calculations, the total spin of the FeFeco with two OH groups is determined to be <IT>S</IT> = 1/2, and the total spin of the FeFeco with one OH group is <IT>S</IT> = 0.</annotationART></s> <s sid="193"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">This might give a hint that the homocitrate ring is opened and only bound to the Fe in a monodentate manner, but this might also be an artefact of our model.</annotationART></s> <s sid="194"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj23" novelty="New" advantage="None">Because of this and because of the fact that the formal oxidation state of our model with 1OH group and agrees with the experimentally determined one [4Fe<SP>3+</SP>4Fe<SP>2+</SP>9S<SP>2−</SP>], we investigate whether an opening of the homocitrate ring is possible.</annotationART></s> <s sid="195"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod39" novelty="None" advantage="None">In our model, we cannot consider the reaction of the opening of the homocitrate ring, as there is no straightforward way to model the reaction, where one OH group is cleaved.</annotationART></s> <s sid="196"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod40" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, by comparing the models with one and two OH groups for FeFeco and FeMoco, we can observe a relative trend in how easily one OH group can be cleaved.</annotationART></s> <s sid="197"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod41" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, we also have calculated a model of the FeMoco with only one OH group, where we started from the model depicted in Fig. 3 and removed one OH group (we will also need this model later for the N<SB>2</SB> adsorption at the Mo site).</annotationART></s> <s sid="198"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod42" novelty="None" advantage="None">The energy difference Δ<IT>E</IT><SB>OH</SB> = [<IT>E</IT><SB>tot</SB>(FeFeco,1OH) − <IT>E</IT><SB>tot</SB>(FeFeco, 2OH)] − [<IT>E</IT><SB>tot</SB>(FeMoco,1OH) − <IT>E</IT><SB>tot</SB>(FeMoco,2OH)]describes how costly it is to remove one OH group from the FeFeco compared to the removal from the FeMoco.</annotationART></s> <s sid="199"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod43" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this equation, <IT>E</IT><SB>tot</SB>(FeFeco,1OH) is the total energy of the FeFeco with one OH group and <IT>E</IT><SB>tot</SB>(FeFeco,2OH) the total energy of the FeFeco with two OH groups; the same notation is used for the total energies of the FeMoco.</annotationART></s> <s sid="200"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs26" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results for Δ<IT>E</IT><SB>OH</SB> are</annotationART></s><P><s sid="201"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs26" novelty="None" advantage="None">Δ<IT>E</IT><SB>OH</SB> = −26 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>   for spin state A1</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="202"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs27" novelty="None" advantage="None">Δ<IT>E</IT><SB>OH</SB> = −31 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>   for spin state A2</annotationART></s></P><s sid="203"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">A negative sign for Δ<IT>E</IT><SB>OH</SB> means that the removal of one OH group from the FeFeco requires less energy than from the FeMoco.</annotationART></s> <s sid="204"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs28" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, dependent on the magnetic state of the FeFeco, we find that the removal of one OH group from the FeFeco requires 26–31 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> less energy than from the FeMoco.</annotationART></s> <s sid="205"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Taking into account that opening of the homocitrate ring has been suggested to be feasible on the FeMoco, it should certainly be feasible on the FeFeco.</annotationART></s> <s sid="206"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, it is relevant that we consider models with both two and one OH groups.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.2">Hydrogen adsorption</HEADER><P><s sid="207"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj24" novelty="New" advantage="None">We first study the effect of a coupled electron and proton flow to the FeFeco.</annotationART></s> <s sid="208"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod44" novelty="None" advantage="None">We model this by adding a proton/electron pair to the FeFeco in various ways.</annotationART></s> <s sid="209"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs29" novelty="None" advantage="None">The investigated configurations are shown in Fig. 5 and the corresponding binding energies are listed in Table 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="210"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod45" novelty="None" advantage="None">Here and in the following, the adsorption energy is defined as the total energy of the structure with the adsorbate XA (X = FeMoco, FeFeco, A = H, N<SB>2</SB>, N<SB>2</SB>H) minus the sum of the total energies of the bare structure X and the adsorbate in the gas phase A, Δ<IT>E</IT><SB>ads</SB> = <IT>E</IT><SB>tot</SB>(XA) − [<IT>E</IT><SB>tot</SB>(X) + <IT>E</IT><SB>tot</SB>(A)] Thus, a negative binding energy means that adsorption of A to X is energetically favorable and occurs spontaneously, whereas a positive binding energy indicates that the complex XA is unstable and that adsorption will not happen spontaneously.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="211"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj25" novelty="New" advantage="None">In this section we consider the adsorption of proton/electron pairs, as in the enzyme electrons are transferred to the FeFeco from the Fe-protein and protons come from solution.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2 cit49">2,49</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="212"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod46" novelty="None" advantage="None">As reference energy, we use ½H<SB>2</SB> in the gas phase.</annotationART></s> <s sid="213"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod47" novelty="None" advantage="None">This energy zero for hydrogen is a matter of choice, but ½H<SB>2</SB> as the zero point corresponds directly to the standard hydrogen electrode (SHE) and is therefore an especially practical choice.</annotationART></s> <s sid="214"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod48" novelty="None" advantage="None">The actual chemical potential of the transferred electrons depends on the redox potential of the [4Fe–4S]<SP>1+/2+</SP> cluster pair.</annotationART></s> <s sid="215"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the energy diagrams Figs. 1 and 2 as well as in Fig. 9 this corresponds to an upwards shift of the initial states, because the protons and electrons are energetically higher than ½H<SB>2</SB> in the gas phase.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="216"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs30" novelty="None" advantage="None">A proton/electron pair on the FeFeco is most stable on one of the <IT>μ</IT><SB>2</SB>S atoms (configuration <B>a</B> in Fig. 5) and this is independent of the number of OH groups or the spin state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="217"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs31" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is reflected in the fact that the binding energies are negative and the smallest ones observed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="218"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs32" novelty="None" advantage="None">In more detail, the proton is located on the <IT>μ</IT><SB>2</SB>S ligand and the electron on the cluster.</annotationART></s> <s sid="219"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs33" novelty="None" advantage="None">The second stable configuration is configuration <B>e</B>, where an H atom is located inside the cluster, but clearly coordinated to one Fe atom from the inside.</annotationART></s> <s sid="220"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs34" novelty="None" advantage="None">The stability of <B>e</B> depends on the number of OH groups and the spin state of the FeFeco.</annotationART></s> <s sid="221"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs35" novelty="None" advantage="None">The positions <B>b</B> and <B>c</B>, where the H atom is bound by one of the triangular Fe atoms, are unstable by 35–56 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> depending on the model, spin state and whether adsorption takes place on an Fe atom in the upper or in the lower triangle.</annotationART></s> <s sid="222"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs36" novelty="None" advantage="None">The position <B>d</B>, where the H atom is bound to an <IT>μ</IT><SB>3</SB>S atom, is unfavorable as well.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="223"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj26" novelty="New" advantage="None">We have also calculated the energies for H adsorption on the FeMoco for the same configurations, although they already have been calculated elsewhere.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit51">4,51</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="224"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj26" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">But by calculating the adsorption energies for the FeFeco and the FeMoco with exactly the same model, we can obtain energy differences, which are relatively precise.</annotationART></s> <s sid="225"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj26" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">Although the energies for both the FeFeco and the FeMoco include some errors, as we for example do not model the environment, the difference of the adsorption energies from the FeFeco to the FeMoco should be significantly more accurate, because to a large extent, we make the same errors in modeling the FeMoco and the FeFeco.</annotationART></s> <s sid="226"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs37" novelty="None" advantage="None">The adsorption characteristics of the FeMoco is very similar to the one of the FeFeco.</annotationART></s> <s sid="227"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs38" novelty="None" advantage="None">The structure <B>a</B>, where the H atom binds to one of the <IT>μ</IT><SB>2</SB>S atoms, is clearly the most stable one followed by structure <B>e</B>, where the H atom is inside the cluster.</annotationART></s> <s sid="228"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs39" novelty="None" advantage="None">The structures <B>b</B> and <B>c</B> with the H atom binding on one of the triangular Fe atoms are equally or slightly more unstable than their counterparts for the FeFeco.</annotationART></s> <s sid="229"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs40" novelty="None" advantage="None">The same holds for structure <B>d</B> which is clearly unfavorable.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.3">Nitrogen adsorption</HEADER><P><s sid="230"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj27" novelty="New" advantage="None">In this section, we study the adsorption of N<SB>2</SB> on the FeFeco.</annotationART></s> <s sid="231"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod49" novelty="None" advantage="None">Concerning possible adsorption sites on the triangular Fe atoms, we choose to study only those positions which Rod and Nørskov<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF> found to be energetically feasible, as all other adsorption positions were at least 80 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> higher in energy and are therefore highly unlikely for the FeFeco as well.</annotationART></s> <s sid="232"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac87" novelty="None" advantage="None">In <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">ref. 4</REF> it was found that only end-on adsorption of N<SB>2</SB> on a triangular Fe atom is is approximately thermoneutral and that all other positions involving the triangular Fe atoms are highly unstable.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="233"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj28" novelty="New" advantage="None">We investigate the binding of N<SB>2</SB> on the FeFeco end-on to the triangular Fe atoms in configurations <B>a</B> and <B>b</B> in Fig. 6.</annotationART></s> <s sid="234"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs41" novelty="None" advantage="None">The corresponding binding energies are listed in Table 3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="235"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj29" novelty="New" advantage="None">Furthermore, we consider the adsorption of N<SB>2</SB> at the Mo atom, which has been suggested in the literature.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit48 cit49 cit73">48,49,73</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="236"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod50" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the FeMoco we remove one of the OH groups to model that the homocitrate ring is opened.</annotationART></s> <s sid="237"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod51" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the FeFeco, we use the model with 1OH group.</annotationART></s> <s sid="238"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs42" novelty="None" advantage="None">This configuration is depicted in Fig. 6c.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="239"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs43" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the FeFeco we find that N<SB>2</SB> adsorption end-on on one triangular Fe atom is slightly endothermic with the exception of the model with two OH groups and spin state A1, for which the adsorption on the upper triangular Fe atoms is slightly exothermic.</annotationART></s> <s sid="240"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The binding energies do not depend very much on the number of OH groups, the magnetic state, and on whether the adsorption takes place on a Fe atom from the upper or from the lower triangle.</annotationART></s> <s sid="241"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs44" novelty="None" advantage="None">Comparing these energies with the corresponding values for the FeMoco, we notice that the energies for the FeMoco are 10–20 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> higher, depending on the number of OH groups and the magnetic state for the FeFeco.</annotationART></s> <s sid="242"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">This means that according to our results it should be slightly more endothermic to bind N<SB>2</SB> to one of the triangular Fe atoms to the FeMoco than to the FeFeco.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="243"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs45" novelty="None" advantage="None">The binding energy for adsorption of N<SB>2</SB> on the bottom Fe atom (the position of the Mo atom for the FeMoco, configuration <B>c</B> in Fig. 6) is quite high, 71 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> for spin state A1 and 83 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> for spin state A2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="244"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">This means that although the homocitrate ring is already assumed to be opened (modeled by one OH group), the adsorption of N<SB>2</SB> is still highly unfavorable.</annotationART></s> <s sid="245"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs46" novelty="None" advantage="None">We observe the same for the FeMoco, where we are not even able to find a stable position for N<SB>2</SB> where it remains bound during the minimization.</annotationART></s> <s sid="246"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs47" novelty="None" advantage="None">In all cases, N<SB>2</SB> left the FeMoco and we just obtained the sum of the energies of the isolated FeMoco and N<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="247"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod52" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, we calculate configuration <B>c</B> for the FeMoco with the bond length Mo–N fixed to 2.01 Å, which is the bond length of the Fe–N bond from the FeFeco in configuration <B>c</B> corrected for the different covalent radii of Fe and Mo (see footnotes in Table 3).</annotationART></s> <s sid="248"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs48" novelty="None" advantage="None">For this constrained system we obtain a binding energy of 63 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>, which is also quite high.</annotationART></s> <s sid="249"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, we can conclude that for both the FeFeco and the FeMoco we do not observe binding and activation of N<SB>2</SB> on the lower Mo/Fe site.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.4">Hydrogenation of adsorbed N<SB>2</SB></HEADER><P><s sid="250"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac88" novelty="None" advantage="None">Rod and Nørskov<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF> suggested a pathway for ammonia synthesis, where N<SB>2</SB> is adsorbed end-on on one of the triangular Fe atoms and then stepwise hydrogenated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="251"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac89" novelty="None" advantage="None">They found that the only endothermic and therefore rate-determining step is the addition of the first H atom to the adsorbed N<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="252"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj30" novelty="New" advantage="None">Therefore, we calculate the energy of this first adsorption step on the FeFeco and FeMoco, as the energy difference of this step between the two clusters may have direct consequences for their reactivity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="253"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod53" novelty="None" advantage="None">We consider hydrogenation of adsorbed N<SB>2</SB> on Fe atoms in both the upper and the lower triangle.</annotationART></s> <s sid="254"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs49" novelty="None" advantage="None">The configurations are shown in Fig. 7 and the corresponding energies are listed in Table 4.</annotationART></s> <s sid="255"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs50" novelty="None" advantage="None">Again, we notice that the energies do not depend much on the number of OH groups present, but for configuration <B>b</B> the energies do depend on the spin state (difference of 30 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="256"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs51" novelty="None" advantage="None">The hydrogenation energies for the FeMoco are higher than for the FeFeco.</annotationART></s> <s sid="257"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs52" novelty="None" advantage="None">They are also higher than the one found in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">ref. 4</REF>, who find a value of about 80 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="258"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">This can again be attributed to the different models in use, as in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">ref. 4</REF> a chain model of the FeMoco is considered, whereas we consider a cluster model.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="5">Discussion</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="5.1">Structure of the FeFeco</HEADER><P><s sid="259"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj31" novelty="New" advantage="None">We have modeled the structure and the magnetic state of the FeFeco.</annotationART></s> <s sid="260"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have found that most are magnetic couplings are indeed antiferromagnetic, as found in experiments<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13 cit20">13,20</REF> and they give rise to a low total spin of S = 1/2 for the model with two OH groups (Fig. 3d) or <IT>S</IT> = 0 for the model with one OH group (Fig. 3e).</annotationART></s> <s sid="261"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is in agreement with EPR experiments, which suggest <IT>S</IT> = 0.</annotationART></s> <s sid="262"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have found two lowest-lying antiferromagnetic states A1 and A2 (Fig. 4b and c), where the energy difference between is not large enough to be decisive compared to the accuracy of our calculation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="263"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The two spin states A1 and A2 give rise to the same total spin on the FeFeco.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="264"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fact that the total spin of the FeFeco model with one OH group <IT>S</IT> = 0 agrees with the experimental EPR results, whereas the total spin of the model with two OH groups with <IT>S</IT> = 1/2 does not, might be an artefact of or model, or it might mean that the homocitrate ring indeed is opened.</annotationART></s> <s sid="265"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj32" novelty="New" advantage="None">Furthermore, the formal oxidation states of the FeFeco with one OH group [4Fe<SP>3+</SP>4Fe<SP>2+</SP>9S<SP>2−</SP>] agrees with the Mössbauer assignment from <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">ref. 13</REF> Therefore, it is relevant to discuss, whether the homocitrate ring indeed might be opened.</annotationART></s> <s sid="266"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac90" novelty="None" advantage="None">The issue of monodentate <IT>versus</IT> bidentate coordination of the homocitrate ring for the FeMoco has been discussed in the literature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="267"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac91" novelty="None" advantage="None">Experimental studies, where homocitrate was substituted, have shown that the proper functionality of the FeMoco crucially depends on the presence of homocitrate.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit71">71</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="268"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac92" novelty="None" advantage="None">A study by Grönberg <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit72">72</REF>. has shown that if homocitrate is substituted by citrate, the reactivity of the FeMoco is altered significantly.</annotationART></s> <s sid="269"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac93" novelty="None" advantage="None">Theoretically, the protonation and opening of the homocitrate ring for the FeMoco have been investigated by Szilagyi <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit48">48</REF>. and by Durrant.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit49">49</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="270"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac94" novelty="None" advantage="None">They both find that the opening of the homocitrate ring is energetically possible and enhanced by protonation of the ring, although it does not happen spontaneously.</annotationART></s> <s sid="271"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac95" novelty="None" advantage="None">The possible opening of the homocitrate ring in the FeFeco has not been investigated in detail yet.</annotationART></s> <s sid="272"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">In our model, we cannot calculate directly the energy required to open the homocitrate ring, but only the trend from FeMoco to FeFeco.</annotationART></s> <s sid="273"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">There, we find that opening of the homocitrate ring in the FeFeco is 26–31 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> lower in energy than for the FeMoco.</annotationART></s> <s sid="274"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus we conclude that it might well be that for the FeFeco the homocitrate ring is opened.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="275"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">The geometrical features of the FeFeco listed in Table 1 do not depend very much on the number of OH groups and on which of the two spin ground states is present.</annotationART></s> <s sid="276"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, the structural features of our models are consistent with the experimental results obtained by EXAFS.</annotationART></s> <s sid="277"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">The structure with one OH group and spin state A1 agrees best with the experimental data.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="278"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">Comparing our results to the ones of Lovell <IT>et al.</IT>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit54">54</REF> we notice that there is some agreement with respect to the magnetic ground state of the FeFeco.</annotationART></s> <s sid="279"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac96" novelty="None" advantage="None">Lovell <IT>et al.</IT> find the spin state A2 (in their notation BS3) to be the lowest in energy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="280"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac97" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, they find the spin state A1 (in their notation BS1) to have an energy of 45 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> higher than the spin state A2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="281"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" advantage="None">This energy difference is rather large compared to ours.</annotationART></s> <s sid="282"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None">Apart from the difference that their model is a bit larger, they also treat the magnetism slightly different in their calculations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="283"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None">Concerning the geometry of the FeFeco, both the Fe–S and Fe–Fe distances of Lovell <IT>et al.</IT> are larger or similar to our results.</annotationART></s> <s sid="284"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res29" novelty="None" advantage="None">One noticable difference is that they observe the total height of the FeFeco to be significantly larger (7.87 Å) than the height of the FeMoco (7.27 Å), whereas we observe their heights to be similar (7.13 Å for the FeMoco, 6.99–7.35 Å for the FeFeco).</annotationART></s> <s sid="285"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac98" novelty="None" advantage="None">One should note that an increase of the height from the FeMoco to the FeFeco is not observed in experimental results, as the latest X-ray structure 1M1N for the FeMoco gives a value of 7.00 Å, and the EXAFS study for the FeFeco gives 6.92 Å<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="5.2">Hydrogen adsorption and H<SB>2</SB> evolution</HEADER><P><s sid="286"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res30" novelty="None" advantage="None">For adsorption of proton/electron pairs on the FeFeco we find that the most stable adsorption site is a <IT>μ</IT><SB>2</SB>S ligand (<B>a</B> in Fig. 5, where the adsorption is exothermic for both models and spin states.</annotationART></s> <s sid="287"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" advantage="None">Another possible place for a H atom to adsorb is inside the cluster, as shown in Fig. 5 <B>e</B>, where the adsorption is exothermic or approximately thermoneutral.</annotationART></s> <s sid="288"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res32" novelty="None" advantage="None">For thr configurations <B>b</B>, <B>c</B> and <B>d</B>, <IT>i.e.</IT> for adsorption on the triangular Fe atoms or on the <IT>μ</IT><SB>3</SB>S atoms, adsorption is endothermic, but the energies are thermodynamically accessible.</annotationART></s> <s sid="289"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Generally, we can conclude that the reactivity of the FeFeco does not crucially depend on the number of OH groups present or on the specific spin state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="290"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">This means that our model should be fairly robust, because the details do not seem to influence the energies strongly.</annotationART></s> <s sid="291"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, the reactivity of the FeFeco follows the same pattern as the reactivity of the FeMoco, as the order of stability of all configurations is the same, and the energy differences are not very large.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="292"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj33" novelty="New" advantage="None">Before we proceed with a discussion of H<SB>2</SB> formation on the FeFeco, we briefly compare to other studies in order to validate our approach.</annotationART></s> <s sid="293"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac99" novelty="None" advantage="None">The adsorption of hydrogen on the FeFeco has not been investigated before, but for the adsorption of hydrogen on the FeMoco, several studies are available for comparison.</annotationART></s> <s sid="294"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs53" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our results are similar to the ones of Rod and Nørskov,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF> who also find that the preferred place for H binding are the <IT>μ</IT><SB>2</SB>S atoms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="295"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs54" novelty="None" advantage="None">For H adsorption on a <IT>μ</IT><SB>2</SB>S atom, we find a binding energy of −30 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>, whereas Rod and Nørskov find a binding energy of −10 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="296"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs55" novelty="None" advantage="None">For H adsorption on the Fe atoms, we find a binding energies in the range of 51 to 54 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> depending on whether the adsorption takes place near the His-end or near the Cys-end, whereas Rod and Nørskov find a binding energy of 30 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="297"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res33" novelty="None" advantage="None">These energy differences can be explained by the different models, as Rod and Nørskov consider an infinite chain constructed of MoFe<SB>6</SB>S<SB>9</SB> units, whereas we consider the whole cluster with truncated ligands.</annotationART></s> <s sid="298"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, one would expect that both models lead to the same trends, and this is indeed the case.</annotationART></s> <s sid="299"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac100" novelty="None" advantage="None">The adsorption of hydrogen on the FeMoco is also studied by Lovell <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit51">51</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="300"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac101" novelty="None" advantage="None">They only list the order of stability of the different adsorption structures, but not the adsorption energies compared to ½H<SB>2</SB> in the gas phase.</annotationART></s> <s sid="301"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs56" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, we can only make a qualitative comparison of the results.</annotationART></s> <s sid="302"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac102" novelty="None" advantage="None">Lovell <IT>et al.</IT> find that the most stable configuration is <B>e</B> in Fig. 5 (E1H1-c in their notation).</annotationART></s> <s sid="303"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac103" novelty="None" advantage="None">They find that the adsorption of H on the <IT>μ</IT><SB>2</SB>S atoms (configuration <B>a</B>, E1H1-b1/E1H1-b2/E1H1-b3 in their notation) is less favorable than configuration <B>e</B>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="304"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res34" novelty="None" advantage="None">This disagrees with our results which predict that the adsorption of H on the <IT>μ</IT><SB>2</SB>S atoms is the most stable configuration of all.</annotationART></s> <s sid="305"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res35" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results of Lovell <IT>et al.</IT> for the relative stability of binding of H to the trigonal Fe sites from the outside (configurations <B>b</B> and <B>c</B>) are similar to ours.</annotationART></s> <s sid="306"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac104" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, Lovell <IT>et al.</IT> find the protonation of the homocitrate ring to be favorable and that they find the protonation of the Mo atom to be very unfavorable.</annotationART></s> <s sid="307"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac105" novelty="None" advantage="None">This might hint at that the homocitrate ring indeed can open, but that the Mo atom is probably not involved in protonation at this stage.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="308"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj34" novelty="New" advantage="None">Now, we can try to take a closer look at the energy differences between the FeFeco and the FeMoco in order to find out, how H<SB>2</SB> indeed can be formed on the FeFeco.</annotationART></s> <s sid="309"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod54" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to limit the numerous possibilities for the FeFeco, we always consider the model and the spin state, which are most stable, in the following and thereby assume that switching between the different states is possible.</annotationART></s> <s sid="310"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res36" novelty="None" advantage="None">The first general result is that the energetics of hydrogen adsorption for the FeFeco is very similar to the one for the FeMoco.</annotationART></s> <s sid="311"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj35" novelty="New" advantage="None">Therefore, to discuss the consequences of our results on the differences in H<SB>2</SB> formation between the FeFeco and the FeMoco, we can use <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">ref. 4</REF> as a starting point.</annotationART></s> <s sid="312"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac106" novelty="None" advantage="None">It was suggested that the first three H atoms adsorb on the <IT>μ</IT><SB>2</SB>S atoms and that this happens very easily.</annotationART></s> <s sid="313"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac107" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fourth atom then adsorbs on one of the triangular Fe atoms, which requires energy and turns out to be the rate-limiting step.</annotationART></s> <s sid="314"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac108" novelty="None" advantage="None">Then H<SB>2</SB> forms on the Fe atom and is released, both steps are exothermic.</annotationART></s> <s sid="315"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res37" novelty="None" advantage="None">From the overall similarity of the energetics of the FeFeco to the FeMoco we can infer that H<SB>2</SB> formation on the FeFeco is possible according to the scheme shown in Fig. 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="316"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res38" novelty="None" advantage="None">We can exclude that positions other than the ones on the <IT>μ</IT><SB>2</SB>S atoms and on the triangular Fe atoms are relevant for H<SB>2</SB> formation in this context on the following grounds, First, we note that H<SB>2</SB> has to be formed on a Fe atom, as sulfur cannot interact simultaneously with two H atoms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="317"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res39" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, it is reasonable to assume that H<SB>2</SB> is formed on the outside of the cluster, as space inside the cluster is limited.</annotationART></s> <s sid="318"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res40" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, configuration <B>e</B> in the formation of H<SB>2</SB> is not possible because of the central N ligand.</annotationART></s> <s sid="319"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res41" novelty="None" advantage="None">The same holds for configuration <B>d</B>, which is unfavorable and cannot contribute to the formation of H<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="320"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, it seems plausible that the formation of H<SB>2</SB> on both the FeMoco and the FeFeco can proceed in the way suggested in .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">ref. 4</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="321"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res42" novelty="None" advantage="None">The first three H atoms adsorb on the <IT>μ</IT><SB>2</SB>S atoms, which is energetically favorable for both the FeMoco and the FeFeco.</annotationART></s> <s sid="322"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res43" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fourth H atom adsorbes on one triangular Fe atom, which requires energy for both the FeMoco and the FeFeco.</annotationART></s> <s sid="323"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res44" novelty="None" advantage="None">All following steps (displacement of one H atom from a <IT>μ</IT><SB>2</SB>S-atom to the Fe atom, desorption of H<SB>2</SB>) are energetically favorable for the FeMoco, and although we have not calculated them for the FeFeco, it is reasonable to assume that they are approximately equally favorable.</annotationART></s> <s sid="324"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, the adsorption of the fourth H atom on a triangular Fe atom is the rate-limiting step and the energies of the configurations <B>b</B> and <B>c</B> determine the energetics for H<SB>2</SB> formation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="325"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res45" novelty="None" advantage="None">As can be seen in Table 2 the energies are slightly lower or equal for the FeFeco than for the FeMoco.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="326"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj36" novelty="New" advantage="None">Having discussed the general scheme of H<SB>2</SB> formation on the FeFeco, we can now turn to more subtle aspects.</annotationART></s> <s sid="327"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod55" novelty="None" advantage="None">At this point, we can further limit the possible configurations for adsorption of N<SB>2</SB> and H by looking at the surroundings of the FeFeco.</annotationART></s> <s sid="328"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod56" novelty="None" advantage="None">The amino acids surrounding the active site are mostly conserved from the Mo-containing nitrogenase to the iron-only nitrogenase, and therefore we can consider the environment of the FeMoco.</annotationART></s> <s sid="329"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs57" novelty="None" advantage="None">The FeMoco with some of the residues located close to it from the crystal structure 1M1N<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF> is shown in Fig. 8.</annotationART></s> <s sid="330"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs58" novelty="None" advantage="None">One notices that the His195 residue is closely located to one Fe atom on the upper triangle, the distance of N<IT>ε</IT> (one of the N atoms in the imidazole ring) to the nearest Fe atom is only 4.1 Å and to the nearest <IT>μ</IT><SB>2</SB>S atom only 3.3 Å.</annotationART></s> <s sid="331"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac109" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both experimental<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit74">74</REF> and theoretical studies<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF> have suggested that the His195 residue is a possible proton donor for the FeMoco.</annotationART></s> <s sid="332"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">As this His residue is conserved in the iron-only nitrogenase, it could also be a possible proton donor for the FeFeco.</annotationART></s> <s sid="333"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res46" novelty="None" advantage="None">This implies that we should concentrate on the results for adsorption on the Fe atoms in the upper triangle, as this is the place where interaction with the His195 residue is possible.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit75">75</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="334"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res47" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the H adsorption this means that the energy of configuration <B>b</B> of Fig. 5 and Table 2 determines the formation of H<SB>2</SB>, as the adsorption of H on a Fe atom in the upper triangle is the rate-limiting step.</annotationART></s> <s sid="335"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res48" novelty="None" advantage="None">As the energy of configuration <B>b</B> is almost equal for the FeMoco and the FeFeco, the formation of H<SB>2</SB> should have very similar energetics on the two clusters.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="336"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, from this discussion we can conclude that a possible scheme for H<SB>2</SB> evolution on the FeFeco is the scenario depicted in Fig. 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="337"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, we have found that the energetics for H<SB>2</SB> formation on the FeFeco is very similar to the one on the FeMoco.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="5.3">Dinitrogen adsorption and hydrogenation</HEADER><P><s sid="338"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res49" novelty="None" advantage="None">The adsorption of N<SB>2</SB> on the triangular Fe atoms of the FeFeco is slightly endothermic or thermoneutral, with the exception of the model with two OH groups and spin state A1, where configuration <B>b</B> in Fig. 6 is slightly exothermic.</annotationART></s> <s sid="339"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res50" novelty="None" advantage="None">We can exclude adsorption of N<SB>2</SB> on the lower Fe atom (the one substituting Mo), as adsorption is clearly endothermic, even though the homocitrate ring is already opened.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="340"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res51" novelty="None" advantage="None">We find that the energetics for both N<SB>2</SB> adsorption and hydrogenation on the FeFeco is very similar to the one on the FeMoco.</annotationART></s> <s sid="341"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res52" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is an interesting result, as the actual activities of the FeFeco and the FeMoco are very different.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="342"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj37" novelty="New" advantage="None">For a discussion of more subtle aspects of N<SB>2</SB> adsorption and hydrogenation on the FeFeco compared to the FeMoco, we can use results from <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">ref. 4</REF> who modeled the influence of the His195 group in an extremely simple way.</annotationART></s> <s sid="343"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac110" novelty="None" advantage="None">They placed a NH<SB>4</SB> molecule in the vicinity of the Fe atom where N<SB>2</SB> was adsorbed and observed that the cluster becomes negatively charged, while the NH<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP> is positively charged.</annotationART></s> <s sid="344"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac111" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, they found that both the adsorption of N<SB>2</SB> and its hydrogenation are much more facile with this proton donor.</annotationART></s> <s sid="345"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac112" novelty="None" advantage="None">They found that the structure of the FeMoco with N<SB>2</SB> adsorbed is stabilized by <IT>ca.</IT> 80 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> and the structure of the FeMoco with N<SB>2</SB>H adsorbed is stabilized by <IT>ca.</IT> 130 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="346"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod57" novelty="None" advantage="None">For our considerations, we assume that these energy shifts are the same for the FeMoco and the FeFeco.</annotationART></s> <s sid="347"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod57" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is reasonable, since their environments should be very similar.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="348"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs59" novelty="None" advantage="None">The energies of the N<SB>2</SB> adsorption and hydrogenation for both the FeFeco and the FeMoco and for both without and with these energy shifts are shown in Fig. 9.</annotationART></s> <s sid="349"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs60" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our calculated energies (upper curve) show that the N<SB>2</SB> adsorption is a bit more energy-demanding on the FeMoco than on the FeFeco.</annotationART></s> <s sid="350"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs61" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the hydrogenated structures, the one for FeMoco lies still a bit higher than FeFeco, but the difference is smaller.</annotationART></s> <s sid="351"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod58" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the structures with the energy shift (lower curve), the relative positions of the FeFeco and FeMoco to each other of course have not changed, as we assumed the energy shift to be the same for them.</annotationART></s> <s sid="352"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res53" novelty="None" advantage="None">But one can see that now the adsorption of N<SB>2</SB> is exothermic for both the FeFeco and the FeMoco and therefore should happen easily.</annotationART></s> <s sid="353"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res54" novelty="None" advantage="None">Once N<SB>2</SB> is adsorbed, energy is needed for the hydrogenation, although this energy is less than for the values without the shift.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="354"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod59" novelty="None" advantage="None">Assuming that the rate-determining step for the formation of NH<SB>3</SB> is the first hydrogenation of the adsorbed N<SB>2</SB>, it follows that the determining energy difference for this process should be the energy difference between the state with N<SB>2</SB>H adsorbed and the state with N<SB>2</SB> adsorbed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="355"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod60" novelty="None" advantage="None">In Fig. 9 this energy difference is marked as Δ<IT>E</IT><SB>hyd</SB>(FeMoco) for the FeMoco and Δ<IT>E</IT><SB>hyd</SB>(FeFeco) for the FeFeco for our calculated energies (no energy shift from proton donor, upper curve).</annotationART></s> <s sid="356"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod61" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the case with the energy shift from the proton donor (lower curve) the energy differences are termed Δ<IT>E</IT><SB>corr,hyd</SB>(FeMoco) for the FeMoco and Δ<IT>E</IT><SB>corr,hyd</SB>(FeFeco) for the FeFeco.</annotationART></s> <s sid="357"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod62" novelty="None" advantage="None">The difference in performance between the FeFeco and the FeMoco should be characterized by the difference of those energy differences</annotationART></s><P><s sid="358"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod63" novelty="None" advantage="None">δΔ<IT>qE</IT> = Δ<IT>E</IT><SB>corr,hyd</SB>(FeFeco) − Δ<IT>E</IT><SB>corr,hyd</SB>(FeMoco)</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="359"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod64" novelty="None" advantage="None">=Δ<IT>E</IT><SB>hyd</SB>(FeFeco) − Δ<IT>E</IT><SB>hyd</SB>(FeMoco)</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="360"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs62" novelty="None" advantage="None">=(107 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> − 5 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>) − (118 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> − 23 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>)</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="361"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs63" novelty="None" advantage="None">=7 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s></P> <s sid="362"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res55" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note, as the shifts due to the proton donor were assumed to be the same for the FeFeco and for the FeMoco, the difference δΔ<IT>E</IT> is of course independent of those shifts.</annotationART></s> <s sid="363"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res56" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus δΔ<IT>E</IT> should be rather accurate, also because, as we argued earlier, to a large extent we make the same errors for the FeMoco and the FeFeco in our calculations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="364"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res57" novelty="None" advantage="None">The result of eqn. (5) means that the rate-determining step, the hydrogenation of the adsorbed N<SB>2</SB> is more energy-demanding for the FeFeco than for the FeMoco.</annotationART></s> <s sid="365"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs64" novelty="None" advantage="None">This agrees with the observation that the FeFeco performs worse for the nitrogen fixation than the FeMoco.</annotationART></s> <s sid="366"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, one general result of our calculations is that the energetics of the FeFeco for nitrogen fixation seems to be slightly less advantageous than the one of the FeMoco.</annotationART></s> <s sid="367"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, the measured differences in activity might at least partially arise from the substitution of Mo by Fe in the active site.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="368"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj38" novelty="New" advantage="None">Having drawn this general conclusion, we try to quantify the differences in activity between the FeFeco and the FeMoco.</annotationART></s> <s sid="369"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac113" novelty="None" advantage="None">One of the few quantitative observations regarding the activity of the Fe-only nitrogenase is that the ratio of produced hydrogen to fixed nitrogen is <IT>H</IT><SB>2</SB>/<IT>N</IT><SB>2</SB> = 75<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF>. while it is <IT>H</IT><SB>2</SB>/<IT>N</IT><SB>2</SB> = 1 for the conventional nitrogenase.</annotationART></s> <s sid="370"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac114" novelty="None" advantage="None">As these two results are ratios, they are to a large extent independent of the specific experimental parameters.</annotationART></s> <s sid="371"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod65" novelty="None" advantage="None">For a moment, we now make the simplified assumption that this difference in the ratios arises from the difference in energies of the least stable intermetiate at the cofactors (see Fig. 9).</annotationART></s> <s sid="372"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod66" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, as we have shown that the energetics for H<SB>2</SB> formation are almost identical for the FeFeco and the FeMoco, we assume that the difference in the <IT>H</IT><SB>2</SB>/<IT>N</IT><SB>2</SB> ratio arises directly from the differences in energies δΔ<IT>E</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="373"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs65" novelty="None" advantage="None">Then they are related <IT>via</IT> an Arrhenius factor This corresponds to an energy difference of δΔ<IT>E</IT> = 5 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> at room temperature (293 K).</annotationART></s> <s sid="374"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res58" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have determined δΔ<IT>E</IT> = 7 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>, which is very close.</annotationART></s> <s sid="375"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res59" novelty="None" advantage="None">One should note that because of the exponential, very slight changes in the energy difference cause large changes in the nitrogen to hydrogen ratio.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="376"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con18" novelty="None" advantage="None">One can and should of course question our assumptions and whether the two energies agree by chance.</annotationART></s> <s sid="377"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, it is clear that our model is extremely simple and that there can be energy shifts due to the environment or a possible central ligand, which are not included in our model.</annotationART></s> <s sid="378"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con20" novelty="None" advantage="None">In further studies one would also have to investigate, whether the proton/electron transfers are activated and how high these possible activation barriers are.</annotationART></s> <s sid="379"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con21" novelty="None" advantage="None">Nonetheless, we have shown that the properties of the FeFeco and the FeMoco are rather similar, but that slight differences are sufficient to considerably modify the reactivity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="380"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con22" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, we speculate that the rôle of the Mo is to optimally tune the FeMoco.</annotationART></s> <s sid="381"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con23" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case, where Mo is not available, nature uses V or Fe, which work, but with a lower reactivity.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
