<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b312620j" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Photocatalytic water splitting on hydrated layered perovskite tantalate A<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB>·<IT>n</IT>H<SB>2</SB>O (A = H, K, and Rb)</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">A series of layered perovskite tantalates, A<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB> (A = H, Li, K, and Rb), were prepared as novel photocatalysts for photocatalytic water splitting into H<SB>2</SB> and O<SB>2</SB> under UV irradiation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The layered perovskite tantalates with hydrated interlayer space, A<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB>·<IT>n</IT>H<SB>2</SB>O (A = H, K, and Rb), showed higher H<SB>2</SB> formation rate than anhydrous layered tantalate, Li<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB>, and anhydrous perovskite tantalate, KTaO<SB>3</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">H<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB>·<IT>n</IT>H<SB>2</SB>O and K<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB>·<IT>n</IT>H<SB>2</SB>O showed high activity for overall splitting of water without loading co-catalysts.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reaction over H<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB>·<IT>n</IT>H<SB>2</SB>O proceeded steadily more than 70 h, demonstrating a high durability of the catalyst.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">Effects of hydrated interlayer space on the catalytic activity were discussed on the basis of the results of photoluminescence spectra and the hydrogen evolution from aqueous solution of <IT>n</IT>-butylamine as a test reaction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results indicate that the availability of interlayer space of layered tantalate as reaction sites is an important factor to improve the photocatalytic activity of Ta-based semiconductor materials.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Among various methods of solar energy conversion, the photocatalytic decomposition of water into H<SB>2</SB> and O<SB>2</SB> over semiconductor materials is one of the most challenging methods.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Much attention has been paid to this reaction, as it can potentially provide clean and renewable source for hydrogen fuel in the future.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since TiO<SB>2</SB> electrode was first studied for water decomposition under UV-light irradiation, a variety of photocatalysts, mainly Ti,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2 cit3 cit4">1–4</REF> Nb<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6">5,6</REF> and Ta<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7 cit8 cit9 cit10 cit11 cit12 cit13">7–13</REF> based oxides, have been reported to be effective for photocatalytic decomposition of water.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">A group of Domen <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6">5,6</REF>. first demonstrated the use of ion-exchangeable layered oxides, K<SB>4</SB>Nb<SB>6</SB>O<SB>17</SB> and K<SB>2</SB>La<SB>2</SB>Ti<SB>3</SB>O<SB>10</SB>, as effective photocatalysts for water splitting.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Upon loading transition metal co-catalyst, NiO<SB><IT>x</IT></SB>, these materials show much higher activity than the “bulk type” catalysts such as Pt/TiO<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">It was explained that these layered materials use their interlayer space as reaction sites, where electron-hole recombination process could be retarded by physical separation of electron and hole pairs generated by photo-absorption.</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the other hand, Ta-based catalysts have recently been developed as a new class of photocatalyst.</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Kudo <IT>et al.</IT> first studied the photocatalytic properties of many Ta-based catalysts, such as Sr<SB>2</SB>Ta<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF> and NaTaO<SB>3</SB>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Among these catalysts, La doped NiO/NaTaO<SB>3</SB> showed extremely high efficiency with quantum yields as high as 50% under UV irradiation.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Recently, Zou <IT>et al.</IT> demonstrated the direct water splitting under visible light irradiation with In–Ni–Ta oxides.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, for most of the photocatalysts, it is necessary to load transition metal co-catalysts to achieve high activity for water splitting.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The above Ta-based catalysts can be classified to anhydrous bulk type photocatalysts.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">We expected that Ta-based materials with hydrous layered structure can be an effective photocatalysts for water splitting.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Machida <IT>et al.</IT> first studied the photocatalytic properties of layered perovskite tantalates.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">They prepared layered tantalates, ANdTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB> (A = H or Na) in hydrous form, whose interlayer space is potentially available for the reaction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the activity of these layered tantalates was lower than that of NaNdTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB> in dehydrated form, indicating that hydration of this type of layered tantalate is not effective in improving the photocatalytic activity.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">A<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB> (A = H, Li, K and Rb) type tantalate are new members of Ruddlesden–Popper type layered perovskite.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14 cit15 cit16 cit17">14–17</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The structure of K<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB> and its hydrate has been recently clarified.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">These materials are composed of layers of Sr–Ta perovskite sheets and potassium ions located in the interlayer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The layered structure allows spontaneous water intercalation when anhydrous K<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB> is kept in air at ambient temperature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">We hypothesized that from these features, A<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB> materials act as new Ta-based photocatalysts with two-dimensional structures in water.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this paper, we report the first successful example of layered perovskite-type tantalates with hydrated interlayer space, A<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB>·<IT>n</IT>H<SB>2</SB>O (A = H, K and Rb), as very active photocatalysts.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None">The activity of these novel catalysts is compared to that of Li<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB> (anhydrous layered perovskite-type tantalate) as well as that of the bulk type perovskite tantalate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="New" advantage="None">Photocatalysts are characterized by XRD, diffuse reflectance UV spectroscopy, photoluminescence spectroscopy, and the hydrogen evolution from aqueous solution of <IT>n</IT>-butylamine as a test reaction, and the relationship between the catalytic activity and the structural characteristics is discussed in terms of the effect of the interlayer.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Experimental</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Catalyst preparation and characterization</HEADER><P><s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">A<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB> (A = Li, K, and Rb) powders were prepared by a conventional solid state reaction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Stoichiometric amounts of SrCO<SB>3</SB> (Kanto Chemical, purity; 99.9%) and Ta<SB>2</SB>O<SB>5</SB> (Rare Metallic, purity; 99.9%) with a 150% molar excess of K<SB>2</SB>CO<SB>3</SB> (Kanto Chemical, purity; 99.5%) or Rb<SB>2</SB>CO<SB>3</SB> (Kanto Chemical, purity; 99.5%) were mixed together and heated in air at 1173 K for 24 h.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Li<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB> was prepared from SrCO<SB>3</SB> and Ta<SB>2</SB>O<SB>5</SB> with a 150% molar excess of Li<SB>2</SB>CO<SB>3</SB> (Kanto Chemical, purity; 99.5%) by heating at 1523 K for 12 h.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">After the calcinations, the excess alkali was washed out with deionized water, and the sample was dried <IT>in vacuo</IT> at 298 K for 20 h.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">According to the previous report,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF> H<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB> was prepared by the K<SP>+</SP>/H<SP>+</SP> exchange: K<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB> (3 g) was added to 150 mL of 0.3 M HNO<SB>3</SB> at room temperature for 24 h with constant stirring, followed by washing with deionized water, and by drying <IT>in vacuo</IT> at 298 K for 20 h.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">After the preparation, A<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB> (A = H, K, and Rb) materials exhibit hydrated structure and are named as A<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB>·<IT>n</IT>H<SB>2</SB>O (A = H, K, and Rb).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The crystal structure of the obtained materials was confirmed by X-ray diffraction (MAC Science; MX Labo) with Cu Kα radiation (40 kV, 25 mA) at room temperature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thermogravimetric (TG) analysis coupled with differential thermal analysis of the hydrated oxides was made using MTC1000 (MAC Science) operating with a heating rate of 10 K min<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Diffuse reflectance spectra were obtained with a UV-Vis spectrometer (Jasco; V-550) and were converted from reflection to absorbance by the Kubelka–Munk method.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The optical band-gap energy was calculated from onset of absorption edges.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Photoluminescence was measured at 77 K using a closed quartz cell and a fluorometer (HITACHI F-4500).</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp12" novelty="None" advantage="None">For K<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB> in anhydrous form, XRD, UV-Vis and photoluminescence measurements were carried out immediately after calcination in order to avoid the hydration process.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Photocatalytic reaction</HEADER><P><s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The photocatalytic decomposition of water was performed with a gas-closed circulating system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The catalyst powder (0.5 g) was dispersed in 200 mL of pure water by a magnetic stirrer in an inner irradiation cell made of quartz.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The light source was a 400 W high-pressure mercury lamp.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Before the reaction, the mixture was degassed completely and then Ar (<IT>ca.</IT> 15 kPa) was introduced.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The amounts of evolved H<SB>2</SB> and O<SB>2</SB> were determined by gas chromatography (Hitachi, TCD, molecular sieve 5A column and Ar carrier) sampler, 3 mL of which was directly connected to the closed gas circulation system to avoid any contamination from air.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Gas evolution was observed only under photoirradiation.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Results and discussions</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Characterization of A<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB></HEADER><P><s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The powder X-ray diffraction patterns of the samples are shown in Fig. 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the XRD pattern of K<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB> recorded immediately after calcination (Fig. 1a), all the observed lines could be indexed on a tetragonal cell (<IT>I</IT>4/<IT>mmm</IT>, <IT>a</IT> = 3.9072 Å, <IT>c</IT> = 21.6006 Å),<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15 cit16">15,16</REF> indicating that this compound consists of a single phase of layered perovskite, K<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 2a represents the schematic crystal structure of K<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB> before hydration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The structure of anhydrous K<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB> can be described as formed from two TaO<SB>6</SB> octahedra thick slabs of a perovskite lattice cut along the <IT>c</IT> direction; these alternate layers are shifted by (<IT>a</IT> + <IT>b</IT>)/2 (body centered), with the large Sr cations fully occupying the 12-coordination sites.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The potassium ions are located in a rock salt type coordination (C.N. = 9).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Recently, Crosnier–Lopez <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF>. reported that anhydrous form of K<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB> completely disappeared after exposing it to humid air for 7 h, and the corresponding hydrated phase appeared simultaneously.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In our case, it was also confirmed that K<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB> allowed intercalation of water when exposed to humid air; the anhydrous form of K<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB> completely disappeared after exposing it to humid air for 24 h or by washing it with deionized water, and the corresponding hydrated phase, K<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB>·<IT>n</IT>H<SB>2</SB>O,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF> appeared simultaneously.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the XRD pattern of K<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB>·<IT>n</IT>H<SB>2</SB>O (Fig. 1d), prepared by washing K<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB> with deionized water and by drying at 298 K, all the observed lines could be indexed on a primitive cell (<IT>P</IT>4/<IT>mmm</IT>, <IT>a</IT> = 3.9974 Å, <IT>c</IT> = 12.133 Å).</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 2b represents the crystal structure of K<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB>·<IT>n</IT>H<SB>2</SB>O. This kind of structural change has already been observed in layered perovskites, and has been attributed to a shift of alternate layers.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The adjacent layers are stacked immediately above each other in the same arrangement leading to halving the length of the <IT>c</IT>-axis upon hydration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj5" novelty="New" advantage="None">The dehydration behaviour of K<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB>·<IT>n</IT>H<SB>2</SB>O was studied by TG analysis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The result showed a distinct loss of water at a temperature range of 373 K &lt; <IT>T</IT> &lt; 743 K, which could be due to the transformation of hydrate to anhydrous layered material K<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The number of hydration in the formula of K<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB>·<IT>n</IT>H<SB>2</SB>O estimated by the analysis was <IT>n</IT> = 0.9.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the XRD patterns of H<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB>·<IT>n</IT>H<SB>2</SB>O (Fig. 1c), the observed lines could be indexed on a primitive cell (<IT>P</IT>4/<IT>mmm</IT>, <IT>a</IT> = 3.9038 Å, <IT>c</IT> = 9.7742 Å).</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The structure of Rb<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB>·<IT>n</IT>H<SB>2</SB>O has not been reported.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Rietveld method with the RIETAN2000 profile refinement program<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF> was used to refine the structure in the space group <IT>P</IT>4/<IT>mmm</IT> (no.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">139) with a starting model for the perovskite slabs similar to that observed in K<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB>·<IT>n</IT>H<SB>2</SB>O. It was found that the Rb<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB>·<IT>n</IT>H<SB>2</SB>O material consists of a single-phase layered perovskite in a hydrated form, whose X-ray diffraction pattern were indexed based on a primitive cell (<IT>P</IT>4/<IT>mmm</IT>, <IT>a</IT> = 3.9727 Å, <IT>c</IT> = 12.7632 Å).</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">From the thermogravimetric analysis, the hydration numbers of H<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB>·<IT>n</IT>H<SB>2</SB>O and Rb<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB>·<IT>n</IT>H<SB>2</SB>O were estimated to be <IT>n</IT> = 0.6 and <IT>n</IT> = 3.6, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In summary, the above three materials, A<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB>·<IT>n</IT>H<SB>2</SB>O (A = H, K, and Rb), consist of the layered perovskite in a hydrated form, as illustrated in Fig. 2b, though the hydration number depends on the type of alkali cation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Among these materials, theb <IT>c</IT>-axis length increased in the order of H &lt; K &lt; Rb, which should be due to the increase in the ionic radius of the alkali metal cations and/or increase in the hydration number at the interlayer space.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the XRD pattern of Li<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB> (Fig. 1b), recorded after exposing it to humid air for 24 h, all the observed lines could be indexed on a tetragonal cell (<IT>I</IT>4/<IT>mmm</IT>, <IT>a</IT> = 3.8470 Å, <IT>c</IT> = 18.1094 Å), indicating that this compound consists of a single phase of layered perovskite, Li<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The XRD pattern of Li<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB> was essentially the same after the dispersion of the sample to the distilled water for 6 h, followed by drying at ambient temperature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">This indicates that water intercalation does not occur on this material.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">UV diffuse reflectance spectra of the catalysts are shown in Fig. 3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">All the samples had an absorption band in the ultraviolet region and showed a clear absorption edge at around 320 ∼ 330 nm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">From the absorption edge, the band gap of H<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB>·<IT>n</IT>H<SB>2</SB>O, Li<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB>, K<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB>·<IT>n</IT>H<SB>2</SB>O, and Rb<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB>·<IT>n</IT>H<SB>2</SB>O was about 3.9 eV, irrespective of the alkali metal cations at the interlayer space.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The band gap of anhydrous K<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB> was about 3.8 eV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">As listed in Table 1, the BET surface areas of the samples were very small (0.2–4.0 m<SP>2</SP> g<SP>−1</SP>).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 4 shows emission and excitation spectra of the layered tantalates.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the emission spectra with an excitation wavelength of 300 nm, the layered tantalates in anhydrous form, Li<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB> and K<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB>, showed intense luminescence peak with a maximum around 490 and 470 nm, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although luminescence properties of these compounds were not reported, the positions of excitation and emission peaks are very close to those of other anhydrous perovskite tantalates, such as KTaO<SB>3</SB> and Sr<SB>2</SB>Ta<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22 cit23 cit24">22–24</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The excitation and emission transitions are known to be due to charge transfer transitions within the octahedral tantalate groups.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The layered tantalates in hydrous form, H<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB>·<IT>n</IT>H<SB>2</SB>O and K<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB>·<IT>n</IT>H<SB>2</SB>O, showed a very weak and broad band with a maximum at around 500 nm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">These results can be interpreted as the photoluminescence intensity of the layered tantalates being drastically decreased when the interlayer water is present.</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The excitation spectra of Li<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB> and K<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB> have onsets at 320 and 330 nm, respectively, which correspond to the diffuse reflectance spectrum.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">This indicates that band gap irradiation is necessary for the appearance of the luminescence spectra, and hence photogenerated electrons and holes play a role in the emissions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is reasonable to assume that in the hydrated layered tantalates, H<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB>·<IT>n</IT>H<SB>2</SB>O and K<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB>·<IT>n</IT>H<SB>2</SB>O, photogenerated electrons and holes can be readily transferred to the interlayer water.</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hence, we consider that significantly low luminescence efficiency of the hydrated layered tantalates is mainly due to the electron and/or hole trapping by the interlayer water rather than the non-radiative transition.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Photocatalytic activity of A<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB></HEADER><P><s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 5 shows a time course of gas evolution for the photocatalytic decomposition of water over H<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB>·<IT>n</IT>H<SB>2</SB>O without any catalyst pretreatment.</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The catalyst produces H<SB>2</SB> and O<SB>2</SB> in a stoichiometric ratio (H<SB>2</SB>/O<SB>2</SB> = 2 ∶ 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp19" novelty="None" advantage="None">After the first run, the system was evacuated, and the reaction was repeated using the same reaction mixture.</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the second and third runs, overall splitting of water occurred with almost the same rate as the first run, which demonstrates a high durability of the catalyst.</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The total amount of H<SB>2</SB> and O<SB>2</SB> evolved during these runs over H<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB>·<IT>n</IT>H<SB>2</SB>O reached 21.2 and 11.2 mol (mol cat.)<SP>−1</SP>, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">These results clearly demonstrate that overall water splitting on this material proceeds catalytically.</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs20" novelty="None" advantage="None">As shown in Fig. 6, the K<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB>·<IT>n</IT>H<SB>2</SB>O material also produced stoichiometric mixtures of H<SB>2</SB> and O<SB>2</SB>, and the reaction proceeded at a steady rate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Durability test of K<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB>·<IT>n</IT>H<SB>2</SB>O was also performed for 65 h, and the total amount of H<SB>2</SB> and O<SB>2</SB> evolved during these runs reached 23.2 and 12.1 mol (mol cat.)<SP>−1</SP>, respectively (result not shown).</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs21" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Rb<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB>·<IT>n</IT>H<SB>2</SB>O material produced H<SB>2</SB> and O<SB>2</SB> simultaneously, though the rate of O<SB>2</SB> evolution was less than the stoichiometric amount.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs22" novelty="None" advantage="None">Li<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB> showed very low activity for H<SB>2</SB> formation as compared to the other layered tantalates, and O<SB>2</SB> evolution was not observed with this material.</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs23" novelty="None" advantage="None">Table 1 summarizes the rate of gas evolution over various Ta-based catalysts.</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs24" novelty="None" advantage="None">Using H<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB>·<IT>n</IT>H<SB>2</SB>O as a photocatalyst, the rates of H<SB>2</SB> and O<SB>2</SB> formation were 385 and 179 μmol h<SP>−1</SP>, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rates of H<SB>2</SB> and O<SB>2</SB> formation with K<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB>·<IT>n</IT>H<SB>2</SB>O were very close to those of H<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB>·<IT>n</IT>H<SB>2</SB>O. It should be noted that the present system is the first example of active Ta-based photocatalysts with hydrous layered structure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rate of H<SB>2</SB> evolution over A<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB>(·<IT>n</IT>H<SB>2</SB>O) was strongly dependent on alkali cation and decreased in the sequence of H ≈ K &gt; Rb ≫ Li.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj6" novelty="New" advantage="None">We also studied the reaction over the non-hydrous perovskite tantalate, KTaO<SB>3</SB>, which was reported to catalyse this reaction.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">This material showed moderate activity for H<SB>2</SB> evolution, though the rate of H<SB>2</SB> evolution was lower than those of A<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB>·<IT>n</IT>H<SB>2</SB>O (A = H, K, and Rb).</annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Together with the result that the anhydrous layered tantalate, Li<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB>, was less effective than hydrous layered tantalate, A<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB>·<IT>n</IT>H<SB>2</SB>O (A = H, K, and Rb), one can conclude that the presence of hydrated interlayer space is important for improving the photocatalytic activity of Ta-based catalysts.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the photoluminescence study shown in Fig. 4, it was shown that the hydrated layered tantalates, A<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB>·<IT>n</IT>H<SB>2</SB>O (A = H and K), exhibited a considerably lower luminescence efficiency than anhydrous layered tantalates, A<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB> (A = Li and K), probably due to the electron and/or hole trapping by the interlayer water.</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">From this result, the positive effect of hydrated interlayer on the activity could be explained as follows.</annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The photogenerated electrons and holes can be effectively transferred to the interlayer water, and this results in the effective photocatalytic water splitting in the hydrated layered tantalates.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Effect of sacrificial agents</HEADER><P><s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">In overall water splitting, oxidation of water by holes is a slower process than reduction by electrons.</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to facilitate the oxidation, hole-scavengers are often introduced.</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp20" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this study, <IT>n</IT>-butylamine was used as a sacrificial agent.</annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs25" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 7 shows the time course of H<SB>2</SB> evolution from aqueous solution of <IT>n</IT>-butylamine (0.25 M) using 0.1 g of the catalyst.</annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs26" novelty="None" advantage="None">The initial rates of H<SB>2</SB> evolution are listed in Table 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs27" novelty="None" advantage="None">For H<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB>·<IT>n</IT>H<SB>2</SB>O the rate of H<SB>2</SB> formation (1490 μmol h<SP>−1</SP>) was much higher than that in the absence of <IT>n</IT>-butylamine (385 μmol h<SP>−1</SP>), though the amount of the catalyst used was lower in the former reaction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs28" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results in Table 2 show that the activity sequence for the <IT>n</IT>-butylamine/H<SB>2</SB>O system (H<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB>·<IT>n</IT>H<SB>2</SB>O ≫ K<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB>·<IT>n</IT>H<SB>2</SB>O &gt; KTaO<SB>3</SB>) is markedly different from that observed in the H<SB>2</SB> evolution from pure water (H<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB>·<IT>n</IT>H<SB>2</SB>O ≈ K<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB>·<IT>n</IT>H<SB>2</SB>O ≫ KTaO<SB>3</SB>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is well known that H<SP>+</SP>-exchanged layered oxides, such as HCa<SB>2</SB>Nb<SB>3</SB>O<SB>10</SB>, can intercalate organic bases such as amines into the interlayer space,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19 cit20">19,20</REF> while K<SP>+</SP>-exchanged one can not intercalate these molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs29" novelty="None" advantage="None">Table 2 includes the amount of <IT>n</IT>-butylamine adsorbed on the samples when the sample was stirred in the dark for 24 h under the same condition as the catalytic reaction shown in Fig. 7.</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs30" novelty="None" advantage="None">As expected, 0.94 mmol g<SP>−1</SP> of <IT>n</IT>-butylamine was adsorbed in H<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB>·<IT>n</IT>H<SB>2</SB>O probably due to the interlayer acidity of this material.</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs31" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast, only negligible amount of <IT>n</IT>-butylamine adsorption was observed on K<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB>·<IT>n</IT>H<SB>2</SB>O and KTaO<SB>3</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">This result can explain the activity sequence for the <IT>n</IT>-butylamine/H<SB>2</SB>O system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs32" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although the band structures of H<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB>·<IT>n</IT>H<SB>2</SB>O and K<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB>·<IT>n</IT>H<SB>2</SB>O are very close to each other (Fig. 3), one of the reactant molecules, <IT>n</IT>-butylamine, is hardly intercalated into the interlayer space of K<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB>·<IT>n</IT>H<SB>2</SB>O during the reaction, whereas <IT>n</IT>-butylamine is intercalated into the interlayer space of H<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB>·<IT>n</IT>H<SB>2</SB>O to act as the hole-scavenger over the reaction site at the TaO<SB>6</SB> perovskite sheet.</annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs33" novelty="None" advantage="None">As for the decomposition of pure water, these two catalysts show similar reactivity, because the water intercalation occurs during the reaction in both catalysts.</annotationART></s> <s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">These results support the above proposal that the photocatalytic reaction proceeds at interlayers of the hydrated layered tantalates.</annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of hydrous tantalates, electron–hole pairs may be easily migrated to the interlayer surface consisting of TaO<SB>6</SB> before their recombination, and thus intercalated H<SB>2</SB>O molecules can be effectively decomposed.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Conclusion</HEADER><P><s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have developed novel photocatalysts A<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB>·<IT>n</IT>H<SB>2</SB>O (A = H, K and Rb) with hydrated layered perovskite structure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None">These catalysts showed higher activity than Li<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB> (anhydrous tantalate with similar layered structure) and the bulk type perovskite tantalate, KTaO<SB>3</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Overall water splitting was accomplished over A<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB>·<IT>n</IT>H<SB>2</SB>O (A = H and K) without any modification.</annotationART></s> <s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is the first successful example of highly active tantalates photocatalysts with hydrated interlayer space.</annotationART></s> <s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results from photoluminescence spectroscopy and H<SB>2</SB> evolution from aqueous <IT>n</IT>-butylamine solution support the hypothesis that the high activity of A<SB>2</SB>SrTa<SB>2</SB>O<SB>7</SB>·<IT>n</IT>H<SB>2</SB>O results from their hydrated layered structure where the photogenerated electrons and holes can be effectively transferred to the interlayer water.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
