<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b313220j" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Modeling protonated water networks in bacteriorhodopsin<XREF TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" /></annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">A model is constructed to investigate in atomistic detail the structure and dynamics of protonated water networks on the extracellular side of the transmembrane proton pump bacteriorhodopsin.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The protein is embedded in a solvated lipid bilayer membrane described by established force fields.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Most importantly, the protonated water network is treated in the framework of a mixed density functional electronic structure theory/molecular mechanics approach.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">This QM/MM Car–Parrinello molecular dynamics approach employed allows for stable dynamics on a picosecond time scale.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None">The structural building process, force field parameterizations and subsequent equilibration of the total system consisting of the protein, the lipid membrane and the hydration layer is described in detail followed by a QM/MM simulation of the protonated water network.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is found that hydrogen-bonded networks around both H<SB>3</SB>O<SP>+</SP> and H<SB>5</SB>O<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP> cores can be stabilized in the protein matrix, leading to so-called Eigen and solvated Zundel complexes, H<SB>3</SB>O<SP>+</SP>· (H<SB>2</SB>O)<SB>3</SB> and H<SB>5</SB>O<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP>·(H<SB>2</SB>O)<SB>4</SB>, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">It turns out that both complexes behave qualitatively similarly to the gas phase, implying that the H<SB>5</SB>O<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP> core displays an essentially symmetric hydrogen bond with the excess proton being equally shared between two water molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The dynamics of this hydrogen bond is found to be complex featuring slow large-amplitude motion of the central proton as well as complex dynamics of the protonated water cluster hydrogen bonds formed with the protein matrix.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">These findings are consistent with the proposal that an essential component of the so-called proton release group “XH” could consist of a protonated water network stabilized by polar aminoacids.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="1">Motivation: Vectorial proton transport through membranes</HEADER><P><s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Bacteriorhodopsin (BR) is a photoactive transmembrane protein residing in the purple membrane of the extreme halophile <IT>Halobacterium salinarium</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Being a light-driven proton pump, BR establishes actively vectorial proton transport from the cytoplasmatic medium to the extracellular side.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The protein consists of seven α-helices, which contain the co-factor retinal acting as the chromophore during the photo-excitation process.</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Upon photon absorption, the all-<IT>trans</IT> 15-<IT>syn</IT> retinal, which is covalently bound to the Lys216 residue through a protonated Schiff base linkage, undergoes an ultrafast isomerization into a 13-<IT>cis</IT> 15-<IT>anti</IT> conformation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">This photo-induced conformational change in the chromophore triggers a cascade of conformational changes in the protein, the so-called BR photocycle, during which a proton is translocated vectorially from cytoplasm to the extracellular side.</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The photocycle consists of various major intermediates, labeled K, L, M, N, and O, which are characterized by their absorption maxima and can be probed individually by a variety of experimental techniques.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">For recent articles that comprehensively summarize the tremendous progress made by experiments on understanding the delicate structure/function relationship evident in BR see <IT>e.g</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2 cit3 cit4 cit5 cit6">refs. 1–6</REF>. and references therein; a very concise exposition of the essentials is given in .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">ref. 7</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although the molecular structure of BR is in parts known even on a time-resolved level in terms of the above-mentioned intermediates, the detailed microscopic nature of the proton translocation process still remains unclear.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, recent experiments and computer simulation studies suggest that BR uses quasi one-dimensional hydrogen-bonded water chains, so-called <IT>water wires</IT>, during the proton relay process, as suggested many years ago for similar situations based on theoretical considerations.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit9">8,9</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">There is also now clear evidence, <IT>e.g.</IT> from high resolution structures of various intermediates, that water molecules are <IT>actively</IT> involved in the proton translocation process in BR as opposed to just being “solvent”.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">A great deal of further insight could be obtained from time-resolved Fourier-transform infrared spectroscopy (FTIR) which allows for the experimental monitoring of the formation of various protonated species throughout the photocycle.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Despite these advances in our understanding mainly driven by experiment, the detailed role and degree of involvement of these water molecules has still not been resolved.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot3" novelty="None" advantage="None">These are exactly the kind of problems where modern <IT>ab initio</IT> molecular dynamics (MD) simulation techniques can step into place in order to gain further insight into the <IT>microscopic details</IT> underlying the proton translocation process in BR.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot4" novelty="None" advantage="None">For a realistic modeling of the overall proton translocation, which very likely has to proceed along a multitude of consecutive hydrogen-bond (H-bond) formation, breaking, and proton transfer steps, an accurate description of the underlying <IT>reactive</IT> potential energy surface has to be employed <IT>and</IT> accompanied by a dynamical treatment of the atomic movements.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">These two prerequisites can be achieved by treating the electronic degrees of freedom explicitly relying on electronic structure calculations, while evolving concurrently the nuclear degrees of freedom using forces obtained “on the fly”.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">Such <IT>ab initio</IT>, and in particular Car–Parrinello molecular dynamics approaches<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF> have proven to be a key tool in studying a large number of chemical reactions ranging from proton transfer in liquid water, systems under extreme conditions, or reactions at surfaces.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="No">Unfortunately, the size of the systems amenable to this elegant approach is limited by the currently available computer resources and will not exceed 10<SP>3</SP> atoms in the near future when it comes to molecular dynamics simulations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="New" advantage="None">Therefore, in order to be able to study such complex biomolecular systems on a microscopic level a so-called quantum-mechanical/molecular-mechanical (QM/MM) approximation has to be employed; note that the system introduced below, <IT>i.e.</IT> one BR molecule in a double-layer lipid membrane which is solvated by explicit water, includes close to 30 000 atoms in total.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">Within the QM/MM framework, the total system is partitioned into a fairly small subsystem, the chemical active region, being treated in a complete electronic structure calculation approach, and the “rest”, which is described by established empirical force fields.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">This partitioning scheme has the advantage that the computational effort is concentrated on the part of the system where it is mandatory to perform an electronic structure calculation, whereas the effects of the surrounding classical MM part is taken into account by more approximate means.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">Due to the saving in computational time the QM/MM approach opens the doorway to study interesting reactive chemical processes in extended biorelevant systems.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the long run our work aims at helping to elucidate the various stages of the proton transfer processes that occur during the BR photocycle <IT>after</IT> retinal isomerization.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">To this end, a recently developed QM/MM methodology<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF> based on a Car–Parrinello type approach<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10 cit11">10,11</REF> for the QM part in the framework of density functional theory (DFT) coupled to a MM part treated within the Gromos force field and software<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13 cit14 cit15">13–15</REF> is used; see <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">ref. 16</REF> for an overview of this novel methodology including several ongoing applications.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The first goal certainly is to build a detailed microscopic all-MM model that resembles the situation found for BR in the experiments as closely as possible, see Fig. 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="New" advantage="None">This implies that a BR monomer<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF> has to be embedded in a membrane, which itself needs to be hydrated by water.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Secondly, the methodology should provide a potential for the proton transfer processes taking place in the QM part with sufficient accuracy and reliability.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Finally, the employed computational framework should result in stable classical dynamics for <IT>all</IT> nuclei in order to be able to extract meaningful dynamical information, in particular for the QM subsystem.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="New" advantage="None">This paper reports our initial results on the structural model building of the total system, the partial force field parametrization done, the dynamical relaxation of the total QM/MM system, and structural as well as dynamical data concerning the embedded protonated water network in two different protonation states.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj5" novelty="New" advantage="None">Hereby we focus on the so-called Eigen and (solvated) Zundel complexes, protonated water clusters based on four and two (six) water molecules, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">They are located in a hydrophilic pocket on the extracellular side of BR, see Fig. 2, which is known to contain about three to four crystallographically resolved water molecules in the proximity of residues Glu194 and Glu204, see <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18 cit19">ref. 18 and 19</REF>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">In particular, close to the L → M transition during the photocycle a proton is released from the so-called “proton release group” (PRG or “XH”) to the extracellular surface of the membrane.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Most interestingly, FTIR experiments<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF> provide evidence that the PRG is unlikely to be Glu204 as suggested earlier, rather IR continuum absorbance changes indicate intramolecular proton transfer to the extracellular side <IT>via</IT> a H-bonded network, and that this network is stabilized by Glu204 and Arg82.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, theoretical studies<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF> of p<IT>K</IT><SB>a</SB> values suggest that the proton is stored in terms of a protonated water cluster, in particular H<SB>5</SB>O<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP>, rather than at the close by glutamic acid residues Glu194 and Glu204.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, it is plausible that this H-bonded water network in the hydrophilic pocket “stores” the proton and as such might constitute the PRG, possibly together with not yet identified neighboring groups.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj6" novelty="New" advantage="None">We report herein results from fully atomistic QM/MM molecular dynamics simulations concerning both the structure <IT>and dynamics</IT> of different protonated water clusters in this pocket of the BR transmembrane proton pump.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2">Building, relaxing and simulating the structural model</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.1">Starting structures</HEADER><P><s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj7" novelty="New" advantage="None">As described in Section 1 we are interested in the proton release after the photo-induced isomerization as is happening close to the L → M stage of the photocycle.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">To this end we have assembled a model starting from a monomeric protein unit<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF> from the crystal structure reported in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">ref. 23</REF> as obtained from the Brookhaven Protein Data Bank entry 1E0P (chain B therein).</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The partially resolved residues (Met163, Arg227, Glu232) were constructed by finding approximate starting locations for the missing atoms based upon known bond lengths and angles for those amino acids.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The missing residues (#1–4 and #233–248), not present in the crystal structure due to the strong disorder in the C and N termini, were neglected with the exception of residues #2–4 which were approximated from the PDB data bank entry 1QM8 representing the structure of wild type BR in the ground state at 100 K. As this structure only contains four water oxygen atom positions with three of them being on the extracellular part of BR, the coordinates of 21 already known internal water molecules have been taken from the wild type ground state reported in crystal structure 1E0P (chain A).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to mimic the cell wall in which the BR is embedded we have chosen to employ a POPC membrane (1-palmitoyl-2-oleoyl-<IT>sn</IT>-glycero-3-phosphatidylcholine).</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">To construct the lipid bilayer we employed a relaxed starting structure as reported in the literature.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24 cit25">24,25</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">This structure was modified to yield a cubic supercell containing 125 POPC molecules in total with a central cavity large enough to accommodate the BR protein assembled as described above.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The entire lipid bilayer including the BR pump was then solvated by 6504 randomly oriented water molecules, represented in terms of three “explicit atoms”, to provide the initial starting configuration for classical molecular dynamics simulations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The position of the proton within the protein was chosen to be in the hydrophilic pocket near Glu204 following the arguments outlined in Section 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod12" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to allow for long classical relaxation and equilibration runs before switching to the QM/MM interface, where the timescale is severely limited by the Car–Parrinello QM component, the crystallographic water molecules Wat403 and Wat404 were replaced by a H<SB>2</SB>O<SB>5</SB><SP>+</SP> model complex as suggested earlier<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.2">Force field parameters</HEADER><P><s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The retinal chromophore is covalently bound to the Lys216 residue <IT>via</IT> a N = C bond resulting from the formation (and subsequent deprotonation) of a Schiff base between C–OH of retinal and the –NH<SB>2</SB> group of Lysine.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the part of the photocycle of current interest the retinal nitrogen atom of the Schiff base is not protonated as it is in the ground state of BR.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod13" novelty="None" advantage="None">This necessitated the parameterization of all-atom Charmm<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26 cit27">26,27</REF> as well as Gromos<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF> force fields, to be used for the classical simulations as outlined in Section 2.3, in order to represent a <IT>deprotonated</IT> “Lysine plus retinal” combined residue which we denote here by Lyr, see <IT>e.g</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28">ref. 28</REF>. for a parameterization of the usually needed <IT>protonated</IT> Schiff base.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod14" novelty="None" advantage="None">For both the Charmm and Gromos force fields the required charges for conjugated C and N atoms and the N = C stretching force constant were obtained from isolated system DFT electronic structure calculations employing the BLYP gradient corrected density functional<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29 cit30">29,30</REF> with the standard 6-31G** basis set using the Gaussian98<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit31">31</REF> quantum chemistry package.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The structure of the gas phase lysine/retinal adduct “Lyr” was hereby fully relaxed and the N = C force constant was taken from the diagonal element of the force constant matrix as projected onto this local stretching mode.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Atomic charges were obtained by performing an Natural Atomic Orbital (NAO) analysis.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit32">32</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The NAO approach gives atomic charges that are known to exibit only a weak basis set dependency, unlike the more ubiquitously employed Mulliken scheme, and has the useful feature that for a given charge group as assigned in either of the two force fields one obtains the same net charge.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that different, though probably very similiar, values for the partial atomic charges could have been obtained from other well-established charge fitting approaches, like <IT>e.g.</IT> ESP fitting<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit33">33</REF> or Bader analysis.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit34">34</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod17" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to bring the computed NAO charges in accord with the existing fragments of the Charmm force field they have been scaled by a common factor of 0.7, see Table 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod18" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the Gromos force field all other parameters required to construct the Lyr fragment were taken from the existing parameters for the all-<IT>trans</IT> retinal.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod19" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of the Charmm force field torsional motion about the conjugated C = C and C = N bonds also required parameterization.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The barrier heights required in the Charmm force field were approximated from the force constant obtained as a diagonal element from the force constant matrix for a given torsional mode assuming a perfect cosinusoidal torsional potential as required for the Charmm force field.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26 cit27">26,27</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod20" novelty="None" advantage="None">The derived force field parameters are listed in Table 2 where labels follow the nomenclature outlined in Fig. 3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod21" novelty="None" advantage="None">Non-bonded Lennard-Jones (LJ) parameters for conjugated C atoms of retinal in Charmm were taken from unsaturated C atoms such as found in benzene or ethylene.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both force fields provided reasonable optimized equilibrium structures, with average absolute deviations in the conjugated C = N and C = C bond lengths of about 0.01–0.03 Å in comparison to the DFT reference data and <IT>ca.</IT> 0.03–0.04 Å with respect to the experimental starting structure, see Table 3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">As a more stringent test of the Charmm force field the neutral Lyr molecule was run as an isolated molecule for 1 ns by molecular dynamics in the gas phase.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">During this time no <IT>cis</IT>/<IT>trans</IT> isomerization about the π-conjugated retinal backbone was observed indicating that the derived force field provides a stable local minimum of the deprotonated 13-<IT>cis</IT> 15-<IT>anti</IT> retinal.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod22" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the classical relaxation and equilibration runs the H<SB>5</SB>O<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP> Zundel cation was defined as a new “residue” (keeping its optimized structure frozen) in the Charmm and Gromos force fields; note that this is only needed for relaxation purposes and that in the QM/MM simulations this species and larger protonated water clusters are treated quantum-mechanically within DFT.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod22" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, the derived force field need only <IT>qualitatively</IT> reflect the proposed species.</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod23" novelty="None" advantage="None">As such LJ parameters were taken to correspond with the appropriate TIP3P water model in Charmm or the SPC water as used in the Gromos force field.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod24" novelty="None" advantage="None">The atomic charges on the Zundel ion (O: −0.82, H<SB>terminal</SB>: 0.53, and H<SB>bridge</SB>: 0.52) and the O–H<SB>bridge</SB> stretching and O–H<SB>bridge</SB>–O bending force constants (147 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> Å<SP>−2</SP> and 32 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> rad<SP>−2</SP>, respectively), have been obtained in the same fashion as for the retinal/lysine complex Lyr from DFT calculations of isolated H<SB>5</SB>O<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod25" novelty="None" advantage="None">The position of this ion within the protein was chosen to coincide with crystallographic waters Wat403 and Wat404 which were replaced with the parameterized Zundel complex H<SB>5</SB>O<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod26" novelty="None" advantage="None">The starting configuration was first relaxed <IT>via</IT> local geometry optimization with all the protein atoms frozen after which the Zundel oxygen atoms were kept fixed in space for the remainder of all the classical simulations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod27" novelty="None" advantage="None">Simulation of the POPC lipids within the Gromos force field was made possible by the availability of the set of LJ parameters within the Gromacs simulation package<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit35 cit36">35,36</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.3">Classical relaxation and equilibration</HEADER><P><s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj8" novelty="New" advantage="None">The equilibration of a complex and inhomogeneous system containing about 30 000 atoms needs to be done in several states which we outline in the following protocol.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Our classical MD run, which targets to generate starting phase space points for the subsequent QM/MM studies, is comprised of two distinct phases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Phase A involves the use of the Charmm all-atom force field<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27">27</REF> and the NAMD simulation package<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit37 cit38">37,38</REF> in order to prepare efficiently a stable structural model at ambient conditions, including the optimization of the lattice constant of the cubic supercell.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Phase B involves the use of the Gromos force field and software<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13 cit14 cit15">13–15</REF> for preparing equilibrated starting configurations being used in the QM/MM production runs.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod28" novelty="None" advantage="None">In phase A (Charmm force field and NAMD code), the following steps have been performed:</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod29" novelty="None" advantage="None">(1) The BR structure (as assembled above) was first relaxed <IT>via</IT> geometry optimization in order to relax the added fragments, while keeping the crystallographically known heavy atoms including the internal water molecules inside the pump fixed.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod30" novelty="None" advantage="None">(2) Next, this partially relaxed BR complex was placed into the membrane cavity (as prepared above) and the resulting BR/membrane assembly was relaxed further by geometry optimization keeping the protein backbone, the internal water molecules, and the phospholipid headgroup atoms fixed.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod31" novelty="None" advantage="None">(3) This relaxed BR/membrane complex was than solvated by 6504 TIP3P water molecules and only these water molecules were allowed to relax (keeping the BR/membrane subsystem fixed including the Zundel complex and the internal water), followed by a 50 ps <IT>NVT</IT> MD simulation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod32" novelty="None" advantage="None">The MD was accomplished with a time step of 0.15 fs, Berendsen temperature thermostatting at a temperature of 300 K, and the Shake algorithm for O–H bonds of water.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod33" novelty="None" advantage="None">(4) Then, the protein side chains, lipid aliphatic tails, internal waters, H-atoms of the Zundel complex, and finally the phospholipid head groups were subsequently released in a stepwise fashion over a period of about 300 ps of simulation time and the system was allowed to equilibrate at constant volume for a further 200 ps, while preserving the other constraints.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod34" novelty="None" advantage="None">(5) After a reasonably equilibrated low energy state had been reached within these constant volume simulations, a MD run within the <IT>NpT</IT> ensemble employing a variable cubic cell and the Berendsen pressure coupling scheme was performed in order to optimize the lattice constant of the supercell.</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod35" novelty="None" advantage="None">The average pressure of the system was slowly equilibrated at 1 bar over a period of 500 ps.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod36" novelty="None" advantage="None">The resulting structure of phase A is the initial configuration for phase B, making use of the Gromos force field and program as required for the QM/MM interface, which proceeded as in the final two steps as in phase A; these simulations were run with a conservative time step of 0.1 fs, the Shake algorithm for all “heavy atom to H-bonds”, and Berendsen thermostats at 300 K and barostats at 300 K and 1 bar.</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod37" novelty="None" advantage="None">The system was first equilibrated with constant volume over a period of 100 ps followed by a further 100 ps constant pressure simulation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod38" novelty="None" advantage="None">Finally the structure was further equilibrated in the <IT>NVT</IT> ensemble using the optimized fixed cubic cell with axis length of 72.35 Å (corresponding to the average lattice constant at <IT>p</IT> ≈ 1 bar) for an additional 1 ns prior to collecting equilibrium all-MM classical data for about 3 ns.</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod38" novelty="None" advantage="None">This trajectory is needed for an analysis of the long-term stability of the classical biomatrix around the QM part as reported in Section 3.2.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod39" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this phase B, in addition to fixing the BR protein backbone atoms and the Zundel ion oxygen atoms (formerly being water Wat403 and Wat404) the oxygen atom of the crystallographically reported<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF> water molecule Wat405, being also located in the hydrophilic pocket close to Glu204, was fixed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod40" novelty="None" advantage="None">This water molecule remained in close proximity with the Zundel ion throughout phase A and was therefore fixed in phase B in order to provide up to three water molecules that will allow the formation of a rather extended protonated water network once the QM/MM interface is switched on.</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">As an aside it is noted that yet another internal water molecule (denoted<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF>) also migrated into this pocket during phase B of our equilibration and continued to reside there throughout the run.</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is in agreement with the propositions advanced in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21 cit22 cit39">ref. 21, 22 and 39</REF> that the cavity should contain about three to four water molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is most interesting to note that upon switching to the quantum treatment of these water molecules including the proton, this network spontaneously rearranged and formed an Eigen cation H<SB>3</SB>O<SP>+</SP>·(H<SB>2</SB>O)<SB>3</SB> with several H-bonds to close by residues from the pocket, see Section 3.3 for a detailed analysis.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.4">QM/MM interfacing</HEADER><P><s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj9" novelty="New" advantage="None">The equilibrated final structural model from above was used as input for the QM/MM simulations runs relying on the recently introduced approach by Laio, VandeVondele, and Röthlisberger.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj9" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">This approach is the basis for an efficient and dynamically stable way of performing mixed QM/MM Car–Parrinello molecular dynamics in biochemical systems.</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In a nutshell, it is based on a DFT description of the electronic structure of the QM subsystem in terms of a plane wave/pseudopotential approach using the well-established CPMD code.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit40 cit11">40,11</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The QM/MM interface<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF> combines this code to the Gromos software<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14 cit15">14,15</REF> that represents the MM part in terms of the Gromos force field.</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The interface approach uses an efficient Hamiltonian electrostatic coupling scheme to include the electrostatic effects due to the classical environment.</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="Old" advantage="None">This is accomplished by a hierarchical multipole method which is used to describe the interaction of the QM and MM regions (in addition to keeping the standard van der Waals interaction terms between the QM and MM atoms or sites as parameterized in the MM force field used).</annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The QM/MM electrostatic energy term is hereby decomposed into a short-range part in which the interactions are accurately described by directly evaluating the Coulombic terms resulting from the electronic charge distribution located on <IT>all</IT> real space grid points with <IT>all</IT> MM atoms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The long-range electrostatic part (for distance larger then about 10 Å in the current simulation) is treated by a multipole expansion of the QM electronic charge distribution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Furthermore, in order to prevent the so-called electron spill-out problem, which is especially severe if very flexible basis sets such as plane waves are used, the bare Coulomb potential is renormalized in terms of a Padé representation such that a finite value is approached as <IT>r</IT> → 0.</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The proper 1/<IT>r</IT> behavior is recovered far away from the nuclei, <IT>rr</IT><SB>c</SB>, where <IT>r</IT><SB>c</SB> is close to the covalent radius of the corresponding atom.</annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">This modification prevents that the MM atoms, which are lacking the Pauli repulsion from the missing electron cloud, act as traps for electron density leading to an artificial over-polarization and electron flow of the electron density.</annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">For further details we refer to the original literature.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod41" novelty="None" advantage="None">In particular, the QM subsystem is treated here using Troullier–Martins pseudopotentials<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit41">41</REF> and the wave function is expanded in a plane wave basis set with 70 Ry cutoff inside a cubic box with length 30 au subject to non-periodic boundary conditions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod42" novelty="None" advantage="None">The BLYP density functional,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29 cit30">29,30</REF> which has proven to give reliable structure, dynamics and energetics for a wide range H-bonded system, is employed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod43" novelty="None" advantage="None">A conservative time step of 0.05 fs was chosen and a fictitious electron mass of 500 au was employed in all QM/MM simulations, whereas a time step of 0.10 fs and the same electron mass was found to guarantee stable numerical integration of the Car–Parrinello equations of motion for pure QM trajectories; note that the proper hydrogen mass is used instead of substituting by deuterium as often done.</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod44" novelty="None" advantage="None">All dynamical DFT simulations were performed in the <IT>NVT</IT> ensemble employing Nosé–Hoover chain thermostats<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF> with a target temperature of 300 K. Despite the fact that these simulations were started using the carefully pre-equilibrated configurations from above, the QM subsystem still needed to be relaxed initially in order to adjust as smoothly as possible to switching from the all-MM to the QM/MM interface treatment.</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The cubic box containing all 28 365 (QM and MM) atoms (not counting the MM hydrogens treated in the united-atom approximation) was 72.35 Å, see Fig. 1, and trajectories in the typical time-regime accessible to Car–Parrinello dynamics,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF><IT>i.e.</IT> ∼10 ps, were generated within the QM/MM framework.</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod45" novelty="None" advantage="None">After switching from all-MM to QM/MM simulations no constraints were applied in the simulation of the Eigen complex, whereas some distance constraints had to be imposed in order to stabilize the solvated Zundel complex, see Section 3.3 for more details.</annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod46" novelty="None" advantage="None">Finally, all-QM reference calculations of protonated water clusters in the gas phase at 300 K were performed to generate consistent data sets for the sake of comparison.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3">Simulation of protonated water networks in BR</HEADER><P><s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Protonated water clusters H<SP>+</SP>·(H<SB>2</SB>O)<SB><IT>n</IT></SB> are quite stable molecular ions in the gas phase<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit42">42</REF> In particular, it is known that the so-called “Zundel” and “Eigen complexes”, obtained by protonating clusters consisting of two and four water molecules, respectively, are two archetypal “solvating schemes”.</annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac20" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the Zundel complex, H<SB>5</SB>O<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP>, the most probable position of the proton is midway between the two solvating water molecules, schematically denoted as [H<SB>2</SB>O⋯H⋯OH<SB>2</SB>]<SP>+</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac21" novelty="None" advantage="None">This situation is very different for the Eigen complex, where the proton and one water molecule form a hydronium core H<SB>3</SB>O<SP>+</SP>, which itself is microsolvated by the three more molecules, <IT>i.e.</IT> H<SB>3</SB>O<SP>+</SP>·(H<SB>2</SB>O)<SB>3</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac22" novelty="None" advantage="None">These two basic structures can be thought of as building blocks of ever larger clusters.</annotationART></s> <s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac23" novelty="None" advantage="None">Of particular importance in the following discussion is what we call the “solvated Zundel complex” obtained by saturating the two terminal water molecules with four additional H-bonds leading to H<SB>5</SB>O<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP>·(H<SB>2</SB>O)<SB>4</SB>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod47" novelty="None" advantage="None">Standard structural parameters to investigate H-bonds in general, and in particular in protonated complexes, are the so-called asymmetric stretch coordinate <IT>δ</IT> = <IT>R</IT><SB>OH</SB>–<IT>R</IT><SB>HO</SB>, defined in terms of the covalent O–H and H–bonding H⋯O distances of the shared proton with respect to the acceptor and donor heavy atoms, in conjunction with the donor–acceptor distance <IT>R</IT><SB>OO</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod47" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, distribution functions in terms of both the <IT>δ</IT> and <IT>R</IT><SB>OO</SB> coordinates, such as the one shown in Fig. 4, are utmost useful in characterizing H-bonds qualitatively (and of course quantitatively).</annotationART></s> <s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod48" novelty="None" advantage="None">Symmetrized H-bonds, where the proton sits right in between donor and acceptor such as in idealized Zundel ions, are characterized by |<IT>δ</IT>| ≈ 0 Å.</annotationART></s> <s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the coordinates <IT>δ</IT> and <IT>R</IT><SB>OO</SB> do not vary independently in real H-bonds, which can be gleaned from the anisotropic shape distributions such as those in Fig. 4.</annotationART></s> <s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod49" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the other hand strongly asymmetric H-bonds like those occurring in Eigen-type complexes have |<IT>δ</IT>| ≫ 0 Å; note that the sign of <IT>δ</IT> depends on the labeling convention of donor <IT>vs.</IT> acceptor.</annotationART></s> <s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod50" novelty="None" advantage="None">In conclusion, <IT>δ</IT> can also be considered a proton <IT>transfer</IT> coordinate that measures, as a function of time, as protons migrate along H-bonds; note that a more complex order parameter is needed in order to describe proton <IT>diffusion</IT> beyond a single H-bond.</annotationART></s></P><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.1">Evaluating the QM/MM interfacing: Water dimer and Eigen complex</HEADER><P><s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj10" novelty="New" advantage="None">As a first assessment of the quality of the interfacing between the QM and MM parts as established <IT>via</IT> H-bonds, the dipole moment of a QM water molecule as solvated by one MM (SPC) water molecule was compared to the proper all-QM treatment of the water dimer in the gas phase at 100 K; here the QM molecule is the donor water, <IT>i.e.</IT> schematically [HOH]<SB>QM</SB>⋯[OH<SB>2</SB>]<SB>MM</SB> where ⋯ denotes the H-bond.</annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod51" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the all-QM case, the dipole moments of both water molecules can be obtained separately <IT>via</IT> the exact Wannier representation of the total dipole moment of the system, which can be decomposed approximately into linearly additive subsystem contributions stemming from the two molecular fragments, see <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit43 cit44">ref. 43 and 44</REF> for background information.</annotationART></s> <s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod52" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the QM/MM case the dipole moment of the donor, <IT>i.e.</IT> the QM fragment, is obtained from the total dipole moment inside the QM box, whereas the one of the MM acceptor molecule is computed using the fixed SPC charges only.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">As seen from Fig. 5(a), the significant polarization of the donor water molecule upon H-bonding, leading to a significant increase of its dipole moment in comparison to the gas phase value of an isolated QM water monomer, is nicely captured by the interface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Actually, using SPC water as acceptor (instead of the “QM acceptor” as in the all-QM reference simulation) seems to even slightly overpolarize the QM subsystem.</annotationART></s> <s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">This would be consistent with the fact that SPC water is parameterized to represent bulk liquid water at ambient conditions, where the average dipole moment of the water molecules is significantly increased from a gas phase value, ≈1.85 D, to about 3 D due to H-bonding, see .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit44">ref. 44</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj11" novelty="New" advantage="None">This consequence of parameterizing a non-polarizable water model to represent bulk water becomes evident by comparing the much larger average MM water monomer dipole moment in panel (b) to the QM monomer distribution in (a).</annotationART></s> <s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, the MM acceptor in the QM/MM dimer acquires a much larger dipole moment as appropriate according to the reference data from the acceptor fragment in the all-QM treatment.</annotationART></s> <s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This delicate point of coupling non-polarizable <IT>bulk</IT> water MM models <IT>via</IT> H-bonds to QM subsystems needs further study.</annotationART></s> <s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">We mention in passing that the coupling of the protonated water network to the BR backbone, see Section 3.4, is far more distant from the relevant H-bond(s) than in this test case where the “crucial” H-bond is cut by the interface.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj12" novelty="New" advantage="None">As a further check on the quality of the interface the microsolvated H<SB>3</SB>O<SP>+</SP> ion, <IT>i.e.</IT> H<SB>3</SB>O<SP>+</SP>· (H<SB>2</SB>O)<SB>3</SB>, was treated in an all-QM approach and using a QM/MM approximation where the QM subsystem was the H<SB>3</SB>O<SP>+</SP> core only.</annotationART></s> <s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The resulting two-dimensional H-bond distribution functions, see Fig. 6, look qualitatively similar, in particular the delicate correlation that shorter H-bonds are also more symmetric, <IT>i.e.</IT> the smaller <IT>R</IT><SB>OO</SB> the smaller |<IT>δ</IT>|, is nicely captured.</annotationART></s> <s sid="143"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The near to quantitative agreement is brought out more clearly in the corresponding one-dimensional representations along <IT>δ</IT> and <IT>R</IT><SB>OO</SB> as plotted in Fig. 7(a) and (b), respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="144"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Closer inspection shows that the coupling to SPC water leads to systematically shorter <IT>R</IT><SB>OO</SB> distances and thus to “stronger” H-bonds, consistent with the analysis of the dipole moment of the water dimer from above.</annotationART></s> <s sid="145"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Nevertheless, the “asymmetry” of the H-bonds as measured by <IT>δ</IT> is well represented in the QM/MM approximation to the all-QM simulation, see Fig. 7(a).</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.2">Evaluating the stability of the biomatrix</HEADER><P><s sid="146"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj13" novelty="New" advantage="None">After having assessed the quality of the QM/MM interface as such, the next checks concern the stability of the biomatrix that hosts the QM subsystem, see Fig. 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="147"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj13" novelty="New" advantage="None">A critical aspect of this concern is the integrity of the interface between the lipid membrane and the solvating water layer which must be stable to provide a proper environment for the BR monomer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="148"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj13" novelty="New" advantage="None">In order to assess this it is necessary to examine the structural stability of the system on time scales much larger then the “few picoseconds” typically accessible in <IT>ab initio</IT> simulations.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="149"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod53" novelty="None" advantage="None">To this end, we perform an analysis on an equilibrated 3 ns classical MM trajectory of the combined biomatrix consisting of the BR protein in a solvated POPC membrane; note that in this all-MM run the BR backbone was constrained as described in Section 2.3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="150"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The total mass density perpendicular to the membrane is decomposed in Fig. 8 into contributions coming from its major components.</annotationART></s> <s sid="151"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">This analysis finds a stable layering in terms of lipid tails providing a hydrophobic membrane interior of approximately 20 Å thickness and an external layer of lipid headgroups which form a well-defined interface with the solvating water phase.</annotationART></s> <s sid="152"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">From this graph one can see that the upper and lower portions of the (periodic) simulation cell are occupied solely by water in a layer which is approximately 6 Å thick with an additional 10 Å which is composed of over 95% water by weight.</annotationART></s> <s sid="153"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Most importantly, the density ≈0.97–0.98 kg/l that is observed in the region comprised entirely of water comes fairly close to the density of 0.988 kg l<SP>−1</SP> reported in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit45">ref. 45</REF> (Table 2) for <IT>bulk</IT> SPC water at 300 K and 1 bar.</annotationART></s> <s sid="154"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Finally, Fig. 8 also shows that the BR protein is well separated from its periodic image by over 14 Å, which corresponds to approximately four water solvation layers.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="155"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj14" novelty="New" advantage="None">Considering the lipid membrane in atomic level detail we first examine the lipid/water interface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="156"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">There are on average about 77 water molecules within the first solvation shell (within a distance cutoff of 4.5 Å) of the 20 atoms representing the lipid head group with six to seven of these within the typical 2.7 Å H-bonding distance of the carbonyl and phosphate oxygens.</annotationART></s> <s sid="157"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is in contrast to the 32 atoms representing the hydrophobic lipid chains where there is less than 12 water molecules within the first solvation shell, the majority of which are associated with the C atoms close to the head groups.</annotationART></s> <s sid="158"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, the head groups of the lipids are well solvated whereas those of the side chains see very little of the solvent.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="159"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj15" novelty="New" advantage="None">The internal structure of the membrane can be analyzed in terms of orientational order parameters that describe the degree of order of the lipid tails along the chains.</annotationART></s> <s sid="160"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod54" novelty="None" advantage="None">In particular, the order parameter <IT>S</IT>CC<IT>k</IT> = 〈3 cos (<IT>θ</IT><SB><IT>k</IT></SB>) − 1〉/2 is evaluated where <IT>θ</IT><SB><IT>k</IT></SB> is the angle of the <IT>k</IT>th carbon–carbon bond with respect to the normal of the lipid membrane surface, which we denote as the absolute <IT>z</IT>-axis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="161"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod55" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is done for 14 carbon–carbon bonds starting from the head group down to the –CH<SB>3</SB> terminus of the hydrophobic lipid chain, see Fig. 9(a).</annotationART></s> <s sid="162"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod56" novelty="None" advantage="None">This analysis is done separately for the two chains in each POPC molecule, one of them, chain A, consisting of only C–C single bonds, whereas chain B contains one CC double bond at position <IT>k</IT> = 9.</annotationART></s> <s sid="163"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both chains display their most pronounced order close to the head group, assuming a standard value of around <IT>S</IT><SP>CC</SP> ≈ 0.3; note that both layers contributing to the membrane were averaged together taking into account the underlying symmetry.</annotationART></s> <s sid="164"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">As expected, the degree of ordering decays strongly towards the center of the lipid double layer for chain A and B. A major difference is that chain B does not decay smoothly, but shows a pronounced zig-zag anomaly centered around <IT>k</IT> = 9, <IT>i.e.</IT> the location of the CC unit in that chain.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="165"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod57" novelty="None" advantage="None">Inspection of the angular distribution functions <IT>p</IT>(cos (<IT>θ</IT><SB><IT>k</IT></SB>)) can be used to get a feel for the spread of the various bond angles along the chain.</annotationART></s> <s sid="166"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" advantage="None">These distributions are shown for <IT>k</IT> = 2 and 14 in Fig. 9(b) for chain B. In general, for the bonds close to the lipid headgroup, <IT>i.e.</IT> small <IT>k</IT>, the distribution <IT>p</IT>(cos (<IT>θ</IT><SB><IT>k</IT></SB>)) is unimodal with a broad but well defined peak.</annotationART></s> <s sid="167"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs19" novelty="None" advantage="None">This peak becomes broader as <IT>k</IT> increases, that is moving away from the headgroups into the hydrophobic lipid interior, and eventually smooths out with all angles having a sizeable probability in the limit of large <IT>k</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="168"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The presence of the CC bond in chain B causes this broadening effect to occur at smaller <IT>k</IT> than in the overall more ordered chain A, which is in qualitative accord with description of the double bond perturbing the local order of this chain.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="169"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Overall, it can be concluded that the POPC bilayer membrane (including the BR monomer) has a stable structure where the head groups are well solvated, the initial part of the lipid chains are orientationally ordered, and where the lipid tails created a hydrophobic interior that is well ordered.</annotationART></s> <s sid="170"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Most importantly, however, is that this structure shows no indication of degradation over the entire 3 ns of the all-MM run (after an additional 1 ns of initial equilibration).</annotationART></s> <s sid="171"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus we have confidence that the biomatrix as set-up and relaxed provides a decent representation of BR embedded in a solvated lipid bilayer, which is stable on time scales 2–3 orders of magnitude larger than the QM/MM simulations.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.3">Embedding Eigen and Zundel complexes in BR</HEADER><P><s sid="172"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">As outlined in the first section, the protonated water networks in BR are thought to be embedded <IT>via</IT> H-bonds to side groups of the protein.</annotationART></s> <s sid="173"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs20" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the present case, the three external water molecules of the Eigen complex H<SB>3</SB>O<SP>+</SP>·(H<SB>2</SB>O)<SB>3</SB> indeed connected <IT>via</IT> H-bonds to the groups Glu194, Glu204, Thr205, Tyr79 and Tyr57 of the BR backbone after switching from the all-MM run to the QM/MM simulation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="174"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs21" novelty="None" advantage="None">The time evolution of these contacts in terms of the H-bond length <IT>R</IT><SB>OO</SB> is plotted in Fig. 10.</annotationART></s> <s sid="175"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">These bond distances are found to fluctuate about meaningful average values without showing any tendency of systematic drifts or H-bond breaking, with the exception of the donor H-bonds of one of the terminal water molecule in the Eigen complex to an oxygen atom of the Glu194 residue.</annotationART></s> <s sid="176"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs22" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the latter case several attempts to break this H-bond take place up to about 9.2 ps, where a successful breaking event occurs leading to a new arrangement for about 0.65 ps.</annotationART></s> <s sid="177"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Closer analysis of the H-bond angles of the respective H-bonds, see Fig. 11 shows that a water molecule is found to rotate about its local <IT>C</IT><SB>2v</SB> axis, thereby trading in one H-bond for another one.</annotationART></s> <s sid="178"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is evident from the “flip” in both H-bond angles of a tagged water hydrogen atom to both Glu194 residue oxygen atoms (labeled O1 and O2 in Fig. 11).</annotationART></s> <s sid="179"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs23" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that after about 0.65 ps a recrossing event occurs during which the system falls back into its previous H-bonding pattern.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="180"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs24" novelty="None" advantage="None">Another interesting fluctuation can be seen in Fig. 12 where the H-bond dynamics of another terminal water molecule in the Eigen complex is shown.</annotationART></s> <s sid="181"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs24" novelty="None" advantage="None">This water molecule forms a donor H-bond with one of its hydrogen atoms to the Tyr57 residue, whereas the other hydrogen atom is bound to Tyr205 (see Fig. 10 for the O–O distances as a function of time in these H-bonds).</annotationART></s> <s sid="182"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs25" novelty="None" advantage="None">This three-fold coordinated water molecule (one strong acceptor bond to the core H<SB>3</SB>O<SP>+</SP> and two donor bonds to the protein residues) performs a rotation about the O–O axis of the acceptor H-bond to the core H<SB>3</SB>O<SP>+</SP> after about 9 ps.</annotationART></s> <s sid="183"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs26" novelty="None" advantage="None">This results in a concerted “flip” in all four H-bond angles describing the two donor H-bonds to Tyr57 and Tyr205.</annotationART></s> <s sid="184"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that the concerted H-bond cleavage event is triggered by large fluctuations evident in the OH<SP>(2)</SP>–O<SP>(Tyr205)</SP> H-bond angle, which also exhibits a recrossing event after about 0.4 ps.</annotationART></s> <s sid="185"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs27" novelty="None" advantage="None">Eventually, this process results in the transient rupture of both H-bonds and subsequent reformation in a different H-bond topology.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="186"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Overall, the observed H-bond dynamics of the protonated water network to the various protein residues follows a complex pattern with the H-bonds of the cluster itself being surprisingly stable considering the strong fluctuations occurring in the next solvation shell.</annotationART></s> <s sid="187"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, the Eigen H<SB>3</SB>O<SP>+</SP>·(H<SB>2</SB>O)<SB>3</SB> QM cluster embedded in the MM environment can be considered to be <IT>dynamically</IT> stable on the picosecond time scale accessible <IT>via</IT> Car–Parrinello molecular dynamics.</annotationART></s> <s sid="188"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Equally important, the protonated network is still free to perform non-trivial fluctuations that involve the QM to MM interface such as H-bond exchange flips.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="189"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj16" novelty="New" advantage="None">Concerning the solvated Zundel complex, H<SB>5</SB>O<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP>· (H<SB>2</SB>O)<SB>4</SB>, there is a crucial difference in the set-up as compared to the Eigen case.</annotationART></s> <s sid="190"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod58" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Zundel-like configuration was formed by taking the equilibrated Eigen-like complex, picking two water molecules from the hydration layer and moving them into positions in the QM pocket that allow for proper H-bonding to the core H<SB>5</SB>O<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="191"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod59" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that this procedure preserves the overall number of particle in our simulation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="192"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod60" novelty="None" advantage="None">This new configuration has then been equilibrated <IT>via</IT> geometry optimization followed by running short QM/MM trajectories in the <IT>NVT</IT> ensemble.</annotationART></s> <s sid="193"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs28" novelty="None" advantage="None">As opposed to the Eigen-like complex, which formed spontaneously during the QM/MM simulation, see Section 2.3, this approach did not result in a Zundel-like complex with |<IT>δ</IT>| being close to zero.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="194"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod61" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to nevertheless analyze Zundel-like H-bonding situations in BR, the coordination number of the core Zundel H<SB>5</SB>O<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP> was enforced to be four in the hope of stabilizing a symmetric H-bond with |<IT>δ</IT>| ≈ 0 Å.</annotationART></s> <s sid="195"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod62" novelty="None" advantage="None">This was achieved by introducing four distance constraints connecting each of the four donor hydrogen atoms of H<SB>5</SB>O<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP> to the acceptor oxygen atom of the respective solvent water molecule thus forming a solvated Zundel complex H<SB>5</SB>O<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP>·(H<SB>2</SB>O)<SB>4</SB>; here the equilibrium value of the corresponding gas phase cluster, 1.68 Å, was used.</annotationART></s> <s sid="196"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs29" novelty="None" advantage="None">This constrained protonated water network stabilized itself by forming H-bonds to the residues Arg82, Tyr79, Glu194, Glu204, and Tyr205 inside the hydrophilic pocket.</annotationART></s> <s sid="197"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs30" novelty="None" advantage="None">As will be shown by a detailed analysis in Section 3.4, the central H-bond in this solvated Zundel complex is close to symmetric.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="198"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">These findings suggest that the strong anisotropic and inhomogeneous nature of the protein matrix seems to lowers the probability of forming a Zundel-like complex, which is quite different to the situation found in the gas phase and in bulk liquid water.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit46 cit47">46,47</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="199"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac24" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that similar behavior was observed in studies of Eigen-like and Zundel-like complexes confined in hydrophobic channel environments.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit48">48</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="200"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Despite these suggestive findings, we stress here that no conclusions concerning the <IT>absolute</IT> stability of Zundel-type <IT>versus</IT> Eigen-type protonated water networks can be drawn based on this qualitative finding.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.4">Structure and dynamics of Eigen and Zundel complexes: BR <IT>versus</IT> gas phase</HEADER><P><s sid="201"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj17" novelty="New" advantage="None">After all these preliminary checks, the dynamical behavior of the Eigen and solvated Zundel complexes in BR as compared to the gas phase can be analyzed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="202"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs31" novelty="None" advantage="None">In Fig. 13 the time evolution of their <IT>δ</IT> coordinate for only a very short time interval of half a picosecond out of more than 10 ps equilibrated QM/MM trajectories is displayed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="203"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs32" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note again that the latter complex in BR is solvated by four additional water molecules saturating the H-bonds of the two terminal water molecules, <IT>i.e.</IT> H<SB>5</SB>O<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP>·(H<SB>2</SB>O)<SB>4</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="204"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">First, the general qualitative behavior seems quite similar in both the gas phase and in BR.</annotationART></s> <s sid="205"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">In particular, the Eigen complexes are strongly asymmetric, <IT>δ</IT> ≪ 0, and thus display well-defined H<SB>3</SB>O<SP>+</SP> cores, whereas the Zundel-type complexes have <IT>δ</IT> fluctuating close to zero.</annotationART></s> <s sid="206"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, it can already be gleaned that the H-bond in the solvated Zundel complex in BR is slightly asymmetric, although clearly not as pronounced as in the Eigen case, see below for more thorough evidence.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="207"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fluctuation pattern of the two complexes is fairly different since the Eigen complexes show high-frequency fluctuations clearly superimposed as a modulation on lower frequency oscillations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="208"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">This pattern is much more congested and thus complex in the Zundel-type cases in the sense that there appears to be no clear-cut separation of time scales, which might also give a hint that the H-bond is more fluxional in this case since the proton can be easily shifted between “donor” and “acceptor”.</annotationART></s> <s sid="209"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj18" novelty="New" advantage="None">It is revealing to look at the time evolution of the symmetry of the H-bond, <IT>i.e.</IT> |<IT>δ</IT>|, together with its instantaneous length <IT>R</IT><SB>OO</SB> as done in Fig. 14 for the Zundel complex in the gas phase.</annotationART></s> <s sid="210"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj18" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">In this way one can nicely see the <IT>dynamical</IT> interplay of a lengthening the H-bond by increasing <IT>R</IT><SB>OO</SB> with a more asymmetric proton location in view of the concurrently increasing |<IT>δ</IT>| value.</annotationART></s> <s sid="211"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs33" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, in particular the symmetric H-bond displays a complex dynamics where many modes are strongly coupled.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="212"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod63" novelty="None" advantage="None">A more quantitative analysis of the H-bonds is achieved by averaging over fluctuations and by considering two-dimensional probability distribution functions in terms of <IT>δ</IT> and <IT>R</IT><SB>OO</SB>, see Fig. 15 and 16.</annotationART></s> <s sid="213"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs34" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the Eigen complex the one H-bond out of the three that has the smallest <IT>R</IT><SB>OO</SB> distance is used for each configuration; this is the “most active H-bond” as introduced in .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit46">ref. 46</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="214"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">In case of the Eigen cation, it can be seen that on average a shortening of the H-bond clearly correlates with a more symmetric H-bond, <IT>i.e.</IT> smaller <IT>R</IT><SB>OO</SB> values are preferentially found in conjunction with smaller |<IT>δ</IT>| values.</annotationART></s> <s sid="215"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, the distribution in BR is astonishingly similar to that in the gas phase.</annotationART></s> <s sid="216"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" advantage="None">Concerning the slightly more localized character of the Eigen complex in BR it could be speculated that the strongly inhomogeneous electric field inside the protein favors localized charges—similar to what is known from the liquid phase.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit46 cit47">46,47</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="217"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None">The distribution function of the Zundel complex in the gas phase is nicely symmetric, see Fig. 16(a) whereas this is not the case in BR, see panel (b).</annotationART></s> <s sid="218"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs35" novelty="None" advantage="None">In both cases, for any given donor–acceptor distance <IT>R</IT><SB>OO</SB> the distribution function is much broader along the <IT>δ</IT> coordinate than the Eigen cation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="219"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None">This implies that the proton in the former complexes is clearly much more mobile than the latter, <IT>i.e.</IT> the proton transfer potential is expected to be fairly “flat”, which is still true for the less symmetric solvated Zundel ion in BR.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="220"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj19" novelty="New" advantage="None">The characteristics of the most active H-bond, in particular concerning the asymmetry in the case of the solvated Zundel complex in BR, comes out most clearly after averaging over the fluctuations of the donor–acceptor distance, see Fig. 17.</annotationART></s> <s sid="221"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs36" novelty="None" advantage="None">For both Zundel-type complexes the peak is much broader than in the Eigen cases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="222"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs37" novelty="None" advantage="None">This clearly shows that the proton is well localized on the central water molecule in the Eigen complex, whereas it is essentially equally shared (or “delocalized”) between the two neighboring water molecules in the Zundel complex.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="223"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res29" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the relative free energy, <IT>i.e.</IT> the free energy profile or the potential of mean force, is related to the minus of the logarithm of such distribution functions, it is evident that the energetically most stable position of the proton in BR at room temperature is the hydronium core in the case of Eigen-like solvation, whereas the “delocalized” position is clearly favored in Zundel-like situations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="224"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs38" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note, however, that the solvated Zundel complex could only be stabilized in BR by applying suitable (though mild) constraints on the four solvating water molecules, whereas the Eigen complex turned out to be very stable from the outset.</annotationART></s> <s sid="225"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res30" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is not too surprising in view of the inhomogeneous electric field due to the protein environment that most probably introduces asymmetry and thus destabilizes symmetrical solvation complexes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="226"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Overall, there seems to be an astonishing structural similarity of the two protonated water networks in BR as compared to gas phase reference data of free protonated clusters.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4">Conclusions and outlook</HEADER><P><s sid="227"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None">A detailed account of building and equilibrating a realistic QM/MM model of bacteriorhodopsin in a solvated lipid bilayer membrane was given where the protonated water network within a hydrophilic pocket on the extracellular side of BR was treated as the QM part.</annotationART></s> <s sid="228"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, we have presented first results from QM/MM Car–Parrinello molecular dynamics simulations of two qualitatively different protonated water networks.</annotationART></s> <s sid="229"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None">We find that an Eigen-type cluster, <IT>i.e.</IT> H<SB>3</SB>O<SP>+</SP>·(H<SB>2</SB>O)<SB>3</SB> connected <IT>via</IT> H-bonds to suitable BR residues in this pocket, is a stable entity on the time scale of several picoseconds.</annotationART></s> <s sid="230"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the same pocket, it was difficult to stabilize a solvated Zundel-type complex, <IT>i.e.</IT> H<SB>5</SB>O<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP>·(H<SB>2</SB>O)<SB>4</SB>, which was achieved only after introducing distance constraints on the hydrogen bonds that connect the solvating water molecules to the H<SB>5</SB>O<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP> core.</annotationART></s> <s sid="231"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con15" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this case, however, an essentially symmetric H-bond in the Zundel-core [H<SB>2</SB>O⋯H⋯OH<SB>2</SB>]<SP>+</SP> was found, where on average the proton resides close to the bond midpoint between the two bridging oxygen atoms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="232"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The dynamics of this particular H-bond appears to be much more complex than that involving the Eigen-core H<SB>3</SB>O<SP>+</SP>, in particular featuring fairly slow large-amplitude motion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="233"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Interestingly, striking similarities in structural and dynamic properties of these protonated networks embedded in BR and the analogues protonated water clusters in the gas phase exist.</annotationART></s> <s sid="234"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Most importantly these findings are consistent with the idea that protonated water networks might play a major role in the extracellular proton release process—possibly being at the heart of the proton release group “XH”.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
