<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b315019d" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Validation of density functional methods for computing structures and energies of mercury(iv) complexes<XREF TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" /></annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">While quantum chemical predictions have strongly suggested a decade ago the existence of mercury in its oxidation state +iv, no experimental evidence has been found yet.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">To enable the search for alternative targets and preparation routes by quantum chemical methods, the present work has validated density functional methods against accurate CCSD(T) results for structures, reaction energies and activation barriers for X<SB>2</SB>-elimination, and atomization energies for three HgX<SB>4</SB> systems (X = F, Cl, H).</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hybrid functionals with <IT>ca.</IT> 20% Hartree–Fock exchange like B3LYP, B1LYP or MPW1PW91 have provided the best energetics, whereas local or gradient-corrected “pure” functionals overestimate, and the BHandHLYP hybrid functional underestimates the stability of the Hg<SP>IV</SP> state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Basis sets are suggested that provide a reasonable compromise between accuracy and computational effort in calculations on larger systems.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="I.">Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The possible existence of species with mercury in an oxidation state higher than +ii has been puzzling experimentalists and theoreticians for almost three decades.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot3" novelty="None" advantage="None">An experimental verification of such high-valent mercury complexes is a fascinating target, as it would turn a group 12 element into a true transition metal.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">An initial report of an electrochemically generated, spectroscopically characterized short-lived [Hg<SP>(iii)</SP>(cyclam)][BF<SB>4</SB>]<SB>2</SB> species by Deming <IT>et al.</IT> in 1976<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF> has never been confirmed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">But it stimulated Jørgensen<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2 cit3">2,3</REF> to predict the possible existence of HgF<SB>4</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Analogous to the 5d<SP>8</SP> Au<SP>III</SP> oxidation state, a 5d<SP>8</SP> Hg<SP>IV</SP> species should be more stable than a Hg<SP>III</SP> d<SP>9</SP> state.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In 1993, we reported the first application of quantum chemical methods to the problem.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit5">4,5</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Using high-level quasirelativistic pseudopotential QCISD(T) calculations with, at the time, respectable basis sets, the square-planar <IT>D</IT><SB>4h</SB> symmetrical HgF<SB>4</SB> was predicted to be thermodynamically stable in the gas phase with respect to the elimination reaction HgF<SB>4</SB> → HgF<SB>2</SB> + F<SB>2</SB> (see Fig. S1 of electronic supplementary information (ESI)<SUP TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" /> for transition state).</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Comparison with nonrelativistic pseudopotential results showed that the stability of the higher oxidation state is of relativistic origin.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Most notably, the results showed that a better description of electron correlation should increase the reaction energy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">This was confirmed five years later by Liu <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF>. using larger basis sets and CCSD(T) methods.</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">HgCl<SB>4</SB> was in contrast suggested to be thermodynamically unstable<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF> with respect to Cl<SB>2</SB> elimination.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Seth <IT>et al.</IT> predicted that the eka-mercury analogue of HgF<SB>4</SB>, (112)F<SB>4</SB>, should be even more stable than HgF<SB>4</SB> with respect to F<SB>2</SB> elimination.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Recently, Pyykkö <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF>. showed computationally that HgH<SB>4</SB> and HgH<SB>6</SB> are significantly endothermic, but have moderate activation barriers to H<SB>2</SB> elimination.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Up to date, none of the discussed high-valent mercury compounds systems has been confirmed experimentally.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The technical difficulties for their synthesis have apparently been too large.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">As aggregation energies disfavor HgF<SB>4</SB> against HgF<SB>2</SB> in the condensed phase, molecular beam or matrix isolation techniques would seem appropriate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the use of aggressive fluorine compounds and of mercury does not make the former route attractive for experimentalists, and the latter route also has not produced evidence for high-valent mercury.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The quest for Hg(iv) complexes remains thus a major challenge, and we have recently started to consider new synthetic targets and routes, including electrochemical access using chelate or macrocyclic ligands and/or oxidizing matrix environments.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot4" novelty="None" advantage="None">A problem arising with quantum chemical predictions is that the accurate coupled-cluster methods employed previously in this field are computationally too expensive to be applied to larger complexes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The only alternative is currently to use density functional theory (DFT) methods.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, as the accuracy of the various DFT approaches may not be improved systematically towards the exact result, and the most appropriate functional is not immediately obvious, it is necessary to validate DFT methods on smaller models, for which accurate coupled cluster methods may still be used.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">In this work we provide such a systematic validation study of various density functionals and basis sets on structures and stability of small HgX<SB>4</SB> complexes (X = F, Cl, H; <IT>n</IT> = 2, 4) against accurate benchmark CCSD(T) calculations.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="II.">Computational methods</HEADER><P><s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The benchmark calculations employed the coupled-cluster method with single and double, as well as perturbative triple excitations [CCSD(T) level].</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">For comparison, CCSD and MP2 calculations are also reported.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">All of these <IT>ab initio</IT> calculations used a quasirelativistic small-core 20-valence-electron (20-VE) pseudopotential<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF> (effective-core potential, ECP) with a (11s10p9d4f3g)/[9s6p5d3f2g] valence basis set<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF> for Hg, as well as aug-cc-pVQZ<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12 cit13">12,13</REF> basis sets for F, Cl, and H. This ECP/basis-set combination will be denoted basis A. Bond lengths were optimized by fitting a fifth-order polynomial to about 7 single-point energy calculations, which were done with the MOLPRO 20001<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF>. program.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">DFT calculations used the Gaussian 98<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF> program and gradient methods.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The following exchange-correlation functionals were scrutinized: The local density approximation in form of the SVWN5<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF> functional, the gradient-corrected BP86<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17 cit18">17,18</REF> functional, and the hybrid functionals B1LYP,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19 cit20">19,20</REF> B3LYP<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF> (based on the work of Becke),<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF> MPW1PW91,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF> and BHandHLYP.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Basis-set requirements in the DFT calculations are expected to be somewhat less dramatic than in the post-HF treatments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Moreover, future applications to larger systems require a reasonable compromise between accuracy and computational effort.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Three different basis-set combinations were compared, denoted B, C, and D (see Table 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">We will in the following report the computational levels by the notation method/basis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Unrestricted Kohn–Sham calculations on nonspherical atoms were performed to obtain atomization energies.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Basis-set superposition errors (BSSE) were considered using the counterpoise correction (CP)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF> at optimized minimum structures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Zero-point energy (ZPE) corrections were computed at the B3LYP/C level.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Spin–orbit corrections were not considered in this study.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod11" novelty="None" advantage="None">They have previously been found to be small for the elimination reaction HgF<SB>4</SB> → HgF<SB>2</SB> + F<SB>2</SB>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF> and the theory against theory comparison is not affected by them.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="III.">Results and discussion</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Minimum structures</HEADER><P><s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The HgX<SB>4</SB> systems were generally found to have <IT>D</IT><SB>4h</SB> minima at all computational levels.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The calculated Hg–X bond lengths are shown in Table 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Using the CCSD(T)/A results as benchmark, CCSD/A underestimates the bond lengths for HgH<SB>4</SB> and HgF<SB>4</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">MP2/A overestimates the distances for HgF<SB>4</SB> but underestimates them for HgCl<SB>4</SB> and HgH<SB>4</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The large and non-systematic differences document the previously discussed<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF> importance of non-dynamical correlation in these systems, particularly for HgF<SB>4</SB> and HgCl<SB>4</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The non-iterative triple excitations in CCSD(T) are known to partially recover the non-dynamical correlation.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25">25</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The CCSD T<SB>1</SB>-diagnostics<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26">26</REF> at the CCSD(T) minima are 0.017, 0.011, and 0.012 for HgF<SB>4</SB>, HgCl<SB>4</SB>, and HgH<SB>4</SB>, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This suggests a reasonable quality of the coupled-cluster results.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The largest <IT>T</IT><SB>1</SB> value for HgF<SB>4</SB> is consistent with large variations between MP2, CCSD, and CCSD(T) results.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">This suggests to view MP2 and CCSD energies with caution.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Compared to the CCSD(T)/A benchmark results, all DFT calculations overestimate the Hg-X bond lengths (see Table 2).</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">This may in part be due to the neglect of dispersion effects<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27">27</REF> in present-day functionals, which would further decrease the distances.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Consistent with this, the discrepancies are by far largest for HgCl<SB>4</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Among the various functionals, the BHandHLYP and SVWN5 results are closest to the CCSD(T) values for HgF<SB>4</SB> and HgCl<SB>4</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">While this may be attributed to error compensation with the typical overbinding of the local density approximation for the SVWN5 case,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28">28</REF> the large fraction of Hartree–Fock exchange shortens the bond lengths for the BHandHLYP functional.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">As might be expected, basis B provides the shortest DFT bond lengths and thus the best agreement with the benchmark CCSD(T)/A results.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is largely due to the inclusion of f-functions for mercury and in part to the still relatively flexible basis sets for X. Basis set C provides results similar to basis set B for HgF<SB>4</SB> and HgH<SB>4</SB> at lower computational cost.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results indicate that the best DFT structure results for HgX<SB>4</SB> are obtained using basis sets B or C, and SVWN5 or BHandHLYP functionals.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Reaction energies for X<SB>2</SB>-elimination</HEADER><P><s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Calculated energies for the elimination reactions HgX<SB>4</SB> → HgX<SB>2</SB> + X<SB>2</SB> (X = F, Cl, H) are provided in Table 3 and in Fig. 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">CCSD underestimates and MP2 overestimates the elimination energies in all cases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">This appreciable level dependence of the results indicates again a significant influence of non-dynamical correlation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">As has been discussed previously,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF> these effects arise mainly for the “true transition-metal” Hg<SP>IV</SP> d<SP>8</SP> species, while non-dynamical correlation effects are much smaller for the Hg<SP>II</SP> d<SP>10</SP> complexes, where metal d-orbitals are unimportant for the bonding (see atomization energies below and in Table 5).</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The resulting lack of error compensation between these effects for the two sides of the reaction is responsible for the appreciable level dependence.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Comparison with previous results<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6">5,6</REF> confirms the notion of larger elimination reactions for larger basis sets.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The full CP procedure to correct for BSSE was not possible at CCSD(T)/A level for HgF<SB>4</SB> and HgCl<SB>4</SB>, as the large dimension of the problem combined with the low symmetry of the CP calculation for the halogen atoms exceeded the available computational resources.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Given the close agreement between CCSD and CCSD(T) CP corrections for the hydride, we may assume that the CCSD values provide also a good estimate for the CCSD(T) CP correction in the other two cases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">In general, the CP corrections tend to lower the reaction energies moderately by <IT>ca.</IT> 10–15 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">We estimate this to be less than the underestimate of correlation effects due to basis-set incompleteness errors, which are expected to cause an underestimate of the reaction energies.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">We presume therefore, that the CCSD(T)/A values in Table 3 provide still lower bounds to the true reaction energies.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Turning now to DFT methods, the best agreement with the benchmark CCSD(T)/A results is achieved using those hybrid functionals (B1LYP, B3LYP, and MPW1PW91) that exhibit about 20% Hartree–Fock (HF) exchange.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Functionals with higher HF exchange admixture, such as BHandHLYP (50% HF exchange) give too low elimination energies, whereas the gradient-corrected BP86, and in particular the local SVWN5 functional overestimate the elimination energies significantly.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The comparison of basis sets B, C, and D (Table 3 and Fig. 1) indicates a moderate basis-set dependence.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs19" novelty="None" advantage="None">After inclusion of CP corrections, the intermediate basis C results are relatively close to those with the larger basis B (<IT>i.e.</IT>, both provide good agreement with the CCSD(T) data when using a hybrid functional like B3LYP).</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the CP corrections obtained for basis C are considerably larger than for basis B with HgF<SB>4</SB> and HgH<SB>4</SB>, making basis B the overall more reliable method of choice, provided the size of system to be studied allows the use of the larger basis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In particular, CP corrections are not easily applicable in all energy calculations (<IT>e.g.</IT> for intramolecular processes), and thus a basis with an inherently smaller BSSE may be preferable.</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs20" novelty="None" advantage="None">Finally, the basis D results for HgF<SB>4</SB> and HgCl<SB>4</SB> (including a segmented valence basis for Hg, <IT>cf.</IT> Table 1) exhibit large BSSE and still appreciable deviations from the basis B results after CP correction.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs21" novelty="None" advantage="None">Zero-point energy (ZPE) corrections calculated at the B3LYP/C level are listed in Table 4.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs22" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ZPE corrections lower the elimination energy almost negligibly for the fluoride and chloride and moderately so for the hydride.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Atomization energies</HEADER><P><s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs23" novelty="None" advantage="None">Table 5 provides computed atomization energies (AE) for the X<SB>2</SB>, HgX<SB>2</SB>, and HgX<SB>4</SB> systems (with CP corrections but without ZPE corrections).</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None">These data allow us to further analyze the contributions from individual species to the elimination reactions in Table 3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Triple excitations in the coupled cluster calculations increase the AE notably for HgF<SB>4</SB>, HgCl<SB>4</SB>, and for F<SB>2</SB>, consistent with nonnegligible non-dynamical correlation effects (see above).</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs24" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the same three cases, the MP2 calculations overestimate the AE appreciably.</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs25" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the other cases, the MP2 results are either somewhat above or slightly below the CCSD(T) data.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of F<SB>2</SB>, Cl<SB>2</SB>, and H<SB>2</SB>, experimental data are available for comparison (see footnote a to Table 5).</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The CCSD(T)/A results deviate only by a few kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> from experiment, indicating an approximate convergence of the halogen (hydrogen) basis sets and of the correlation level in this case.</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Any remaining errors in the CCSD(T)/A results for the elimination reactions (Table 3) will thus mostly be due to the description of the metal complexes themselves, probably in particular that of the Hg<SP>IV</SP> species.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">While any of the density functionals tested should perform reasonably well for the AE of H<SB>2</SB> (the MPW1PW91/B results appear a bit low), the more complicated electronic structure of the dihalogens is reflected in larger variations between the functionals.</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs26" novelty="None" advantage="None">Again, hybrid functionals with <IT>ca.</IT> 20% Hartree–Fock exchange (B1LYP, B3LYP, MPW1PW91) tend to perform best (with an underestimate of <IT>ca.</IT> 10–30 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>), whereas the BHandHLYP functional underestimates the AE of both F<SB>2</SB> and Cl<SB>2</SB> appreciably, and the gradient-corrected BP86 overestimates the AE for F<SB>2</SB> (the local SVWN5 functional overestimates both AEs appreciably).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs27" novelty="None" advantage="None">Similar behavior of the functionals is seen for the tetrahalide complexes: again B1LYP, B3LYP, and MPW1PW91 appear to perform best, BHandHLYP underbinds compared to the CCSD(T)/A benchmark results, whereas BP86 and particularly the local SVWN5 overbind appreciably.</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs28" novelty="None" advantage="None">In these cases, deviations for the tetrahalides are much larger than for the dihalides.</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs29" novelty="None" advantage="None">This translates into appreciable errors in the energies of the elimination reactions (<IT>cf.</IT> Table 3).</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">While the B3LYP/B AE are too high by <IT>ca.</IT> 70 and 60 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> for HgF<SB>4</SB> and HgF<SB>2</SB>, respectively, these errors compensate largely for the elimination reaction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Similar comparisons apply to the B1LYP and MPW91PW91 functionals.</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In consequence, these types of hybrid functionals (with basis B) reproduce most reliably the CCSD(T)/A thermochemistry.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Transition states for elimination reactions</HEADER><P><s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="New" advantage="None">We have also attempted to calculate the transition states and activation barriers for the concerted elimination of X<SB>2</SB> (Table 6).</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Full structure optimization at the CCSD(T)/A level exceeded the available computational resources.</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod12" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of the post-HF methods, we were thus restricted to single-point energy calculations at various DFT-optimized structures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj5" novelty="New" advantage="None">Full optimizations were, however, attempted for all density functionals.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">The transition states located are structurally similar to that computed for the HgH<SB>4</SB> case by Pyykkö <IT>et al.</IT>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF> a planar arrangement with <IT>C</IT><SB>2v</SB> symmetry (see supporting information).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs30" novelty="None" advantage="None">For HgF<SB>4</SB>, the computed activation barriers appear to be very large and vary over a wide range (Table 6).</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs31" novelty="None" advantage="None">Already the variation of the structure with different functionals changes the CCSD(T)/A barrier over a range of more than 100 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">The DFT barriers are only about half of the CCSD(T) results but still appear unrealistically large relative to the average Hg–F binding energies deducible from the atomization energies in Table 5.</annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">Matters are less dramatic for HgCl<SB>4</SB> and HgH<SB>4</SB>, where the computed barriers range from <IT>ca.</IT> 60 to 80 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>, and from <IT>ca.</IT> 40 to 50 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs32" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the latter two cases, the DFT results are not very far from the best CCSD(T) values.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs33" novelty="None" advantage="None">Closer inspection of the electronic structure at the F<SB>2</SB>-elimination transition state for HgF<SB>4</SB> suggests very small HOMO-LUMO gaps already for the hybrid functionals (<IT>ca.</IT> 1–1.7 eV for B3LYP, B1LYP, and MPW1PW91 and <IT>ca.</IT> 3–3.5 eV for BHandHLYP).</annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs34" novelty="None" advantage="None">With gradient-corrected and local functionals, no electronically stable Kohn–Sham wavefunction could be obtained.</annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">This suggests appreciable multi-reference character for the transition state, and both approximate DFT and single-reference coupled-cluster theory appear problematic.</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs35" novelty="None" advantage="None">Matters are not much better for the HgCl<SB>4</SB> case (although here the BP86 and SVWN5 calculations afford small gaps of <IT>ca.</IT> 0.1–0.2 eV), and it is presently unclear why the computed barriers are less level dependent.</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs36" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast, the HgH<SB>4</SB> case exhibits appreciable HOMO-LUMO gaps at any of the levels employed (<IT>ca.</IT> 4.5 eV with BP86 and SVWN5, <IT>ca.</IT> 6 eV with the “regular” hybrid functionals, and <IT>ca.</IT> 8 eV with BHandHLYP).</annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">It appears that the simpler electronic structure of the HgH<SB>4</SB> transition state, and possibly the relatively large Hg–H covalency, make this system an easier case for single-reference methods (<IT>T</IT><SB>1</SB> diagnostics at CCSD level in this case are only <IT>ca.</IT> 0.015, compared to values around 0.04–0.06 for HgF<SB>4</SB> and HgCl<SB>4</SB>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In particular, we think that repulsive effects between the nonbonding electron pairs of the halogen ligands and the 5p semi-core shell on mercury may be responsible<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29">29</REF> for the generally larger non-dynamical correlation effects in the tetrahalides compared to the tetrahydride.</annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs37" novelty="None" advantage="None">The present results for the HgH<SB>4</SB> system agree well with the previous study by Pyykkö <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="IV.">Conclusions</HEADER><P><s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">This validation study of various density functionals and basis sets against accurate benchmark CCSD(T) results for structures and energetics of small Hg<SP>IV</SP> complexes provides a basis for our ongoing studies<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF> on larger target systems of potential interest for experimental studies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">While relatively reliable structures of minima (except for HgCl<SB>4</SB>) may already be obtained with the local SVWN5 or the hybrid BHandHLYP functionals (due to error compensation), the energetics are better described by hybrid functionals like B1LYP, B3LYP, and MPW1PW91, that incorporate <IT>ca.</IT> 20% Hartree–Fock exchange.</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The choice of basis sets will depend on the size of system to be studied.</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Optimizations may employ the moderate-sized, economical basis C, whereas accurate DFT energy calculations may require the larger basis B that exhibits considerably lower BSSE.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None">A search for transition states and activation barriers for X<SB>2</SB>-elimination from HgX<SB>4</SB> (X = F, Cl, H) indicated considerably larger multi-reference character for X = F, Cl than for the previously studied HgH<SB>4</SB> system, possibly due to the presence of nonbonding electron pairs at the halogens.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29">29</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None">At least for X = F, no reliable activation barriers could thus be computed with the available methods.</annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Unfortunately, multi-configurational approaches would currently also be prohibitively expensive in this case, due to the large active orbital space that would be required.</annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, based on the comparison with the other two cases, we expect an appreciable activation barrier for concerted F<SB>2</SB>-elimination, in view of the multi-reference character of the transition state probably the largest of the three systems studied.</annotationART></s> <s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con15" novelty="None" advantage="None">In any case, the calculations confirm clearly the previously noted exothermic character of HgF<SB>4</SB> as a gas phase species, in contrast to HgH<SB>4</SB> and HgCl<SB>4</SB>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
