<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b316620a" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Conformational control of electron delocalisation in geometrically-constrained, binuclear ruthenium(ii) <IT>bis</IT>(2,2′:6′,2″-terpyridine) complexes</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the basis of temperature-dependent emission studies made with the target binuclear compounds, it is concluded that the extent of electron delocalisation at the triplet level depends on the torsion angle imposed by the bridge.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER /><P><s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is well established that the triplet lifetime of ruthenium(ii) <IT>bis</IT>(2,2′:6′,2″-terpyridine) at ambient temperatures can be prolonged by attaching an alkynylene substituent at the 4′-position.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This strategy works particularly well for the corresponding binuclear complexes, where the triplet lifetimes at 20 °C exceed that of the parent complex by a factor of at least .1000<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">2</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Prolongation of the triplet lifetime is due to two complementary effects; namely, decoupling of the lowest-energy triplet state from upper-lying metal-centred states and extended delocalisation of the promoted electron over the substituted ligand.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Electron delocalisation can occur because the lowest-energy triplet is of metal-to-ligand, charge-transfer (MLCT) character and is formed by selective charge injection into the alkyne-substituted ligand.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">We now show that the extent of electron delocalisation is subject to conformational control, as imposed by constraining the geometry of the alkynylene-based bridge.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The target molecules comprise the following units: (i) The main chromophore is a ruthenium(ii) <IT>bis</IT>(2,2′:6′,2″-terpyridine) unit.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">(ii) To ensure luminescence at ambient temperature, an ethynylene group is attached at the 4′-position.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">(iii) A central biphenylene unit is used as a variable rotor.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">(iv) A strap of predetermined length is attached at the 2,2′-positions of the rotor so as to restrict internal twisting around the connecting bond.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The generic molecular structures, and their abbreviations, are shown in Fig. 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">These compounds were synthesized as outlined previously<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF> and fully characterised by <SP>1</SP>H and <SP>13</SP>C NMR, mass spectrometry and elemental analysis.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Each compound shows a prominent MLCT transition centred at 490 nm, with a tail stretching towards 600 nm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The tail is due to the spin-forbidden MLCT transitions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">At higher energy, the parent terpyridine ligand absorbs around 270 nm whilst the polytopic ligand displays absorption bands between 290 and 400 nm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Very weak luminescence can be observed in deoxygenated solution at ambient temperature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This emission is centred around 675 nm and can be assigned to phosphorescence from the lowest-energy MLCT triplet state of the metal complex.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">At room temperature, the emission quantum yields are very low (<IT>Φ</IT><SB>LUM</SB> ≈ 0.0004) and the lifetimes are relatively short (<IT>τ</IT><SB>LUM</SB> ≈ 20 ns).</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Even so, emission is much more intense than that observed from the parent complex under these conditions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Luminescence from the binuclear complexes becomes more pronounced as the temperature is lowered.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In all cases, there is good agreement between the increase in quantum yield and lifetime.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The corrected excitation spectrum matches the absorption spectrum over the entire visible and near-UV regions and all spectroscopic measurements indicate that only a single species emits.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Even in a frozen glass, there is no suggestion of emission from either a ligand-centred triplet or an intramolecular charge-transfer state.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">As such, the temperature dependence is due to perturbation of the photophysical properties of the lowest-energy MLCT triplet state.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The photophysical properties of metal poly(pyridine) complexes are subject to the energy-gap law.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">But, in order to expose this relationship, it is necessary to allow for coupling between the emitting state and higher-lying triplets.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">The energy of the lowest triplet excited state (<IT>E</IT><SB>T</SB>) can be derived by detailed analysis of the emission spectrum.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the target compounds in fluid solution, <IT>E</IT><SB>T</SB> (≈15,800 cm<SP>–1</SP>) is independent of temperature and insensitive to the length of the strap.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Likewise, the total reorganisation energy (<IT>λ</IT><SB>T</SB> ≈ 700 cm<SP>–1</SP>) accompanying decay of the first triplet excited state remains essentially constant for all the complexes studied here.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rate constant (<IT>k</IT><SB>NR</SB>) for nonradiative deactivation of the lowest-energy triplet state was found to follow eqn. (1) over a wide temperature range (Fig. 2).</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">This expression provides for the activationless rate of decay (<IT>k</IT><SB>0</SB>), seen at low temperature, and for coupling to two additional excited triplet states.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Of these two higher-energy triplets, one is accessed by passage over a small barrier (<IT>E</IT><SB>1</SB>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">This upper-lying state is probably a second MLCT triplet but with increased singlet character.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The overall rate constant (<IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB>) associated with reaching this state is rendered complex by the reversible nature of the barrier crossing.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">At ambient temperature, a metal-centred (MC) state can be accessed by crossing a more substantial barrier (<IT>E</IT><SB>2</SB>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this case, barrier crossing is considered to be irreversible such that the derived rate constant (<IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB>) is set by the rate of decay of the MC state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">This latter process results in direct population of the ground state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The various values extracted from the kinetic fits are collected in Table 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is seen that only <IT>k</IT><SB>0</SB> depends on the length of the strap.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is known from related systems that <IT>k</IT><SB>0</SB> decreases with increasing extent of electron delocalisation of the promoted electron.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fact that <IT>k</IT><SB>0</SB> depends on the length of the strap is clear indication that the conformation of the bridging unit affects the degree of electronic communication along the molecular axis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Two possibilities need be considered on the basis of molecular dynamics simulations made for the target compounds in a bath of acetonitrile molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">First, the strap controls the torsion angle between the phenylene rings.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">As such, the length of the strap should influence the degree of orbital overlap, in the event that the promoted electron extends to the LUMO on the biphenylene group.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Second, the strapped biphenylene unit does not lie coplanar with the covalently-linked terpyridine groups.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The mean torsion angle between nearby phenylene and pyridine rings varies markedly with strap length, especially for optimised structures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">This torsion angle controls the degree of electronic coupling between the terpyridine ligand and the ethynylene group and will have a pronounced effect on the extent of electron delocalisation over the acetylenic unit.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">As mentioned above, the variation in <IT>k</IT><SB>0</SB> should be explainable within the framework of the energy-gap law, eqn. (2).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The most important variable within this expression is the amount of energy to be dissipated during nonradiative decay.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, since <IT>E</IT><SB>T</SB> remains invariant throughout this series it is clear that other factors combine to affect the magnitude of <IT>k</IT><SB>0</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The remaining parameters in eqn. (2) are the Huang–Rhys factor (<IT>S</IT><SB>M</SB>),<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF> the electron-vibrational coupling matrix element (<IT>C</IT>) and the averaged medium-frequency vibrational mode (<IT>hω</IT><SB>M</SB>) coupled to nonradiative decay.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The coefficient <IT>γ</IT> depends on both the energy gap and the extent of nuclear displacement.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both <IT>S</IT> and <IT>hω</IT><SB>M</SB> can be determined by analysis of the emission spectra recorded in fluid solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Usually, the full emission spectrum, at any temperature, can be expressed<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF> in terms of a weighted average, medium-frequency mode (<IT>hω</IT><SB>M</SB>) of around 1380 cm<SP>–1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">This was not the case for the target compounds studied here since, even in fluid solution, it was necessary to include an additional low frequency mode (<IT>hω</IT><SB>L</SB>) to properly express the emission spectra.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, the normalised emission spectra could be reconstituted on the basis of eqn. (3)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF> and using the data collected in Table 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">It should be stressed that the inclusion of <IT>hω</IT><SB>L</SB> in fluid solution is unique to those metal complexes equipped with the constraining strap.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">In fitting the experimental data to eqn. (3) (Fig. 3), <IT>I</IT>(<IT>ν</IT>) is the normalised emission intensity at wavenumber <IT>ν</IT>, <IT>n</IT><SB>M</SB> and <IT>n</IT><SB>L</SB> are the vibrational quantum numbers for the averaged medium (<IT>hω</IT><SB>M</SB>) and low (<IT>hω</IT><SB>L</SB>) frequency acceptor modes, Δ<IT>v</IT><SB>1/2</SB> is the half-width of individual vibronic bands and <IT>E</IT><SB>00</SB> is the energy gap for the 0–0 transition.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The quantities <IT>S</IT><SB>M</SB> and <IT>S</IT><SB>L</SB> are the Huang–Rhys factors for medium and low frequency modes, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Only the half-width depends on temperature and the other parameters were averaged over the entire temperature range (Table 2).</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The best fits to the experimental data gave <IT>hω</IT><SB>M</SB> and <IT>hω</IT><SB>L</SB> values, respectively, of <IT>ca.</IT> 1400 and <IT>ca.</IT> 800 cm<SP>–1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The latter value increases systematically with increasing temperature; <IT>e.g.</IT> for C4 <IT>hω</IT><SB>L</SB> varies from <IT>ca.</IT> 535 cm<SP>–1</SP> at 90 K to 1020 cm<SP>–1</SP> at 290 K.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The medium-frequency mode corresponds to CC and CN stetching vibrations associated with the terpyridine ligand.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The low frequency vibration can be assigned to substituted phenylene bending modes.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is now clear that motion around the bridging phenylene unit is coupled to nonradiative decay of the lowest-energy triplet state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Presumably, this effect relates to the system trying to achieve the maximum orbital overlap at the triplet level.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">It should be noted that the strap exerts a pronounced effect on <IT>k</IT><SB>0</SB> since there is a 90-fold increase in rate between C2 and the corresponding complex lacking the strap.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The exact details underlying this behaviour will be described elsewhere.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
