<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b400471j" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Calculations of interaction energies of ellipticine derivatives with DNA base pairs<XREF TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" /></annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">Properties of various derivatives of ellipticine and their stacking interactions with adenine–thymine and guanine–cytosine base pairs were investigated with an <IT>ab initio</IT> correlated method.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None">The dependence of the interaction energy on the distance between an intercalator and a base-pair and on the twist angle between them was studied.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="New" advantage="None">The results were compared with three empirical potentials, two of which being based on the AMBER force field and the other one based on the Lifson–Hagler empirical potential.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj5" novelty="New" advantage="None">The global interaction energy minima geometries of three systems were searched.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj6" novelty="New" advantage="None">The performance of the empirical potentials is discussed.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Ellipticine (<B>1</B>) is an alkaloid isolated from <IT>Ochrosia elliptica.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Ellipticine and its derivatives are highly toxic to malignant cells in culture<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">2</REF> and 2<IT>N</IT>-methyl-9-hydroxy-ellipticinium (<B>2</B>) and other ellipticine derivatives have reached the phase II of clinical trials.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">These effects are believed to result from DNA-binding, with intercalation being a necessary condition for antitumor activity.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">2</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Little is known, however, about the specific factors involved in stabilising ellipticine–DNA complexes.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot3" novelty="None" advantage="None">One of the possible approaches to evaluate various factors involved in the intercalator–DNA binding is computational chemistry.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Electrostatic energy, dispersion energy, induction energy and charge transfer are the contributions of stacking energy in the intercalated systems.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">When the problem is treated with <IT>ab initio</IT> methods, correlated calculations are strictly required for calculations of interaction energy, because the Hartree–Fock method and the DFT methods do not include the dispersion energy.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">High level <IT>ab initio</IT> calculations are prohibitively expensive for large systems (such as an intercalator and a DNA fragment) and there is so far only one paper reporting interaction energies of intercalator–base pair systems<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF> and one paper reporting interaction energies of intercalator–single base.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Stacking interactions of various DNA bases and DNA base pairs were already studied.</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">For example, in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">ref. 7</REF> the interaction energies between base pairs in A-DNA and B-DNA are discussed.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Simple empirical potentials consisting of a van der Waals term and a Coulombic term with atom-centred point charges are able to reproduce the <IT>ab initio</IT> stacking energy quite well.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, this does not mean that each empirical potential is accurate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot4" novelty="None" advantage="None">A comparison with the <IT>ab initio</IT> calculated data can help to evaluate the empirical potential results.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit9">4,9</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj7" novelty="New" advantage="None">We have chosen various ellipticine derivatives (<B>2</B>–<B>6</B>) as model compounds for studying and evaluating the performance of simple empirical potentials.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj7" novelty="New" advantage="No">In biological reality there are more principal components that combine to stabilise DNA–drug interactions (drug structure, solution conditions and deformability of DNA strands).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this study all the calculations were performed in gas phase, so other components than drug structure were omitted.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">We believe that this approach does not affect the credibility of comparison between various simple empirical potentials.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Calculations</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Geometries</HEADER><P><s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The structure and geometries of various ellipticine derivatives and of adenine–thymine and of guanine–cytosine Watson–Crick base pairs were optimised at the DFT level using the B3LYP functional and 6-31G* basis set.</annotationART></s> The structure of guanine–cytosine base pair was determined with the assumption of its planarity. </P><TGROUP><THEAD><ROW><ENTRY> </ENTRY><ENTRY>name</ENTRY><ENTRY>R1</ENTRY><ENTRY>R2</ENTRY><ENTRY>R3</ENTRY></ROW></THEAD><TBODY><ROW><ENTRY>1</ENTRY><ENTRY>E</ENTRY><ENTRY>H</ENTRY><ENTRY>H</ENTRY><ENTRY>—</ENTRY></ROW><ROW><ENTRY>2</ENTRY><ENTRY>9HNME</ENTRY><ENTRY>OH</ENTRY><ENTRY>H</ENTRY><ENTRY>CH<SB>3</SB></ENTRY></ROW><ROW><ENTRY>3</ENTRY><ENTRY>9HE</ENTRY><ENTRY>OH</ENTRY><ENTRY>H</ENTRY><ENTRY>—</ENTRY></ROW><ROW><ENTRY>4</ENTRY><ENTRY>7HE</ENTRY><ENTRY>H</ENTRY><ENTRY>OH</ENTRY><ENTRY>—</ENTRY></ROW><ROW><ENTRY>5</ENTRY><ENTRY>E+</ENTRY><ENTRY>H</ENTRY><ENTRY>H</ENTRY><ENTRY>H</ENTRY></ROW><ROW><ENTRY>6</ENTRY><ENTRY>9AE+</ENTRY><ENTRY>NH<SB>2</SB></ENTRY><ENTRY>H</ENTRY><ENTRY>H</ENTRY></ROW></TBODY></TGROUP></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER><IT>Ab initio</IT> interaction energies</HEADER><P>An ellipticine derivative and a base pair were located in coplanar “planes” (the molecules are almost planar) in such a way that the main system axes were parallel. <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Vertical separation of the subsystems was changed and energy was calculated at the MP2 level with the 6-31G* basis set with modified exponents of the polarisation functions (0.25 instead of the routinely used value 0.8, abbreviation 6-31G*(0.25)).</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">This basis set is considered to be very appropriate for systems with stacking interactions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit5 cit11">4,5,11</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The basis set superposition error (BSSE) was systematically removed by counterpoise method.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The interaction energy was calculated as a difference between the energy of the whole system and the sum of the energies of the subsystems (the intercalator and the base pair).</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The interaction energy is the energy necessary to separate the ellipticine derivative and the DNA base pair to infinity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">It was shown previously that one molecule of an intercalator and one base pair is a reasonably simple model for intercalating systems<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Empirical potential interaction energies</HEADER><P><s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Three empirical potentials were used.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In all of them the electrostatic energy was calculated according to the Coulomb law: <IT>E</IT><SB>elst</SB> = 332 Σ<IT>q</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB><IT>q</IT><SB><IT>j</IT></SB>/<IT>r</IT><SB><IT>ij</IT></SB>where <IT>q<SB>i</SB></IT> and <IT>q<SB>j</SB></IT> are the atomic charges and <IT>r<SB>ij</SB></IT> is the distance between the atoms <IT>i</IT> and <IT>j</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The point charges were localised on all atomic centres and they were derived from molecular electrostatic potential (ESP)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF> at the HF/6-31G*, B3LYP/6-31G* and MP2/6-31G*(0.25) levels and from restrained electrostatic potential fit (RESP)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF> at the same levels.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The RESP is a modification of original ESP method and it uses hyperbolic restraints to charges of zero for non-hydrogen atoms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">In two of the empirical potentials van der Waals term was calculated with the Lennard-Jones potential: <IT>E</IT><SB>vdW</SB> = Σ<IT>A</IT><SB><IT>ij</IT></SB>/<IT>r</IT>12<IT>ij</IT> − <IT>B</IT><SB><IT>ij</IT></SB>/<IT>r</IT>6<IT>ij</IT>where <IT>A<SB>ij</SB></IT> and <IT>B<SB>ij</SB></IT> are empirical van der Waals constant.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The force field parameter set ff86<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF> and the more recent ff99<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16 cit17">16,17</REF> from AMBER program package were used for calculating of constants <IT>A<SB>ij</SB></IT> and <IT>B<SB>ij</SB></IT> (empirical potential A-ff86 and A-ff99, respectively).</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod12" novelty="None" advantage="None">In one of the empirical potentials (LH) the van der Waals term was calculated with the 9–6 Lifson–Hagler<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF> potential: <IT>E</IT><SB>vdW</SB> = Σ<IT>A<SB>ij</SB></IT>/<IT>r</IT>9<IT>ij</IT> − <IT>B</IT><SB><IT>ij</IT></SB>/<IT>r</IT>6<IT>ij</IT>and the van der Waals energies were scaled by a factor of 0.7.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">This empirical potential was shown to give good results in calculating of interaction energies of stacked DNA bases<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19">19</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Global minima search</HEADER><P><s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In the <IT>ab initio</IT> calculations and in the comparative empirical potential calculations, the intersystem distance was changed only in one dimension.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="No">This approach can not be used in the global energy minima search, because the molecules can move in three dimensions and can also rotate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod13" novelty="None" advantage="None">So we have written a Microsoft Excel macro that looks for the minima.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod14" novelty="None" advantage="None">It changes the position and orientation of the base pair in close neighbourhood of the intercalator and calculates the interaction energy using an arbitrary empirical potential and the analytical derivations of the energy with respect to the position (axes <IT>x</IT>, <IT>y</IT> and <IT>z</IT>) of the molecules and the twist angle (the twist angle is defined as the angle between the main subsystem axes).</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Then the molecule position and the twist angle are changed with the aim to minimise the energy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod16" novelty="None" advantage="None">All the conformational space is investigated, this approach ensuring that the global minimum is found.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Results</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Subsystem properties</HEADER><P>The optimised geometries, the ESP and RESP charges (calculated from various wave functions), the energies of frontier orbitals and the AMBER atom types of five derivatives of ellipticine (<B>2</B>–<B>6</B>) and of adenine–thymine and guanine—cytosine pairs are presented in the electronic supplementary information in Tables S1–S7.<SUP TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" /></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER><IT>Ab initio</IT> interaction energies</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>The AT–E+ system</HEADER><P>The AT–E+ (adenine–thymine–E+) system was studied more deeply and will be discussed with more details. <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The structure of the AT–E+ system is presented in Fig. 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The distance between the ellipticine molecule and the adenine–thymine base pair was changed from 3.15 to 3.75 Å (in 0.15 Å step increments).</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 2 shows the dependence of the interaction energy on the intersystem distance.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The interaction energy has a minimum at 3.33 Å, which is a typical intercalator-base pair distance.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj8" novelty="New" advantage="None">For the AT–E+ system, the dependence of the interaction energy on the twist angle was also investigated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The twist angle (defined as the angle between main axes of the subsystems) was changed from 0 to 180 degrees with a step of 30°, the intersystem distance was constant (3.3 Å).</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 3 shows the results of the <IT>ab initio</IT> calculated dependence of the stacking energy on the twist angle.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj9" novelty="New" advantage="None">It was also interesting to evaluate the additivity of the energy components, it means to answer the question if it is possible to calculate the interaction energy of an intercalator–base pair complex as the sum of two interaction energies of the intercalator–single base systems.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj9" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">The evaluation of the “many body term” can be helpful in calculations of interaction energies of larger systems.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Table 1 presents the interaction energies of the thymine–E+ and the adenine–E+ systems and compares them with the energies of the adenine–thymine–E+ system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The many body terms are quite small.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Other systems</HEADER><P><s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod19" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the other ellipticine derivatives and base pairs, the interaction energy was calculated only for three intersystem distances (3.15, 3.30 and 3.45 Å).</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The minimum energy distances and minimum interaction energies are presented in Table 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The minimum energy distances are always close to 3.35 Å, but the minimum energies are highly dependent on the structure of the intercalator.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Comparison of the <IT>ab initio</IT> data with empirical potentials</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>The AT–E+ system</HEADER><P><s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj10" novelty="New" advantage="None">In Fig. 4 the dependence of interaction energy of the AT–E+ complex on the intersystem distance calculated with the A-ff86 force field with various sets of atomic charges and the reference <IT>ab initio</IT> data are presented.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">It can be seen, that there is almost no difference between the points calculated using the ESP and RESP charges (derived from the same wave function).</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">One can also see that there is practically no difference between the energies calculated using the charges derived from DFT and MP2 wave function.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In general, the coincidence of the <IT>ab initio</IT> curve with all the A-ff86 ones is very good, the energy differences are always less then 1 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj11" novelty="New" advantage="None">The interaction energies evaluated by the A-ff99 force field and the energies evaluated by the LH force field together with the reference <IT>ab initio</IT> data are presented in Fig. 5 and Fig. 6, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">It can be seen again that the differences between the points evaluated by ESP and RESP charges (derived from the same wave function) are rather insignificant and also the differences between the points evaluated with the charges derived from the DFT and MP2 wave function are very small.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The coincidence of the <IT>ab initio</IT> energies with the A-ff99 ones is quite small, especially for short distances (the energy difference for 3.15 Å is almost 5 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the other hand the coincidence of the energies calculated with the LH force field with the <IT>ab initio</IT> energies is very good.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj12" novelty="New" advantage="None">The comparison of selected empirical potentials and <IT>ab initio</IT> calculated interaction energies of the twisted AT–E+ complex are presented in Fig. 7.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this case, the best coincidence of the empirical potential calculated energies with the <IT>ab initio</IT> data gave the LH force field.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Other systems</HEADER><P><s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Figs. 8–13 present the empirical potential calculated interaction energies and the reference <IT>ab initio</IT> data for the other ellipticine derivative-base pair complexes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The same conclusions as for the adenine–thymine–E+ system can be done.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The differences between the ESP and RESP charges derived from the same wave function are very small and the differences between the charges derived from DFT and MP2 wave functions are also very small.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">For neutral systems (AT-9HE, AT-7HE, GC-9HE, Figs. 8, 9 and 13), the electrostatic term contribution is less then 1 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> and therefore the differences between the HF and MP2 derived charges are also rather insignificant.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In general, the A-ff86 empirical potential gives the best results in comparison to the reference <IT>ab initio</IT> calculated energies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The differences between the <IT>ab initio</IT> calculated energies and the A-ff86 (ESP-MP2) ones are always less than 1 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>, only for the AT-9HE and AT-7HE systems are closed to 2 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The performance of the LH empirical potential is also quite good, the worst results gives the A-ff99 empirical potential, where the differences for 3.15 Å are in the range 2–5.5 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Global minima search</HEADER><P><s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj13" novelty="New" advantage="None">For the AT–E+, AT–9HNME and GC–9AE+ systems, the global energy minima geometries were searched as was described above.</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod20" novelty="None" advantage="None">The A-ff86 empirical potential and the ESP-MP2 sets of charges were used for the search.</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Table 3 presents the number of minima found and the global energy minimum for each complex.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Figs. 14–16 present the global energy minima geometries for the three systems.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj14" novelty="New" advantage="None">For three arbitrary selected minima of each system, the energies of interaction were also recalculated <IT>ab initio</IT> and with the other empirical potentials.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results are summarised in Table 4.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The order of the interaction energies of the minima is the same for all the empirical potentials used but the order of the interaction energies calculated <IT>ab initio</IT> is different.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs20" novelty="None" advantage="None">For example for the AT–E+ system, the minimum 6 has the lowest <IT>ab initio</IT> calculated interaction energy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">These empirical potentials are not very suitable for the search of global energy minima geometries.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>The performance of the empirical potentials</HEADER><P><s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj15" novelty="New" advantage="None">Fig. 17 presents the correlation of the <IT>ab initio</IT> calculated interaction energies with the empirical potentials (with ESP-MP2 charges).</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The figure shows very good agreement between the <IT>ab initio</IT> method and the A-ff86 and LH force fields.</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs21" novelty="None" advantage="None">The maximal positive and negative deviations, the average absolute deviations, the slopes, intercepts and correlation coefficients for the three empirical potentials with the HF and MP2 derived atomic charges are presented in Table 5.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs22" novelty="None" advantage="None">The importance of the electrostatic energy term is illustrated in Fig. 18.</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj16" novelty="New" advantage="None">Fig. 18, left, presents the van der Waals term and Fig. 18, right, the total interaction energies calculated with the A-ff86 (ESP-MP2) force field for all intercalator-base pair systems studied.</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs23" novelty="None" advantage="None">One can see from Fig. 18 that the van der Waals term (dispersion energy) is almost the same for all systems, but the total interaction energy differs considerably (8 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>) according to the structure of the intercalator.</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">It means that the electrostatic term is crucial when drug–DNA interactions are calculated.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Conclusions</HEADER><P><s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">(i) The A-ff86 force field reproduced the <IT>ab initio</IT> calculated interaction energies very well.</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">This empirical potential takes into account only the electrostatic energy and the dispersion energy contributions, which means that the induction and charge transfer energy contribution are rather small.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">(ii) The ESP-DFT derived atomic charges give almost the same electrostatic energy as the charges derived from the MP2 wave function.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">(iii) The use of the RESP charges does not affect the magnitude of the interaction energy.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">(iv) The A-ff99 force field gave worse results then the A-ff86 one.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">It can be surprising that the older parameters (ff86) are better than the new parameters (ff99), but the ff99 parameters are designated for calculations with explicitly expressed water molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the other hand, the ff86 parameters were used for calculations in vacuum (as the <IT>ab initio</IT> calculations in this study are) and for calculations where the presence of solvent was simulated with distance dependent dielectric constant.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">(v) The LH force field also reproduced the <IT>ab initio</IT> interaction energies very well.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Especially good results were given by the LH force field for the twisted AT–E+ system.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None">(vi) The empirical potentials used in this study did not find the global energy minima geometries well.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The surface of the potential energy of stacked systems is quite flat<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6 cit19">6,19</REF> and the energy differences between minima are rather small.</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Small errors of the interaction energy calculations can cause bad order of the minima.</annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The doubts about the global energy minima geometries could resolve, for example, an NMR experiment.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
