<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b402410a" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Charge transfer through the nucleosome: a theoretical approach</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">In this work, we approach the problem of charge transfer in deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) from a theoretical and numerical perspective.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None">We focus on a DNA geometry characteristic of the eukaryotic genome and study transport along a superhelix that contains 292 nucleobases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The electronic structure is described within the Su–Schrieffer–Heeger model in an atomistic parameterization, which has been extended by a nonretarded reaction field to take dielectric polarization effects into account.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The emerging potential energy surface is analyzed using the Marcus theory of electron transfer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="New" advantage="None">The computed reaction coefficients are compared to their counterparts originating from idealized geometries and to experimental findings.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj5" novelty="New" advantage="None">This comparison and the palindromic nature of the DNA sequence used here permit the assessment of fluctuations in the local orientation of the bases and their impact upon transport properties.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="1.">Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Charge transfer in DNA has been a subject of considerable interest in recent years.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2 cit3 cit4">1–4</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition to potential sensor and nanoelectronics applications, it has been suggested that charge migration may provide new insight into the direction of mutations upon oxidative stress.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot3" novelty="None" advantage="None">This question is intimately related to the stability of the genome, its repair mechanism and the origin of molecular diseases emerging from DNA defects, including cancer.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">DNA charge transfer (CT) is now a well-established experimental effect.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Photochemical kinetic studies have been pioneered by Barton and coworkers by intercalating donor and acceptor molecules into the DNA macromolecule,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF> a technique that has now enabled investigations down to the femtosecond time scale.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Using an ingenious chemical approach, Giese and coworkers have oxidatively created holes in DNA and have studied their migration by an analysis of the products resulting from the consecutive reactions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Finally, DNA fixation between two nano-sized contacts permits the study of charge mobility upon the application of an external voltage.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">We note that photochemical charge separation, the creation of excess charges (which is equivalent to a doping process in the terminology of solid state physics) and transport measurements in nanodevices all address the same question, whether DNA can support rapid and long-range charge transfer, albeit in different time and energy regimes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Finally, there is now evidence that charge transfer is operative not only in carefully designed artificial DNA oligomers, but also in structures relevant to living organisms: Núñez <IT>et al.</IT> have been able to attach a rhodium intercalator to the 5′ end of a nucleosome core particle and have induced DNA damage more than 80 Å away from the site of the initial oxidation process.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Further evidence suggesting the possibility of <IT>in vivo</IT> charge transfer comes from long-range oxidative damage in whole nuclei.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">To describe the experiments of the Giese group, a phenomenological hopping model has been developed by Bixon <IT>et al</IT>.,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF> which rationalizes DNA hole transport in terms of interbase hopping and trapping.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">From this model, the following picture emerges: short-range transport occurs between the guanine bases, which act as traps due to their low oxidation potential; and intervening AT base pairs give rise to tunneling via a superexchange mechanism.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, adenine states may participate in long-range hopping processes.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">This phenomenological model has been substantiated by two recent numerical studies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Siriwong <IT>et al</IT>. have combined quantum chemical calculations and molecular dynamics simulations of a DNA oligomer.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">This approach gives access to the fluctuations of the reaction enthalpy Δ<IT>G</IT> and its origin due to potential energy fluctuations of the individual bases, which have been analysed qualitatively by these authors: potential energy fluctuations have a correlation time of 0.3 to 0.4 ns, and the local oxidation potentials of individual adenine and guanine may reverse at certain times and thus enable charge hopping.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">A similar gating process induced by solvent ion center-of-mass fluctuations has also been suggested by Schuster and Landman.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Recently, we have approached the problem of charge transfer using a chemically specific, atomistic Su–Schrieffer–Heeger model,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF> as detailed in the following section.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">This model addresses the question of charge trapping and hopping, and it permits the computation of the potential energy surface relevant to charge transfer using a single Hamiltonian.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">This surface can be analyzed using the Marcus theory of electron transfer and provides guanine–guanine nearest-neighbour and guanine–guanine superexchange charge transfer rates as a function of the sequence and the geometrical arrangement of the bases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">In addition, it effortlessly enables a quantitative description of the long-range adenine–adenine hopping mechanism.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Here, we will use this model to approach the question of charge transfer in an arrangement of nucleobases that is typical for complex organisms, the nucleosome core particle (NCP), as studied experimentally by Núñez <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The remaining part of our work is organized as follows.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj6" novelty="New" advantage="None">In the next section, we present the model Hamiltonian and the underlying geometry.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj7" novelty="New" advantage="None">Results, in particular hopping rates, are presented in the third section.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj7" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">They are discussed with reference to ideal DNA geometries and considering the palindromic nature of the DNA sequence at hand, thus enabling the assessment of the role of nonideal geometries and fluctuations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Conclusions are derived in the final section.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.">Model and methods</HEADER><P><s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Chromatine DNA is organized in nucleosomes, highly conserved nucleoprotein complexes that contain 145–147 base pairs wrapped around an octameric protein core.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">In eukaryotic organisms, nucleosomes occur every 200 ± 40 base pairs throughout the genome.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The geometry of our model is based on the NCP X-ray crystal structure obtained by Luger <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF>. with a 2.8 Å resolution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">A graphical representation of this complex is shown in Fig. 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">It contains 146 base pairs, organized in the form of a helix, which is wrapped around the histone octamer in 1.65 turns of a left-handed superhelix.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The nucleic acid sequence corresponds to human α satellite DNA, it is given in the appendix.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although the sequence is palindromic, the nucleoprotein complex does not reflect this symmetry, a fact that becomes important once the geometry dependence of charge transfer rates is considered.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Inspecting the temperature factors, it is found that the protein octamer exhibits a considerable degree of rigidity, whereas the DNA part is comparatively flexible, a statement that holds in particular for the outer bases not directly connected to the protein.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">As an ideal reference geometry, we have used a model of the DNA B form with an identical sequence generated by the NUCLEIC program of Ponder’s TINKER suite.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">In its default form, it corresponds to the bulk structure of DNA fibres with a low salt content.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod11" novelty="None" advantage="None">We assume that the nucleobases with their high-energy frontier molecular orbitals dominate the charge transport properties, and we hence neglect the deoxyribose units, the phosphates and the protein part of the complex beyond their role of providing a scaffold for the base pairs.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod12" novelty="None" advantage="None">As the isolated bases are planar and the interbase tight-binding matrix elements are small, the σ–π-separation approximately holds, and theories of the chemical bond approriate to π systems can be applied.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod13" novelty="None" advantage="None">A highly successful atomistic model suitable to the description of charge transport in systems that are dominated by π-electron frontier molecular orbitals has been presented in the seminal work of Su, Schrieffer and Heeger (SSH).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Its potential energy part incorporates a classical harmonic interaction between two atoms <IT>i</IT> and <IT>j</IT> and a distance-dependent tight-binding matrix element that gives rise to linear electron–phonon coupling:The deviation of the distance between a pair of atoms from that of a single bond is denoted by <IT>x</IT><SB><IT>ij</IT></SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The <IT>k</IT><SB><IT>ij</IT></SB> are the corresponding force constants, the <IT>t</IT>0<IT>ij</IT> the tight-binding matrix elements and the <IT>α</IT><SB><IT>ij</IT></SB> the electron-phonon coupling constants.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod16" novelty="None" advantage="None">For these parameters, we use the standard values of SSH.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Usually, the interactions are restricted to covalently bonded nearest neighbours, and the constants <IT>k</IT> and <IT>α</IT> do not depend on <IT>i</IT> and <IT>j</IT>; an approach that we have followed here.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The low-energy twisting modes of the nucleobases are not taken into account.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The <IT>a</IT>†<IT>i</IT>/<IT>a</IT><SB><IT>j</IT></SB> are the creation and annihilation operators acting on a basis of carbon 2p<SB><IT>z</IT></SB> atomic orbitals, which is assumed to be orthogonal.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod20" novelty="None" advantage="None">We note that <IT>a</IT>†<IT>i</IT><IT>a</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB> = <IT>n</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB>, which is the number operator and that <IT>n</IT><SB><IT>ij</IT></SB> = <IT>a</IT>†<IT>i</IT><IT>a</IT><SB><IT>j</IT></SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod21" novelty="None" advantage="None">The expectation value of the latter is equal to the bond order.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod22" novelty="None" advantage="None">The nuclear coordinates and momenta are treated as classical quantities.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">With each base pair represented by a single site, Conwell and Rakhmanova have applied the SSH model to study the formation of DNA polarons and their mobility upon the application of an external field.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19">19</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac20" novelty="None" advantage="None">Recently, we have extended the standard SSH model by the following elements.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod23" novelty="None" advantage="None">To account for the heterocyclic character of the nucleobases, diagonal parameters <IT>t</IT><SB><IT>ii</IT></SB> for oxygen and nitrogen atoms have been introduced.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod24" novelty="None" advantage="None">Interbase coupling has been considered <IT>via</IT> additional distance-dependent tight-binding matrix elements <IT>t</IT><SB><IT>ij</IT></SB>(<IT>r</IT>), and the nucleobases may exhibit an arbitrary orientation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod25" novelty="None" advantage="None">The parameters beyond those of the standard SSH model have been obtained by a careful fit to <IT>ab initio</IT> quantum chemical calculations and to the experimental oxidation potentials.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod26" novelty="None" advantage="None">Outer sphere degrees of freedom have been incorporated into the Hamiltonian by a nonretarded reaction field, which is based upon a straightforward extension of the Marcus model of two cavities that are dispersed in a dielectric medium.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod27" novelty="None" advantage="None">The outer sphere reorganization energy can be written as:Here, <IT>ε</IT><SB>∞</SB> and <IT>ε</IT><SB>s</SB> denote the high-frequency and the static limits of the dielectric response function, the <IT>σ</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB> are particle diameters and the <IT>r</IT><SB><IT>ij</IT></SB> the interparticle distances.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod28" novelty="None" advantage="None">Whenever fast and slow time scales can be separated, the charge differences Δ<IT>z</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB> can be replaced by the corresponding number operators <IT>n</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB> − <IT>n̄</IT><SB><IT>i</IT>,0</SB>, and the model turns into the interaction part of the so-called attractive Hubbard Hamiltonian.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod29" novelty="None" advantage="None">As reference charges <IT>n̄</IT><SB><IT>i</IT>,0</SB>, we use the atomic tight-binding charge orders of the neutral nucleobases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod30" novelty="None" advantage="None">As in the tight-binding part of the SSH model, we consider the long-range Coulomb interactions as being absorbed into effective parameters.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod31" novelty="None" advantage="None">To enable an efficient numerical mean-field treatment, the SSH Hamiltonian has been transformed by the introduction of a displaced phonon coordinateto decouple nuclear and electronic degrees of freedom.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25 cit22">25,22</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod32" novelty="None" advantage="None">The resulting mean-field restricted Hartree–Fock expression that combines the polaron-transformed eqn. (2.1) and the reaction field eqn. (2.2) reads:<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF>We apply the usual corrections for counting the electron–electron interaction twice.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod33" novelty="None" advantage="None">The overbar denotes the expectation values taken within a self-consistent field iterative calculation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod34" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Hamiltonian eqn. (2.4) only depends on the tight-binding parameters <IT>t</IT><SB><IT>ij</IT></SB>, the diagonal Hubbard parameter <IT>U</IT><SB>d</SB>, both as given in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">ref. 15</REF>, and its off-diagonal counterpart <IT>U</IT><SB><IT>ij</IT></SB>, which equals <IT>α</IT><SP>2</SP>/2<IT>k</IT> = 0.32 eV for covalently bonded atoms in the original SSH parameterization used here<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF> and is set to zero otherwise.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod35" novelty="None" advantage="None">As this value provides an excellent fit for SSH model nucleobase π-orbital energies and HOMO shapes to their <IT>ab initio</IT> density functional counterparts,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF> there is no necessity to introduce additional bond-specific parameters for matrix elements within the bases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod36" novelty="None" advantage="None">We note, however, that the one-electron matrix element for a carbon–nitrogen bond has been set to a smaller value than that of a carbon–carbon bond, <IT>t</IT><SB>CN</SB> = 0.8<IT>t</IT><SB>NN</SB>, as customary in π-electron theories.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod37" novelty="None" advantage="None">In our model, the <IT>U</IT><SB>d</SB> parameter describes the local strengths of a reaction field that describes the interaction with all polarization degrees of freedom (and hence mainly represents outer sphere contributions) the <IT>U</IT><SB><IT>ij</IT></SB> represent the locally transformed electron-phonon coupling and vibrational terms, <IT>i.e.</IT> the inner sphere reorganization degrees of freedom.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">These contributions are treated on the same footing and are incorporated into the same Hamiltonian, a fact that is not only aesthetically pleasing (at least for a theorist), but also enables an efficient solution of the emerging self-consistent field problem.</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Effective reorganization energies stemming from these terms, as extracted from the potential energy surface, roughly contribute to the total reorganization energy in an equal weight.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">One has to keep in mind that the polarization terms, as interpreted here, also include intramolecular charge deformation effects, which are automatically taken into account in quantum chemical calculations even in the absence of a reaction field.</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hence, quantum chemical inner sphere reorganization energies are usually larger than those extracted from our model.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit31">31</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Inner and outer sphere terms on their own provide the qualitatively correct picture of hole localization on guanine and guanine–guanine hopping, whereas the corresponding hopping rates are overestimated by two orders of magnitude and long-range hopping via intervening adenines is absent.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">A quantitative description requires both terms, as present here.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj8" novelty="New" advantage="None">The model Hamiltonian has been carefully parameterized using state of the art quantum chemical calculations and experimental oxidation potentials.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj8" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">It provides the correct functional dependence of the hopping rates upon the interbase separation and the location of the crossover regime between the superexchange and the adenine–adenine hopping mechanism.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Short-range hopping rates lie close to the upper limit of their experimental counterparts, as expected for reaction coefficients obtained from a model geometry with perfectly ordered base stacking.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">For example, we find <IT>k</IT><SB>CT</SB> = 8 × 10<SP>11</SP> s<SP>−1</SP> for a transfer between two guanines separated by one A–T pair, as compared to experimental values of 10<SP>10</SP>–10<SP>11</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF> and long-range adenine–adenine hopping rates are of the order of <IT>k</IT><SB>CT</SB> ≃ 10<SP>4</SP>–10<SP>5</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj8" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">Providing full variational control, superexchange CT rates can be computed without taking refuge to perturbation theory, which can only be applied in the small coupling regime.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj8" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">The Marcus parameters, effective inner and outer sphere reorganization energy, the tunnel splitting and the driving force of the reaction, can be computed within a <IT>single</IT> model and computation rather than from separate calculations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj8" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">We are not aware of any atomistic calculations that predict these parameters for systems with a number of nucleobases that even comes close to the 292 studied here.</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj8" novelty="New" advantage="No">As drawbacks of our model, we first consider the nonretarded approximation that relies on the proper separability of fast and slow reaction field degrees of freedom; for a more detailed discussion see <IT>e.g</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28 cit29">refs. 28,29</REF>..</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj8" novelty="New" advantage="No">Second, <IT>U</IT><SB>d</SB> remains a quantity not easily parameterized, but it is expected to lie in a small energy interval, 0.8 eV ≤ <IT>U</IT><SB>d</SB> ≤ 1.2 eV.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In that interval, the reorganization energy shows a linear dependence on the reaction field strength.</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">For a typical model, we find <IT>λ</IT> = 0.45, 0.48, 0.52, 0.57 and 0.61 eV for <IT>U</IT><SB>d</SB> = 0.8, 0.9, 1.0, 1.1 and 1.2 eV, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have found a similar linear dependence of the reorganization energy upon <IT>U</IT><SB><IT>ij</IT></SB> = <IT>α</IT>2<IT>ij</IT>/2<IT>k</IT><SB><IT>ij</IT></SB> with a proportionality constant smaller than unity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj8" novelty="New" advantage="No">Third, entropy contributions are not considered within our model.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.">Results and discussion</HEADER><P><s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj9" novelty="New" advantage="None">The results presented in this section originate from the numerical solution of the mean-field approach to the polaron-transformed extended Su–Schrieffer–Heeger Hamiltonian, as given in eqn. (2.4).</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod38" novelty="None" advantage="None">The electronic structure problem contains 2774 atoms and, in its nonoxidised form, 3604 electrons.</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Starting from the charge and bond orders that are characteristic of the isolated nucleobases or their cations, the convergence of the SCF algorithm is fast and unambiguous.</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Due to their small oxidation potentials, excess positive charges localize solely on guanine bases, and every guanine acts as a potential center of charge localization, <IT>i.e.</IT> there are as many SCF minima as guanines.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Which center actually becomes a charge trap depends on the initial conditions of the SCF procedure.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj10" novelty="New" advantage="None">To provide a graphical impression of the charge distribution associated with DNA polaron formation, we return to Fig. 1, which was used above to visualize the structure of the nucleosome core particle.</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">We display the results of a calculation involving twelve positive charges, which localize on guanines separated far enough from each other to treat the corresponding centers of localization as non-interacting.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The excess positive charges are drawn in a linear representation, ranging from light grey (maximum charge) to dark grey (no excess charge).</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Self-trapping and the associated strong charge localization within the extended Su–Schrieffer–Heeger model are evident from the figure; each positive charge is mainly confined to a single guanine base with smaller contributions on neighbouring base pairs.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Details of the localization properties depend on the local environment, G<SB>2</SB> doublets give rise to a slightly higher degree of delocalization.</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac21" novelty="None" advantage="None">Strong hole localization with a half-width of the excess charge distribution of about one nucleobase is also found within the simpler SSH implementation of Conwell and coworkers, where one site represents a nucleobase and outer sphere reorganization terms are not taken into account.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19">19</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac22" novelty="None" advantage="None">The spatial extent of the highest occupied molecular orbital has been computed by Schuster and Landman within a quantum chemical approach using MD geometries.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac23" novelty="None" advantage="None">As the HOMO is populated by the excess hole charge, the size of this orbital, which extends over two neighbouring guanine basis, provides an estimate of charge localization.</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac24" novelty="None" advantage="None">We note, however, that in this manner inner and outer sphere polarization effects due to the introduction of the excess charge are not taken into account.</annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac25" novelty="None" advantage="None">These effects will lead to further trapping and induce additional charge localization.</annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac26" novelty="None" advantage="None">A finite-difference approach to the Poisson equation in combination with quantum chemical calculations has been used by Kurnikov <IT>et al.</IT> to estimate the size of the excess charge.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30">30</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac26" novelty="None" advantage="None">These authors find hole localization within one to three consecutive guanines.</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac27" novelty="None" advantage="None">Using quantum chemical calculations to parameterize a simple model of hole localization, Olofsson and Larsson have found charge trapping on a single guanine for nonperiodic arrangements of nucleobases,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit31">31</REF> in agreement with EPR experiments.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit32">32</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac27" novelty="None" advantage="None">We note that in the Olofsson–Larsson model, a small fraction of periodic sequences not containing guanine exhibit a delocalized behaviour.</annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">As the nucleosome sequence used in our work is deterministic, but not periodic and as it contains guanine, these findings do not contradict our results.</annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod39" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is possible to take temperature effects into account by applying Fermi–Dirac statistics to the orbital populations within the self-consistent field approach used here (<IT>T</IT> = 300 K).</annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The spatial extent of the polarons does not change significantly.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">In Fig. 2, we display the corresponding density of states.</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The energy levels obtained from the diagonalization of the converged SSH matrix have been broadened by a Gaussian function with a root mean square deviation of 0.2 eV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac28" novelty="None" advantage="None">We may refer to clusters of the thus broadened levels as bands, as frequently encountered in the terminology of the solid-state sciences not only for translationally invariant, but also for disordered systems.</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The occupied <IT>π</IT> orbitals – or the valence band states – are located in a broad energy interval of ∼8 eV, which is in accord with the range of energies encountered in <IT>ab initio</IT> density functional calculations on the isolated bases.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the absence of excess charges, the valence band and the conduction band are separated by an energy gap of ∼3 eV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Upon oxidation, the Fermi level is shifted into the top of the valence band.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, we depict in Fig. 2 the partial density of states with respect to all guanines and to the particular guanine base on which polarons are centered.</annotationART></s> <s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod40" novelty="None" advantage="None">The partial DOS (PDOS) is computed by weighting the eigenstates <IT>E</IT><SB><IT>a</IT></SB> by the molecular orbital expansion coefficients <IT>c</IT><SB><IT>ia</IT></SB>, where <IT>i</IT> refers to the site and <IT>a</IT> to the index of the molecular orbital.</annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod41" novelty="None" advantage="None">The PDOS emerging from the eigenstate <IT>a</IT> is given bywhere the prime indicates the restriction of the sum over <IT>i</IT> to the atomic orbitals of interest.</annotationART></s> <s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Eigenstates at the top of the valence band are dominated by guanine contributions which consequently are the first to be populated by excess holes upon oxidation, as seen by the partial density of states corresponding to charged guanines.</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">For singly oxidised cations, only the relative weight of the polaron state changes with respect to the bulk of the density of states.</annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast to related models of inorganic polymers<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26">26</REF> and hyperbranched organic macromolecules<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27">27</REF> with a strong contribution of <IT>π</IT> orbitals to the valence band, no well-separated impurity band exists in the SSH model of the DNA.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod42" novelty="None" advantage="None">The mean-field Hamiltonian, eqn. (2.4), gives access to the entire potential energy surface as a function of the charge and the bond orders.</annotationART></s> <s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac29" novelty="None" advantage="None">For small molecules, the energy of the system can be computed as a function of all relevant density matrix elements, leading to the potential energy surface of the charge transfer reaction.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28 cit29">28,29</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod43" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the large systems studied here, this approach is not feasible, and we apply the linear synchronous transit approximation, as advocated by Clark and coworkers for electron transfer reactions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit33">33</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj11" novelty="New" advantage="None">For a singly charged DNA macromolecule, we compute all possible basins of attraction for the SCF procedure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Their number is given by the number of guanines in the system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj12" novelty="New" advantage="None">For two adjacent minima A and B we have calculated the corresponding density matrices.</annotationART></s> <s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod44" novelty="None" advantage="None">With <IT>n̄</IT><SB><IT>ii</IT></SB> ≡ <IT>n̄</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB>, these matrices can be written as {<IT>n̄</IT><SB>A,1,1</SB>, <IT>n̄</IT><SB>A,1,2</SB>...<IT>n̄</IT><SB>A,<IT>N</IT>−1,<IT>N</IT></SB>, <IT>n̄</IT><SB>A,<IT>N</IT>,<IT>N</IT></SB>} and {<IT>n̄</IT><SB>B,1,1</SB>, <IT>n̄</IT><SB>B,1,2</SB>…<IT>n̄</IT><SB>B,<IT>N</IT>−1,<IT>N</IT></SB>, <IT>n̄</IT><SB>B,<IT>N</IT>,<IT>N</IT></SB>}, where the last two indices refer to the atomic orbitals that form the localized AO basis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod45" novelty="None" advantage="None">We then scan the potential energy surface along the cross-section given by <IT>n̄</IT><SB><IT>i</IT>,<IT>j</IT>,int</SB> = <IT>αn̄</IT><SB><IT>i</IT>,<IT>j</IT>,A</SB> + (1 − <IT>α</IT>)<IT>n̄</IT><SB><IT>i</IT>,<IT>j</IT>,B</SB>, where the linear interpolation parameter <IT>α</IT> serves as a reaction coordinate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod46" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this scan, <IT>α</IT> varies between zero and unity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj13" novelty="New" advantage="None">We now consider conduction paths connecting a series of such minima.</annotationART></s> <s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod47" novelty="None" advantage="None">Then the transfer can be visualized as a series of consecutive hops between neighbouring minima, in which <IT>α</IT> increases by one at each elementary transfer step.</annotationART></s> <s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod48" novelty="None" advantage="None">We call this scheme the linear synchronous transit (LST) approach; it corresponds to the computation of a cross-section of the total potential energy surface.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" advantage="None">In Fig. 3, we display the LST potential energy surface for eight consecutive hops in the center of the nucleosome DNA.</annotationART></s> <s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod49" novelty="None" advantage="None">We proceed to show that from this figure the energy parameters relevant to the Marcus two-site theory of charge transfer can be extracted.</annotationART></s> <s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod50" novelty="None" advantage="None">These are the activation barrier <IT>E</IT><SB>A</SB>, the electronic tunnel splitting <IT>t</IT>, the reorganization energy <IT>λ</IT> and the thermodynamic driving force of the reaction, Δ<IT>G</IT>, which is here approximated as Δ<IT>U</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs19" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the DNA sequence studied here, activation barriers range from 68 o 127 meV, and we may estimate the associated reorganization energies as <IT>λ</IT> ≃ 400 meV, with an equal contribution of inner and outer sphere terms.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="143"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs20" novelty="None" advantage="None">The driving force, Δ<IT>U</IT>, becomes as large as 60 meV and depends on the number of consecutive guanines.</annotationART></s> <s sid="144"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs21" novelty="None" advantage="None">Interestingly, no stabilization of polarons located within guanine doublets was observed for the sequentially identical ideal B DNA used as a reference (Δ<IT>U</IT> &lt; 10 meV).</annotationART></s> <s sid="145"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac30" novelty="None" advantage="None">We note that G<SB>2</SB> is the largest guanine cluster within the satellite DNA studied here, and that estimates of the stabilization of guanine <IT>triplets</IT> with reference to isolated bases range from 80 meV (photochemical experiments<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit34">34</REF>) over 130 meV (semiempirical calulations<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit35">35</REF>) to 680 meV (<IT>ab initio</IT> values<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit36">36</REF>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="146"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">At the LST transition states – roughly located halfway between two consecutive SCF minima – the donor and the acceptor potential energy surface experience an electronic coupling; the ground state and the excited state are separated by an energy that equals twice the effective electronic tunnel splitting <IT>t</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="147"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod51" novelty="None" advantage="None">Using a bisection algorithm, <IT>t</IT> is located at the reaction coordinate value corresponding to the minimum energetic separation between the ground and the excited state following the LST reaction path through the entire potential surface, which is shown in parts in Fig. 3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="148"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs22" novelty="None" advantage="None">Within the framework of the model, <IT>t</IT> is determined with machine precision <IT>ε</IT><SB><IT>M</IT></SB> = 10<SP>−12</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="149"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The magnitude of the tunnel splitting depends on the distance between the two guanine bases which mainly participate in the charge transfer process, their mutual orientation and the nature and orientation of the intervening bases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="150"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The distance-dependence can be associated with the number of A–T base pairs intervening the two guanines and is immediately evident from Fig. 3: charge transfers between nearest neighbours (G78 → G214, G87 → G205 and G205 → G204) exhibit an energy gap of at least 60 meV, whereas the transfer G204 → G94 with four intervening adenines is associated with a tunnel splitting of 1.9 × 10<SP>−3</SP> meV, a number too small to be resolved within the figure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="151"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj14" novelty="New" advantage="None">The impact of orientational degrees of freedom upon <IT>t</IT> will be discussed below.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="152"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Due to the palindromic nature of the DNA sequence considered here, an effective electronic coupling <IT>t</IT> only depending on the number of A-T pairs intervening two guanines would give rise to identical tunnel splittings, and thus identical reaction rates, following the sequence along the forward 5′ → 3′ or the backward 3′ → 5′ path.</annotationART></s> <s sid="153"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj15" novelty="New" advantage="None">To test this conjecture, we have plotted in Fig. 4 the backward tunnel splitting (<IT>t</IT>′) as a function of its forward (<IT>t</IT>) counterpart.</annotationART></s> <s sid="154"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Deviations from a purely sequence-controlled behaviour are as large as three orders of magnitude, they highlight the influence of the local geometry upon <IT>t</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="155"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs23" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the ideal B form reference geometry, on the other hand, forward and backward tunnel splitting are almost identical, as also shown in Fig. 4.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="156"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj16" novelty="New" advantage="None">With an analysis of the charge transfer potential energy surface performed as described above, we are able to estimate the corresponding reaction coefficients using Marcus’ expression for charge transfer,Here, we have absorbed Δ<IT>U</IT> into the activation energies and thus use different barriers for forward and backward charge transfer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="157"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs24" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reaction coefficients are plotted as a function of the minimum interbase distance (referring to nonhydrogen atoms only) in Fig. 5.</annotationART></s> <s sid="158"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Again, for a given interbase distance, roughly corresponding to the number of intervening adenines, fluctuations are large; and the three orders of magnitude in <IT>t</IT> visible in Fig. 4 now translate into six orders of magnitude in <IT>k</IT><SB>CT</SB> due to the quadratic appearence of the further in eqn. (3.2).</annotationART></s> <s sid="159"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Again, fluctuations in <IT>k</IT><SB>CT</SB> for the ideal B form are considerably smaller and well obey the Marcus–Levich–Jortner relation, <IT>k</IT><SB>CT</SB> ≈ exp(−<IT>βr</IT>), with <IT>β</IT> = 1.38 ± 0.11 Å<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="160"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">We note that nonadiabaticity corrections may become necessary for very fast rates, which will mainly effect hopping between nearest-neighbour guanines.</annotationART></s> <s sid="161"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod52" novelty="None" advantage="None">The corresponding <IT>k</IT><SB>CT</SB> values are not included in the analysis performed here, as they are not relevant to charge transfer within a longer nonrepeating DNA sequence, where other hopping processes constitute the rate-limiting steps.</annotationART></s> <s sid="162"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs25" novelty="None" advantage="None">For a given interbase distance, <IT>k</IT><SB>CT</SB> values strongly cluster around a value typical for the ideal geometry, and only few extremely slow processes exist.</annotationART></s> <s sid="163"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">This behaviour suggests a strongly peaked charge transfer rate distribution function with a long tail towards small hopping rates.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="164"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Do the fluctuations in <IT>k</IT><SB>CT</SB> prevent the accurate computation of DNA charge transfer properties?</annotationART></s> <s sid="165"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj17" novelty="New" advantage="None">To address this question, we have to inspect the time scales associated with the transport processes and compare them to those of the internal dynamics of the nucleosome.</annotationART></s> <s sid="166"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac31" novelty="None" advantage="None">For free nucleosides, the effective reorientation correlation time, <IT>τ</IT><SB>eff</SB>, for rotations around the desoxyribose-nucelobase bond is of the order of 100 ps, as attested by <SP>2</SP>H NMR studies.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit37">37</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="167"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac32" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hartree–Fock <IT>ab initio</IT> computations of the electronic tunnel splitting between two adjacent A–T pairs based upon snapshots from a classical molecular dynamics simulations of a decamer also suggest a correlation time for this quantity that is smaller than 100 ps.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit38">38</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="168"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod53" novelty="None" advantage="None">We consider this time scale as an order-of-magnitude estimate for those degrees of freedom that correspond to nucleobase reorientations within the DNA macromolecule, in particular for those not tightly bound to the protein.</annotationART></s> <s sid="169"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs26" novelty="None" advantage="None">Whenever these reorientations are fast compared to the inverse charge transfer rates computed for individual frozen disorder realizations, the charge transfer process experiences a Boltzmann-weighted average of all possible mutual orientations of the nucleobases involved.</annotationART></s> <s sid="170"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">As seen in Fig. 5, this averaging process is required for all transfers between guanines that are separated by more than one adenine and for a considerable fraction of transfers between next-nearest neighbours.</annotationART></s> <s sid="171"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs27" novelty="None" advantage="None">Those pairs of guanines that are characterized by a small charge transfer rate either exhibit the highest temperature factor altogether (G63 ⇌ G233 [a], the small letters refer to Fig. 5) or they cluster in a small region of the nucleosome with isotropic temperature factors larger than 10<SP>−2</SP> Å (G98 ⇌ G100 [b], G103 ⇌ G192 [c] and G268 ⇌ G271 [d]).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="172"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj18" novelty="New" advantage="None">Finally, we turn to the analysis of the charge transfer kinetics using the reaction coefficients computed above both for the X-ray structure (that reflects orientational disorder) and the ideal realization.</annotationART></s> <s sid="173"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod54" novelty="None" advantage="None">We consider the processG290 ⇌ G284 ⇌ G283 ⇌ G281 ⇌ G280 ⇌ G15 ⇌…,which can be described by a set of coupled linear homogenous first-order differential equations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="174"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod55" novelty="None" advantage="None">The individual equations that specify the change of the hole populations <IT>P</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB> with time <IT>t</IT> at the now sequentially renumbered guanines read:<IT>Ṗ</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB>(<IT>t</IT>) = <IT>k</IT><SB><IT>i</IT>−1,<IT>i</IT></SB><IT>P</IT><SB><IT>i</IT>−1</SB>(<IT>t</IT>) − (<IT>k</IT><SB><IT>i</IT>,<IT>i</IT>+1</SB> + <IT>k</IT><SB><IT>i</IT>,<IT>i</IT>−1</SB>) <IT>P</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB>(<IT>t</IT>) + <IT>k</IT><SB><IT>i</IT>+1,<IT>i</IT></SB><IT>P</IT><SB><IT>i</IT>+1</SB>(<IT>t</IT>).We make the familiar <IT>ansatz P</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB>(<IT>t</IT>) = <IT>p</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB> exp (<IT>λt</IT>), where <IT>p</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB> is independent of <IT>t</IT>, and arrive at the eigenvalue problem(<B><IT>K</IT></B> − <B><IT>λ</IT></B><B>1</B>)<IT>p⃑</IT> = 0⃑,which leads to the eigenvalues <IT>λ</IT><SB><IT>α</IT></SB> and the eigenvectors <IT>p⃑</IT><SB><IT>α</IT></SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="175"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod56" novelty="None" advantage="None">Here, <B><IT>K</IT></B> denotes the tridiagonal matrix of reaction coefficients, <IT>k</IT><SB><IT>i</IT>,<IT>j</IT></SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="176"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod57" novelty="None" advantage="None">The populations as a function of time are given by:where the coefficients <IT>A</IT><SB><IT>α</IT></SB> are computed to match the initial conditions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="177"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs28" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that <IT>λ</IT><SB><IT>α</IT></SB> ≤ 0 ∀ <IT>α</IT> with a largest eigenvalue identical to zero in the absence of trapping.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="178"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac33" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the experiments of Núñez <IT>et al</IT>.,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF> a rhodium complex was attached to the 5′ end of the DNA (see Appendix for the sequence).</annotationART></s> <s sid="179"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac34" novelty="None" advantage="None">Upon irradiation, consecutive DNA cleavage has been found only for GG clusters, but not for single guanines.</annotationART></s> <s sid="180"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs29" novelty="None" advantage="None">As the first candidates for a cleavage reaction within the sequence, we have GG1 (the G284, G283 pair), GG2 (G281, G280), GG3 (G275 and an exchanged T274 not considered here, fact that does not influence the transport properties due to the small distance to G271), GG4 (G268, G267) and GG5 (G39, GG40).</annotationART></s> <s sid="181"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs30" novelty="None" advantage="None">DNA fragmentation has been observed up to GG4, whereas no indication for a cleavage at GG5 has been detected.</annotationART></s> <s sid="182"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">Consequently, charge transfer processes in the nucleosome have a range of ∼24 base pairs or 80 Å.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="183"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj19" novelty="New" advantage="None">We now solve the kinetic scheme 3.4 for the first 42 base pairs with the initial condition of charge localization on GG1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="184"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod58" novelty="None" advantage="None">The probabilities of finding a hole charge on one of the GG clusters is computed using eqn. (3.6) and displayed in Fig. 6 for GG2, GG4 and GG5.</annotationART></s> <s sid="185"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs31" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both for the X-ray and the ideal structure, GG2 is rapidly populated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="186"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs32" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the ideal structure, a notable population of GG4 begins to show at 10<SP>−9</SP> to 10<SP>−8</SP> s, whereas the population of GG5 is delayed until 10<SP>−4</SP> s due to five A-T pairs preceding this cluster.</annotationART></s> <s sid="187"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">Reaction coefficients for trapping and oxidation processes are estimated to lie in the 10<SP>8</SP> to 10<SP>9</SP> s<SP>−1</SP> range,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF> which is compatible with DNA cleavage for GG1 to GG4 and its absence for GG5.</annotationART></s> <s sid="188"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs33" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the X-ray structure, on the other hand, a small <IT>k</IT><SB>CT</SB> = 31 s<SP>−1</SP> for the reaction G271 → G268 is computed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="189"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs34" novelty="None" advantage="None">This transfer involves two intervening adenines, the process is also labelled in Fig. 5 (data points [d]) and discussed above.</annotationART></s> <s sid="190"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">It delays the onset of the GG4 population until 10<SP>−4</SP> to 10<SP>−3</SP> s, a process considerably slower than the oxidation of GG3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="191"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">In summary, our calculations for an ideal structure, corresponding to averaged reaction coefficients, <IT>cf.</IT> Fig. 5, are fully compatible with the experiment, whereas a naive calculation based on a X-ray structure fails to do so.</annotationART></s> <s sid="192"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" advantage="None">These findings substantiate the need for an averaging of the conductivity over disorder realizations for slow DNA charge transport processes.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="193"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj20" novelty="New" advantage="None">In addition to CT along the DNA sequence, we have also considered through-space hopping.</annotationART></s> <s sid="194"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod59" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although nucleobases that are far apart sequentially may come as close as 15 Å due to the superhelical structure of the DNA, the corresponding through-space couplings can be neglected.</annotationART></s> <s sid="195"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs35" novelty="None" advantage="None">The emerging rate coefficients amount to a maximum of 10<SP>−5</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>; and although the corresponding pathes provide a significant shortcut, this mechanism is severly outperformed by sequential CT.</annotationART></s> <s sid="196"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None">As a final remark, we note that the differential eqn. (3.4) can be solved for CT through the entire DNA sequence, leading to a time scale of ∼100 ms regardless of the averaging process.</annotationART></s> <s sid="197"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None">This transport process does, of course, require the complete absence of trapping or oxidative side reactions.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.">Conclusions</HEADER><P><s sid="198"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj21" novelty="New" advantage="None">In this work, we have addressed the problem of charge transfer through the nucleosome using a theoretical and numerical approach.</annotationART></s> <s sid="199"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj22" novelty="New" advantage="None">The DNA sequence and geometry are based on a structure relevant to the human genome; its selection has been motivated by a recent experimental CT study on this system.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="200"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot4" novelty="None" advantage="None">As the subject of DNA charge transfer is now changing its status from an, albeit very interesting, laboratory curiosity to a process observable <IT>in vivo</IT>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF> we are faced with a quest for theories and computational methods that can describe transport processes in complex biosystems in a chemically specific manner.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="201"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj23" novelty="New" advantage="None">As recently suggested,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF> we apply a chemically specific, atomistic Su–Schrieffer–Heeger Hamiltonian to compute potential energy surfaces relevant to charge transfer in a large and complex arrangement of 292 nucleobases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="202"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj24" novelty="New" advantage="None">From a linear synchronous transit approximation to the potential energy surface, the energy parameters relevant to the Marcus theory of electron transfer have been extracted, and we have been able to directly compute reaction coefficients for superexchange processes between polarons localized on guanine bases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="203"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj25" novelty="New" advantage="None">Utilizing the palindromic nature of the DNA sequence, we have assessed the role of local geometry distortions, which lead to strong fluctuations in the effective electronic tunnel splittings <IT>t</IT> and reaction coefficients <IT>k</IT><SB>CT</SB>, as compared to their counterparts obtained from an idealized DNA geometry.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="204"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">As <SP>2</SP>H NMR studies<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit37">37</REF> and computer simulations<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit38">38</REF> suggest correlation times for orientational disorder on the 100 ps scale, we advocate that reaction coefficients for hopping processes that proceed on a slower time scale have to be the subject of an averaging over orientations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="205"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">This corresponds to an averaging over reaction coefficients that originate from CT between guanines that show a comparable interbase distance and local environment; the thus computed rates reproduce the experimental findings of Núñez <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF>. for charge transfer between GG clusters: Within our computations we find that the excess hole charge is transferred along the nucleosome with a superexchange mechanism comparable to charge transfer in much smaller DNA fragments that are unprotected by proteins.</annotationART></s> <s sid="206"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">This transport process enables the consecutive cleavage reactions that predominantly occur at GG clusters.</annotationART></s> <s sid="207"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Assuming a cleavage rate of 10<SP>8</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF> the excess charge can be transferred to the first four GG clusters, but is – according to our calculations – entirely trapped before even a small fraction populates GG5.</annotationART></s> <s sid="208"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">This finding is again in accord with the experiment, as the largest fragment found upon irradiation extends only up to GG4.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="209"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Concerning the biochemistry of oxidative stress in eukaryotic DNA, the following implications can be derived from experiments and our model.</annotationART></s> <s sid="210"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">DNA that is not coordinated to histone proteins, as it may either lie within an interhistone sequence or is in the stage of mitosis, is in danger of ubiquitous oxidization.</annotationART></s> <s sid="211"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">DNA coordinated to the histone proteins, on the other hand, is protected from a direct chemical reaction with oxidants like the usual DNA intercalators; in their presence, no DNA cleavage is observed deep within the histone-coordinated sequence.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="212"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Nevertheless, charge transfer from an unprotected DNA segment, to which the intercalators bind, into the nucleosome occurs and finally damages the double helix.</annotationART></s> <s sid="213"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The location of this damage depends on the sequence of the DNA, the corresponding transfer rates can be computed from our model.</annotationART></s> <s sid="214"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None">As it can be applied to arbitrary geometries without the need of a reparametrization, it allows, unlike purely phenomenological theories, the calculation of CT rates in more complex systems, including DNA junctions and strongly intercalating proteins.</annotationART></s> <s sid="215"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The range of systems that we have studied up to now is, of course, limited.</annotationART></s> <s sid="216"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although the results obtained for charge transfer in isolated oligomers<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF> and within the nucleosome, as presented here, are not in discord with experimental findings, further tests are required to provide additional elements of verification or falsification of the model or its underlying parameters.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="217"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Whereas Erwin Schrödinger’s 1944 statement, “We believe a gene—or perhaps the whole chromosome fibre—to be an aperiodic solid”<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit39">39</REF> may not cover every aspect of the DNA microphysics in the living cell, we consider it appropriate to quote regarding the theoretical methods used and the physical quantities addressed in our work.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
