<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b402496f" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Kinetic measurements for the reactions of ozone with crotonaldehyde and its methyl derivatives and calculations of transition-state theory<XREF TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" /></annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">The rate coefficients for the reactions of O<SB>3</SB> with six unsaturated carbonyls have been measured with the relative-rate method in the presence of a sufficient radical scavenger.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The experiments were conducted using a 6-m<SP>3</SP> reaction chamber combined with a long-path FTIR system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rate coefficients (measured in 10<SP>−18</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>) were 1.58 ± 0.23 for crotonaldehyde, 1.59 ± 0.22 for <IT>trans</IT>-2-pentenal, 1.82 ± 0.26 for 3-methyl-2-butenal, 5.34 ± 0.73 for <IT>trans</IT>-2-methyl-2-butenal, 29.5 ± 4.1 for 3-pentene-2-one and 8.3 ± 1.1 for mesityl oxide.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None">Conventional transition-state theory (CTST) calculations based on <IT>ab initio</IT> molecular orbital and density functional methods were performed to evaluate the rate constants for nine unsaturated carbonyls including six compounds examined in the present experiment as well as acrolein, methacrolein, and methyl vinyl ketone.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">A log–log plot of the rate coefficients measured in the present and previous works <IT>vs.</IT> the calculated results of the rate constants, showed a linear relationship.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Unsaturated carbonyls are produced through the atmospheric oxidation of conjugated dienes emitted into the lower troposphere from vegetations<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF> and human activities such as road vehicles.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">2</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The unsaturated carbonyls are then oxidized with OH radicals and/or O<SB>3</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, kinetic data for this class of molecules are often necessary in the atmospheric model calculations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">For example, some unsaturated carbonyls with complex structures have recently been paid attention because these are possible intermediates of the formations of the secondary organic aerosols.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot3" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, for complex molecules, there are only preliminarily kinetic data<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit5 cit6">4–6</REF> because of the high reactivity and difficulties in the preparation of these molecules.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">To predict unknown but necessary kinetic data, structure–activity relationships have often been applied to the electrophillic reactions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7 cit8">7,8</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this method, the logarithms of the rate coefficients are plotted as a function of the ionization potentials (IP) or the highest-occupied molecular orbital (HOMO) energies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">This plot shows an almost linear correlation for the reactions of OH radical with unsaturated hydrocarbons.</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot4" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the other hand, a correlation of the plot for the reactions of O<SB>3</SB> with unsaturated hydrocarbons is much poorer than that for the reactions of OH radical.</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">As an example of the poor correlation, Grosjean and Grosjean pointed out that the rate coefficient for 1,2-distributed alkene, <IT>e.g.</IT>, <IT>trans</IT>-2-butene, is <IT>ca.</IT> 20 times larger than that for 1,1-distributed alkene, <IT>e.g.</IT>, isobutene, despite these ionization potentials being close to each other.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The poor correlation is tentatively attributed to the difference in the steric factor between 1,1- and 1,2-distributed alkenes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">If this is the case, the method such as conventional transition-state theory (CTST), in which the pre-exponential factor is taken into account, must be applicable to predictions of unknown rate constants for the reactions with O<SB>3</SB>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="New" advantage="None">In this study, the rate coefficients have been measured for the reactions of O<SB>3</SB> with crotonaldehyde (2-butenal) and five its methyl derivatives including both 1,1- and 1,2-methyl substituted unsaturated carbonyls.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj5" novelty="New" advantage="None">The rate coefficients measured are compared with results of CTST calculations based on <IT>ab initio</IT> molecular orbital (MO) and density functional theory (DFT) calculations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The purpose of this work is to determine these rate coefficients experimentally and to check whether CTST is applicable to the evaluations of these rate constants.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Experimental</HEADER><P><s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Experiments were conducted with a bakeable and evacuable 6-m<SP>3</SP> photochemical chamber whose inner surface was coated with perfluoroethylene–perfluoroalkyl vinyl ether copolymer.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10 cit11">10,11</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rate coefficients were determined with a relative-rate method in the presence of sufficient diethyl ether (Et<SB>2</SB>O) as a scavenger of OH radicals produced through the O<SB>3</SB> + alkene reactions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Propylene and isobutene were used as reference alkenes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Prior to each experiment, the chamber was filled with purified air under 101 kPa.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The desired pressures of the sample alkene, the reference alkene and Et<SB>2</SB>O were collected into calibrated bulbs.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">These gases were flushed into the chamber with N<SB>2</SB> carrier gas.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">A diluent of O<SB>3</SB>/O<SB>2</SB> was prepared as needed with an ozone generator (Nippon ozone, 2058) and then injected into the chamber.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Rapid mixing was ensured using two stirring fans.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The initial mixing ratios of the sample alkene, the reference alkene, Et<SB>2</SB>O and O<SB>3</SB> were 0.5, 0.5, 19–84 and 1.1–2.4 ppmv, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Under these conditions, the concentrations for the sample and reference alkenes are presented in eqn. (1), assuming that both alkenes are only consumed through the reactions with O<SB>3</SB>where [X]<SB>0</SB> and [X]<SB><IT>t</IT></SB> are the concentrations of X at times 0 and <IT>t</IT>, respectively; <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB> and <IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB> are the rate constants for the reactions of O<SB>3</SB> with the sample alkene and reference alkene, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The experimental data were analyzed according to eqn. (1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The concentrations of the sample and reference alkenes were obtained from infrared absorption spectra measured by an FTIR spectrometer (Nicolet, Nexus 670) with a multi-reflection mirror system whose optical path length was 221.5 m.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The chemicals used and their stated purities were crotonaldehyde (CA: Wako, 99%, mainly <IT>trans</IT>), 3-methyl-2-butenal (MBA32: Aldrich, 97%), <IT>trans</IT>-2-methyl-2-butenal (MBA22: Aldrich, 96%), mesityl oxide (MSO: Aldrich, 90%), 3-pentene-2-one (PO32: Aldrich, 65%, mainly <IT>trans</IT>), <IT>trans</IT>-2-pentenal (PA2: Aldrich, 95%), Et<SB>2</SB>O (Kanto, 99.5%), propylene (Takachiho, 99%) and isobutene (Takachiho, 95%).</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The impurity of PO32 was identified to be MSO with the FTIR analysis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The concentration of MSO was shown to be <IT>ca</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">15% of that of the used reagent.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp14" novelty="None" advantage="None">All experiments were carried out at 298 ± 2 K.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Method of calculations</HEADER><P><s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rate constants were calculated with CTST for the reactions of O<SB>3</SB> with nine unsaturated carbonyls, <IT>i.e.</IT>, six molecules examined in the present experiment as well as acrolein (AC), methacrolein (MAC) and methyl vinyl ketone (MVK).</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">These reactions are believed to proceed on the singlet ground-state potential-energy surface <IT>via</IT> the addition of O<SB>3</SB> to the CC double bond.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">In these reactions, O<SB>3</SB> approaches the double bond from the directions vertical to the alkene plane, leading to the transition-state (TS) involving a five-membered ring.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">There are two possible TS conformers referred as <IT>syn</IT>- and <IT>anti</IT>-TS;<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF>where R<SB><IT>i</IT></SB> and X indicate the alkyl and carbonyl groups, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the energies and all the bond lengths are close to each other between these TS conformers, it was assumed that the rate constants are the same between two reaction pathways <IT>via</IT> these TS conformers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rate constants were calculated with CTST for reaction pathways <IT>via</IT><IT>syn</IT>-TS molecules and were then doubled to determine the overall rate constants (<IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB><SP>CTST</SP>);<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14 cit15">14,15</REF>where <IT>E</IT><SB>0</SB>, <IT>L</IT> and <IT>Q</IT><SB>X</SB> represent the barrier-height energy, the statistical factor and the partition function of the internal motions for molecule X, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The statistical factor was set to 4 because there are two configurations of ozone, <IT>i.e.</IT>, O<SB>1</SB>–O<SB>2</SB>–O<SB>3</SB> and O<SB>3</SB>–O<SB>2</SB>–O<SB>1</SB>, for each of two attack sites located in both sides of the alkene plane.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The partition functions for the intra-molecular rotations of methyl groups in unsaturated carbonyls were calculated with a method proposed by Troe.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">All rate constants were calculated for temperature of 298 K.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The vibrational frequencies, the rotational constants and the barrier-height energies necessary in the calculations of eqn. (2) were determined by <IT>ab initio</IT> MO and DFT calculations.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17 cit18">17,18</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Prior to the calculations, a conformer with the lowest energy was found with an RHF/6-31G(d) method for each reactant.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the conformers found, the geometries for the reactant and the TS were optimized by the RHF/6-31G(d) method and the hybrid density functional consisting of Becke's three parameter nonlocal hybrid exchange potential with the nonlocal correlation functional of Lee, Yang, and Parr (B3LYP) method<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19">19</REF> with the 6-31G(d,p) basis set.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Harmonic vibrational frequencies were calculated at the optimized geometries by the respective methods.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results of vibrational frequencies were scaled with factors of 0.89 and 0.96 for the results of the RHF and B3LYP methods, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The single-point energies were calculated by the fourth order Møller–Plesset perturbation theory (MP4) with the 6-31G(d,p) basis set and the coupled-cluster singles and doubles including a perturbational estimate of triple excitations (CCSD(T)) method<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF> with the 6-311G(d,p) basis set for the geometries optimized by the RHF/6-31G(d) and B3LYP/6-31G(d,p) methods, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod14" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to examine validities of the basis sets used in the above calculations, geometry optimizations were also carried out at by the B3LYP/6-311G(d,p) method for the reactants and TS for the O<SB>3</SB> + ACR reaction, and the single-point energies were also calculated at the CCSD(T) level with 6-311G(d,p), 6-311++G(d,p), 6-311G(2d,2p) and 6-311++G(2d,2p) basis sets.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The HOMO energies of unsaturated carbonyls were calculated by the B3LYP/6-31+G(d,p) method for the geometries optimized at the RHF/6-31G(d) level of theory.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Results and discussion</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Experimental results of rate coefficient <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB></HEADER><P><s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The concentrations of the sample and the reference alkenes were determined from the infrared spectra measured as follows: A contribution of Et<SB>2</SB>O to the infrared spectrum measured was subtracted prior to each analysis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The concentration of the reference alkene was then determined with an absorption line peaked at 912 cm<SP>−1</SP> for propylene or 890 cm<SP>−1</SP> for isobutene.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The concentration of the sample alkene was determined with an absorption line attributed to the CC stretching mode at around 1640 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">For PO32, the CC absorption line contained a contribution of the MSO impurity of ≤25% in the absorbance.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp18" novelty="None" advantage="None">This component was subtracted with an absorption line at 968 cm<SP>−1</SP> before the evaluation of the concentration of PO32.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">All the concentrations could be determined without interference from any product absorption.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The concentrations of the sample and reference alkenes are plotted in Fig. 1 in accordance with eqn. (1) for the measurements with propylene as the reference alkene.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the plots for all measurements examined were almost linear, the relative rate coefficients (<IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB>/<IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB>) were obtained from the slopes with the linear least-squares analysis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results of <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB>/<IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB> are listed in Table 1 along with initial experimental conditions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp20" novelty="None" advantage="None">The initial conditions were varied to check validities of <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB>/<IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB> obtained as follows: First, <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB>/<IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB> of each compound were measured at both [Et<SB>2</SB>O]<SB>0</SB> ≈ 80 and ≈ 20 ppmv to confirm that OH radicals were entirely scavenged.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">For example, for CA, <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB>/<IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB> obtained at 18.9 ppmv (0.152 ± 0.016) shows good agreement with that obtained at 82.6 ppmv (0.152 ± 0.008).</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Similar results were obtained for all the other compounds examined as listed in Table 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">These results indicate that OH radicals are entirely scavenged even at [Et<SB>2</SB>O]<SB>0</SB> ≈ 18 ppmv.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Next, if the decay rate of the sample alkene due to the reaction with O<SB>3</SB> (<IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB>[O<SB>3</SB>]<SB>t</SB>) was comparably as low as that due to the wall loss, <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB>/<IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB> obtained would be overestimated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj6" novelty="New" advantage="None">To check that there is no such overestimation, a dependence of <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB>/<IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB> upon [O<SB>3</SB>]<SB>0</SB> was measured for MBA32.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">As shown in Table 1, <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB>/<IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB> is almost independent of [O<SB>3</SB>]<SB>0</SB> between 1.21 and 2.38 ppmv.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">This overestimation is negligible even at [O<SB>3</SB>]<SB>0</SB> = 1.21 ppmv.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp21" novelty="None" advantage="None">Finally, for MSO, both propylene and isobutene were employed as the reference alkene. <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB>/<IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB> obtained for isobutene was 0.767 ± 0.011.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp22" novelty="None" advantage="None">Multiplying this value to a literature value of <IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB> of isobutene,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF> the rate coefficient <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB> is determined to be (8.82 ± 0.35) × 10<SP>−18</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The result of <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB> agrees with that obtained from propylene data, (8.3 ± 1.1) × 10<SP>−18</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>, which is described later.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">This suggests that a systematic error due to the use of propylene is negligible.</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp23" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the possible systematic errors could be ruled out for all the results of <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB>/<IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB>, the results of <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB>/<IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB> for each compound were averaged.</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results of averaged values are listed in Table 1.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp24" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rate coefficients <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB> were calculated with the averaged values of <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB>/<IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB> and a literature value of <IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB> for propylene,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF> (1.04 ± 0.14) × 10<SP>−17</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rate coefficients <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB> determined are listed in Table 2 along with previous data.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">To our knowledge, the previous kinetic data are available for CA and PO32.</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">For CA, two literature values have been reported.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23 cit24">23,24</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both data were measured by monitoring the O<SB>3</SB> decay curves with UV absorption methods in the presence of excess CA.</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">A literature value,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF> (1.74 ± 0.20) × 10<SP>−18</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>, is consistent with the present result, (1.58 ± 0.23) × 10<SP>−18</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>, within the experimental uncertainties.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, another literature value,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF> (0.90 ± 0.18) × 10<SP>−18</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>, is a factor of 0.57 lower than the present result.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">For PO32, two literature values are available.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24 cit25">24,25</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">A literature value,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25">25</REF> (35.0 ± 8.9) × 10<SP>−18</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>, was measured with a relative-rate method.</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">This data agrees with the present result, (29.5 ± 4.1) × 10<SP>−18</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Another literature value, (21.3 ± 3.9) × 10<SP>−18</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>, which is taken from <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">ref. 24</REF> is again slightly lower than the present data.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj7" novelty="New" advantage="None">The rate coefficients measured in the present and previous works for unsaturated carbonyls were compared with those for unsaturated hydrocarbons to study the substituent effects on the rate coefficients.</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp25" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 2 shows the available data of the rate coefficients plotted as a function of a series of five molecular structures, <IT>i.e.</IT>, CH<SB>2</SB>CHX, CH<SB>3</SB>CHCHX, (CH<SB>3</SB>)<SB>2</SB>CCHX, C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>5</SB>CHCHX and CH<SB>3</SB>CHC(CH<SB>3</SB>)X, and compares the kinetic data for molecules with XH (<IT>k</IT><SB>HC</SB>), CHO (<IT>k</IT><SB>ALD</SB>) and COCH<SB>3</SB> (<IT>k</IT><SB>KET</SB>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The previous kinetic data plotted in the figure for ACR, MAC and MVK are listed in Table 2,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12 cit23 cit24 cit26 cit27">12,23,24,26,27</REF> and these for hydrocarbons, in units of 10<SP>−18</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>, are 1.43 ± 0.19 for ethylene,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF> 10.4 ± 1.4 for propylene,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF> 11.5 ± 4.6 for isobutene,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF> 9.80 ± 0.29 for 1-butene<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF> and 129 ± 9 for <IT>cis</IT>-2-butene.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 2 shows that the ratio of <IT>k</IT><SB>ALD</SB> to <IT>k</IT><SB>HC</SB> was kept almost constant among all five structures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">An averaged value of <IT>k</IT><SB>ALD</SB>/<IT>k</IT><SB>HC</SB> with an error of one standard deviation was 0.14 ± 0.06.</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">This means that the rate coefficient for unsaturated hydrocarbon is suppressed with a substitution of the H atom in the unsaturated hydrocarbon with an electron-withdrawing CHO group.</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">An averaged value of <IT>k</IT><SB>KET</SB>/<IT>k</IT><SB>ALD</SB> was also calculated to be 14 ± 9.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast to the result of <IT>k</IT><SB>ALD</SB>/<IT>k</IT><SB>HC</SB>, the rate coefficient for unsaturated aldehyde is enhanced with a substitution of the H atom in the CHO group with an electron-releasing methyl group.</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results of the substituent effects suggest that the reactions of O<SB>3</SB> with alkenes are electrophillic reactions.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Conventional structure–activity relationships</HEADER><P><s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj8" novelty="New" advantage="None">Assuming that the reactions of O<SB>3</SB> with alkenes are electrophillic, a relationship of the present and previous experimental results of the rate coefficients with –<IT>E</IT><SB>HOMO</SB> was studied.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj9" novelty="New" advantage="None">Prior to this analysis, validities of the present results of –<IT>E</IT><SB>HOMO</SB> were checked with previous experimental data of IP.</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results of –<IT>E</IT><SB>HOMO</SB> calculated for nine compounds, <IT>i.e.</IT> six molecules examined in the present experiment as well as ACR, MAC and MVK are listed in Table 2 together with the available data of IP.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28">28</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 3 shows the data of IP plotted as a function of the results of –<IT>E</IT><SB>HOMO</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod16" novelty="None" advantage="None">With the linear least-square analysis, the data plotted can be approximated with a straight line, IP = (1.43 ± 0.08) × (–<IT>E</IT><SB>HOMO</SB>) − 0.50 ± 0.59.</annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The errors quoted for the slope and the intercept are two standard deviations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The correlation coefficient (<IT>R</IT><SP>2</SP>) was 0.994 and was nearly the same as unity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">This suggests that the results of –<IT>E</IT><SB>HOMO</SB> can be used instead of the experimental data of IP.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp26" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 3b shows the experimental rate coefficients for the reactions of O<SB>3</SB> with nine unsaturated carbonyls plotted as a function of −<IT>E</IT><SB>HOMO</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The data plotted in the figure are taken from Table 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp27" novelty="None" advantage="None">All the data plotted in Fig. 3b were fitted with the linear least-squares analysis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The line fitted was represented as log<SB>10</SB><IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB> = −(2.83 ± 0.80) × (−<IT>E</IT><SB>HOMO</SB>) + 2.50 ± 5.72.</annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The errors for the slope and the intercept are two standard deviations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The correlation coefficient was 0.723 and was smaller than unity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">This indicates that the correlation of log<SB>10</SB><IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB> with −<IT>E</IT><SB>HOMO</SB> was so poor that the plot cannot be used for the predictions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The data for seven compounds, <IT>i.e.</IT>, PO32, MBA22, MVK, MAC, PA2, CA and ACR, can be approximated with a single straight line as shown in Fig. 3b with a dotted line.</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs20" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rate coefficients for 1,1-dimethyl alkenes, <IT>i.e.</IT>, MBA32 and MSO, are lower than those predicted with the dotted line.</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">This result would be consistently attributed to the steric hinderance of 1,1-distributed substituents, as described by the previous workers.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs21" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the data for 1-methyl-1-carbonyl alkenes, <IT>i.e.</IT>, MBA22 and MAC, are fitted with a single line together with the data for 1,2-distributed alkenes, PO32, PA2 and CA.</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">This suggests that the present results of the scattered plot cannot simply be interpreted with the steric hinderance of the 1,1-distributed substituents.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Results of <IT>ab initio</IT> and DFT calculations</HEADER><P><s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj10" novelty="New" advantage="None">In order to study the reaction dynamics of O<SB>3</SB> with unsaturated carbonyls and check whether accurate rate constants can be predicted, the calculations of the rate constants were performed with CTST based on the <IT>ab initio</IT> MO and DFT calculations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the previous theoretical studies on the reactions of O<SB>3</SB> with alkenes, the barrier heights have been successfully predicted by employing the MP4/6-31G(d,p)//MP2/6-31G(d,p) method<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29">29</REF> and the CCSD(T)/6-31G(d)//B3LYP/6-31G(d,p) method.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30">30</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod20" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this work, we have employed the MP4(SDQ)//RHF/6-31G(d) and CCSD(T)/6-311G(d,p)//B3LYP/6-31G(d,p) methods for the reactions of O<SB>3</SB> with nine unsaturated carbonyls.</annotationART></s> <s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs22" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results of the energies and the zero-point energies (ZPE) calculated at the RHF/6-31G(d) level are listed in Table 3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs23" novelty="None" advantage="None">Table 4 shows the barrier-height energies (<IT>E</IT><SB>0</SB>) for the respective reactions, calculated from the single-point energies and the ZPEs, as well as the available experimental data for MAC and MVK.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27">27</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs24" novelty="None" advantage="None">For MAC, the barrier-height energies were evaluated as 23.9, 21.5, and 10.8 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> for the MP4(SDQ), CCSD, and CCSD(T) methods, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs25" novelty="None" advantage="None">These values are close to the experimental activation energy of 17.5 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> and distribute within a range of ±8.4 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> (= ±2 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is noted that an estimation of the barrier height with an error smaller than ±4.2–8.4 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> may be difficult even at a higher level of theory.</annotationART></s> <s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">The higher the level of theory, the lower the result of the barrier height.</annotationART></s> <s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs26" novelty="None" advantage="None">The difference in <IT>E</IT><SB>0</SB> between the CCSD and CCSD(T) methods are larger than that between the MP4(SDQ) and CCSD methods.</annotationART></s> <s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs27" novelty="None" advantage="None">The similar tendency can be seen for the other reactions, as listed in Table 4.</annotationART></s> <s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">This suggests that contributions of highly electronic excited configurations are important in the present reaction systems.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj11" novelty="New" advantage="None">To check the dependence of the results of <IT>E</IT><SB>0</SB> upon the basis sets, CCSD(T) calculations were carried out for the O<SB>3</SB> + ACR reaction, with 6-311G(d,p), 6-311++G(d,p), 6-311G(2d,2p), and 6-311++G(2d,2p) basis sets for geometries optimized by the B3LYP/6-311G(d,p) method.</annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs28" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results are listed in Table 4.</annotationART></s> <s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod21" novelty="None" advantage="None">The barrier-height energies determined by CCSD(T)/6-311G(d,p)//B3LYP/6-31G(d,p) and CCSD(T)/6-311G(d,p)//B3LYP/6-311G(d,p) are 20.1 and 22.9 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>, respectively, and their difference is just 2.8 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod22" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the same B3LYP/6-311G(d,p) geometries, the CCSD(T) barrier-height energies were evaluated as 22.9, 22.5, 15.8 and 20.4 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> with the 6-311311G(d,p), 6-311++G(d,p), 6-311G(2d,2p), and 6-311++G(2d,2p) basis sets, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">As shown in these results, no systematic trend is seen as to the basis sets.</annotationART></s> <s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs29" novelty="None" advantage="None">The width of the distribution of the results of <IT>E</IT><SB>0</SB> is <IT>ca.</IT> ±4.2 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod23" novelty="None" advantage="None">This value is used as an uncertainty of the results of <IT>E</IT><SB>0</SB> in the present CTST calculations described in the next section.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Rate constants calculated with CTST method</HEADER><P><s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj12" novelty="New" advantage="None">The CTST calculations were performed using the results of <IT>E</IT><SB>0</SB> obtained at the MP4(SDQ), CCSD and CCSD(T) levels.</annotationART></s> <s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod24" novelty="None" advantage="None">The pre-exponential factors, <IT>A</IT><SP>CTST</SP> and <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB><SP>CTST</SP>, were calculated following eqn. (2) for nine unsaturated carbonyls.</annotationART></s> <s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs30" novelty="None" advantage="None">These results are listed in Table 4 together with results of the <IT>ab initio</IT> calculations of <IT>E</IT><SB>0</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs31" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 4a shows the experimental results of the rate coefficients plotted as a function of <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB><SP>CTST</SP> calculated with the results of <IT>E</IT><SB>0</SB> for the MP4(SDQ) method.</annotationART></s> <s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod25" novelty="None" advantage="None">In Fig. 4a, the errors of the experimental data represent the experimental uncertainties, whereas the errors of <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB><SP>CTST</SP> represent those evaluated taking into account the uncertainties of the results of <IT>E</IT><SB>0</SB>, as described previously.</annotationART></s> <s sid="143"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod26" novelty="None" advantage="None">With the linear least-squares analysis, the data plotted in Fig. 4a were fitted with a straight line:log<SB>10</SB><IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB> = <IT>a</IT> log<SB>10</SB><IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB><SP>CTST</SP> + <IT>b</IT>,where <IT>a</IT> and <IT>b</IT> are fitting parameters.</annotationART></s> <s sid="144"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod27" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fit results of the parameters with errors of two standard deviations were <IT>a</IT> = 0.585 ± 0.107 and <IT>b</IT> = –7.04 ± 1.93.</annotationART></s> <s sid="145"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs32" novelty="None" advantage="None">The correlation coefficient was 0.863.</annotationART></s> <s sid="146"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs33" novelty="None" advantage="None">Figs. 4b and 4c show similar plots with <IT>E</IT><SB>0</SB> obtained with the CCSD and CCSD(T) methods, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="147"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod28" novelty="None" advantage="None">These plots were also fitted with eqn. (3).</annotationART></s> <s sid="148"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod29" novelty="None" advantage="None">The parameters fitted were <IT>a</IT> = 0.352 ± 0.107 and <IT>b</IT> = −11.6 ± 1.8 for the CCSD method, and these were <IT>a</IT> = 0.395 ± 0.097 and <IT>b</IT> = −11.6 ± 1.5 for the CCSD(T) method.</annotationART></s> <s sid="149"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs34" novelty="None" advantage="None">The correlation coefficients were 0.692 and 0.778 for the CCSD and CCSD(T) methods, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="150"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs35" novelty="None" advantage="None">The slopes of the fitted lines for Figs. 4a–c are smaller than unity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="151"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is because the results of <IT>E</IT><SB>0</SB> still contain errors even for the CCSD(T)/6-311G(d,p)//B3LYP/6-31G(d,p) method.</annotationART></s> <s sid="152"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, all the plots for the MP4(SDQ), CCSD and CCSD(T) methods show linear relationships within the errors of <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB><SP>CTST</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="153"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" advantage="None">Especially the correlation coefficients for the MP4(SDQ) and CCSD(T) methods are larger than that for the plot of log<SB>10</SB><IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB><IT>vs.</IT> of −<IT>E</IT><SB>HOMO</SB> (0.723).</annotationART></s> <s sid="154"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">CTST calculations combined with an <IT>ab initio</IT> MO and DFT methods can predict the relative values of the rate constants with a higher accuracy than those predicted with the conventional structure–activity relationships.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="155"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj13" novelty="New" advantage="None">Finally, the difference in the rate coefficient between 1,2-methyl substituted alkene (MBA22) and 1,1-methyl substituted alkene (MBA32) is discussed using the present results of <IT>A</IT><SP>CTST</SP> and <IT>E</IT><SB>0</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="156"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs36" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rate coefficients for the reaction of MBA22, (5.34 ± 0.73) × 10<SP>−18</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>, is 2.9 times larger than that for the reaction of MBA32, (1.82 ± 0.26) × 10<SP>−18</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>, as listed in Table 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="157"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">If this is caused by the steric hindrance of 1,1-methyl substituents, the potential energy curves for the TS for the reaction of MBA32 should be tighter than those for the reaction of MBA22, and thus the result of <IT>A</IT><SP>CTST</SP> for MBA32 should be smaller than that for MBA22.</annotationART></s> <s sid="158"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs37" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the results of <IT>A</IT><SP>CTST</SP> obtained at the B3LYP level for MBA32 (9.63 × 10<SP>−15</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>) is very close to that for MBA22 (1.02 × 10<SP>−14</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>) as listed in Table 4.</annotationART></s> <s sid="159"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs38" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, <IT>A</IT><SP>CTST</SP> for MBA32 is also close to those for the other two isomers, PO32 (1.04 × 10<SP>−14</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>) and PA2 (2.77 × 10<SP>−14</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="160"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None">These results indicate that the pre-exponential factor is almost independent of the molecular structure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="161"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the other hand, the result of <IT>E</IT><SB>0</SB> obtained at the CCSD(T) level for MBA32 (11.7 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>) is higher than that for MBA22 (2.6 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>), <IT>i.e.</IT>, <IT>E</IT><SB>0</SB> depends on the molecular structure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="162"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res29" novelty="None" advantage="None">This suggests that the rate constant is determined by <IT>E</IT><SB>0</SB> rather than the pre-exponential factor.</annotationART></s> <s sid="163"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod30" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 5 shows the geometries optimized with the B3LYP/6-31G(d,p) method for MBA32 and MBA32-TS molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="164"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs39" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reactant alkene has a structure with <IT>C</IT><SB>s</SB> symmetry.</annotationART></s> <s sid="165"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs40" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast, the methyl and carbonyl substituents in the TS move out of the original <IT>C</IT><SB>s</SB> plane into the opposite side of the O<SB>3</SB> group.</annotationART></s> <s sid="166"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs41" novelty="None" advantage="None">The methyl groups move further from the original geometry <IT>via</IT> the intramolecular rotations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="167"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res30" novelty="None" advantage="None">These results suggest that motion of the TS along the intrinsic reaction coordinate consists of the relative translation between the O<SB>3</SB> and alkene groups as well as the symmetric out-of-plane vibration of the alkene group and the intramolecular rotations of the methyl groups.</annotationART></s> <s sid="168"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the geometry change of the alkene group is necessary for the formation of the TS, there is a substantial barrier for the reactions of O<SB>3</SB> with alkenes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="169"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs42" novelty="None" advantage="None">The normal mode frequency assigned to the methyl rotation for MBA32 (127 cm<SP>−1</SP>) is larger than that for MBA22 (90 cm<SP>−1</SP>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="170"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res32" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the tightness of the potential energy curves for the internal motions of alkene depends on the combination of the substituted sites, the barrier-height energy depends on the molecular structure.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Conclusion</HEADER><P><s sid="171"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj14" novelty="New" advantage="None">In summary, the rate coefficients of the reactions of O<SB>3</SB> with six unsaturated carbonyls were measured with a relative-rate method in the presence of sufficient diethyl ether.</annotationART></s> <s sid="172"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res33" novelty="None" advantage="None">Using the present and previous experimental results of the rate coefficients, the correlation of the rate coefficients with the HOMO energies was investigated, and it was found that the linearity of the plot is poor.</annotationART></s> <s sid="173"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj15" novelty="New" advantage="None">To evaluate the rate constants taking into account the reaction dynamics, conventional transition-state theory calculations based on <IT>ab initio</IT> molecular orbital and DFT methods were performed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="174"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res34" novelty="None" advantage="None">A log–log plot of the experimental rate coefficients <IT>vs.</IT> the results of the calculated rate constants show linear relationships for the results with the MP4(SDQ), CCSD and CCSD(T) barrier-height energies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="175"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Among four isomers of MBA32, the result of the pre-exponential factor is almost independent of the reactant, while the result of the barrier-height energy depends on the reactant.</annotationART></s> <s sid="176"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">These results suggest that the rate constant is determined by the barrier-height energy rather than the pre-exponential factor.</annotationART></s> <s sid="177"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In future works, both theoretical and experimental studies of the rate coefficients are necessary for the reactions of O<SB>3</SB> with unsaturated carbonyls, which are considered to be possible intermediates of the secondary organic aerosols, such as cyclic carbonyl alkenes, dicarbonyl alkenes and carbonyl dienes.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
