<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b402989p" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Are Hartree–Fock atoms too small or too large?</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">We address the simple question, whether Hartree–Fock atoms are smaller or larger than exact (Schrödinger) atoms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">As a measure, we use 〈<IT>r</IT><SP>2</SP>〉.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">We study the ground state of the atoms He–Kr.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The unrestricted Hartree–Fock method is used.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">To obtain the Schrödinger values we use the finite field CASPT2 approach, and the full CI scheme where possible.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None">CASSCF calculations are also reported.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Very large basis sets are employed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">We find that for those atoms for which the CASSCF wavefunction is distinct from the HF wavefunction, the Schrödinger values are distinctly smaller than the HF values.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Most other atoms are also smaller than the HF values, (or the same within a numerical uncertainty), the exceptions being the hard atoms N–Ne, and Cl, Ar and Kr.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="New" advantage="None">We interpret our results in terms of categories of correlation contribution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj5" novelty="New" advantage="None">It is also of interest to test the performance of density functional theory (DFT); we find on the whole that the predictions are good, with B3LYP giving close agreement with finite field CASPT2 for nearly all atoms, in particular for the transition metals.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="1.">Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">One of the outstanding problems of computational quantum chemistry is the understanding of electron correlation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The correlation energy is defined as the difference between the Hartree–Fock energy and the exact (non-relativistic) energy of the molecule.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is often separated into two parts, a short range effect due to the reduction in probability as two electrons come together, and a long range effect which is often responsible for electrons proceeding correctly to their atoms as the molecule dissociates.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The first part is called ‘dynamic correlation’, and is often associated with the necessity of including the interelectronic distance <IT>r</IT><SB><IT>ij</IT></SB> in accurate wavefunctions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The importance of the electron–electron cusp is a dynamic correlation effect.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Quantum chemical calculations often introduce dynamic correlation through the introduction of ‘double replacement configurations’ into a configuration interaction (CI) expansion, although excluding double replacements into anti-bonding or non-bonding orbitals.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Dynamic correlation is often thought to be associated with a reduction in size because it allows electrons to arrange themselves in the most efficient manner possible.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The second part is called ‘left–right correlation’ for obvious reasons, but it is equally well called ‘static correlation’ or ‘near-degeneracy correlation’ or ‘non-dynamic correlation’.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Quantum chemists introduce this correlation through the introduction of double replacement configurations which involve anti-bonding or non-bonding or other valence orbitals.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Such correlations are responsible for an increase in molecular size: indeed for diatomic molecules, Hartree–Fock (HF) often predicts too short bonds, with CI calculations correctly lengthening them.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">We deduce that this correlation has a greater effect on molecular shape than dynamic correlation.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The great difficulty is that in quantum chemistry these two forms of correlation cannot be cleanly separated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">For H<SB>2</SB>, the dominant double replacement CI configuration is σ2g → σ2u, which is clearly a left–right effect, but as the bond length decreases it becomes 1s<SP>2</SP> → 2p<SP>2</SP> in united atom notation, which is a dynamic effect.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is often proclaimed that the correlation in atoms is all dynamic, because there are no long-range correlations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The assignment is not clear for Be for which the near-degeneracy configuration 1s<SP>2</SP>2p<SP>2</SP> is very important, and this is commonly called ‘static correlation’.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Alternatively it may be argued that this configuration introduces <IT>r</IT>2<IT>ij</IT> and it is therefore a dynamic effect.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">We recognise that angular correlation can be interpreted as an effect of <IT>r</IT>2<IT>ij</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Similar arguments can be presented for other atoms, where (<IT>n</IT>s)<SP>2</SP>→(<IT>n</IT>p)<SP>2</SP> are possible, for example the carbon atom ((2s)<SP>2</SP> (2p)<SP>2</SP>,<SP>3</SP>P→(2p)<SP>4</SP>,<SP>3</SP>P), and the transition metals with a filled <IT>n</IT>s shell in the ground state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Intuitively one might think these Hartree–Fock atoms are too large, because angular correlation should make them smaller (less screening).</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the other hand radial correlation could make them bigger, since one of the electrons moves to the next shell.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot3" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is therefore relevant to ask the question whether HF atoms are too large or too small.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">We attempt to ascertain the true size of atoms by performing CASSCF,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">2</REF> CASPT2<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF> and full CI (FCI) calculations using large basis sets.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj6" novelty="New" advantage="None">We study the ground states of all atoms in the first three rows.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj7" novelty="New" advantage="None">In all our investigations we shall calculate 〈∑<IT><SB>i</SB> r</IT>2<IT>i</IT>〉, <IT>r</IT>2<IT>i</IT> = <IT>x</IT>2<IT>i</IT> + <IT>y</IT>2<IT>i</IT> + <IT>z</IT>2<IT>i</IT>, as a measure of atomic size.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Results from these investigations are given in section 3.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac20" novelty="None" advantage="None">The tail behaviour of the wavefunction gives information on size.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The asymptotic behaviour of the exact density is exp(−2(2<IT>I</IT>)<SP>1/2</SP><IT>r</IT>), whereas the asymptotic behaviour of the HF density is exp(−2(−2<IT>ε</IT><SB>homo</SB>)<SP>1/2</SP><IT>r</IT>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">If −<IT>ε</IT><SB>homo</SB>&gt;<IT>I</IT>, then the HF atom may be too small and vice-versa.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Indeed this analysis agrees with later results in this paper.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">However we doubt whether the tail behaviour tells us about size because the emphasis should be on those regions where the electron density is high.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac21" novelty="None" advantage="None">There are more accurate values of 〈<IT>r</IT><SP>2</SP>〉 for selected small atoms, but they will not give a systematic comparison.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac22" novelty="None" advantage="None">Density functional theory (DFT) introduces correlation effects rather differently.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac23" novelty="None" advantage="None">The correlation functionals for the uniform electron gas, ascribed to Volko, Wilk and Nusair (VWN)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF> or Perdew and Wang (PW91)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF> are called dynamic correlation functionals, because there are no near-degeneracy configurations in that model system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac24" novelty="None" advantage="None">Perdew has extended his functional to include density gradients (P91).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac25" novelty="None" advantage="None">The functional LYP<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF> is also called a dynamic functional, because it was derived from the He correlated wavefunction of Colle and Salvetti (CS),<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF> basing one’s argument on the fact that all correlation in that atom must be dynamic.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac26" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is also of the generalised gradient approximation (GGA) form.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac27" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is well-known from many molecular calculations that these functionals do not introduce all molecular correlation; for example for N<SB>2</SB>, it is found<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF> that LYP (or P91) only introduces ∼50% of the necessary correlation for molecular binding.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac28" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore self-consistent Kohn–Sham (KS) calculations with HF+LYP (HFLYP) predict bondlengths which are even shorter than HF bondlengths.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac29" novelty="None" advantage="None">The remarkable success of DFT hinges upon the fact that local exchange functionals introduce a localised exchange hole, which is close to the reference electron, in contradiction to the HF model which favours delocalised exchange holes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac30" novelty="None" advantage="None">The most popular local exchange functionals are the original uniform electron gas functional due to Dirac (LDAX) and the GGA exchange functional of Becke (B88X).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac31" novelty="None" advantage="None">The functional B88X introduces the other ∼50% of the correlation for the binding of N<SB>2</SB>; for these reasons it is said to introduce left–right correlation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac32" novelty="None" advantage="None">Such an analysis has been shown to work in practice for many hundreds of molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac33" novelty="None" advantage="None">Calculations with BLYP often successfully lengthen the too-short HF bondlengths.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac34" novelty="None" advantage="None">The geometrical effects of the exchange functional are more significant than those of the dynamic functional.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac35" novelty="None" advantage="None">B88X contains one parameter <IT>β</IT>, which was determined so that the exchange energies of the atoms He, Ne, Ar, Kr, Xe at the HF level were optimally reproduced.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac36" novelty="None" advantage="None">For these noble gas atoms therefore, Becke believed that all the correlation should be dynamic.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore one can ask the question, is dynamic or non-dynamic correlation more important for the determination of atomic size, in this DFT terminology?</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Because the GGA functional BLYP is known to be good, we can analyse separately the contributions from B88X and LYP.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj8" novelty="New" advantage="None">We therefore perform investigations using the LDA and BLYP functionals.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj9" novelty="New" advantage="None">We first perform Hartree–Fock calculations and Kohn–Sham calculations, because of their similarity and simplicity.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.">Hartree–Fock and density functional calculations</HEADER><P><s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">For these single reference (one electron in each spin orbital) calculations, we have chosen to use the basis set which yields the lowest Hartree–Fock energy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">For all the calculations in this section we have used the unrestricted algorithm, because this is the proper procedure for KS calculations (see for example Pople <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF>.), and therefore for comparison we should compute UHF energies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The basis set used is due to Partridge<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF>, which of course is appropriate for the occupied orbitals only.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">All calculations were performed within CADPAC, with ∫ <IT>ρ</IT>(<B><IT>r</IT></B>)<IT>r</IT><SP>2</SP> d<B><IT>r</IT></B> being calculated using high radial quadrature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The open shell atoms in many cases are not spherically symmetrical (eg C 2p<IT>α</IT><IT>x</IT> 2p<IT>α</IT><IT>y</IT>), but the values obtained would be the same if the atom was spherically symmetrised.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod12" novelty="None" advantage="None">All orbitals are real.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj10" novelty="New" advantage="None">We perform calculations on the atoms H-Kr; relevant ground states are Sc(d<SP>1</SP>s<SP>2</SP>,<SP>2</SP>D), Ti(d<SP>2</SP>s<SP>2</SP>,<SP>3</SP>F), V(d<SP>3</SP>s<SP>2</SP>,<SP>4</SP>F), Cr(d<SP>5</SP>s<SP>1</SP>,<SP>7</SP>S), Mn(d<SP>5</SP>s<SP>2</SP>,<SP>6</SP>S), Fe(d<SP>6</SP>s<SP>2</SP>,<SP>5</SP>D), Co(d<SP>7</SP>s<SP>2</SP>,<SP>4</SP>F), Ni(d<SP>8</SP>s<SP>2</SP>,<SP>3</SP>F), Cu(d<SP>10</SP>s<SP>1</SP>,<SP>2</SP>S), Zn(d<SP>10</SP>s<SP>2</SP>,<SP>1</SP>S).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod13" novelty="None" advantage="None">In Fig. 1 we plot percentage ratio values of 〈∑<IT><SB>i</SB>r</IT>2<IT>i</IT>〉 (denoted as <IT>r</IT><SP>2</SP> in our discussions) for the local exchange LDAX (Dirac) and the GGA exchange B88X<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF> functionals, compared to the UHF values.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod14" novelty="None" advantage="None">In Fig. 2 we show the percentage ratio for the local LDA (LDAX+VWN) and the GGA BLYP exchange–correlation functionals.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 1 shows that the LDAX atoms are larger than the B88X atoms, for H through Ar, but for the heavier atoms there is little percentage difference.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">B88X atoms are larger than UHF atoms for H-Li, B-Ne, Al–Ar, Cr, Ga–Kr.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The introduction of dynamic correlation through the correlation functionals reduces atomic size, see Fig. 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">We see that LDA and BLYP atoms are similar in size; only He, C–Ne, BLYP atoms are substantially larger than UHF atoms, with S-Ar and Se-Kr marginally larger.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">DFT is suggesting that most Schrödinger atoms are smaller than UHF atoms, with the clear exception of the hard first row atoms, and He, P–Ar, Se–Kr.</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">It will be seen below that these predictions are in agreement with those from <IT>ab initio</IT> quantum chemistry calculations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj11" novelty="New" advantage="None">These we now report, and then in the final section we will compare the two sets of calculations, and give our explanation for the results.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.">CASSCF, CASPT2, and full CI calculations</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.1.">Details of the calculations</HEADER><P><s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Calculations have been performed using ANO-L basis sets<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF> for the atoms He-Zn with the exception of K and Ca for which a relativistic basis set (ANO-RCC)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF> was used (designed for use with the Douglas–Kroll Hamiltonian).</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Slightly smaller values of 〈<IT>r</IT><SP>2</SP>〉 were consequently obtained for these two atoms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ANO-L basis sets were not available for Ga–Kr.</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Instead, a smaller ANO-S basis set<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF> was used.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Comparison of the HF results shows that also this basis set is adequate for the present purpose.</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The details of the basis sets are: <TGROUP><THEAD><ROW><ENTRY>Atoms</ENTRY><ENTRY>Primitive</ENTRY><ENTRY>Contracted</ENTRY></ROW></THEAD><TBODY><ROW><ENTRY>He</ENTRY><ENTRY>9s4p3d2f</ENTRY><ENTRY>5s4p2d</ENTRY></ROW><ROW><ENTRY>Li–Ne</ENTRY><ENTRY>14s9p4d3f</ENTRY><ENTRY>6s5p3d1f</ENTRY></ROW><ROW><ENTRY>Na–Ar</ENTRY><ENTRY>17s12p5d4f</ENTRY><ENTRY>7s6p4d2f</ENTRY></ROW><ROW><ENTRY>K</ENTRY><ENTRY>21s16p5d4f</ENTRY><ENTRY>10s9p5d3f</ENTRY></ROW><ROW><ENTRY>Ca</ENTRY><ENTRY>20s16p6d2f</ENTRY><ENTRY>10s9p6d2f</ENTRY></ROW><ROW><ENTRY>Sc–Zn</ENTRY><ENTRY>21s15p10d6f4g</ENTRY><ENTRY>8s7p5d3f2g</ENTRY></ROW><ROW><ENTRY>Ga–Kr</ENTRY><ENTRY>17s15p9d</ENTRY><ENTRY>9s9p5d</ENTRY></ROW></TBODY></TGROUP></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The active space used in the CASSCF calculations<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">2</REF> comprises all valence orbitals: 2s,2p for atoms Li–Ne, 3s,3p for Na-Ar, 4s,4p for K–Ca, 3d,4s,4p for Sc–Zn and 4s,4p for Ga–Kr.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">CASSCF is therefore identical to restricted open-shell HF (ROHF) for the atoms: He, Li, N–Ne, Na, P–Ar, K, Cr, Cu, and As–Kr.</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod20" novelty="None" advantage="None">Spherical symmetry is assured by performing the calculations in C<IT><SB>i</SB></IT> symmetry and averaging over the components of a given term.</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod21" novelty="None" advantage="None">The wave functions are of course eigenfunctions of the spin operator <IT>Ŝ</IT><SP>2</SP>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod22" novelty="None" advantage="None">The CASPT2 calculations<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF> are performed using the G1 correction to the zeroth order Hamiltonian.</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod23" novelty="None" advantage="None">A small imaginary level shift (0.05) was used for the transition metals.</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod24" novelty="None" advantage="None">The outermost core electrons were included in the correlation treatment (specifically 1s for Li–B, 2s,2p for Na-Ar, 3s–3p for K–Zn, and 3d for Ga–Kr).</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod25" novelty="None" advantage="None">The 〈<IT>r</IT><SP>2</SP>〉 values have been obtained using finite field perturbation theory (FFPT).</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod26" novelty="None" advantage="None">The method was calibrated by controlling it to give the same result as the expectation value for CASSCF wavefunctions.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj12" novelty="New" advantage="None">Full CI (FCI) calculations were also performed for the atoms He–N and Mg–P.</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results are quite similar to FFPT/CASPT2, which is reassuring.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod27" novelty="None" advantage="None">The calculations have been performed using the MOLCAS-6.0 software.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The percentage ratios for FFPT/CASPT2 (denoted PT2) <IT>r</IT><SP>2</SP> values compared to UHF have been given in Fig. 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 3 gives the percentage ratios for FFPT/CASPT2 and the hybrid functional B3LYP<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.2.">Analysis of the results</HEADER><P><s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj13" novelty="New" advantage="None">In order to calibrate the present results with those obtained using UHF and the Partridge basis set in section 2, we first compared the <IT>r</IT><SP>2</SP> values with the ROHF results obtained using the CASSCF method.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac37" novelty="None" advantage="None">The appropriate atoms for this comparison were listed above.</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">There were no notable differences for the atoms Li–Ar and As–Kr, (indeed less than 0.05 <IT>a</IT>20).</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The difference is marginally larger for K (0.20 <IT>a</IT>20), which could be due to the different basis sets used.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the other atoms CASSCF is not identical to ROHF.</annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reason is that in these cases there are important intra-valence correlation effects due to excitations from the doubly occupied <IT>n</IT>s shell to the empty (for the transition metals) or partially empty (for the main group atoms) <IT>n</IT>p shell.</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have collected the results for these atoms in the Table 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Also the the hybrid DFT functional B3LYP<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF> and the FFPT/CASPT2 results are presented in this table.</annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">(For completeness we give the FFPT values for the atoms not in the table: H 3.00, He 2.39, Li 18.45, N 12.20, O 11.39, F 10.49, Ne 9.62, Na 26.65, P 30.09, S 29.12, Cl 27.68, Ar 26.13, K 47.64, Cr 36.60, Cu 31.01, As 40.74, Se 41.04, Br 40.48, Kr 39.55).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">We now see a clear difference between the UHF and CASSCF results.</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The latter are constantly smaller and the difference is larger the more empty the p-shell.</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">This difference was anticipated in the introduction and can be easily understood.</annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The s<SP>2</SP> → p<SP>2</SP> excitation introduces angular correlation between the s-electrons, which increases the probability to find the two electrons in different sides of the atom.</annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The separation of the electron pair leads to a decreased screening of the core and the atom shrinks.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj14" novelty="New" advantage="None">The DFT functionals attempt to correct for this error in the UHF density.</annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is quite successful.</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The atom-sizes for BLYP are close (in the majority of cases) to the results obtained with FFPT/CASPT2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Comparing to the full CI results we see that DFT/B3LYP slightly overcompensates (except for Mg), while the FFPT/CASPT2 results are quite similar to the FCI results.</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Indeed the B3LYP predictions are very close (in magnitude) to the FFPT/CASPT2 predictions.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Finally, the overall effect of static correlation is to decrease the atomic size!</annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The effect is particularly pronounced for transition metal atoms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs20" novelty="None" advantage="None">However both atoms with large intra-valence correlation effects (eg V) and those with none (eg Cr) decrease in size on including dynamic correlation effects through introducing PT2 to CASSCF.</annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">We conclude that dynamic correlation reduces atomic size.</annotationART></s> <s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore both the static and the dynamical correlation effects lead to a decreased size of the atoms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The effect is largest for atoms with large static correlation effects.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.">Summary</HEADER><P><s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac38" novelty="None" advantage="None">Within the scope of the present calculations, we are now able to answer the posed questions.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Firstly, most Schrödinger atoms are smaller than the UHF atoms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">For He, Li, C, S, Cl, Ar, Se, Br and Kr the sizes (〈<IT>r</IT><SP>2</SP>〉) are the same within numerical accuracy (estimated to be 0.1 <IT>a</IT>20).</annotationART></s> <s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">N (0.13), O (0.17), F (0.24) and Ne (0.25) are indicated to have larger Schrödinger atoms than UHF atoms (the values in parenthesis are the differences in 〈<IT>r</IT><SP>2</SP>〉).</annotationART></s> <s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">But these differences are small.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the cases for which the CASSCF wavefunction is distinct from the HF wavefunction, the Schrödinger atoms are significantly smaller than the HF atoms (see the table, C is the exception).</annotationART></s> <s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Angular correlation therefore reduces atomic size.</annotationART></s> <s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the hard atoms N–Ne, there is no s<SP>2</SP> → p<SP>2</SP> excitation, and thus radial correlation is more important, leading to an increase in size for these atoms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the second row it is probable that angular correlation is introduced through the 3d orbitals, leading to the difference with the first row atoms, but radial correlation becomes dominant for Cl and Ar.</annotationART></s> <s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the third row radial correlation only dominates for Kr.</annotationART></s> <s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The summary is that these size differences reflect the balance between angular and radial correlation effects.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The predictions from DFT are in general in good agreement with the predictions from FFPT/CASPT2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">In particular the predictions with B3LYP are within 0.3 <IT>a</IT>20 for nearly all atoms (exceptions are Li, Be, B, Na, Mg, Ca and Cr), in particular the transition metal atoms are very well predicted (except Cr).</annotationART></s> <s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The predictions with BLYP are a little inferior, but they are superior to the predictions of CASSCF, as might be expected.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
