<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b403071k" hasDoc="yes" version="1168" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">X-ray absorption spectroscopy under reaction conditions: suitability of different reaction cells for combined catalyst characterization and time-resolved studies</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Structure–activity correlations of solid catalysts and time-resolved studies generally require that the structure within a solid catalyst is probed simultaneously and at the same location where the catalysis and the structural changes occur.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">These requirements lead to a compromise between the spectroscopic arrangement and the optimum design for an <IT>in situ</IT> reactor cell.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">Opportunities and limitations of <IT>in situ</IT> and time-resolved X-ray absorption spectroscopy (XAS) combined with gas analysis are critically analysed with the help of two different cell designs, an <IT>in situ</IT> EXAFS cell designed for solids in the form of pressed wafers and a capillary cell where the catalyst is packed similarly to a plug flow reactor.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None">On the basis of three examples, the reduction of CuO/ZnO, the reduction of PdO/ZrO<SB>2</SB> and methane oxidation over PdO<SB><IT>x</IT></SB>/ZrO<SB>2</SB>, criteria are developed which allow to judge the appropriate cell design in solid–fluid reactions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The prerequisites for the design of an <IT>in situ</IT> cell including the catalyst shape strongly depend on the time resolution required.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Important issues embrace the type of reaction to be investigated (slow <IT>vs.</IT> fast), the reaction medium, and the porosity of the catalyst material.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Criteria for assessing the role of pore and film diffusion in <IT>in situ</IT> studies are of paramount importance for a proper experimental design.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="1.">Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Time-resolved spectroscopic studies and the combined investigation of the structure and activity are important in the field of heterogeneous catalysis.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2 cit3 cit4 cit5 cit6 cit7 cit8 cit9 cit10 cit11">1–11</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">While time-resolved studies can elucidate information on intermediates on the catalyst surface, the combination of structure and activity aims at possible relationships between the active centres and the reactivity of the catalyst, being a first step to rational catalyst design.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both goals require <IT>in situ</IT> investigations and the design of appropriate <IT>in situ</IT> cells for simultaneous structural and catalytic studies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None"><IT>Ex situ</IT> studies have been performed to a great extent but it is generally accepted nowadays<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2 cit3 cit10">2,3,10</REF> that such studies provide structure–activity relationships only in selected cases, <IT>i.e</IT>. if it has been ruled out in advance that the structure does not change if the catalyst is exposed to ambient atmosphere or reaction conditions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Even cooling from the reaction temperature to room temperature may change the catalyst structure (<IT>cf</IT>. example in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">ref. 12</REF>).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In particular, techniques based on X-rays (X-ray diffraction, scattering techniques, X-ray absorption) have been used,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit8 cit9 cit13 cit14 cit15 cit16">4,8,9,13–16</REF> since <IT>in situ</IT> cells can be constructed that mimic conditions close to the reaction conditions, even in liquid phase or at high pressure.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17 cit18 cit19">17–19</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">This can be traced back to the fact that a number of cell window materials exist (Kapton, Al foil, thin diamond, Be and quartz windows), which have sufficient low absorbance of hard X-rays: thus the absorption of the probing beam by reaction gasses or window materials can be held marginal.</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the characterization of heterogeneous catalysts, the EXAFS technique is advantageous,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit20 cit21">4,20,21</REF> since it can detect element-specifically both amorphous and crystalline structures.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to interrelate the structure and activity of the catalysts, the flow properties in the EXAFS cell have to be similar to those usually met in the reactor and for time resolved studies, diffusion (film and pore diffusion) should be faster than the corresponding chemical reaction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Different designs have been reported, such as a disk of pelletized catalyst powder (also denoted as pressed wafer<SUP TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" />) placed in an environmental cell (<IT>cf</IT>. <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22 cit23">refs. 22 and 23</REF>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Another approach is the use of a powdered catalyst in an <IT>in situ</IT> cell as, <IT>e.g.</IT>, proposed by Bazin <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF>. and Clausen and Topsøe.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25">25</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Moreover, Clausen <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26">26</REF>. and Sankar <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27">27</REF>. used a capillary cell for combined XRD–EXAFS studies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">This cell design has recently also been used to obtain both structure and activity data on heterogeneous catalysts.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28 cit29">28,29</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot5" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, none of the studies compared the advantages and limitations of the different cell designs to provide truly <IT>in situ</IT> EXAFS studies, both under dynamic and static conditions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="New" advantage="None">Following the different concepts, we have constructed two kinds of <IT>in situ</IT> setups (using either an environmental chamber for a plate-like pellet/pressed wafer or a capillary cell for spectroscopic studies), which are shortly described in this paper.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Their characteristics are illustrated using exemplary case studies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj5" novelty="New" advantage="None">In the first case, the reduction of CuO/ZnO is investigated as an example for time-resolved studies since Cu<SP>+</SP> species occur as an intermediate during the reduction of CuO/ZnO which is important for the activation of such catalysts.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30 cit31 cit32">30–32</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj6" novelty="New" advantage="None">In addition, the reduction behaviour of PdO/ZrO<SB>2</SB> at room temperature was investigated in dependence of the material used for pressing a mechanically stable catalyst pellet.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj7" novelty="New" advantage="None">In the subsequent chapter, examples based on the PdO<SB><IT>x</IT></SB>/ZrO<SB>2</SB> catalyst are presented during methane combustion at 500 °C.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj8" novelty="New" advantage="None">Both structure and catalytic activity were determined at the same time under reaction conditions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj9" novelty="New" advantage="None">For comparison, reduction of PdO/ZrO<SB>2</SB> by methane and re-oxidation by oxygen are shown.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot6" novelty="None" advantage="None"><IT>In situ</IT> studies of such catalysts are important, since several mechanisms for the oxidation of methane have been proposed<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit33 cit34 cit35 cit36 cit37 cit38">33–38</REF> and the structure of Pd under reaction conditions is still a matter of discussion.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit35">35</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj10" novelty="New" advantage="None">Based on these examples, the setup of <IT>in situ</IT> cells in gas–solid, liquid–solid and dense fluids (<IT>e.g</IT>., supercritical fluids)–solid reactions are discussed with respect to catalyst shape, influence of external film and pore diffusion, catalyst efficiency and time-resolved studies.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.">Experimental</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.1">Design of <IT>in situ</IT> EXAFS cells</HEADER><P><s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Different <IT>in situ</IT> cell types that have been reported in literature are schematically gathered in Figs. 1a–c.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The first category of cells is based on a pressed wafer placed in an environmental chamber, which has been widely used for <IT>in situ</IT> studies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The gas bypasses the pressed wafer either from one or from two sides.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">An alternative design is shown in Fig. 1b.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In this case, the gas stream passes through the catalyst pellet instead of just by-passing it.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Another possibility is the use of a design that is similar to a plug flow reactor.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Since the wall thickness of normal glass reactors is too high, a glass tube with thin windows (0.5–2 mm diameter, 0.01 mm thick windows)—typically a glass capillary—has been proposed for such experiments.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26 cit27">26,27</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Alternative proposals using powdered catalysts have been made in literature as well.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24 cit25 cit39">24,25,39</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Based on the designs in literature, we have constructed two <IT>in situ</IT> cells that correspond to Fig. 1a (“pellet cell”) and Fig. 1c (“capillary cell”).</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">While the first cell is optimal with respect to spectroscopy (homogeneous sample), the second cell should be ideal for on-line catalytic studies (optimal thickness <IT>d</IT>/length <IT>l</IT>, no dead volume).</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj11" novelty="New" advantage="None">The <IT>in situ</IT> cell applicable for the investigation of self-supporting pellets has been designed according to Fig. 1a, embedding the cell inside an oven with X-ray transparent windows.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">A catalyst pellet (diameter of 13 mm) was pressed (<IT>ca</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">1 ton) and then loaded into the stainless steel cell.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The thickness of the pellet was <IT>ca</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">2 mm, and the total X-ray path through the cell <IT>ca</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">6 mm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The gas could pass along the pellet from both sides.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">From these dimensions, a dead volume of about 0.5 cm<SP>3</SP> resulted.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Three mass flow controllers (Brooks, 0–50 ml min<SP>−1</SP>) were used to control the feed of different pre-mixed gasses through the <IT>in situ</IT> cell.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The outlet of the reactor cell was connected to a mass spectrometer (Balzers).</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The whole <IT>in situ</IT> setup was mounted on an <IT>x</IT>,<IT>z</IT>,<IT>θ</IT>-table (<IT>x</IT> = translation, <IT>z</IT> = height, <IT>θ</IT> = angle to X-ray axis), directly fixed on an X95-profile (Newport) usually applied at synchrotron beamlines.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The setup according to Fig. 1c was constructed on the basis of a previous successful design<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26">26</REF> and some more details are given in Fig. 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj12" novelty="New" advantage="None">Focus was put on an <IT>in situ</IT> cell that allows both XAS studies and the determination of the catalytic performance of the catalysts.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The catalyst was loaded between two glass wool plugs in a glass reactor (quartz capillary, Markröhrchen, Hilgenberg GmbH) of 1–1.5 mm diameter.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The capillary is heated by a hot gas stream (here air, which can be substituted also by nitrogen) with a controlled air flow adjusted by a mass flow controller (Brooks, 0–2000 ml min<SP>−1</SP>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The temperature of the heater (<IT>T</IT><SB>control</SB>) was measured by a thermocouple at the heating element (ring cartridge, SUVAG, Zürich, 300 W/230 V) in order to control a constant temperature ramp.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The actual sample temperature (<IT>T</IT><SB>sample</SB>) was monitored just below the sample.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The heater was embedded in glass wool and the outer side of the oven could be cooled by water or air in order to prevent the surroundings from warming up (<IT>i.e.</IT> important for ionization chambers).</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The capillary was enclosed in a Kapton cap just above the heater where the hot stream of air passed out of the oven.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Similar to the pellet cell, the outlet of the capillary was connected using gas-tight Swagelok fittings to a mass spectrometer (Balzers).</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The whole assembly (<IT>in situ</IT> cell, heater) was mounted on a small <IT>x</IT>,<IT>z</IT>-table (<IT>x</IT> = translation, <IT>z</IT> = height) to align the sample in the X-ray beam.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.2">Materials and treatment of the samples</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.2.1">Reduction of 30% CuO/ZnO in 5% H<SB>2</SB>/He</HEADER><P><s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The 30% CuO/ZnO catalyst was prepared by controlled co-precipitation of Cu(NO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>2</SB> and Zn(NO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>2</SB> (precipitation pH = 9.2) followed by filtration through a 0.45 μm cellulose acetate membrane filter.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit40">40</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp19" novelty="None" advantage="None">After drying at 90 °C and grinding, 1.0 g of the precursor powder was calcined in an oven with a temperature ramp of 3 °C min<SP>−1</SP> and a final temperature of 250 °C for 10 h.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp20" novelty="None" advantage="None">The sample was diluted 1∶3 with boron nitride (Aldrich, hexagonal, 99.9%) during dry grinding and pressed either to a pellet of 13 mm diameter or loaded in a capillary cell (see above, 80–120 μm sieved fraction).</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp21" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the reduction, 5% H<SB>2</SB>/He was used.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.2.2">Reduction of PdO/ZrO<SB>2</SB> in 5% H<SB>2</SB>/He and re-oxidation in 2.5% O<SB>2</SB>/He</HEADER><P><s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp22" novelty="None" advantage="None">The PdO/ZrO<SB>2</SB> material was prepared from amorphous Pd<SB>33</SB>Zr<SB>67</SB> by oxidation in air at 400 °C.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit41">41</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp23" novelty="None" advantage="None">The sample was diluted with boron nitride (2∶7, Aldrich, hexagonal, 99.9%) or Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> (2∶7, Engelhard) and pressed to a pellet of 13 mm diameter (after dry grinding).</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp24" novelty="None" advantage="None">For experiments in the capillary cell, a sieved fraction of about 80–120 μm particles (diluted <IT>ca</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp24" novelty="None" advantage="None">1∶3 with Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB>) was filled into a 1.5 mm diameter capillary.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp25" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reduction was performed at room temperature in 5% H<SB>2</SB>/He, monitoring the outlet gas by a mass spectrometer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp26" novelty="None" advantage="None">Re-oxidation of the samples was performed in 2.5% O<SB>2</SB>/He to 500 °C with a ramp rate of 5 °C min<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.2.3">Methane combustion over PdO<SB><IT>x</IT></SB>/ZrO<SB>2</SB></HEADER><P><s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp27" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the first experiment the PdO/ZrO<SB>2</SB> material—prepared from amorphous Pd<SB>33</SB>Zr<SB>67</SB> by oxidation in air at 400 °C<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit41">41</REF>—was heated in the reaction mixture 1% CH<SB>4</SB>/4% O<SB>2</SB>/He to 500 °C with 5 °C min<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp28" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both the pellet and plug flow reactor cell were utilized using samples prepared in a similar way as for the reduction in 5% H<SB>2</SB>/He.</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp29" novelty="None" advantage="None">The space velocity was adjusted to the conversion degree of methane over the catalyst in order to study the <IT>in situ</IT> activation of the catalyst.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp30" novelty="None" advantage="None">Also, the reaction temperature was varied between 500 and 550 °C.</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp31" novelty="None" advantage="None">Afterwards, the catalyst was reduced by 5% H<SB>2</SB>/He at room temperature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp32" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the next step, the reduced Pd/ZrO<SB>2</SB> sample was studied during temperature programmed reaction in 1% CH<SB>4</SB>/4% O<SB>2</SB>/He.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.3">XAS experiments</HEADER><P><s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp33" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reduction of CuO/ZnO was performed at the Swiss Norwegian Beamline (SNBL) at the European Synchrotron Facility (ESRF) in Grenoble, France.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp34" novelty="None" advantage="None">The electron energy was 6.0 GeV and the ring current between 150 and 200 mA.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp35" novelty="None" advantage="None">A Si(111) crystal was used as channel-cut monochromator.</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp36" novelty="None" advantage="None">Harmonic rejection was performed by a double-bounce gold coated mirror system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp37" novelty="None" advantage="None">EXAFS data were collected in the transmission mode at room and elevated temperatures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp38" novelty="None" advantage="None">Three ionization chambers were used for detecting the intensity of the X-rays—of the incoming <IT>I</IT><SB>0</SB> (filled with 3% Ar and 97 % N<SB>2</SB>, 17 cm length), of the transmitted <IT>I</IT><SB>t</SB> (filled with 50% Ar and 50% N<SB>2</SB>, 31 cm length) and of the through the reference transmitted <IT>I</IT><SB>ref</SB> (filled with 50% Ar and 50% N<SB>2</SB>, 31 cm length) X-rays.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp39" novelty="None" advantage="None">The spectra were taken in a step scanning mode around the Cu K-edge (for fast spectra 8.96 – 9.08 keV, 3 min per scan).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp40" novelty="None" advantage="None">Characterization of the beam behind the sample in the capillary and the pellet cell was performed by an X-ray eye of Micro Photonics (Allentown, PA, USA).</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp41" novelty="None" advantage="None">Using the X-ray eye, the homogeneity of the samples was checked and the alignment of the <IT>in situ</IT> cell was optimised.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp42" novelty="None" advantage="None">The experiments with PdO/ZrO<SB>2</SB> were performed at SNBL, at ESRF, and at beamline X1 at HASYLAB (DESY, Hamburg).</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp43" novelty="None" advantage="None">In particular, for faster acquisition time (20–80 s) the QEXAFS mode at the Hamburger Synchrotronlabor (HASYLAB) at Deutsches Elektronen Synchrotron (DESY in Hamburg, Germany) at beamline X1 was applied using a Si(311) double crystal monochromator.</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp44" novelty="None" advantage="None">The typical beam current was 80–120 mA (operating positron energy at 4.5 GeV).</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp45" novelty="None" advantage="None">Higher harmonics were effectively removed by detuning of the crystals to 70% of the maximum intensity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp46" novelty="None" advantage="None">Three ionisation chambers filled with Ar were used to record the intensity of the incident and the transmitted X-rays (<IT>in situ</IT> reactor cell located between the first and second ionisation chamber, a Pd-reference foil for energy calibration between the second and third ionization chamber).</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp47" novelty="None" advantage="None">Under stationary conditions EXAFS spectra were taken around the Pd K-edge in the step scanning mode between 24 000 and 25 800 eV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp48" novelty="None" advantage="None">Faster scans around the Pd K-edge were recorded using the normal step scanning EXAFS mode (<IT>ca</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp48" novelty="None" advantage="None">5 min per scan) or the continuous EXAFS scanning mode between 24 300 and 24 800 eV (80 s per scan, QEXAFS, cf<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit42">42</REF>.).</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp49" novelty="None" advantage="None">During reduction with hydrogen faster scans were recorded (24 310–24 490 eV, 20 s per scan).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp50" novelty="None" advantage="None">The raw data were energy-calibrated (Pd K-edge energy of the Pd-foil: 24 350 eV, first inflection point), smoothed, background corrected, and normalized using the WINXAS 2.1 software.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit43">43</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp51" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to quantify the relative ratio of Cu<SP>2+</SP>/Cu<SP>+</SP>/Cu<SP>0</SP> and Pd<SP>2+</SP>/Pd<SP>0</SP>, respectively, linear combination analysis of the XANES region (8.97 to 9.03 keV for the Cu K-edge and 24.33–24.45 keV for the Pd K-edge) around the edge was performed, using the spectra of the completely reduced (after hydrogen treatment) and the oxidized (as prepared) materials as model spectra.</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp52" novelty="None" advantage="None">Additionally, the XANES spectrum of Cu<SB>2</SB>O was included in the fit.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.">Results and discussion</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.1.">Characterization of the X-ray beam behind the catalyst sample in the <IT>in situ</IT> cells</HEADER><P><s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 3 gives a comparison of the X-ray beam behind the plug-flow reactor and the pellet reactor <IT>in situ</IT> cell.</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Figs. 3a and 3d represent the optimal position of the <IT>in situ</IT> cells.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">While the beam is homogeneous in the image of Fig. 3d (pellet cell), several shadows of the particles can be seen in the image of Fig. 3a (capillary cell).</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hence, some inhomogeneity of the sieved catalyst in the capillary cell can be seen with the X-ray eye.</annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Images 3b and 3c (capillary cell) show what happens if the capillary is not properly aligned: the intensity is higher at the outer region (Fig. 3b) or at the bottom of the capillary (Fig. 3c).</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, no pinhole is present as, <IT>e.g</IT>., shown in image 3e (pellet cell) where the beam bypasses the catalyst pellet.</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results show that inhomogeneities in the sample may lead to inhomogeneous penetration of the X-ray through the sample.</annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="New" advantage="None">These inhomogeneities can be minimized using a small sieved fraction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="New" advantage="No">They lead in principle to a lower <IT>μ</IT><IT>d</IT>, and hence a lower sensitivity of the method.</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">This effect is not so relevant, unless the beam moves during the experiment (or the beam is inhomogeneous in intensity and the particles move).</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="New" advantage="No">Also, the use of a position sensitive detector, as applied, <IT>e.g.</IT>, in the DEXAFS technique,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit44 cit45">44,45</REF> may be difficult if the sieved fraction is not small enough.</annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">For this technique, it is important to use a sample as homogeneous as possible, which is best achieved with finely ground powder pressed as a wafer, as is visible in Fig. 3d.</annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">QEXAFS is not so sensitive to inhomogeneities in the sample since it probes the whole sample at all energies as an average<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit32 cit45">32,45</REF> and was thus exclusively used in these studies.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.2.">Reduction of CuO/ZnO in 5% H<SB>2</SB>/He</HEADER><P><s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The time-resolved reduction of CuO/ZnO in the form of powder or pressed wafers has been subject to a number of studies.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30 cit31 cit32">30–32</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj13" novelty="New" advantage="None">Here, we compare the reduction of a 30% CuO/ZnO sample (diluted in boron nitride) when using it as pressed wafer (pellet cell, Fig. 1a) or as sieved fraction (capillary cell, Fig. 1c).</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 4 shows the results.</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the left, normalised spectra at the Cu K-edge are shown for illustration (note that there are less “intermediate” spectra in Fig. 4a than in 4b).</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The right part of the figure shows that in both cases the reduction started at about 175–180 °C.</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Accordingly, on-line gas analysis uncovered the consumption of hydrogen and the formation of water (not shown).</annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although hydrogen was only consumed to a small extent during reduction (&lt;30%) and the temperature ramp was the same (1 °C min<SP>−1</SP>) in both cases, the reduction in the capillary cell was faster than that observed with the pellet cell.</annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Analysis of the XANES region by linear combination of spectra originating from Cu<SP>0</SP>, Cu<SP>+</SP>, and Cu<SP>2+</SP> showed that in both cases Cu<SP>+</SP> is formed as an intermediate (region 8.97–9.03 keV).</annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The major part of the copper oxide is, however, directly reduced to Cu<SP>0</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is in agreement with recent studies.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30 cit31 cit32">30–32</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fraction of Cu<SP>+</SP> is also slightly different and principal component analysis gave similar results.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Despite the low heating rate, a different behaviour was found which is attributed to the different design of the <IT>in situ</IT> cells.</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reduction of CuO/ZnO starts in both cases at the same temperature but the reduction time is markedly different.</annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since hydrogen was used in excess and in the mass spectrometer a conversion of &lt;30% was observed, the difference can be attributed to mass transfer limitations or different flow conditions in the pellet cell.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">A rough estimate of the significance of the various steps of the gas–solid reaction (external film diffusion, pore diffusion, chemical reaction) can be obtained by applying a shrinking core model with constant size (thickness) of the plate-like pellet/particle.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit46 cit47 cit48 cit49">46–49</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The duration for complete reduction <IT>τ</IT><SB>t</SB> can be expressed aswhere <IT>τ</IT><SB>film</SB>, <IT>τ</IT><SB>pore</SB>, and <IT>τ</IT><SB>chem</SB> are the times for external mass transfer, pore diffusion and the chemical reaction, respectively, necessary if the corresponding steps control the overall reaction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Models describing the fluid–solid reaction for different rate limiting steps have been summarized by Levenspiel both for flat plates and spheres.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit47">47</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Assuming a laminar flow in case of the pellet cell (200 °C, isothermal pellet), the different contributions to the complete reduction time (<IT>τ</IT><SB>t</SB>) can be calculated using the expressions developed for the shrinking core model of unchanging size for flat plates:where <IT>ρ</IT><SB>CuO</SB> is the molar density of copper in the pellet, d the thickness of the pellet, <IT>c</IT><SB>H<SB>2</SB></SB> the concentration of hydrogen and <IT>k</IT><SB>m</SB> the mass transfer coefficient.</annotationART></s> <s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The different geometric parameters and fluid properties used for the evaluation are summarized in Table 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to estimate the mass transfer coefficient <IT>k</IT><SB>m</SB>, we consider a laminar flow across a flat plate of length <IT>L</IT> = 13 mm, which can be described and analytically solved using a boundary layer model<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit50">50</REF> resulting in an average mass transfer coefficientwhere <IT>Re</IT><SB><IT>L</IT></SB> is the Reynolds number for a plate of length <IT>L</IT>, <IT>Sc</IT> the Schmidt number and <IT>D</IT><SB>H<SB>2</SB></SB> the diffusion coefficient of H<SB>2</SB> in He (Table 1).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None">By using eqn. (2), a time for complete reduction of 6.5 s is estimated if external mass transport (film diffusion) is rate-determining.</annotationART></s> <s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, diffusion through the gas film cannot be the limiting step during reduction of CuO/ZnO in the pellet cell.</annotationART></s> <s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The control by the chemical reaction cannot explain the difference between the two reaction cells either.</annotationART></s> <s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, pore diffusion can be assumed to be the limiting step.</annotationART></s> <s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Pore diffusion coefficients in porous solids depend on the porosity of the solid and slightly on the temperature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Assuming an effective diffusion coefficient <IT>D</IT><SB>e</SB> between 10<SP>−6</SP> and 10<SP>−8</SP> m<SP>2</SP> s<SP>−1</SP> and a pellet thickness of <IT>d</IT> = 2 mm, reduction times can be calculated according to:<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit47">47</REF>(disk of 2 mm diameter, molar density of copper in the pellet <IT>ρ</IT><SB>CuO</SB> = 67 mol m<SP>−3</SP>, concentration of hydrogen <IT>c</IT><SB>H<SB>2</SB></SB> = 1 mol m<SP>−3</SP>, compare with Table 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">For <IT>D</IT><SB>e</SB> = 10<SP>−6</SP> and 10<SP>−8</SP> m<SP>2</SP> s<SP>−1</SP> reduction times of 33 s and 56 min, respectively, can be calculated and thus <IT>τ</IT><SB>t</SB> can strongly depend on the pore diffusion.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" advantage="None">In comparison, using a sieved fraction of 100 μm in a capillary microreactor under continuous flow conditions the terms for both film diffusion and pore diffusion are less significant as the following calculation shows.</annotationART></s> <s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Applying the expressions for spherical particles (constant particle size), the contribution from film diffusion in a plug flow reactor can be calculated as:where <IT>R</IT><SB>p</SB> is the radius of the spherical particle.</annotationART></s> <s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac20" novelty="None" advantage="None">Mass transfer coefficients (<IT>k</IT><SB>m</SB>) for fluids flowing around spheres in packed-bed reactors have been widely estimated for different cases (<IT>e.g</IT>., <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit50 cit51 cit52">refs. 50–52</REF>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="143"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac21" novelty="None" advantage="None">For Reynolds numbers in the range 0.1 &lt; <IT>Re</IT><SB>p</SB> &lt; 50 applied in this study (Table 1), a suitable relation is reported in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit50 cit52">ref. 50 and 52</REF>:</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="144"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The calculation of the mass transfer coefficient from the Reynolds number and the Schmidt number is given in Table 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="145"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs20" novelty="None" advantage="None">Calculation of the reduction time, assuming that film diffusion is rate-limiting (eqn. (5)), results in a <IT>τ</IT><SB>film</SB> of 1.7 ms.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="146"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Assuming pore diffusion instead of film diffusion being the rate limiting step, the corresponding reduction times for round-shaped particles can be calculated according to:</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="147"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs21" novelty="None" advantage="None">Also, these reduction times are much smaller with 0.02–2 s for a diffusion coefficient <IT>D</IT><SB>e</SB> of 10<SP>−6</SP>–10<SP>−8</SP> m<SP>2</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="148"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">As long as the CuO/ZnO reduction takes more than 1 s at a <IT>D</IT><SB>e</SB> &gt; 10<SP>−7</SP> m<SP>2</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>, the rate-limitation results from the chemical reaction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="149"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hence, the differences between the two <IT>in situ</IT> cells is expected to be due to pore diffusion effects.</annotationART></s> <s sid="150"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that here we assumed different pore diffusion coefficients for hydrogen.</annotationART></s> <s sid="151"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac22" novelty="None" advantage="None">The same accounts for the gaseous product (water formation) and it has recently been shown that the reduction of CuO/ZnO is strongly affected by the presence of water.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit53">53</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="152"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hence, also the pore diffusion of water could be limiting.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="153"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, we can conclude from these estimations that for gas–solid reactions in the subsecond region,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit32 cit54 cit55">4,32,54,55</REF> intermediates may not only be a consequence of the reaction itself but also be indirectly affected by film and/or pore diffusion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="154"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is, in particular, the case if the flow properties are not as good as in a plug flow reactor or the particle diameter is too high.</annotationART></s> <s sid="155"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Moreover, differences can be more significant if larger molecules and, in particular, liquids are used (smaller diffusion coefficient).</annotationART></s> <s sid="156"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both <IT>in situ</IT> cells can give similar results during temperature programmed reaction if the ramp rate is small, the flow properties are good and the pore diffusion of the molecules is sufficiently fast.</annotationART></s> <s sid="157"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The latter is also strongly dependent on the material used to dilute the catalyst sample as shown in the next part.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.3">Comparison of differently prepared PdO/ZrO<SB>2</SB> samples during reduction</HEADER><P><s sid="158"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac23" novelty="None" advantage="None">Reduction of an oxidized PdO/ZrO<SB>2</SB> catalyst by hydrogen turned out to lead to a more active methane combustion catalyst.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit41 cit56">41,56</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="159"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac24" novelty="None" advantage="None">Reduction occurs very fast at room temperature.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit37">37</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="160"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs22" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 5 shows the reduction of PdO/ZrO<SB>2</SB> (capillary cell, diluted 1∶3 with Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB>) in 5% H<SB>2</SB>/He using the QEXAFS (20 s per scan) mode.</annotationART></s> <s sid="161"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs23" novelty="None" advantage="None">On-line gas analysis showed that the response time inside the reactor is &lt;5 s, while the reaction occurs over a time interval of 2 min.</annotationART></s> <s sid="162"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp53" novelty="None" advantage="None">The XANES region (24.33–24.45 keV) of all spectra could be reconstructed from the spectrum of the reduced and the oxidized form of the sample.</annotationART></s> <s sid="163"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs24" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fraction <IT>α</IT> of oxidized or metallic palladium is shown in Fig. 5b.</annotationART></s> <s sid="164"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs25" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that some palladium hydride formed as well, since EXAFS analysis indicated the formation of some Pd hydride due to an increased Pd–Pd distance to 2.80 Å.</annotationART></s> <s sid="165"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The analysis in Fig. 5b reveals that the reduction occurs <IT>via</IT> an induction and acceleration period.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="166"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs26" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 6 shows the comparison of two different pellets in the pellet cell.</annotationART></s> <s sid="167"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp54" novelty="None" advantage="None">Using a pressed wafer of PdO/ZrO<SB>2</SB> diluted once with BN (thickness <IT>d</IT> = 1.5 mm) and once with Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> (thickness <IT>d</IT> = 2 mm), shows a striking difference in the reduction behaviour.</annotationART></s> <s sid="168"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs27" novelty="None" advantage="None">The same reduction conditions were used in both cases and also the response time of the pellet cell was only a few seconds.</annotationART></s> <s sid="169"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs28" novelty="None" advantage="None">Nevertheless, both the start of the PdO/ZrO<SB>2</SB> reduction, as well as the reduction rate, are negatively affected in the case of the dilution with boron nitride.</annotationART></s> <s sid="170"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">This shows that not only the catalyst shape (sieved catalyst powder <IT>vs</IT>. pellet) but also the material plays an important role.</annotationART></s> <s sid="171"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs29" novelty="None" advantage="None">BET measurements of the reduced pellets revealed that the surface area and the pore structure of the BN- and Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB>-pellet are significantly different.</annotationART></s> <s sid="172"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs30" novelty="None" advantage="None">While the specific pore volume of the used Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> pellet is 0.327 cm<SP>3</SP> g<SP>−1</SP> (the BET surface area is <IT>ca</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="173"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs30" novelty="None" advantage="None">133 m<SP>2</SP> g<SP>−1</SP>), the pore volume of the BN pellet is only 0.036 cm<SP>3</SP> g<SP>−1</SP> and the BET surface area 2 m<SP>2</SP> g<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="174"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hence, using BN for pressing the pellets led to pellets with significantly lower porosity, and these results suggest the use of high porosity materials.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.4.">The oxidation state of palladium during catalytic combustion of methane over PdO<SB><IT>x</IT></SB>/ZrO<SB>2</SB></HEADER><P><s sid="175"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac25" novelty="None" advantage="None">Several mechanisms concerning the oxidation of methane over Pd/ZrO<SB>2</SB> catalysts have been proposed.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit35 cit37">35,37</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="176"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac26" novelty="None" advantage="None">Interestingly, Pd/ZrO<SB>2</SB> (pre-reduced in hydrogen) performs better than PdO/ZrO<SB>2</SB> in this reaction.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit56">56</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="177"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hence, the question arises on the role which metallic Pd plays in the combustion of methane.</annotationART></s> <s sid="178"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj14" novelty="New" advantage="None">Once again, results over PdO<SB><IT>x</IT></SB>/ZrO<SB>2</SB> in a pellet and a capillary cell are considered.</annotationART></s> <s sid="179"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj15" novelty="New" advantage="None">As a basis, the re-oxidation of a (reduced) Pd/ZrO<SB>2</SB> sample in 2.5% O<SB>2</SB>/He and reduction in 1% CH<SB>4</SB>/He are discussed.</annotationART></s></P><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.4.1.">Re-oxidation of Pd/ZrO<SB>2</SB> in oxygen and reduction of PdO/ZrO<SB>2</SB> in methane</HEADER><P><s sid="180"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs31" novelty="None" advantage="None">Figs. 7 and 8 show the oxidation of Pd/ZrO<SB>2</SB> in 2.5% O<SB>2</SB>/He and the reduction of PdO/ZrO<SB>2</SB> in 1% CH<SB>4</SB>/He, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="181"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs32" novelty="None" advantage="None">While reduction of PdO/ZrO<SB>2</SB> in hydrogen already occurs at room temperature (Figs. 5 and 6), the re-oxidation only partly occurs at room temperature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="182"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac27" novelty="None" advantage="None">Interestingly, this oxidation has not been observed by TPO on Pd/ZrO<SB>2</SB>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit57">57</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="183"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Some shift in the edge position was observed as well, indicating the decomposition of the Pd hydride phase (also supported by EXAFS analysis).</annotationART></s> <s sid="184"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs33" novelty="None" advantage="None">Above 320 °C, most of the palladium is re-oxidized and XANES/EXAFS analysis reveals no detectable metallic palladium after oxidation at 500 °C, supported by thermal analysis (not shown).</annotationART></s> <s sid="185"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs34" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reduction by methane also occurs only at higher temperatures (&gt;275 °C) and results in a completely reduced catalyst.</annotationART></s> <s sid="186"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs35" novelty="None" advantage="None">No reduction took place up to 275 °C.</annotationART></s> <s sid="187"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs36" novelty="None" advantage="None">Above this temperature, a very sudden reduction within 1 scan (50 s per scan) was observed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="188"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">It seems that once methane can be activated on the PdO/ZrO<SB>2</SB> catalyst a fast reaction occurs.</annotationART></s> <s sid="189"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs37" novelty="None" advantage="None">PdO was rapidly reduced once metallic particles started to be formed, which seem to catalyse the activation of methane.</annotationART></s> <s sid="190"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is in agreement with temperature programmed reduction and Raman studies,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit57">57</REF> where it was also found that a certain temperature is needed to activate methane.</annotationART></s> <s sid="191"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Once metallic palladium is formed, dissociative adsorption of methane is enhanced (on the metallic Pd particles) and further reduction occurs.</annotationART></s> <s sid="192"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac28" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fact that an autocatalytic reduction occurs at 275 °C is also supported by the fact that dissociative adsorption of methane is reported to occur already at 200 °C<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit58">58</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.4.2.">Reaction in 1% CH<SB>4</SB>/4% O<SB>2</SB>/He</HEADER><P><s sid="193"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs38" novelty="None" advantage="None">The oxidation behaviour of Pd/ZrO<SB>2</SB> during temperature programmed reaction in 1% CH<SB>4</SB>/4% O<SB>2</SB>/He (Fig. 9) uncovers in the low temperature region (&lt;350 °C) a similar behaviour as in 2.5% O<SB>2</SB>/He.</annotationART></s> <s sid="194"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs39" novelty="None" advantage="None">The methane combustion (according to on-line gas analysis) sets in at 300–320 °C.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="195"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj16" novelty="New" advantage="None">Likewise, in the reduction of the CuO/ZnO, both the plug-flow reactor cell (based on the capillary) and the cell using a pelletized sample (disk-shape) were compared.</annotationART></s> <s sid="196"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs40" novelty="None" advantage="None">In both setups, methane combustion was more effective over Pd/ZrO<SB>2</SB> (pre-reduced) than PdO/ZrO<SB>2</SB> (oxidized form by direct oxidation of amorphous PdZr alloy).</annotationART></s> <s sid="197"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs41" novelty="None" advantage="None">During the temperature programmed reaction the conversion of methane over Pd/ZrO<SB>2</SB> reached already its maximum well below 500 °C, whereas only partial conversion of methane was observed over the PdO/ZrO<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="198"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs42" novelty="None" advantage="None">As Table 2 summarizes, the conversion over the Pd/ZrO<SB>2</SB> pellet only reached about 80%, while total conversion was observed over Pd/ZrO<SB>2</SB> in the capillary cell.</annotationART></s> <s sid="199"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is traced back to the dead volume of the pellet cell, allowing some of the methane to pass through the cell without contact with the catalyst (by-passing).</annotationART></s> <s sid="200"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs43" novelty="None" advantage="None">The observed conversions and rates are summarized in Table 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="201"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs44" novelty="None" advantage="None">In both cases, it was observed that PdO/ZrO<SB>2</SB> was not reduced to an extent measurable by EXAFS/XANES, while starting from Pd/ZrO<SB>2</SB> evidenced that Pd was not completely re-oxidized or possessed a different structure (Fig. 10), both if either the pellet or the glass capillary cell was used.</annotationART></s> <s sid="202"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs45" novelty="None" advantage="None">The “whiteline” in the XANES spectra was slightly different and EXAFS analysis indicated a different number of coordination shells in the PdO/ZrO<SB>2</SB> and the Pd/ZrO<SB>2</SB> catalyst after methane combustion at 500 °C.</annotationART></s> <s sid="203"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs46" novelty="None" advantage="None">While the PdO/ZrO<SB>2</SB> sample had mainly contributions at 2.02 Å (Pd–O) and at 3.02 Å (Pd–Pd in oxide), a significantly higher contribution at 2.76 Å (Pd–Pd shell) was found in the Pd/ZrO<SB>2</SB> catalyst (<IT>cf</IT>. more details and similar results in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit37">ref. 37</REF>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="204"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hence, the findings on the structure of the catalyst are similar in both <IT>in situ</IT> studies, though the catalytic activity is different but with the same tendency in the two cells.</annotationART></s> <s sid="205"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj17" novelty="New" advantage="None">Nevertheless, the significantly lower methane oxidation rate over the catalyst pellet compared to the corresponding particles in the capillary reactor requires an explanation.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.4.3.">Comparison of the effectiveness of the catalyst in a plug flow and a pellet <IT>in situ</IT> cell</HEADER><P><s sid="206"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">One reason for the lower catalytic activity of disk-shaped catalyst samples compared to the sieved catalyst powder is by-passing of the gas due to the dead volume in the pellet reactor cell.</annotationART></s> <s sid="207"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This would, however, still lead to a representative result for both the catalytic activity and the active species if the whole catalyst contributes to the catalytic activity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="208"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj18" novelty="New" advantage="None">In order to verify this hypothesis for methane combustion, the influence of pore diffusion in both kinds of cells is considered.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="209"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac29" novelty="None" advantage="None">The pore diffusion resistance can dramatically influence the effectiveness of heterogeneous catalysts.</annotationART></s> <s sid="210"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac30" novelty="None" advantage="None">The phenomenon has been intensively investigated in kinetics and reaction engineering studies in heterogeneous catalysis.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit47 cit59 cit60">47,59,60</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="211"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj19" novelty="New" advantage="None">This concept can be directly transferred to estimate the influence of the catalyst shapes (porosity, characteristic length) in the two cell designs used in the present study.</annotationART></s> <s sid="212"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">According to Thiele<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit61">61</REF> and Aris,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit62">62</REF> for a plate-like pellet and a first order reaction the effectiveness factor <IT>η</IT> can be described in terms of the Thiele modulus <IT>ψ</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit47">47</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="213"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod11" novelty="None" advantage="None">For a plug flow reactor, the equations are correspondingly given (see Table 3), and for a rough estimation the same relation as given in eqn. (8) can be used with a characteristic length: <IT>L</IT><SB>c</SB> = <IT>d</IT><SB>p</SB>/6.</annotationART></s> <s sid="214"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod12" novelty="None" advantage="None">For estimating the effectiveness factor in the methane oxidation reaction over a cylindrical platelet of thickness <IT>d</IT> = 2 mm and over spherical particles of <IT>d</IT><SB>p</SB> = 80 μm both the reaction rate and the diffusion coefficient were taken from a recent work on methane combustion over Pd/Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> catalysts by Groppi <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit63">63</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="215"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">The calculations summarized in Table 3, show that the effectiveness factor of the plate-like pellet is only 0.03%, which means that due to pore resistance only a thin layer on each side is contributing to the reaction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="216"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs47" novelty="None" advantage="None">For an efficiency of 50% over a Pd/ZrO<SB>2</SB> catalyst pellet, a very thin platelet of <IT>d</IT> ≤ 0.06 mm is required.</annotationART></s> <s sid="217"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs48" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 11 shows the estimated concentration gradient in the pellet, it dropped by 90% already at 70 μm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="218"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">If this drop in reactant concentration can be tolerated in the middle of the pellet, a Thiele modulus of about <IT>ψ</IT> = 3 is required, corresponding in the case of a flat plate to a thickness of <IT>d</IT> = 160 μm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="219"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs49" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the capillary cell the effectiveness factor is much larger but still only 88% of the catalyst are effectively contributing to the reaction (due to the fast reaction rate).</annotationART></s> <s sid="220"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs50" novelty="None" advantage="None">The concentration gradient of the reactants inside a catalyst particle is flat, as Fig. 11 shows.</annotationART></s> <s sid="221"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hence, the structure monitored by the bulk technique EXAFS is particularly representative if the catalyst is used as powder.</annotationART></s> <s sid="222"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">For pellet-like shapes a more surface-sensitive technique (<IT>e.g</IT>., electron yield XAS, grazing incidence XAS) would be required.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.">Discussion</HEADER><P><s sid="223"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The experiments in this study have shown the importance of appropriate cell designs for <IT>in situ</IT> X-ray absorption spectroscopy and related <IT>operando</IT> spectroscopic techniques.</annotationART></s> <s sid="224"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The EXAFS technique offers a number of opportunities in the field of time-resolved studies and for combining structural analysis with catalytic activity measurements.</annotationART></s> <s sid="225"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj20" novelty="New" advantage="None">Here, the reduction of CuO/ZnO and PdO/ZrO<SB>2</SB> was uncovered in a time-resolved manner and the structure of PdO<SB><IT>x</IT></SB>/ZrO<SB>2</SB> was monitored during methane combustion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="226"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac31" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reduction of CuO occurs <IT>via</IT> Cu<SP>+</SP> species, as also supported in .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30 cit31 cit32">refs. 30–32</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="227"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, it seems that the reduction is dependent on the cell design/sample preparation which may also influence the occurrence of Cu<SP>+</SP> species.</annotationART></s> <s sid="228"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs51" novelty="None" advantage="None">In case of methane oxidation over PdO<SB><IT>x</IT></SB>/ZrO<SB>2</SB> catalysts, the pre-reduced catalyst was more active under reaction conditions, in accordance with literature, and some of the palladium remained in reduced state at 500 °C under reaction conditions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="229"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs52" novelty="None" advantage="None">Reduction of PdO/ZrO<SB>2</SB> to Pd/ZrO<SB>2</SB> by hydrogen occurred within 5 min at room temperature, while re-oxidation was only to a small extent observed up to 250 °C.</annotationART></s> <s sid="230"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs53" novelty="None" advantage="None">Above this temperature, the palladium constituent was continuously and completely oxidized.</annotationART></s> <s sid="231"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None">These studies support the conclusions in literature that reduced palladium is one of the active species in methane combustion.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit37 cit57 cit64">37,57,64</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="232"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs54" novelty="None" advantage="None">Studies with an X-ray eye uncovered that the X-ray intensity behind a sample pressed as pellet was more homogeneous than behind a catalyst sample used in a sieved powder fraction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="233"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, a pellet will lead to a better signal/noise ratio (due to a higher <IT>μd</IT>), in particular, if the position of the beam varies slightly.</annotationART></s> <s sid="234"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res29" novelty="None" advantage="None">The use of pellets also allows to irradiate a larger area resulting in a better signal/noise ratio.</annotationART></s> <s sid="235"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res30" novelty="None" advantage="None">A further limitation of the capillary cell used in this study is that the temperature is measured below the catalyst sample and not in the catalyst bed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="236"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" advantage="None">Temperature measurement in the catalyst sample may become of paramount importance for highly exothermic or endothermic reactions, particularly at high conversion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="237"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac32" novelty="None" advantage="None">Moreover, the catalyst composition may change in such a plug flow reactor, so that local probing of the catalyst composition over the catalyst bed would be interesting as we recently proposed.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit65">65</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="238"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac33" novelty="None" advantage="None">Effects due to pore diffusion resistance can be encountered both in time-resolved studies and in catalytic studies, in particular in the case of pressed wafers.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="239"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Eqns. (2), (4), (5) and (7) show that time-resolved changes on heterogeneous catalysts depend on the gas–solid mass transfer coefficient and the effective diffusion of the reactants/products in the solid.</annotationART></s> <s sid="240"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res32" novelty="None" advantage="None">Effects caused by pore diffusion limitations can be eliminated or at least mitigated by the use of macroporous materials and/or small particles or very thin pellets.</annotationART></s> <s sid="241"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs55" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our study has shown two extreme cases: the pore structure/volume of BN and Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> are very different.</annotationART></s> <s sid="242"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res33" novelty="None" advantage="None">This shows that high porosity materials, such as Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> used in this study, are preferable.</annotationART></s> <s sid="243"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since boron nitride is a favoured material in X-ray absorption spectroscopy due to the light elements, the use of a high porosity form would be of interest for spectroscopic purposes—here hexagonal BN with low porosity was used.</annotationART></s> <s sid="244"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Nevertheless, in slow gas–solid reactions the pore diffusion is relatively fast compared to the chemical reaction rate so that using a disk may be preferred due to the better signal/noise ratio in spectroscopy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="245"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj21" novelty="New" advantage="None">We suggest therefore a comparison of the measured reaction time <IT>τ</IT><SB>t</SB> with the time <IT>τ</IT><SB>film</SB> expected if film resistance is rate-limiting or with the time <IT>τ</IT><SB>pore</SB> if pore diffusion is limiting, using eqns. (2)–(7), respectively.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="246"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj21" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">These effects become even more relevant in liquid/solid reactions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="247"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs56" novelty="None" advantage="None">Recently, we observed in the reduction of PdO/Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> by benzyl alcohol that the reduction of palladium occurred within less than 2 min using PdO/Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> as powder, while the reduction over a PdO/Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> pellet took more than 45 min.</annotationART></s> <s sid="248"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Assuming a diffusion coefficient of <IT>D</IT><SB>e</SB> = 1 × 10<SP>−9</SP> m<SP>2</SP> s<SP>−1</SP> of the alcohol in a fluid and a typical viscosity of 0.33 × 10<SP>−3</SP> m<SP>−1</SP> kg s<SP>−1</SP>, it already turns out with eqns. (2) and (5) that the external film resistance (fluid–solid) in liquid phase is much higher than in gas phase.</annotationART></s> <s sid="249"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs57" novelty="None" advantage="None">In case of film diffusion controls the reduction, some example calculations are given in Table 4 for reduction of a catalyst pellet (platelet) and a catalyst powder (spherical particles) of 5% Pd/Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> in toluene.</annotationART></s> <s sid="250"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac34" novelty="None" advantage="None">Also, pore diffusion resistance is supposed to be considerably higher than in gas phase.</annotationART></s> <s sid="251"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hence, combination of on-line catalytic monitoring combined with EXAFS analysis has to be performed on finely sieved catalysts, as recently reported in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit66 cit67">refs. 66 and 67</REF>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="252"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Another possibility is the use of shell-impregnated catalysts.</annotationART></s> <s sid="253"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj22" novelty="New" advantage="None">We applied this approach in the field of supercritical (or dense) fluids, since sufficiently large particles are required for proper flow conditions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit68">68</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="254"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac35" novelty="None" advantage="None">A recent ATR-IR study<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit69">69</REF> has proven that the supercritical fluid inside the pores has a similar density to the corresponding liquid and it can thus be assumed to have a similar effective diffusion coefficient as in liquid carbon dioxide.</annotationART></s> <s sid="255"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac35" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fluid–solid mass transfer coefficient is, however, much higher than in liquid phase.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="256"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Another important consequence of the presented influence of film and pore resistance is the appropriate design of cells for time-resolved studies on heterogeneous catalysts.</annotationART></s> <s sid="257"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj23" novelty="New" advantage="None">Both the QEXAFS and DEXAFS techniques are used with the aim to identify possible intermediates and/or reveal the mechanism of reduction/oxidation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="258"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res34" novelty="None" advantage="None">Considering the reduction of a catalyst by hydrogen on a pressed wafer, it turns out according to eqn. (2) that studies on the second scale will even be influenced by the gas film diffusion using the <IT>in situ</IT> cell sketched in Fig. 1c.</annotationART></s> <s sid="259"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs58" novelty="None" advantage="None">The calculations using a plug flow reactor with catalyst particles of mean particle size of 100 μm show that in this case the response time is <IT>ca</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="260"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs58" novelty="None" advantage="None">1 ms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="261"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res35" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hence, 1 ms seems to be the lower reasonable limit of time-resolved studies in a fluid/solid reaction.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="262"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Not only during time-resolved studies but also in case of reactions, such as methane oxidation, pore resistance may influence the spectroscopic results, in particular if the diffusion of reactants inside the pores is slow compared to the chemical reaction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="263"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this case, only a fraction of the catalyst may be involved in the reaction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="264"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac36" novelty="None" advantage="None">Though methane oxidation is a rapid reaction, such limitations by pore/film diffusion have also been observed in other studies.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit70">70</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="265"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="Old" advantage="None">A possible solution may be the use of electron yield XAS.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit71">71</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="266"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="Old" advantage="No">However, special care has to be taken concerning the influence of the reaction mixture on the detection technique.</annotationART></s> <s sid="267"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Another possibility is once again the use of particles with small characteristic length <IT>L</IT><SB>c</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="268"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod15" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is suggested to calculate the Thiele modulus <IT>ψ</IT></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="269"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs59" novelty="None" advantage="None">If <IT>ψ</IT> &lt; 0.5, the effectiveness factor is higher than 90%.</annotationART></s> <s sid="270"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs60" novelty="None" advantage="None">For <IT>ψ</IT> &gt; 3 the reactant concentration drops to less than 10% inside the particle.</annotationART></s> <s sid="271"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res36" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus sufficiently thin pellets or particles (resulting in a small characteristic length <IT>L</IT><SB>c</SB>) will lead to <IT>η</IT> &gt; 0.9.</annotationART></s> <s sid="272"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod16" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case when the reaction rate <IT>k</IT><SB>r</SB> cannot be estimated, the Weisz modulus can be used instead as well known from mass transfer literature (<IT>cf</IT>. <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit59">ref. 59</REF>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="273"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="Old" advantage="None">As pointed out above, also shell-impregnated particles can be used for the studies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="274"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this way, <IT>operando</IT> studies become feasible not only for gas/solid but also for liquid/solid or dense fluid/solid reactions.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Conclusions</HEADER><P><s sid="275"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con15" novelty="None" advantage="None">In summary, the different examples show that, as in kinetic studies, special care has to be taken to account for possible film and pore diffusion limitations during time-resolved or <IT>operando</IT> spectroscopy studies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="276"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Limitations due to film and pore diffusion may occur due to flow conditions, catalyst shape, the chosen reactor design or material to dilute the catalyst to an optimal absorption length <IT>μd</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="277"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Low porosity materials, such as hexagonal boron nitride, are not ideal for this purpose, even though samples can be easily pelletized and its low absorption coefficient of hard X-rays makes it a preferable material for spectroscopy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="278"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The use of a high porosity material is desired.</annotationART></s> <s sid="279"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both the cell design and the catalyst system need to be adapted to the reaction of interest (kind of fluid, reaction rate regime, diffusion coefficient, pore size distribution, <IT>etc</IT>.).</annotationART></s> <s sid="280"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con20" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to find a balance between optimal design for spectroscopy and catalysis we suggest to estimate the importance of film diffusion (<IT>τ</IT><SB>film</SB>), pore diffusion (<IT>τ</IT><SB>pore</SB>) and/or the effectiveness factors (Thiele modulus), as discussed in this work.</annotationART></s> <s sid="281"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con21" novelty="None" advantage="None">These criteria are important for describing and estimating the reaction conditions during <IT>operando</IT> spectroscopy and time-resolved studies, not only in X-ray absorption spectroscopy but <IT>in situ</IT> spectroscopy in general such as XRD, Raman or IR spectroscopy (transmission mode).</annotationART></s> <s sid="282"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con22" novelty="None" advantage="None">The discussed criteria will make both <IT>in situ</IT> spectroscopic and time-resolved studies more powerful for elucidating the working mechanism of heterogeneous catalysts, as exemplified here for two well-known catalyst systems (Cu/ZnO for methanol synthesis and PdO<SB><IT>x</IT></SB>/ZrO<SB>2</SB> for methane combustion).</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
