<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b405025h" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">The search for stable and efficient sonoelectrocatalysts for oxygen reduction and hydrogen peroxide formation: azobenzene and derivatives<XREF TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" /></annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">We report the electrochemical reduction of oxygen using glassy carbon electrodes modified with azobenzene, hydroazobenzene, or fast black K salt (2,5-dimethoxy-4-[(4-nitrophenyl)azo] benzenediazonium tetrachlorozincate).</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None">The performance of the electrodes under ultrasound was explored.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">At the highest intensity (87 W cm<SP>−2</SP>) with one hour continuous insonation, voltammetric signals for azobenzene decreased by 7%, hydroazobenzene by 9% and fast black K by 18%.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="New" advantage="None">The catalytic rate constants of the immobilised species towards oxygen reduction were assessed <IT>via</IT> cyclic, rotating disc and sono-voltammetry.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rate constants were found to be 6.1 × 10<SP>3</SP> M<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP> for azobenzene, 7.4 × 10<SP>3</SP> M<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP> for hydroazobenzene and 10.4 × 10<SP>3</SP> M<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP> for fast black K. These values suggest the use of these modified electrodes as practical hydrogen peroxide generators.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="1.">Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The electrochemical reduction of oxygen to form hydrogen peroxide is of wide interest.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2 cit3 cit4">1–4</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The usual approach is through the immobilisation of catalytic materials to reduce the typically large over-potentials which are required for the direct reduction of oxygen at most electrode substrates.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Electrode modification for electro-catalysis of oxygen reduction is popular since through immobilisation onto electrode surfaces <IT>via</IT> physically or covalent attachment electrocatalytic activities can be significantly improved.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Many different materials have been proposed as electrocatalysts.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">These include carbon nanotubes,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF> Co(ii)-macrocycle complexes,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF> poly(naphthoquinone) films,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF> manganese dioxide,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF> copper-nickel alloys,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF> platinum modified gold electrodes,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF> cobaloxime complexes,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF> transition metal phthalocyanines,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF> anthraquinone polymers<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF> and gold nanoparticles<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF> and anthraquinones.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit16 cit17 cit18 cit19 cit20">5,16–20</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the last example, immobilization of anthraquinone species onto the surface of electrodes leads to hydrogen peroxide production <IT>via</IT> the following reaction:<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6 cit18 cit19 cit20 cit21">5,6,18–21</REF>Q(ads) + 2e<SP>−</SP> + 2H<SP>+</SP>(aq) → H<SB>2</SB>Q(ads)where Q(ads) is the adsorbed anthraquinone moiety.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot3" novelty="None" advantage="None">A large number of synthetic chemists seeking <IT>greener</IT> syntheses are turning toward hydrogen peroxide based oxidations, since water is the sole by-product of these oxidations.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Moreover expensive catalysts and solvents may be avoided while the need for costly organic peroxides or chlorine based oxidations can be eliminated.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Noyori has pioneered ‘green’ oxidation chemistry with aqueous hydrogen peroxide as oxidant<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF> showing that cyclohexene can be oxidized to adipic acid,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF> benzylic alcohols to benzaldehydes and benzoic acids.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25">25</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Also possible is the epoxidation of terminal olefins<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26">26</REF> and the oxidation of alcohols.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27">27</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Recently <IT>trans</IT>-1,2-diols have been synthesized using olefins and hydrogen peroxide with high yield and selectivity.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hydrogen peroxide is made commercially <IT>via</IT> anthraquinone reduction known as the ‘AO-process’.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28">28</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">This involves the hydrogenation, for example, of 2-alkyl-9,10-anthraquinone (with a catalyst such as nickel or palladium) forming the corresponding hydroquinone and oxidation with oxygen (usually air) to yield hydrogen peroxide and reforming the starting anthraquinone.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Commonly the anthraquinone is dissolved in a solvent or solvent mixture for hydrogenation, oxidation and extraction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Due to the differing solubility of the quinone and hydroquinone species, solvent mixtures are commonly employed.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28">28</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The benefits of ultrasound in electrochemistry have recently been highlighted.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29 cit30 cit31">29–31</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this context sustained high rates of mass transport are achieved from a combination of acoustic streaming and interfacial cavitational activity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is extremely useful in sono-electrosynthesis where the sustained transport can very significantly reduce electrolysis times whilst cavitational activity can keep the electrode ‘active’ under circumstances where passivation otherwise takes place.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Last it is worth noting that when ultrasound is applied to an aqueous media, cavitational collapse can produce low levels of <IT>in-situ</IT> formed hydrogen peroxide.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30 cit32 cit33">30,32,33</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Recently we have investigated the electro-catalytic reduction of oxygen at an Alizarin physically modified glassy carbon under ultrasound where catalytic currents were significantly enhanced under the high mass-transport conditions of ultrasound and quantitatively consistent with a modified Koutecky–Levich equation.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore we have explored 9,10-phenanthraquinone and 1,2-naphthoquinone physically absorbed onto glassy carbon working electrodes and found them to be suitable as sonoelectrocatalysts for oxygen reduction and hydrogen peroxide formation.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Such sono-electrodes offer scope for a green source of hydrogen peroxide in which oxygen (air) can be reduced with a high efficiency at an insonated electrode to provide a cheap and clean supply of hydrogen peroxide at the point of usage.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj5" novelty="New" advantage="None">In this paper we report the use of azobenzene, hydroazobenzene and fast black K salt (2,5-dimethoxy-4-[(4-nitrophenyl)azo] benzenediazonium chloride) for the catalytic reduction of oxygen.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj6" novelty="New" advantage="None">Azobenzene can be adsorbed either in its oxidised form, or in its two electron reduced form, hydroazobenzene: C<SB>6</SB>H<SB>5</SB>–N=N–C<SB>6</SB>H<SB>5</SB> + 2e<SP>−</SP> + 2H<SP>+</SP> ⇌ C<SB>6</SB>H<SB>5</SB>–NH–NH–C<SB>6</SB>H<SB>5</SB>All three species were physically adsorbed onto glassy carbon electrodes with the catalytic rate constants assessed using cyclic, rotating disc and sono-voltammetry.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj7" novelty="New" advantage="None">The stability of the modified glassy carbon electrodes were investigated under ultrasound and were found to be extremely stable providing a basis for the sono-electrochemical production of hydrogen peroxide.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.">Experimental</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.1">Reagents and chemicals</HEADER><P><s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">All chemicals used in this work were of analytical grade and used as received without further purification.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">These were: azobenzene (Aldrich, 96%), fast black K salt (2,5-dimethoxy-4-[(4-nitrophenyl)azo] benzenediazonium tetrachlorozincate, Sigma,+98%), hydrazobenzene (Aldrich, 99%) and acetonitrile (Fischer Chemicals, synthetic grade).</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The buffers used were as follows: acetate buffers for pH 3.0 and 5.0, phosphate buffers for pH 2.0, 7.0 and 8.0 and boric buffer for pH 10.0.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">All solutions were prepared with deionised water of resistivity not less than 18.2 MΩ cm (Vivendi Water Systems, UK).</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Before commencing experiments, nitrogen (BOC, Guildford, Surrey, UK) was used for deaeration of solutions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Conversely, for oxygen measurements, oxygen (BOC, Guildford, Surrey, UK) was bubbled for at least 10 min to saturate the solution.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.2">Instrumentation</HEADER><P><s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Voltammetric measurements were carried out on a μ-Autolab (ECO-Chemie, Utrecht, The Netherlands) potentiostat.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">All measurements were conducted in a thermostatted (22 °C) three-electrode cell with a solution volume of 40 cm<SP>3</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The working electrodes were either an edge plane pyrolytic graphite electrode (Le Carbone Ltd, Sussex, UK, 5 mm diameter) or a glassy-carbon electrode (GC, 3 mm diameter, BAS, Indiana, USA).</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp10" novelty="None" advantage="None">A different glassy carbon disc (3 mm diameter, mounted in teflon) was used for rotating disc experiments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The counter electrode was a bright platinum wire, with a saturated calomel electrode (Radiometer, Copenhagen, Denmark) completing the circuit.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Sonoelectrochemical studies were performed using an ultrasonic horn, model CV 26 (Sonics and Materials Inc. USA), operating at a frequency of 25 kHz and fitted with a 3 mm diameter titanium alloy microtip (Jencons, Leyton Buzzard, UK).</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The intensity of the ultrasound was determined calorimetrically<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit34 cit35 cit36">34–36</REF> and it was found that a 20% amplitude corresponded to 87 W cm<SP>−2</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The working electrode was placed in a face-on arrangement to the ultrasonic horn.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The horn was immersed beyond the shoulder of the stepped tip to ensure that ultrasound is efficiently applied into the solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The horn-to-electrode distance was fixed at 10 mm throughout all measurements.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp17" novelty="None" advantage="None">During experiments, the temperature was kept constant at 22 °C (±2 °C) by the use of a stainless steel cooling coil.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is important to note that for sono-Koutecky–Levich measurements, the concentration of oxygen under insonation has already been investigated where it was observed that ultrasound can be applied for up to 2 min before 10% of the oxygen is lost<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.3.">Electrode modification</HEADER><P><s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp18" novelty="None" advantage="None">GC electrodes were carefully pre-treated before modification since it has been reported<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit37">37</REF> that the electrode history has effects on both the modification and the electrochemical behaviour of the electrode.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Prior to each modification, GC electrodes were polished with diamond lapping compounds (Kelmet, UK) and then carefully rinsed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp20" novelty="None" advantage="None">The oxidative pre-treatment of GC electrodes was the same as the one reported by Salimi and co-workers:<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF> the polished GC electrodes were subjected to cycling between −0.5 and +2.0 V at a scan rate 100 mV s<SP>−1</SP> in 0.1 M sulfuric acid for 10 min.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp21" novelty="None" advantage="None">The electrode was then poised at +1.8 V in the same solution for 3 min.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp22" novelty="None" advantage="None">The pre-treated electrode was modified with azobenzene by pippetting 20 μL of 1 mM solution of azobenzene in acetonitrile on to the electrode surface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp23" novelty="None" advantage="None">The solvent was allowed to evaporate off at room temperature leaving azobenzene physically adsorbed on to the GC electrode.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that, as discussed below, microcrystals of azobenzene are also formed by this procedure so that the electrode surface immediately after modification has both physically adsorbed azobenzene and microcrystals on it.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp24" novelty="None" advantage="None">The latter can be removed by potential cycling (<IT>vide infra</IT>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp25" novelty="None" advantage="None">Glassy carbon electrodes modified with hydrazobenzene or fast black K salt were prepared by the same procedure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that if the electrode is simply placed into a 1 mM solution of azobenzene, left for 5 min, removed and rinsed and then placed into a pH 2 buffer solution, no voltammetric waves are observed.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.">Results and discussion</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.1">Characterisation of azobenzene modified electrodes</HEADER><P><s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj8" novelty="New" advantage="None">The voltammetry of azobenzene at an edge plane pyrolytic graphite electrode was first explored.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp26" novelty="None" advantage="None">The electrode was modified as described in section 2.3 and placed into an oxygen free pH 2 phosphate buffer solution with cyclic voltammograms recorded over various scan rates.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">As shown in Fig. 1, a reduction peak is visible at <IT>ca</IT>. −0.60 V (<IT>vs.</IT> SCE) and this corresponds to the reduction of azobenzene to hydroazobenzene as described by eqn. (3)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit38 cit39">38,39</REF> with the corresponding oxidation peak observed at <IT>ca.</IT> +0.40 V. Next a new electrode was prepared and the voltammetric window extended to more negative potentials.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The first scan is shown in Fig. 2, curve A, where the reduction peak of azobenzene to hydroazobenzene is first observed with the second wave at <IT>ca.</IT> −1.2 V (<IT>vs.</IT> SCE) corresponding to the irreversible reduction of hydroazobenzene to aniline.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit38">38</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">[C<SB>6</SB>H<SB>5</SB>–HN–NH–C<SB>6</SB>H<SB>5</SB> + 2e<SP>−</SP> + 2H<SP>+</SP>→ 2C<SB>6</SB>H<SB>5</SB>–NH<SB>2</SB>]On the second scan (Fig. 2, curve B) a single reduction wave is only seen corresponding to azobenzene reduction, with continual scanning resulting in a decrease of the voltammetric response, consistent with literature reports that hydroazobenzene is reduced <IT>irreversibly</IT> to aniline.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit38 cit39">38,39</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp27" novelty="None" advantage="None">A polished edge plane electrode was left in a 2 mM acetonitrile solution of azobenzene for 12 h, removed, carefully rinsed and put in fresh, oxygen-free pH 2 phosphate buffer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is interesting to note that cyclic voltammograms recorded after this treatment show a small reduction wave at <IT>ca.</IT> −0.6 V (<IT>vs.</IT> SCE), which is <IT>ca</IT>. seven times smaller than that seen compared to the electrode modified <IT>via</IT> evaporation.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj9" novelty="New" advantage="None">We next turn to investigating the response of a modified glassy carbon (GC) electrode.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp28" novelty="None" advantage="None">The electrochemical behaviour of the modified GC electrode was examined in an oxygen free pH 2 phosphate buffer solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The first scan is shown in Fig. 3A which shows two reduction waves at −0.11 (±0.01) V and −0.45 (±0.01) V (<IT>vs.</IT> SCE) with a single oxidation wave on the cathodic sweep.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 3B shows the second scan (curve A), fifth (curve B) and the final stabilised scan (curve C).</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Comparison of the first scan (Fig. 3A) and second scan (Fig. 3B, curve A) reveals a large decrease in the peak current.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">This suggests that when the electrode is modified a mixture of azobenzene microcrystals and a monolayer (or less) exists such that as the potential is scanned to negative values, the first reduction peak at −0.11 V is the reduction of azobenzene to hydroazobenzene (eqn. (3)) with both species in the form of a monolayer while the large broader peak at −0.45 V is the reduction of azobenzene in the form of crystals which dissolve from the electrode surface when reduced, such that on the second scan the large broad peak is absent suggesting that only the monolayer (or less) response is left.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">We note that Komorsky-Lovrić has studied the voltammetry of azobenzene microcrystals abrasively attached to a basal plane pyrolytic graphite electrode, observing a reduction peak at <IT>ca</IT>. −0.40 V at pH .2<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit38">38</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj10" novelty="New" advantage="None">The effect of pH on the response of azobenzene was explored (after the signal had stabilised).</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">It was observed that redox peak was pH-dependent and shifted towards more negative potentials upon increasing the solution pH.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The potential of the reduction peak shifts by 57 mV (pH unit)<SP>−1</SP> consistent with a two-proton two-electron process.</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">A plot of peak current <IT>vs.</IT> scan rate was found to be linear, as expected for surface confined species with the surface concentration of azobenzene physically adsorbed on glassy carbon electrode (after stabilisation) was calculated using the following relationship:<IT>Γ</IT> = <IT>Q</IT>/<IT>nFA</IT>where <IT>Q</IT> is charge under voltammetric peak, <IT>n</IT> is the number of electrons transferred, <IT>F</IT> is the Faraday constant and <IT>A</IT>, the electrode area.</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The surface coverage was found to be 68.9 (±0.6) × 10<SP>−10</SP> mol cm<SP>−2</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj11" novelty="New" advantage="None">The reduction of oxygen on glassy carbon electrodes modified with monolayer physically adsorbed azobenzene was next studied.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.2">Oxygen reduction at azobenzene (AB) modified GC electrodes</HEADER><P><s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj11" novelty="New" advantage="None">The reduction of oxygen using an azobenzene modified glassy carbon electrode was next studied.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp29" novelty="None" advantage="None">First, cyclic voltammograms were run in an oxygen-saturated solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Shown in Fig. 4 are the responses obtained for a bare glassy carbon electrode (curve C) and for a modified glassy carbon electrode modified with azobenzene in a pH 2 phosphate buffer solution saturated with oxygen (curve B).</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">For comparison the modified electrode in the absence of oxygen (curve A) is shown.</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">At a bare electrode, the oxygen reduction occurs with a peak potential at <IT>ca</IT>. −0.53 (±0.01) V (<IT>vs.</IT> SCE).</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the modified electrode a large reduction wave is observed with the corresponding oxidation peak disappearing on the reverse scan suggesting excellent catalytic behaviour.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Comparison of oxygen reduction at the modified and bare glassy carbon electrodes reveals that the oxygen wave in the latter case shifts to less negative potentials from −0.53 (±0.01) V to −0.37 (±0.01) V.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj12" novelty="New" advantage="None">Cyclic voltammograms were next recorded in various pH buffer solutions saturated with oxygen with the ‘best’ pH for oxygen reduction investigated; this criterion is met when the oxygen reduction wave using the modified electrode is at its most positive potential.</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">This was found to correspond to pH 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp30" novelty="None" advantage="None">Consequently all further electrochemical studies using azobenzene were carried out at pH 2.0.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The electrocatalytic rate constant for oxygen reduction on a GC electrode modified with azobenzene was determined from cyclic voltammetry data using Andrieux and Savéant theory:<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit40">40</REF><IT>I</IT><SB><IT>p</IT></SB> = <IT>yFAC</IT><SB>bulk</SB><IT>D</IT><SP>1/2</SP>(<IT>Fv</IT>/<IT>RT</IT>)<SP>1/2</SP>where <IT>F</IT> is the Faraday constant, <IT>A</IT> is the electrode area, <IT>C</IT><SB>bulk</SB> is the bulk concentration of oxygen, <IT>D</IT> is the diffusion coefficient of oxygen, <IT>ν</IT> is the scan rate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp31" novelty="None" advantage="None">Experimentally, the modified electrode for the voltammetric reduction of oxygen in an oxygen-saturated solution is scanned at slow scan rates.</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The gradient of a plot of peak current <IT>versus</IT> square root of scan rate produces <IT>y</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">This value is used <IT>via</IT> a theoretically derived curve to determine <IT>x</IT>, where <IT>x</IT> is:<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit40">40</REF>where the symbols have their usual meanings.</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Shown in the electronic supplementary information (ESI) is a plot of peak current <IT>versus</IT> square root of scan rate, which is linear.</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rate constant from this plot using the Andrieux and Savéant theory was found to be 6.1 (±0.1) × 10<SP>3</SP> M<SP>−1</SP>s<SP>−1</SP> for the surface coverage of azobenzene of 69 (±0.3) × 10<SP>−10</SP> mol cm<SP>−2</SP> using the oxygen diffusion coefficient of 1.6 × 10<SP>−5</SP> cm<SP>2</SP> s<SP>−1</SP> and a value of 1.2 mM as the concentration of an oxygen saturated aqueous solution.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">For comparison, the kinetic parameters for the oxygen reduction reaction on a GC electrode modified with azobenzene was next evaluated using the rotating disc electrode (RDE) method <IT>via</IT> the Koutecky–Levich equation:<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit41">41</REF>where <IT>k</IT> is catalytic rate constant, <IT>C</IT><SB>bulk</SB> the bulk concentration of oxygen, <IT>ν</IT> is the hydrodynamic viscosity, <IT>ω</IT> is the rotation speed, while all other parameters have usual meaning.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp32" novelty="None" advantage="None">First however, a glassy carbon rotating disc electrode was modified with azobenzene by the same procedure as used for the GC electrode as described in section 2.3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Using cyclic voltammetry the coverage of azobenzene on the RDGCE was found to be 66.4 (±0.5) × 10<SP>−10</SP> mol cm<SP>−2</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp33" novelty="None" advantage="None">Rotating disc voltammograms at a range of rotation speeds were recorded in oxygen saturated solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp34" novelty="None" advantage="None">Using a potential of −0.37 V (<IT>vs.</IT> SCE), a Koutecky–Levich plot was constructed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp35" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rate constant was evaluated from the intercept of Koutecky–Levich plot.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Using this plot, the catalytic rate constant was found to be 5.9 (±0.2) × 10<SP>3</SP> M<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>, which is in excellent agreement with the value obtained <IT>via</IT> cyclic voltammetry data.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj13" novelty="New" advantage="None">Next, we turn to oxygen reduction at a glassy carbon electrode modified with azobenzene using sonovoltammetry.</annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj14" novelty="New" advantage="None">First we consider the behaviour and stability under ultrasound of the azobenzene modified glassy carbon electrode: it is recognised that for some adsorbates sustained insonation can lead to significant ablation<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit42">42</REF> Ultrasound was applied to the modified electrode at different intensities for various time periods at a constant horn-to-electrode distance of 10 mm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 5 shows cyclic voltammograms recorded at different time intervals, with a plot of the peak current <IT>versus</IT> applied time of insonation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Applying a maximum ultrasound intensity of 87 W cm<SP>−2</SP> resulted in practically no ablation; the value of initial peak current before application of ultrasound was 21 μA, while after 10 min of insonation the peak current decreased to 20 μA, corresponding to a 5% decrease.</annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs19" novelty="None" advantage="None">After applying ultrasound for 1 h, a 7% decrease in the signal was observed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs20" novelty="None" advantage="None">Conversely applying ultrasound intensity of 36 W cm<SP>−2</SP>, the peak current was observed to decrease by 4% after 10 min and 5% after 1 h of continuous insonation from its original value.</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">These results show that the azobenzene-modified electrodes are very stable under ultrasound and therefore potentially suitable for use as sonoelectrocatalysts for hydrogen peroxide generation.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj15" novelty="New" advantage="None">Next, the catalytic rate constant was measured <IT>via</IT> sono-voltammetry.</annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs21" novelty="None" advantage="None">First the surface coverage of azobenzene on the GC electrode was determined <IT>via</IT> cyclic voltammetry and found to be 57.5 (±0.4) × 10<SP>−10</SP> mol cm<SP>−2</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp36" novelty="None" advantage="None">The modified GC electrode was placed into a face-on arrangement in an oxygen-saturated pH 2 phosphate buffer solution at a fixed horn-to-electrode distance of 10 mm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs22" novelty="None" advantage="None">As shown in Fig. 6, comparison of the response of the modified electrode in the absence and presence of an acoustic field reveals a significant increase in current arising from the acoustic streaming.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30">30</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rate constant for oxygen reduction was calculated using the following equation:<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF>where <IT>n</IT> is the number of electrons transferred, <IT>F</IT>, is the Faraday constant, <IT>A</IT> is the electrode area, <IT>D</IT> is the diffusion coefficient, <IT>C</IT><SB>ox</SB> is the bulk concentration of oxygen, and <IT>Γ</IT> is the surface coverage of the adsorbate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs23" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rate constant was found to be 7.3 (±0.2) 10<SP>3</SP> M<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP> if the value of surface coverage before insonation was used (57.5 (±0.4) × 10<SP>−10</SP> mol cm<SP>−2</SP>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs24" novelty="None" advantage="None">If the value of 52.6 (±0.3) × 10<SP>−10</SP> mol cm<SP>−2</SP> obtained for surface concentration after applying ultrasound was used, the rate constant was calculated to be 8.0 × 10<SP>3</SP> M<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs25" novelty="None" advantage="None">The average value of 7.6 × 10<SP>3</SP> M<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP> is in reasonable agreement with the values obtained by cyclic voltammetry and RDE analysis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs26" novelty="None" advantage="None">The chemical rate parameter, defined as the catalytic rate constant multiplied by the surface coverage, was calculated for all three methods and found to be 41.9 × 10<SP>−3</SP> cm s<SP>−1</SP> for cyclic voltammetry measurements, 39.2 × 10<SP>−3</SP> cm s<SP>−1</SP> for the RDE method and 41.9 × 10<SP>−3</SP> cm s<SP>−1</SP><IT>via</IT> sonovoltammetry.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.3">Oxygen reduction at hydrazobenzene (HAB) modified GC electrodes</HEADER><P><s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj16" novelty="New" advantage="None">First the voltammetry of hydroazobenzene was explored at an edge plane pyrolytic graphite modified electrode.</annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp37" novelty="None" advantage="None">The cyclic voltammogram was started at −0.3 V (<IT>vs.</IT> SCE), scanned positive to +0.5 V and reversed back to −0.6 V. This was repeated several times.</annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs27" novelty="None" advantage="None">As shown in Fig. 7 an oxidation wave corresponding to the oxidation of hydroazobenzene to azobenzene is clearly seen at <IT>ca</IT>. +0.2 V, and on the reverse scan a reduction peak of azobenzene back to hydroazobenzene is observed at −0.3 V which is comparable to that seen for the electrochemical reduction of azobenzene on the edge plane electrode.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj17" novelty="New" advantage="None">Next a modified glassy carbon electrode was investigated in a pH 2 buffer solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs28" novelty="None" advantage="None">Shown in Fig. 8 are the cyclic voltammograms for the first (curve A), second (curve B) and tenth (curve C) scans.</annotationART></s> <s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the first scan, two reduction peaks are observed at <IT>ca.</IT> −0.13 V and −0.4 V (<IT>vs.</IT> SCE), which again can be assigned to the reduction of azobenzene as two different forms from the electrode surface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">A peak is observed on the oxidation scan corresponding to the oxidation of hydroazobenzene to azobenzene.</annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the second scan the latter reduction peak has virtually disappeared suggesting that hydroazobenzene in the form of crystals is dissolved from the electrode surface with a single reduction wave due to the reduction of azobenzene to hydroazobenzene.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs29" novelty="None" advantage="None">The scan rate was varied and a plot of peak current <IT>vs.</IT> scan rate was found to be linear, consistent with a surface bound species.</annotationART></s> <s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs30" novelty="None" advantage="None">The surface concentration of hydrazobenzene on a glassy carbon electrode (after stabilisation, ten scans) was determined using cyclic voltammogram, and was found to be 54.7 (±0.4) × 10<SP>−10</SP> mol cm<SP>−2</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp38" novelty="None" advantage="None">Cyclic voltammograms for glassy carbon electrode modified with hydrazobenzene were recorded in various buffer solutions in pH range from 2 to 10.</annotationART></s> <s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">A plot of peak potential against pH was linear with a gradient of 57 mV (pH unit)<SP>−1</SP> which is in excellent agreement with expected value for a two-electron, two-proton process.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj18" novelty="New" advantage="None">Next, oxygen reduction at a glassy carbon electrode modified with hydrazobenzene was investigated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp39" novelty="None" advantage="None">Buffer solutions were saturated with cyclic voltammograms run.</annotationART></s> <s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Comparison of oxygen reduction at the modified (Fig. 9, curve B) and bare glassy carbon electrode (Fig. 9, curve C) reveals that the reduction waves shift to a more positive potential with a significantly large increase in the peak current suggesting good electro-activity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs31" novelty="None" advantage="None">The largest enhancement was observed for pH 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp40" novelty="None" advantage="None">All further measurements with hydroazobenzene were carried out in pH 2 phosphate buffer solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs32" novelty="None" advantage="None">The catalytic rate constant analysing cyclic voltammetry data <IT>via</IT> Andrieux and Savéant theory<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit40">40</REF> was 7.4 × 10<SP>3</SP> M<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP> for a surface coverage of 54.7 (±0.3) × 10<SP>−10</SP> mol cm<SP>−2</SP>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Kinetic parameters for the reduction of oxygen on a glassy carbon electrode modified with hydrazobenzene were evaluated <IT>via</IT> the RDE method (eqn. (7)).</annotationART></s> <s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp41" novelty="None" advantage="None">A modified rotating disc GC electrode was placed into an oxygen saturated solution and run at various rotation speeds.</annotationART></s> <s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp42" novelty="None" advantage="None">A plot of reciprocal of limiting current <IT>versus</IT> square root of rotation speed was constructed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs33" novelty="None" advantage="None">Using the Koutecky–Levich equation with a surface coverage of hydroazobenzene, which was found to be 47.7 (±0.4) × 10<SP>−10</SP> mol cm<SP>−2</SP> the catalytic rate constant of oxygen reduction was determined to be 7.3 × 10<SP>3</SP> M<SP>−1</SP>s<SP>−1</SP> which is in excellent agreement with that obtained using cyclic voltammetry.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj19" novelty="New" advantage="None">Next, oxygen reduction under an acoustic field was evaluated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj20" novelty="New" advantage="None">First however, the stability under ultrasound of the glassy carbon electrode modified with physically adsorbed hydrazobenzene was addressed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="143"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp43" novelty="None" advantage="None">The modified electrode was first exposed to ultrasound of 87 W cm<SP>−2</SP> at a horn-to-electrode distance of 10 mm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="144"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs34" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that this is the highest intensity used in analysis for the catalytic rate constant <IT>via</IT> use of the modified Koutecky–Levich equation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="145"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs35" novelty="None" advantage="None">Shown in Fig. 10 are the cyclic voltammograms recorded at different time intervals, along with a plot showing the peak current of the hydroazobenzene as a function of time applying an ultrasound intensity of 87 W cm<SP>−2</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="146"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs36" novelty="None" advantage="None">After 10 min of insonation, the initial peak current before application of ultrasound decreased only <IT>ca.</IT> 10%, from 19 μA to 17 μA.</annotationART></s> <s sid="147"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs37" novelty="None" advantage="None">For 1 h of insonation a 16% decrease was observed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="148"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, 10 min insonation at 36 W cm<SP>−2</SP> was found to decrease the voltammetric signal from 23 μA to 21 μA corresponding to a 9% decrease while for 1 h a 10% decrease was observed suggesting that the hydrazobenzene is extremely stable under ultrasound and therefore appropriate as a sonoelectrocatalyst for oxygen reduction and hydrogen peroxide producer.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="149"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">As in the case of azobenzene modified glassy carbon electrode, the catalytic rate constant of oxygen reduction at glassy carbon electrode modified with hydrazobenzene was calculated from the intercept of the sono-Koutecky–Levich plot.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="150"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs38" novelty="None" advantage="None">The surface coverage of hydrazobenzene before applying ultrasound was found to be 51.7 (±0.3) × 10<SP>−10</SP> mol cm<SP>−2</SP>, while after application of acoustic field it was found to decrease to 48.9 (±0.4) × 10<SP>−10</SP> mol cm<SP>−2</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="151"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs39" novelty="None" advantage="None">Using an average value for the surface coverage, the catalytic rate constant was evaluated to be 8.1 × 10<SP>3</SP> M<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="152"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs40" novelty="None" advantage="None">The combined chemical rate constant obtained was 40.7 × 10<SP>−3</SP> cm s<SP>−1</SP> which is the same as that found from cyclic voltammetry, differing slightly from the one obtained for RDE method (34.8 × 10<SP>−3</SP> cm s<SP>−1</SP>).</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.4">Oxygen reduction at fast black K salt (FBK) modified GC electrode</HEADER><P><s sid="153"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj21" novelty="New" advantage="None">The electro-reduction of fast black K salt (2,5-dimethoxy-4-[(4-nitrophenyl)azo] benzenediazonium tetrachlorozincate) was first explored.</annotationART></s> <s sid="154"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs41" novelty="None" advantage="None">The structure of fast black K is shown in Scheme 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="155"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs42" novelty="None" advantage="None">As shown in Fig. 11a three reduction waves are observed at +0.15 V, −0.30 V and −0.41 V with an oxidation peak at +0.4 V (<IT>vs.</IT> SCE).</annotationART></s> <s sid="156"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The two reduction peaks at −0.30 and −0.41 V can be attributed to the reduction of the nitro group of the FBK salt as two different forms on the GC electrode, specifically as a monolayer and as microcrystals, while the first at +0.15 V can be assigned to the reduction of the azo linkages of the fast black K compound with the corresponding oxidation wave at +0.4 V.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit43">43</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="157"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs43" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 11b shows the second scan which clearly shows two reduction waves at <IT>ca.</IT> +0.15 V and −0.41 V.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="158"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj22" novelty="New" advantage="None">The electrochemical behaviour of FBK/GC electrode was examined over a range of potentials at various pHs.</annotationART></s> <s sid="159"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs44" novelty="None" advantage="None">The variation of the (first) peak potential as a function of pH was found to be linear with a slope of 51 mV (pH unit)<SP>−1</SP> consistent with a two-proton, two-electron process.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="160"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp44" novelty="None" advantage="None">Next an oxygen-saturated solution was prepared with the cyclic voltammetric response recorded.</annotationART></s> <s sid="161"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs45" novelty="None" advantage="None">As shown in Fig. 12, the peak current corresponding to the reduction of oxygen was increased with the peak potential shifting to a more positive potential compared to the unmodified GC electrode.</annotationART></s> <s sid="162"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs46" novelty="None" advantage="None">The biggest increase in peak current was observed in pH 2 solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="163"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp45" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore subsequent measurements were performed at this pH.</annotationART></s> <s sid="164"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs47" novelty="None" advantage="None">A new modified electrode was prepared and found to have a surface coverage of 48.1 (±0.3) × 10<SP>−10</SP> mol cm<SP>−2</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="165"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs48" novelty="None" advantage="None">The catalytic rate constant was evaluated using cyclic voltammetry data <IT>via</IT> the Andrieux and Savéant theory<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit40">40</REF> which was found to be 10.4 (±0.1) × 10<SP>3</SP> M<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="166"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp46" novelty="None" advantage="None">For comparison, oxygen reduction at a FBK modified GC electrode was determined by RDE method.</annotationART></s> <s sid="167"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp47" novelty="None" advantage="None">A RDGC electrode was modified as described in section 2.3 and placed into a pH 2 phosphate buffer solution, which was saturated with oxygen.</annotationART></s> <s sid="168"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs49" novelty="None" advantage="None">Using the Koutecky – Levich equation,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit41">41</REF> the catalytic rate constant for oxygen reduction was calculated to be 9.9 (±0.1) × 10<SP>3</SP> M<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP> using a surface coverage of 59.0 (±0.3) × 10<SP>−10</SP> mol cm<SP>−2</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="169"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">This value is identical to the one obtained from cyclic voltammetry.</annotationART></s> <s sid="170"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs50" novelty="None" advantage="None">The combined chemical rate parameter was found to be 58.4 × 10<SP>−3</SP> cm s<SP>−1</SP> for RDE method compared to 50.0 × 10<SP>−3</SP> cm s<SP>−1</SP> obtained from cyclic voltammetry.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="171"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj23" novelty="New" advantage="None">Next, the reduction of oxygen using the FBK modified electrode was explored using sonovoltammetry.</annotationART></s> <s sid="172"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj24" novelty="New" advantage="None">First the stability under ultrasound of the modified glassy carbon electrode was investigated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="173"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp48" novelty="None" advantage="None">The modified electrode was exposed to ultrasound of 87 W cm<SP>−2</SP> at fixed horn-to-electrode distance of 10 mm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="174"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp49" novelty="None" advantage="None">Shown in Fig. 13 are the cyclic voltammograms recorded at different time intervals, along with a plot showing the peak current of the FBK as a function of time applying an ultrasound intensity of 87 W cm<SP>−2</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="175"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs51" novelty="None" advantage="None">After 10 min of insonation, the initial peak current before application of ultrasound decreased only 13.5%, from 12.6 μA to 10.9 μA with an 1 h of insonation resulting in an 18.2% decrease.</annotationART></s> <s sid="176"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs52" novelty="None" advantage="None">When 36 W cm<SP>−2</SP> ultrasound intensity was used, 10 min of insonation was found to decrease the voltammetric signal from 9.4 μA to 8.5 μA corresponding to a 9.9% decrease while 1 h insonation produced a 15% decrease.</annotationART></s> <s sid="177"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Clearly the fast black K modified electrode is extremely stable under ultrasound and therefore appropriate as a sonoelectrocatalyst.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="178"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp50" novelty="None" advantage="None">The catalytic rate constant of oxygen reduction at a glassy carbon electrode modified with FBK was calculated <IT>via</IT> the sono-Koutecky–Levich equation.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="179"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs53" novelty="None" advantage="None">The surface coverage of FBK before applying ultrasound was found to be 47.2 × 10<SP>−10</SP> mol cm<SP>−2</SP>, while after application of acoustic field it was found to decrease to 43.7 × 10<SP>−10</SP> mol cm<SP>−2</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="180"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs54" novelty="None" advantage="None">Using an average value for the surface coverage, the catalytic rate constant was evaluated to be 10.9 (±0.1) × 10<SP>3</SP> M<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="181"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs55" novelty="None" advantage="None">The combined chemical rate parameter obtained was 49.5 × 10<SP>−3</SP>cm s<SP>−1</SP> which is almost the same as that found from cyclic voltammetry, 50.0 × 10<SP>−3</SP>cm s<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.5">Comparison of electro-catalytic activity of the modified electrodes for oxygen reduction</HEADER><P><s sid="182"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs56" novelty="None" advantage="None">Table 1 shows the deduced electrocatalytic rate constant and combined chemical rate parameter values for the oxygen reduction on glassy carbon electrodes modified with azobenzene, hydroazobenzene and fast black K salt.</annotationART></s> <s sid="183"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Also included are the values for anthraquinone species previously reported.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="184"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs57" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that all the data refers to pH 2; faster rates can be found at different pH’s.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="185"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Comparisons of the combined chemical rate parameters for azobenzene and derivatives with the anthraquinone species, reveal that the former is <IT>ca.</IT> five times faster.</annotationART></s> <s sid="186"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that this is the first time these have been investigated for the electrochemical reduction of oxygen.</annotationART></s> <s sid="187"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore the modified electrodes investigated in this work were more stable under ultrasound and exhibited a more remarkable electro-catalytic activity toward oxygen reduction.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.">Conclusions</HEADER><P><s sid="188"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj25" novelty="New" advantage="None">The electrochemical reduction of oxygen using glassy carbon electrodes modified with azobenzene, hydroazobenzene, or fast black K salt (2,5-dimethoxy-4-[(4-nitrophenyl)azo] benzenediazonium tetrachlorozincate) at glassy carbon electrodes have been explored.</annotationART></s> <s sid="189"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The performance of the modified electrodes under ultrasound was found to be highly stable; the superiority of these modified electrodes under insonation over their anthraquinone counterparts<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19 cit44">19,44</REF> is noted.</annotationART></s> <s sid="190"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The catalytic rate constants of the immobilised species towards oxygen reduction were assessed <IT>via</IT> cyclic, rotating disc and sono- voltammetry with the values obtained suggesting their use as practical hydrogen peroxide generators.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
