<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b409589h" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Recognition of reactive high-energy conformations by shape complementarity and specific enzyme–substrate interactions in family 10 and 11 xylanases</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">Binding of xylotetraose to the family 10 xylanase (CEX) from <IT>Cellulomonas fimi</IT> and the family 11 xylanase (BCX) from <IT>Bacillus circulans</IT> was investigated using quantum mechanical calculations, molecular dynamics simulations and molecular mechanics–Poisson–Boltzmann surface area (MM-PBSA) free energy calculations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the reactive enzyme–substrate conformation, in which the catalytic groups are precisely positioned for the catalytic reaction, the −1 sugar moiety of the substrate adopted a B<SB>3,O</SB> (boat) conformation for CEX and a <SP>2</SP>S<SB>O</SB> (skew-boat) conformation for BCX.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Upon binding the internal energies of the reactive substrate conformations are increased by about 9 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast to this, the internal energies of substrates in all-chair conformation are increased by 33–43 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>, with somewhat larger increase for BCX than CEX.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">As a consequence, the stability order of the all-chair conformation, which is the most stable conformation in aqueous solution, and the distorted reactive conformations is reversed upon binding to the enzyme.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, in addition to specific enzyme–substrate interactions, CEX and especially BCX recognise the reactive high-energy conformation by the substrate-binding site of several sugar-binding subsites complementary in shape to the reactive conformation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None">The role of substrate distortion in glycosidase-catalysed reactions is discussed.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Xylanases (β-1,4-d-xylan xylanohydrolases, EC 3.2.1.8) are β-glycosidases, which degrade Nature’s most abundant hemicellulose, xylan.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the basis of amino acid sequence similarities, the majority of xylanases are members of families 10 and 11 of the glycosyl hydrolases.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2">1,2</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Xylanases of both enzyme families catalyse the hydrolysis of β-1,4-linked xylose polymer by a double-displacement mechanism and net retention of the anomeric center of the reaction.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the active site there are two key catalytic glutamic acid residues, one acting as an acid/base catalyst and another as a nucleophile, which forms a covalent reaction intermediate with the substrate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The transition states to and from the covalent intermediate have considerable oxocarbenium ion character (Fig. 1a).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3 cit4 cit5">3–5</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="New" advantage="None">Binding of xylotetraose (X4, Fig. 1b) to two xylanases, CEX from <IT>Cellulomonas fimi</IT> and BCX from <IT>Bacillus circulans</IT>, was studied computationally in this work.</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">CEX is a member of family 10 and BCX of family 11 glycosyl hydrolase.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">These two xylanases are good representatives of families 10 and 11 as several X-ray structures and a lot of other biochemical data are available about their functional properties.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although CEX and BCX catalyse the hydrolysis of xylan with a similar type of mechanism, there are differences in the details of the reaction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Mechanism-based inhibitors, like 2′,4′-dinitrophenyl 2-deoxy-2-fluoro-β-xylobioside, form stable covalent glycosyl–enzyme intermediates with xylanases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the intermediate the catalytic nucleophile forms a covalent bond with the C1 of the xylose moiety bound in the −1 subsite of the enzyme.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of CEX, the 2-deoxy-2-fluoroxylose residue bound in the −1 subsite adopts a <SP>1</SP>C<SB>4</SB> (chair) conformation,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF> whereas in the case of BCX, the corresponding residue is bound in a <SP>2,5</SP>B (boat) conformation.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">These structures have shed light on the atomic details of the covalent reaction intermediate, but it is less clear in which conformation the sugar of the −1 subsite is bound in the Michaelis complex.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ambiguity is mainly due to difficulties in finding suitable substrates, which are not hydrolysed, occupy at the same time subsites also at the reducing end (+1) of the binding site, and are structurally similar to the natural substrates.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Distortion of the reactive pyranose ring has been observed in the X-ray structures of several β-glycosidases complexed with uncleaved substrates.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit9 cit10">8–10</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Lysozyme is a classical example of an enzyme binding the substrate’s reactive sugar in a distorted sofa conformation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">It has been suggested that distortion of the reactive sugar moiety is important for the rate of the enzyme-catalysed reaction.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast to this, it has been suggested that distortion plays a minor role in the catalysis.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11 cit12">11,12</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Knowledge of the energetics involved in the substrate binding in different conformations can be obtained with computer simulations and further our understanding on factors responsible for enzyme-catalysed reactions.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj5" novelty="New" advantage="None">In this work, the binding of xylotetraose to CEX and BCX was studied computationally.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj6" novelty="New" advantage="None">QM calculations were used to compare the (internal) energy of the substrate X4 free in aqueous solution and complexed with the two xylanases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj7" novelty="New" advantage="None">MD simulations of 4.0 ns were used to provide the structures of enzyme–substrate complexes and substrate free in aqueous solution, and molecular mechanics–Poisson–Boltzmann surface area (MM-PBSA) free energy calculations<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF> were applied to study the energetics of the binding.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The MM-PBSA method has recently been used with good success in predicting and explaining the binding of various ligands to proteins<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14 cit15 cit16 cit17 cit18 cit19">14–19</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Computational methods</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>MD simulations</HEADER><P><s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The starting coordinates for the MD simulations were obtained from the X-ray crystal structures of the <IT>endo</IT>-1,4-β-xylanases from <IT>C. fimi</IT> (CEX, PDB code 1FH8 <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF>) and from <IT>B. circulans</IT> (BCX, 1BVV<SP>7</SP>) determined to 1.95 Å and 1.8 Å resolution, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hydrogen atoms were added with the Xleap program<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF> to the protein atoms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">His85 and His107 of CEX and His149 and His156 of BCX were protonated at the δ-nitrogen, while ε-tautomers were assigned for the rest of the histidines.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The acid/base catalysts Glu127 (CEX) and Glu172 (BCX) were protonated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the MD simulations X4 was docked to the −2, −1, +1 and +2 subsites of the xylanases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The sugar moieties of the −2, +1 and +2 subsites most probably bind to the xylanases in the <SP>4</SP>C<SB>1</SB> conformation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">More variations have been observed in the conformations of the −1 subsite<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7 cit22 cit23">7,22,23</REF> and it is possible that xylanases distort the −1 sugar in the Michaelis complex.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, MD simulations were done for both enzymes with X4 in an all-chair conformation and in a conformation having the −1 sugar in a distorted conformation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the latter simulations, X4 was docked to the binding site with the −1 moiety in different skew-boat conformations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">These structures were first visually checked and if they were found to fit in the binding site without unreasonably large steric overlap with the protein atoms, MD simulations for such enzyme–X4 complexes were started.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">It turned out that simulations with distorted −1 sugar produced stable trajectories only when the sugar adopted a B<SB>3,O</SB> conformation for CEX and a <SP>2</SP>S<SB>O</SB> conformation for BCX (Fig. 2).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">An appropriate number of counterions (seven Na<SP>+</SP> ions for CEX and four Cl<SP>−</SP> ions for BCX) were added to neutralize the simulation systems.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Xylanase-X4 complexes were solvated with a truncated octahedron of TIP3P water molecules extending at least 12 Å from the protein atoms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Crystal waters were included in the simulations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This resulted in 9087 water molecules for CEX and 6365 water molecules for BCX.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod12" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the MD simulations the water molecules and hydrogens of protein and substrate were first energy minimized for 1000 steps, heated to 300 K in 7.5 ps and equilibrated by 50 ps at a constant temperature of 300 K and pressure of 1 atm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod13" novelty="None" advantage="None">After that the whole simulation system was minimized for 1000 steps, the temperature of the system was increased to 300 K in 7.5 ps and equilibrated for 300 ps using a time step of 1.5 fs and the SHAKE algorithm<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF> to constrain the bonds involving hydrogen atoms to their equilibrium values with a geometrical tolerance of 10<SP>−5</SP> Å.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod14" novelty="None" advantage="None">After that the production simulations of 4.0 ns were started.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod15" novelty="None" advantage="None">During the production simulations structures were saved every 5 ps for analyses.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The cutoff for Lennard-Jones interactions was 8 Å and the particle mesh Ewald (PME) method<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25">25</REF> was used for the treatment of electrostatic interactions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod17" novelty="None" advantage="None">A charge grid of ∼1 Å with cubic B-spline interpolation and the direct sum tolerance of 10<SP>−5</SP> were used.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Continuum model correction was applied for energy and pressure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The MD simulations were done with the AMBER 7.0 program<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26">26</REF> and the Cornell <IT>et al.</IT> force field.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27">27</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod20" novelty="None" advantage="None">The modified parameters of the GLYCAM_93 set<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28">28</REF> were used for the substrates and their atomic point charges were calculated using the RESP method<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29">29</REF> at the HF/6-31G(d) level.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod21" novelty="None" advantage="None">Periodic water box simulations of 4.0 ns were done for free xylotetraose in an all-chair (<SP>4</SP>C<SB>1</SB>) conformation (X4(c)) and in a conformation in which the −1 sugar moiety was in the <SP>2</SP>S<SB>O</SB> conformation (X4(sb)) while the other moieties were in the <SP>4</SP>C<SB>1</SB> conformation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod22" novelty="None" advantage="None">The trajectories were analysed with the ANAL, PTRAJ and CARNAL programs of AMBER 7.0 and visually examined with the assistance of the Moil-view program<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30">30</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>MM-PBSA free energy calculations</HEADER><P><s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod23" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the MM-PBSA method<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF> MD simulations in explicit water are first carried out for the system studied.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod24" novelty="None" advantage="None">After that solvent water molecules of the “snapshot” structures collected from the molecular dynamics trajectories are removed, and the average free energies (G) of the protein–ligand complex and separated protein and ligand are calculated as a sums of the average molecular mechanical gas-phase energies (<IT>E</IT><SB>MM</SB>), solvation free energies (Δ<IT>G</IT><SB>solv</SB>) and entropy contributions (−<IT>TS</IT>):<IT>G</IT> = <IT>E</IT><SB>MM</SB> + Δ<IT>G</IT><SB>solv</SB> − <IT>TS</IT>The average free energies of the species are then used to calculate binding free energies (Δ<IT>G</IT>) for protein-ligand association.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod25" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this work the molecular mechanical (<IT>E</IT><SB>MM</SB>) energies were calculated using the SANDER program of AMBER7 with all protein pair-wise interactions included using a dielectric constant (<IT>ε</IT>) of 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod26" novelty="None" advantage="None">The solvation free energy (Δ<IT>G</IT><SB>solv</SB>) is the sum of electrostatic solvation, calculated by the finite-difference solution of the Poisson–Boltzmann equation (Δ<IT>G</IT><SB>PB</SB>) with the Delphi program,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit31">31</REF> and non-polar solvation energy (Δ<IT>G</IT><SB>np</SB>), calculated from the solvent-accessible surface area (SASA):Δ<IT>G</IT><SB>solv</SB> = Δ<IT>G</IT><SB>PB</SB> + Δ<IT>G</IT><SB>np</SB>A probe radius of 1.4 Å and atomic radii of the PARSE parameter set<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit32">32</REF> was used to determine the molecular surface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod27" novelty="None" advantage="None">Atomic charges of the Cornell <IT>et al.</IT> force field<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27">27</REF> were used for amino acid residues and RESP charges were calculated at the HF/6-31G* level for the substrate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod28" novelty="None" advantage="None">An 80% boxfill cubic lattice and a grid resolution of 0.5 Å (grid point)<SP>−1</SP> were used in the Delphi calculations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod29" novelty="None" advantage="None">The MSMS program<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit33">33</REF> was used to calculate the SASA for the estimation of Δ<IT>G</IT><SB>np</SB> using eqn. (3) and <IT>γ</IT> = 0.02268 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>Å<SP>−2</SP> and <IT>β</IT> = 3.85 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit32">32</REF>.Δ<IT>G</IT><SB>np</SB> = <IT>γ</IT> × SASA + <IT>β</IT>The calculated Δ<IT>G</IT><SB>bind</SB> values can be divided into contributions of different force-field terms and solvation energies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj8" novelty="New" advantage="None">This allows us to analyse the energetics of the ligand binding in more detail.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod30" novelty="None" advantage="None">The energy terms used in the binding energy analyses are explained in the footnote of Table 1.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod31" novelty="None" advantage="None">The energy contribution from entropy changes upon ligand binding was not included here primarily because the main interest in this work was in calculating the binding free energies of one substrate molecule in different conformations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">This was justified by the good agreement between the calculated and experimental relative binding free energies in several earlier studies applying the same approximation.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13 cit14 cit15 cit16 cit17 cit18">13–18</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac20" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, there is no straightforward way to quantitatively calculate entropy contribution to binding.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13 cit34 cit35">13,34,35</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod32" novelty="None" advantage="None">The single-trajectory method was applied in this work to calculate the binding free energies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod33" novelty="None" advantage="None">This means that the snapshot structures of the protein–ligand complex and separated protein and ligand were taken from the MD trajectory of the protein–ligand complex.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac21" novelty="None" advantage="None">It has been observed that the single-trajectory method provides fairly good estimates for the relative binding energies.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13 cit15 cit16">13,15,16</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac22" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, in cases where there are reorganizations in the protein structure due to ligand binding, separate trajectories are often needed to get reliable binding energies<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13 cit36 cit37">13,36,37</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>QM calculations</HEADER><P><s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod34" novelty="None" advantage="None">Density functional theory and <IT>ab initio</IT> QM calculations were done with the Gaussian98 program.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit38">38</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod35" novelty="None" advantage="None">The geometries of xylose monomers were optimised at the B3LYP/6-31G(d) and MP2/6-31G(d) levels.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod36" novelty="None" advantage="None">These geometries were then used to calculate energies with the 6-311G(d,p) and 6-311G(3d,2p) basis sets.</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod37" novelty="None" advantage="None">The energies of xylotetraose snapshots collected from the MD simulations were calculated at the B3LYP/6-31G* level without geometry optimisation (B3LYP/6-31G(d)//MM).</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Results and discussion</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Structures of the xylanase–xylotetraose complexes</HEADER><P><s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj9" novelty="New" advantage="None">MD simulations of 4.0 ns were done for CEX and BCX complexed with X4 in two different conformations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the CEX(c) and BCX(c) simulations X4 was in an all-chair (<SP>4</SP>C<SB>1</SB>) conformation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod38" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the CEX(b) and BCX(sb) simulations the −2, +1 and +2 moieties were in the chair conformation and the −1 sugar in a skew-boat starting conformation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the basis of the root-mean-squared deviations (RMSD) of the protein atoms and the calculated free energies (see below) all four simulations produced stable trajectories.</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The average RMSDs for the Cα atoms from the corresponding X-ray structure during the last 1.0 ns of the 4.0 ns MD simulation were 1.04 Å for the CEX(c), 0.99 Å for the CEX(b), 0.79 Å for the BCX(c), and 0.87 Å for the BCX(sb) simulation.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the CEX(c) simulation all monomers of the substrate stayed in an almost relaxed <SP>4</SP>C<SB>1</SB> conformation during the simulation time.</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Inspection of the arrangement of the catalytic nucleophile, the acid/base catalyst, the reacting C1 and the glycosidic oxygen of the substrate revealed that this conformation is not a reactive one (<IT>i.e.</IT> conformational arrangements would be required for the catalytic reaction).</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of CEX(b) simulation, the −1 sugar adopted during the equilibration period a slightly twisted B<SB>3,O</SB> conformation and stayed in this conformation for the rest of the simulation (Fig. 3a).</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The average C1-C2-C4-C5 torsion angle during the last 1.0 ns of the production simulation was −2.1° (standard deviation = 8.3°), close to 0° of an ideal boat conformation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the B<SB>3,O</SB> conformation the −1 sugar is in a reactive conformation: (i) the catalytic nucleophile, Glu233, forms a hydrogen bond with the 2-OH of the −1 sugar and is ready to attack the C1 carbon, (ii) the breaking glycosidic bond is in a pseudoaxial orientation suitable for a facile bond cleavage, and (iii) the acid/base catalyst (Glu127) is suitably positioned to deliver a proton to the leaving glycosidic oxygen.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the BCX(c) simulation the −1 sugar stayed in a slightly distorted <SP>4</SP>C<SB>1</SB> conformation for the first 1.8 ns.</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">After that the conformation of the −1 monomer changed to a <SP>1</SP>C<SB>4</SB> conformation where it stayed the rest of the 4.0 ns simulation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Like in the CEX(c) simulation, the interactions of the reactive groups were not suitable for the catalytic events without conformational changes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">During the equilibration period of the BCX(sb) simulation, the −1 sugar adopted a <SP>2</SP>S<SB>O</SB> conformation while the rest of the monomers (−2, +1, and +2) stayed in a <SP>4</SP>C<SB>1</SB> conformation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the basis of structures and energies, this X4 conformation was particularly stable during the whole 4.0 ns simulation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the <SP>2</SP>S<SB>O</SB> conformation the −1 sugar has the leaving glycosidic bond in a pseudoaxial orientation and the reactive groups ideally positioned for the catalytic reaction (Fig. 3b).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the reactive substrate conformations of CEX and BCX the leaving +1 sugar is rotated so that the acid/base catalysts, Glu127 and Glu172, may approach the glycosidic oxygens without steric hindrance.</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of CEX the acid/base catalyst protonates the glycosidic oxygen from the <IT>anti</IT> direction relative to the endocyclic C1–O6 bond of the −1 sugar ring and in the case of BCX from the <IT>syn</IT> direction<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Single-trajectory binding free energies</HEADER><P><s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The free energies for the binding (Δ<IT>G</IT><SB>bind</SB>) of X4 calculated from the CEX(c), CEX(b), BCX(c) and BCX(sb) simulations as a function of simulation time are shown in Figs. 4a and 4b.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The free energy analysis of Δ<IT>G</IT><SB>bind</SB> values calculated from the last two ns of 4.0 ns MD simulations are listed in Table 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod39" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since in the single-trajectory method the structures of the isolated ligand and enzyme are taken from the enzyme-ligand complex, these energies measure the interactions present between the enzyme and ligand in the structure of the complex, and no changes in the internal energy of protein or ligand taken place upon ligand binding are included.</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of CEX(c) simulation, the Δ<IT>G</IT><SB>bind</SB> is on average −90.8 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> during the first 1.0 ns, increases to −72.8 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> and −67.8 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> for the next two nanoseconds, respectively, and decreases to −87.9 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> for the last 1.0 ns of the 4.0 ns MD simulation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None">More consistent behaviour is seen for CEX(b): Δ<IT>G</IT><SB>bind</SB> is −58.6 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> in the first 1.0 ns but as the simulation progresses it decreases being −77.0 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> when calculated from the structures of the last 1.0 ns.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of BCX, the average Δ<IT>G</IT><SB>bind</SB> of the BCX(c) simulation is −89.1 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> and −85.4 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> in the first and second ns of simulation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, at about 1.8 ns a conformational change takes place and the −1 sugar adopts an <SP>1</SP>C<SB>4</SB> conformation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs19" novelty="None" advantage="None">As a consequence, the Δ<IT>G</IT><SB>bind</SB> increases sharply being −46.9 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> when calculated from the structures of the last 1.0 ns.</annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs20" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Δ<IT>G</IT><SB>bind</SB> of BCX(sb) is exceptionally stable and stays between −84.5 and −87.0 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> during the whole 4.0 ns of MD simulation.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs21" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of CEX the calculated Δ<IT>G</IT><SB>bind</SB> value predicts (Table 1) that the all-chair substrate conformation (X4(c)) and the reactive conformation (X4(b)) are bound equally tightly (−77.8 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP><IT>vs.</IT> −78.0 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs22" novelty="None" advantage="None">The analysis of different components of the Δ<IT>G</IT><SB>bind</SB> values of Table 1 show, that electrostatic enzyme–substrate interactions (Δ<IT>E</IT><SB>ele</SB>) clearly favour (by 93.9 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>) the binding of the reactive conformation as compared to X4(c).</annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs23" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the other hand, the van der Waals interactions (Δ<IT>E</IT><SB>vdW</SB>) favour the binding of X4(c) over X4(b) by 28.7 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs24" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of BCX, Δ<IT>E</IT><SB>ele</SB> favours the binding of X4(sb) by 78.1 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> whereas Δ<IT>E</IT><SB>vdW</SB> is slightly unfavourable (4.0 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>) for the binding of X4(sb) as compared to X4(c).</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, in the cases of CEX and BCX the specific enzyme–substrate interactions favour the binding of the reactive conformations, whereas the unspecific van der Waals interactions are more favourable for the binding of the non-reactive conformations.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the basis of Δ<IT>G</IT><SB>bind</SB> values, CEX binds xylotetraose in an all-chair conformation and a conformation having a distorted −1 sugar (B<SB>3,O</SB>) with comparable affinities, and BCX prefers a conformation having the −1 sugar in a reactive (<SP>2</SP>S<SB>O</SB>) high-energy conformation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">This may partly explain why CEX binds various xylobiose-derived imino sugars and xylobiose much tighter (10<SP>2</SP>–10<SP>4</SP> fold) than BCX, which prefers distorted substrates.</annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac23" novelty="None" advantage="None">For example, the inhibition constant (<IT>K</IT><SB>i</SB>) for xylobiose is 4800 μM for CEX and 80 000 μM BCX<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Intramolecular energies of the free and enzyme-bound xylotetraose conformations</HEADER><P><s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac24" novelty="None" advantage="None">When a substrate is bound to the enzyme active site its structure is deformed to optimise the enzyme–substrate interactions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac25" novelty="None" advantage="None">This evidently results in increase in the substrate’s internal energy (deformation energy) as compared to its energy in aqueous solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The estimation of the substrate deformation energy was one of the main goals of this study.</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod40" novelty="None" advantage="None">To this end, MD simulations of 4.0 ns were done also for free X4 in aqueous solution in an all-chair conformation (X4(c)) and in a conformation in which the −1 sugar was in the <SP>2</SP>S<SB>O</SB> conformation and the other moieties in the <SP>4</SP>C<SB>1</SB> conformation (X4(sb)).</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj10" novelty="New" advantage="None">The internal energies obtained from these simulations were compared to those of the enzyme-bound X4.</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac26" novelty="None" advantage="None">The <SP>4</SP>C<SB>1</SB> conformation has been experimentally found to be the most stable conformation for most natural carbohydrates.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit39">39</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod41" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the following discussion X4(c,aq) and X4(sb,aq) denote the all-chair and skew-boat (−1 sugar) xylotetraose conformations free in aqueous solution, X4(c,CEX) and X4(b,CEX) denote the all-chair and boat (−1 sugar) conformations bound to CEX, and X4(c,BCX) and X4(sb,BCX) denote the all-chair and skew-boat (−1 sugar) conformations bound to BCX.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj11" novelty="New" advantage="None">Because it is not guaranteed that the MM force-field correctly describes the distorted substrate conformations, we first compared the energies of xylotetraose conformations calculated with MM and QM methods.</annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod42" novelty="None" advantage="None">It must be noted here that MM force-fields in general are not parameterised to reproduce exact gas-phase energies but molecular properties in the condensed phase.</annotationART></s> <s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod43" novelty="None" advantage="None">The accuracy of the B3LYP/6-31G(d) method, which was used in the QM energy calculations of xylotetraose conformations, was first checked by calculating the energies of <SP>4</SP>C<SB>1</SB>, <SP>2</SP>S<SB>O</SB> and B<SB>3,O</SB> conformations of xylose monomer with various QM methods (up to MP2/6-311G(d,p)//MP2/6-31G(d) and B3LYP/6-311G(3d,2p)//B3LYP/6-31G(d) levels).</annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs25" novelty="None" advantage="None">The B3LYP/6-31G(d) calculations were found to provide the relative energies of the conformations with reasonable accuracy (Table 2).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod44" novelty="None" advantage="None">The energy comparison of X4 conformations was done by calculating the average MM (the same force-field was used as in MD simulations) and QM (at the B3LYP/6-31G(d)) gas-phase energies for snapshot structures collected from the first nanoseconds of the MD simulations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod45" novelty="None" advantage="None">The average MM and QM energies were calculated for the MD snapshot structures without geometry optimisation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs26" novelty="None" advantage="None">The relative average gas-phase energies are reported in Table 3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs27" novelty="None" advantage="None">These results show that excluding X4(c,BCX), the energies of the conformations studied are somewhat overestimated (relative to X4(c,aq)) with the MM force-field as compared to the B3LYP/6-31G(d) method.</annotationART></s> <s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the conclusions that (i) on binding to enzyme the energies of the reactive conformations (X4(sb,CEX) and X4(sb,BCX)) are increased by significantly less than those of the all-chair conformations (X4(c,CEX) and X4(c,BCX)), and that (ii) the energy increase is larger for binding to BCX than CEX, can be drawn with both energy calculation methods.</annotationART></s> <s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs28" novelty="None" advantage="None">These conclusions are also in line with those drawn from the free energies obtained from the MM-PBSA analysis (see below, Fig. 5).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj12" novelty="New" advantage="None">The internal energies of xylotetraoses were studied in more detail by calculating MM-PBSA free energies for free and enzyme-bound substrates over the 4.0 ns MD simulations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs29" novelty="None" advantage="None">The free energies of enzyme-bound X4s as a function of simulation time are shown in Figs. 4c and 4d, and the relative free energies are presented in Fig. 5.</annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs30" novelty="None" advantage="None">The average MM-PBSA free energy of X4(c) free in aqueous solution was 640.6 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>, calculated from the 4.0 ns simulation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs31" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the X4(sb) simulation the −1 sugar stayed in the <SP>2</SP>S<SB>O</SB> conformation for the first 1.8 ns after which its conformation changed to the <SP>4</SP>C<SB>1</SB> conformation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs32" novelty="None" advantage="None">The average free energy of the X4(sb) was 658.1 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>, calculated from the structures of the first 1.8 ns.</annotationART></s> <s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs33" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, in water X4(c) is calculated to be 17.6 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> more stable than X4(sb).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs34" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the CEX(c) simulation, the energy of the enzyme-bound X4(c) is 675.3 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> during the first 1.0 ns, it decreases by 5–11 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> for the next 2.0 ns, and increases to 682.0 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> for the last 1.0 ns (Fig. 4c).</annotationART></s> <s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The changes in the internal energy of X4(c) can be seen to be coupled with the changes in the single-trajectory free energy of binding (Δ<IT>G</IT><SB>bind</SB>, Fig. 4a): the relaxation of the substrate structure to a less distorted one compensates partly for the formation of less tight protein–substrate interactions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs35" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the CEX(b) simulation the energy of the bound X4(b) was 666.1 to 668.2 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> during the whole simulation, on average 6 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> lower than the energy of X4(c) in the CEX(c) simulation (Fig. 5).</annotationART></s> <s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs36" novelty="None" advantage="None">Interestingly, the order of stability of the enzyme-bound X4(c) and X4(b) is reversed from that in aqueous solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is due to the clearly larger deformation energy (32 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP><IT>vs.</IT> 9 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>) for the binding of X4(c) than X4(b) to CEX (the energy of the unconstrained <SP>2</SP>S<SB>O</SB> simulation was used here as a reference).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs37" novelty="None" advantage="None">Even more pronounced differences in the deformation energies of X4 conformations take place upon binding to BCX.</annotationART></s> <s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs38" novelty="None" advantage="None">During the first 1.0 ns of BCX(c) simulation the energy of X4(c) was on average 683.7 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>, 43 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> higher than the energy of the free X4(c) (Fig. 4d).</annotationART></s> <s sid="143"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">After 1.8 ns of BCX(c) simulation the conformation of the −1 sugar changed from <SP>4</SP>C<SB>1</SB> to <SP>1</SP>C<SB>4</SB> and, as in the CEX(c) simulation, the change in the internal energy of X4 is linked to the changes in the enzyme–substrate interactions (Fig. 4b and d).</annotationART></s> <s sid="144"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs39" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the BCX(sb) simulation the average energy of X4(sb) was 664.4 to 669.9 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> during the simulation, on average 15.6 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> lower than the energy of the enzyme-bound all-chair conformation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="145"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs40" novelty="None" advantage="None">The energy of the enzyme-bound X4(sb) is only 9 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> higher than that of the free X4(sb).</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Implications to enzyme-catalysed reactions</HEADER><P><s sid="146"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac27" novelty="None" advantage="None">Simply stated, enzymes catalyse chemical reactions by decreasing the free energy of activation for reaching the transition state from the ground state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="147"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac28" novelty="None" advantage="None">A wide range of different theories have been developed to provide more detailed explanations for the large rate enhancements of enzyme-catalysed reactions as compared to the corresponding solution reactions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit40 cit41 cit42">40–42</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="148"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac29" novelty="None" advantage="None">In general enzymes achieve rate enhancement by providing environments, which specifically stabilize transition states and high-energy intermediates of the reaction using mainly electrostatic interactions of the preorganised environment.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11 cit42 cit43 cit44 cit45">11,42–45</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="149"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac30" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, part of the enzymes’ catalytic potency has been suggested to originate from their ability to bind substrate(s) in a reactive conformation,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit41 cit44 cit45 cit46">41,44–46</REF> also named as a near-attack conformation (NAC),<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit47">47</REF> although there has been some disagreement about the importance of NACs in enzyme-catalysed reactions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit48">48</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="150"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac31" novelty="None" advantage="None">A NAC is an enzyme–substrate conformation closely resembling the reaction transition state through which the reaction must pass to reach the transition state.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit47">47</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="151"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac32" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this conformation, which is not necessarily a stationary point on the (free) energy surface, the catalytic groups are in a precisely correct position for the reaction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="152"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac33" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is likely that enzymes owe their catalytic properties to several different factors, which have varying relative importance in different enzymatic reactions, especially because the nature of chemical transformations catalysed by enzymes varies greatly.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="153"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac34" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is likely that significant part of the catalytic properties of CEX and BCX, in analogy to the lysozyme-catalysed hydrolysis studied computationally by Warshel <IT>et al.</IT>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11 cit12">11,12</REF> is due to the fact that they provide suitable catalytic groups, a nucleophile and an acid/base catalyst, for the reaction and a preorganised environment, which electrostatically stabilises the reaction transition state relative to the ground state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="154"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac35" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the role of substrate distortion in the catalytic mechanisms of glycoside hydrolases has been of some controversy<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12 cit49 cit50">12,49,50</REF> ever since the publication of lysozyme–substrate X-ray structure, showing that in the Michaelis complex the reactive sugar moiety adopts a sofa conformation.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit49">49</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="155"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac36" novelty="None" advantage="None">Such experimental structural data is not available for xylanase–substrate complexes.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="156"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The calculations of this work showed that in the reactive enzyme–xylotetraose conformations of CEX and BCX the −1 sugar adopts a B<SB>3,O</SB> and <SP>2</SP>S<SB>O</SB> conformation, respectively (Fig. 3).</annotationART></s> <s sid="157"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">These reactive conformations were stable during the 4.0 ns MD simulations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="158"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs41" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the basis of binding free energies, CEX binds X4(b) with a comparable affinity to X4(c), and BCX binds X4(sb) tighter than X4(c).</annotationART></s> <s sid="159"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition that CEX and BCX form tighter specific enzyme–substrate interactions with the reactive than non-reactive conformations, recognition of the reactive conformations is accomplished by shape complementarity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="160"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Namely, the reactive conformations fit in the active sites of CEX and BCX with only a modest increase in their internal energies (9 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>) as compared to the corresponding conformations free in aqueous solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="161"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast to this, the internal energies of all-chair conformations are increased by 33–43 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> upon binding to the enzymes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="162"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">As a result of this, the internal energies of the reactive xylotetraose conformations of CEX and BCX are lower than the internal energies of the bound all-chair conformations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="163"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs42" novelty="None" advantage="None">In aqueous solution the all-chair conformation was calculated to be 17.6 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> more stable than the reactive conformations (Fig. 5).</annotationART></s> <s sid="164"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">So, selective binding of reactive high-energy conformations, through which the CEX- and BCX-catalysed reactions pass, likely provides a contribution to the rate enhancement of the enzyme reaction as compared to the reaction in aqueous solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="165"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">Namely, in solution the all-chair xylotetraose conformation was calculated to be about 15 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> more stable than the <SP>2</SP>S<SB>O</SB> conformation (Fig. 5).</annotationART></s> <s sid="166"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">If in the xylanase-xylotetraose Michaelis complex xylotetraose is bound in a skew-boat or boat conformation, it can be estimated that the binding of this high-energy conformation may contribute up to 15 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> to the rate enhancement of the enzyme-catalysed reaction as compared to the same reaction in solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="167"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">An accurate estimation of this contribution would require the calculation of the reaction both in aqueous solution and within enzyme, which is out of scope of this work.</annotationART></s> <s sid="168"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">It must also be noted that enzyme deformation energy (<IT>i.e.</IT> change in enzyme energy taking place upon substrate binding) is not included here.</annotationART></s> <s sid="169"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac37" novelty="None" advantage="None">This energy contribution may play some role in determining the relative energies of substrate conformations and different states of the enzyme-catalysed reaction.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit44">44</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="170"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac38" novelty="None" advantage="None">Unfortunately, its accurate calculation with the MM-PBSA approach, and also in general, is a demanding task.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit36 cit37">36,37</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="171"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac39" novelty="None" advantage="None">It has been suggested, on the basis of X-ray structures, that glycoside hydrolases distort their substrates by favourable enzyme–substrate interactions, which are only present when the substrate adopts a distorted conformation.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit49 cit50 cit51">49–51</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="172"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac40" novelty="None" advantage="None">In such a case the increase in the substrate energy is compensated by the enzyme–substrate interactions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="173"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None">That this suggestion holds also in the case of CEX and BCX is supported by the calculated structures (Fig. 3) and more favourable specific enzyme–substrate interactions (Δ<IT>E</IT><SB>ele</SB>, Table 1) for reactive than non-reactive conformations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="174"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac41" novelty="None" advantage="None">It has also been suggested that substrate distortion is not important because enzymes and substrates are so flexible that no significant distortion is possible in enzyme–substrate complexes and, therefore, distortion of substrate does not play important role in enzyme catalysis.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11 cit12 cit48">11,12,48</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="175"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac42" novelty="None" advantage="None">This idea is based on the argument, that because energetically significant substrate distortion involves small movements in the positions of atoms, it is not likely that protein structure could exert large enough forces to distort substrates.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit48 cit50">48,50</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="176"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None">That CEX and BCX do not exert large forces on individual substrate monomers is likely true.</annotationART></s> <s sid="177"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, because the substrate-binding site with several subsites is complementary in shape with the relatively rigid carbohydrate chain having the reactive −1 sugar in a high-energy conformation, the all-chair substrate conformation does not fit well in the binding site resulting in considerable deformation energy (33–43 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>), if such a conformation is tightly bound.</annotationART></s> <s sid="178"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the overall shapes of saccharide polymers are sensitive to the conformations of individual subunits, in this case of the reactive −1 sugar, the recognition of substrates in reactive conformations by shape complementarity may be operating also in the mechanisms of other glycosyl hydrolases.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="179"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">Distortion of oligosaccharide substrate, which seems to be more pronounced for the family 11 xylanase BCX than the family 10 CEX, requires that substrate occupies several sugar-binding subsites in order to become strong enough to enhance substrate hydrolysis rate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="180"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">If substrate distortion plays role in the catalysis and is larger for BCX than CEX, should be seen in different substrate specificities for the enzymes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="181"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None">This suggestion is supported by the fact that xylanases of family 10 hydrolyse more readily and show higher affinity for shorter xylooligosaccharides than family 11 xylanases.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23 cit52">23,52</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="182"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con15" novelty="None" advantage="None">To conclude, the results of this work led us to suggest that selective binding of reactive high-energy substrate conformations by favourable specific enzyme–substrate interactions and by shape complementarity is an important contribution, especially in the case of BCX, to the catalytic properties of xylanases.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
