<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b305670h" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">“Wash and go”: sodium chloride as an easily removable catalyst support for the synthesis of carbon nanotubes</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">A sodium chloride supported cobalt catalyst was found to be active in the synthesis of carbon nanotubes by a CCVD method.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Carbon nanotubes (CNTs) are widely considered as promising materials both in nanochemistry and nanoelectronics.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2 cit3">1–3</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">New generations of composite materials, semiconductor circuits or TV screens based upon CNT technology are under construction and very near to being realized.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, in order to appear on the market and later in the households, these products as well as their components must be cheap enough.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In contrast to the laser ablation<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF> and arc discharge<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF> techniques catalytic chemical vapour deposition (CCVD) is able to produce nanotubes in industrial quantities.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In the laboratory scale C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>2</SB> or C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>4</SB> as carbon sources, cobalt, iron or nickel as catalyst particles, and high surface area SiO<SB>2</SB>, Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> or zeolite supports are commonly used for the synthesis of multiwalled nanotubes (MWNTs).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7 cit8 cit9 cit10 cit11">7–11</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="No">After the synthesis process nanotubes must be removed from the catalyst.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="No">This means strong acidic (HF in the case of zeolites) or basic (concentrated NaOH in the case of Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> and SiO<SB>2</SB>) treatment in most of the cases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Applying a water soluble catalyst support could make the purification step easier controllable, more economical, and environmentally friendly.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Experimental</HEADER><P><s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Sodium chloride (2 g, ACROS) was ground into a fine powder in a mortar, and impregnated with a methanolic solution of 0.1198 g of Co(NO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>2</SB>·6H<SB>2</SB>O (Vel).</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The materials were sonicated in an ultrasound bath for 10 min.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The solvent was evaporated under vacuum at 80 °C by a rotary evaporator.</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The sample was dried at 120 °C for 5 h and ground again into a fine powder.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">1 g of the catalyst prepared this way was placed in a quartz boat and slipped into a horizontal quartz tube reactor with a diameter of about 5 cm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">After purging the system by N<SB>2</SB> at room temperature the reaction was carried out at 700 °C for 30 min in a 10 ∶ 100 C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>2</SB>–N<SB>2</SB> mixture with a total flow rate of 330 ml min<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The original light violet colour of the catalyst changed to dark grey during the reaction, caused by the appearance of carbon species on the surface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The amount of carbon deposite was determined by thermal analysis on a Netzsch STA 409PC Luxx thermogravimeter.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The resulting carbon forms were characterised with a Philips XL20 scanning electron microscope before, and with a Philips Tecnai transmission electron microscope after removing the sodium chloride support by washing with distilled water.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Results and discussion</HEADER><P><s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Results of the TG analysis showed a weight loss of 2.6% in the 300–700 °C temperature range, which is attributed to the burning of different carbon species.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This means about 200% carbon deposit relative to the weight of the cobalt particles.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">SEM investigations verifyed the presence of nanotubes in the sample.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Carbon nanotubes winding from the surface of catalyst particles can be seen in Fig. 1.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 2a and 2b show the TEM pictures of the purified sample.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Next to the encapsulated cobalt particles well graphitized MWNTs with rather large diameter (up to 30 nm) can be observed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Coiled carbon nanotubes were also formed.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In spite of its low specific surface area, melting point (about 810 °C), and unfavourable thermal conductivity<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF> sodium chloride can support dispersed cobalt particles suitable for building of CNTs.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">In order to avoid the formation of small metal islands stemming from the aggregation of metal particles,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF> one has to use low cobalt concentrations and to avoid the preliminary reduction step.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">Employing the very reactive C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>2</SB> as the carbon source makes possible the use of a synthesis temperature of 100 °C below the melting point of the support.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Conclusion</HEADER><P><s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast with the results of other authors<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF> we have proved the possibility of CNT synthesis by CCVD method on cobalt particles supported on sodium chloride.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The support material can be quickly and easily dissolved and completely removed by distilled water.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Optimisation of catalyst preparation and reaction conditions will be directed towards the development of a high performance and highly recyclable CCVD catalyst system producing carbon nanotubes with low defect walls and a more uniform size distribution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Reduction should be sought in the total number of graphite coated cobalt particles and additional carbon forms produced during the reaction, because current post-synthetic purifying treatments are mostly incapable of removing them.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
