<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b308202d" hasDoc="yes" version="1168" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Urethane cross-linked poly(oxyethylene)/siliceous nanohybrids doped with Eu<SP>3+</SP> ionsPart 2.<XREF TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" /> Ionic association</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fourier transform mid-IR and Raman spectroscopies were employed to investigate the anionic local surrounding in sol–gel derived organic/inorganic materials–<IT>monourethanesils</IT>–incorporating europium triflate, Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The hybrid framework of these xerogels contains short methyl end capped polyether segments grafted to a siliceous network through urethane cross-links.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">Samples with compositions ∞ &gt; <IT>n</IT> ≥ 10 (where <IT>n</IT> indicates the ratio of (OCH<SB>2</SB>CH<SB>2</SB>) moieties per lanthanide ion) were examined.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The spectral data obtained provide conclusive evidence of the presence of “free” and weakly coordinated CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB><SP>–</SP> ions located in two distinct sites in the whole range of salt concentration analyzed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">At <IT>n</IT> = 30 and 10, along with these species, two new anionic configurations, assigned to contact ion pairs and “cross-link separated” ions pairs, emerge.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Two-dimensional correlation spectroscopic analysis allowed to clarify the number of components present in two critical bands containing strongly overlapped spectral profiles.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The number of anionic environments found in the m-Ut(750)<SB><IT>n</IT></SB>Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB> family confirms the rich coordinating possibilities offered by polymer systems incorporating trivalent triflate salts.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None">This paper is the second of two papers devoted to the investigation of a family of Eu<SP>3+</SP>-based sol–gel derived organic/inorganic materials designated as <IT>monourethanesils.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2 cit3">1–3</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="None" advantage="Yes">These xerogels were recently introduced with the goal of serving as model compounds of a series of structurally complex poly(oxyethylene), POE/siloxane hybrids (<IT>diureasils</IT>)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF> that are excellent candidates for the construction of new low cost, multipurpose, one material-based devices, combining several technologically useful features, such as, for instance, conducting, optical and magnetic properties.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit5 cit6 cit7">4–7</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">With the scope of gaining a deeper knowledge of the structure/properties relationship in the diureasil system, we will continue to examine in the present work the same set of europium triflate, Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB>-doped <IT>monourethanesil</IT> samples analyzed in Part .1<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj5" novelty="New" advantage="None">The compounds studied include short methyl end capped POE chains covalently bonded to a siliceous backbone through urethane groups.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The host matrix was termed m-Ut(750), where m stands for mono, Ut indicates the urethane linkage and 750 denotes the average molecular weight of the organic precursor used (corresponding to about 17 (OCH<SB>2</SB>CH<SB>2</SB>) repeat units).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In Part 1, Fourier transform mid-IR (FT-IR) and Raman (FT-Raman) spectroscopies, photoluminescence spectroscopy and differential scanning calorimetry enabled us to conclude that, in terms of cation/polymer and cation/cross-link interactions, the m-Ut(750)-based xerogels may be viewed as an adequate replica of the long-chain U(2000)<SB><IT>n</IT></SB>Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB> diureasil parent analogs (where U indicates the urea group, 2000 denotes the average molecular weight of the organic precursor used and <IT>n</IT> is the ratio of (OCH<SB>2</SB>CH<SB>2</SB>) units per Eu<SP>3+</SP> ion).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa3" novelty="None" advantage="None">As the role of the anion on the coordination of the Eu<SP>3+</SP> ions in the monourethanesil-type system has not been considered yet, we will be specifically concerned in Part 2 with the evaluation of the extent of ionic association in the m-Ut(750)<SB><IT>n</IT></SB>Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB> nanocomposites in order to shed more light into the description of the local chemical environment of the lanthanide ions which was initiated in Part .1<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj6" novelty="New" advantage="None">The Eu<SP>3+</SP>⋯CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB><SP>–</SP> interactions in the m-Ut(750)<SB><IT>n</IT></SB>Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB> hybrids will be assessed through a FT-IR/FT-Raman spectroscopic analysis of the characteristic modes of the CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB><SP>–</SP> ion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj6" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">This anion is an excellent probe for investigating the cationic and anionic environments in salt/polymer systems, since the assignment of its internal vibration modes is well established.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit9">8,9</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">The differentiation between the various associated species (contact ion pairs, solvent separated ion pairs, ionic multiplets or salt aggregates) is manifested in the spectra through different frequency shifts and/or splittings of different magnitude of characteristic vibrational bands of the “free” anion.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit9 cit10 cit11 cit12 cit13 cit14 cit15 cit16 cit17 cit18 cit19 cit20 cit21">8–21</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="New" advantage="None">The present spectroscopic analysis will essentially rely on deconvolution procedures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="New" advantage="No">Unfortunately, the curve-fitting of some of the triflate bands which are most sensitive to coordination effects is not straightforward, as they are in general broad and commonly contain multiply overlapped components.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">To unravel the most critical triflate regions of the spectra of the monourethanesils, we will also employ two-dimensional (2D) correlation spectroscopic analysis<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Results and discussion</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="1">IR and Raman spectroscopic data</HEADER><P><s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is generally assumed that a “free” CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB><SP>–</SP> ion in a staggered configuration with a <IT>C</IT><SB>3v</SB> point group symmetry possesses 18 normal modes with the symmetry representations 5A<SB>1</SB> + A<SB>2</SB> + 6E.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The A<SB>1</SB> and E modes are IR and Raman active, whereas the A<SB>2</SB> mode, associated with the internal torsion of the anion, is inactive both in IR and Raman.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">All these modes are to a greater or lesser extent sensitive to coordination effects and can thus be employed to probe the local chemical surrounding experienced by the anion.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit9 cit10 cit11 cit12 cit13 cit14 cit15 cit16 cit17 cit18 cit19 cit20 cit21">8–21</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The characteristic bands of the CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB><SP>–</SP> ion are clearly discerned in the room-temperature FT-IR spectra of the m-Ut(750)<SB><IT>n</IT></SB>Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB> monourethanesils between 1400 and 550 cm<SP>–1</SP> (Fig. 1) and in the room-temperature FT-Raman spectra of the same compounds in the 1600–100 cm<SP>–1</SP> spectral range (Fig. 2).</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Their frequency and assignment are given in Table 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj7" novelty="New" advantage="None">The specific spectral behavior of the xerogels investigated in the present work as a function of salt content will be discussed in detail below.</annotationART></s></P><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER><IT>ν</IT><SB>a</SB>(SO<SB>3</SB>) region</HEADER><P><s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The FT-IR spectra of the m-Ut(750)-based compounds with 400 ≥ <IT>n</IT> ≥ 30 exhibit a broad envelope in the <IT>ν</IT><SB>a</SB>(SO<SB>3</SB>) region (Fig. 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the contrary, the FT-IR spectrum of the m-Ut(750)<SB>10</SB>Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB> hybrid displays a series of sharp, distinct bands centered at about 1317, 1293, 1284, 1252, 1239 and 1216 cm<SP>–1</SP> (Fig. 1).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Close analysis of the FT-IR spectrum of the non-doped hybrid host represented in Fig. 1 reveals that between 1350 and 1200 cm<SP>–1</SP> the contribution of the polymer vibration modes is quite strong, a fact that complicates the detection of the triflate bands in the spectra of the materials incorporating Eu<SP>3+</SP> ions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj8" novelty="New" advantage="None">In order to discriminate the spectral changes introduced by the addition of Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB> to m-Ut(750), we will examine the FT-IR difference spectra reproduced in Fig. 3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="New" advantage="None">These curves were obtained by subtracting the spectrum of the non-doped matrix from those of the salt containing xerogel materials with <IT>n</IT> &gt; 10.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="New" advantage="No">This approach was not applied, however, to the m-Ut(750)<SB>10</SB>Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB> sample because in this compound, unlike in the more dilute monourethanesils, the polyether segments play an active role in the coordination of the lanthanide ions, that results in dramatic morphological modifications in the polymer chains (Fig. 1 and Part .1<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF>)</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 3 allows to infer that in the <IT>ν</IT><SB>a</SB>(SO<SB>3</SB>) region the most pronounced effect originating from the addition of increasing amounts of the guest lanthanide salt is the growth of a wide structured feature centered around 1274 cm<SP>–1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The inset in Fig. 3 shows that this band can be resolved into three components centered at about 1287, 1274 and 1262 cm<SP>–1</SP> (Table 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The typical results of the curve-fitting carried out in this envelope for the xerogel with <IT>n</IT> = 70 are reproduced in Fig. 4.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 3 also demonstrates that the band shape of the <IT>ν</IT><SB>a</SB>(SO<SB>3</SB>) event remains practically unchanged for a wide range of salt concentration (400 ≥ <IT>n</IT> ≥ 50), meaning that the increase of the guest salt content within this composition range does not change the general picture of the cation–anion interactions in the system.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 1 substantiates that, in the <IT>ν</IT><SB>a</SB>(SO<SB>3</SB>) region, the band contour of the rich-salt m-Ut(750)-based composite with <IT>n</IT> = 10 is drastically different from those of the monourethanesils with 400 ≥ <IT>n</IT> ≥ 50.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The tremendous spectral modifications discerned in this spectrum start to develop already in that of m-Ut(750)<SB>30</SB>Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB> (Figs. 1 and 3).</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa4" novelty="None" advantage="None">To gain additional information of the changes undergone by the <IT>ν</IT><SB>a</SB>(SO<SB>3</SB>) mode of the monourethanesil xerogels at high Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB> content (<IT>n</IT> = 30 and 10), we performed curve-fitting in the 1345–1200 cm<SP>–1</SP> frequency envelope.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The obtained results lead us to conclude that, apart from the peaks positioned at about 1286, 1274 and 1263 cm<SP>–1</SP> (already produced by the more dilute samples), four new components exist in the spectra of these two samples near 1317, 1295, 1251 and 1213 cm<SP>–1</SP> (Fig. 4, Table 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">These four bands dominate in the <IT>ν</IT><SB>a</SB>(SO<SB>3</SB>) envelope of m-Ut(750)<SB>10</SB>Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB> (Fig. 4, Table 1).</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER><IT>ν</IT><SB>s</SB>(CF<SB>3</SB>) and <IT>ν</IT><SB>a</SB>(CF<SB>3</SB>) regions</HEADER><P><s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the FT-IR spectra of the monourethanesils with <IT>n</IT> &gt; 30 the <IT>ν</IT><SB>s</SB>(CF<SB>3</SB>) band is found at about 1224 cm<SP>–1</SP> (Figs. 1 and 3, Table 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">This feature shows intensity growth with salt addition and becomes a prominent band centered at approximately 1237 cm<SP>–1</SP> in the FT-IR spectra of the two most concentrated samples (Figs. 3 and 4, Table 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of m-Ut(750)<SB>10</SB>Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB>, the 1237 cm<SP>–1</SP> band is the second strongest absorption feature of the spectrum (Fig. 1).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The <IT>ν</IT><SB>a</SB>(CF<SB>3</SB>) band is seen in the FT-IR spectra of the m-Ut(750)-based materials with <IT>n</IT> &gt; 10 as a shoulder situated around 1156 cm<SP>–1</SP> (Table 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">As already noted in Part 1,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF> the identification of this feature is subject to some uncertainty, because it overlaps the polymer band originated from the coupled vibration of the <IT>ν</IT>(CO) and <IT>ρ</IT><SB>r</SB>(CH<SB>2</SB>) modes, situated near 1142 cm<SP>–1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Nevertheless, the IR-difference spectra (Fig. 3) demonstrate that a sharp asymmetric band centered at about 1165 cm<SP>–1</SP> develops in the spectrum as salt concentration rises.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">This event becomes a very intense band in the spectrum of the most concentrated sample analyzed (Figs. 1 and 4).</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is noteworthy that the broad <IT>ν</IT><SB>a</SB>(CF<SB>3</SB>) profile of the latter monourethanesil becomes multicomponent (Fig. 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">It was resolved into five components: a very intense peak situated at about 1170 cm<SP>–1</SP>, a strong component that appears as a shoulder near 1178 cm<SP>–1</SP>, and three other less intense shoulders at 1186, 1164 and 1156 cm<SP>–1</SP> (Table 1).</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER><IT>ν</IT><SB>s</SB>(SO<SB>3</SB>) region</HEADER><P><s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Figs. 1 and 5 (left) evidence that in the <IT>ν</IT><SB>s</SB>(SO<SB>3</SB>) region the FT-IR spectra of m-Ut(750)-based compounds with 400 ≥ <IT>n</IT> ≥ 30 exhibit a narrow feature located at 1032 cm<SP>–1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Its intensity progressively rises with the incorporation of more Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB>, but its position is salt concentration independent.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Figs. 2 and 5 (right) show that, in this range of wavenumbers, the Raman spectra of the xerogel materials with <IT>n</IT> &gt; 10 also display a very sharp peak centered at 1032 cm<SP>–1</SP>, whose intensity grows with salt addition.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="New" advantage="None">The <IT>ν</IT><SB>s</SB>(SO<SB>3</SB>) envelope was analyzed in more detail by means of 2D correlation spectroscopy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results of this study will be presented in the next section.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">As expected, the spectral signature of the most concentrated material differs deeply from those of the more dilute monourethanesils.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus in the FT-IR spectrum of this sample two main events at 1037 and 1032 cm<SP>–1</SP> and two shoulders situated at 1042 and 1022 cm<SP>–1</SP> are evident (Fig. 5 (left), Table 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The corresponding Raman spectrum exhibits a strong band at 1039 cm<SP>–1</SP> and shoulders at 1045, 1032 and 1025 cm<SP>–1</SP> (Figs. 5 (right) and 6, Table 1).</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER><IT>δ</IT><SB>s</SB>(CF<SB>3</SB>) region</HEADER><P><s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the FT-IR spectra of the doped monourethanesils the <IT>δ</IT><SB>s</SB>(CF<SB>3</SB>) mode appears as a very weak to weak, ill-defined event (Fig. 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 7 (left) shows that the intensity maximum of this band is progressively shifted toward higher wavenumbers as more salt is incorporated into the m-Ut(750) matrix (about 754, 756 and 765 cm<SP>–1</SP> in the FT-IR spectra of the compounds with <IT>n</IT> = 400, 30 and 10, respectively).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The FT-Raman spectra illustrated in Fig. 2 allow us to conclude that in the <IT>δ</IT><SB>s</SB>(CF<SB>3</SB>) region the Eu<SP>3+</SP>-doped monourethanesils with 400 ≥ <IT>n</IT> ≥ 30 produce a sharp, weak to medium intensity feature, whose intensity maximum is displaced from approximately 755 cm<SP>–1</SP> in the most dilute material to 757 cm<SP>–1</SP> in the sample with <IT>n</IT> = 30.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the spectrum of the most concentrated sample this band becomes significantly broader and weaker and its intensity maximum appears at 761 cm<SP>–1</SP> (Fig. 2).</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, a shoulder located around 769 cm<SP>–1</SP> emerges (Fig. 7 (right)).</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">A closer consideration of this spectral range clearly suggests, however, that several components can be resolved in this region.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj9" novelty="New" advantage="None">A deeper investigation of the <IT>δ</IT><SB>s</SB>(CF<SB>3</SB>) feature will be performed in the following section.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>700–300 cm<SP>–1</SP> region</HEADER><P><s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">Between 700 and 500 cm<SP>–1</SP> the spectrum of the “free” triflate ion displays a band of the symmetric deformation vibration of the SO<SB>3</SB> group, <IT>δ</IT><SB>s</SB>(SO<SB>3</SB>), around 637 cm<SP>–1</SP> and a peak, originated from the asymmetric deformation vibration of the CF<SB>3</SB> group, <IT>δ</IT><SB>a</SB>(CF<SB>3</SB>), positioned at about 572 cm<SP>–1</SP>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">On coordination of the anion to metal cations, both features shift to higher wavenumbers.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9 cit14b cit19b">9,14<IT>b</IT>,19<IT>b</IT></REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the 500–300 cm<SP>–1</SP> envelope, a non-bonded CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB><SP>–</SP> ion produces two spectral bands around 346 and 308 cm<SP>–1</SP> ascribed to the rocking vibration of the SO<SB>3</SB> group, <IT>ρ</IT><SB>r</SB>(SO<SB>3</SB>), and to the symmetric stretching vibration of the CS group, <IT>ν</IT><SB>s</SB>(CS), respectively.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">These two modes are also upshifted upon coordination.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9 cit14b cit19b">9,14<IT>b</IT>,19<IT>b</IT></REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the FT-IR spectra of the monourethanesil compounds under investigation the <IT>δ</IT><SB>s</SB>(SO<SB>3</SB>) band is a sharp feature found at 639 cm<SP>–1</SP>, whose intensity progressively increases with the addition of lanthanide salt (Fig. 1, Table 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the FT-IR spectrum of m-Ut(750)<SB>10</SB>Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB> sample this mode becomes a very strong event (Fig. 1, Table 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None">A shoulder located near 644 cm<SP>–1</SP> is also detected in the FT-IR spectra of the monourethane xerogels in the whole range of salt concentration (Table 1).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">A comprehensive curve-fitting allowed us to conclude that the m-Ut(750)<SB><IT>n</IT></SB>Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB> hybrids with 400 ≥ <IT>n</IT> ≥ 30 produce in the FT-Raman spectra a very weak to weak band at about 573 cm<SP>–1</SP> with a shoulder situated around 582 cm<SP>–1</SP> (Table 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" advantage="None">The characteristic <IT>ρ</IT><SB>r</SB>(SO<SB>3</SB>) and <IT>ν</IT><SB>s</SB>(CS) bands are discerned in the same spectra near 347 and 314 cm<SP>–1</SP>, respectively (Fig. 2, Table 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None">Their intensity is enhanced with the incorporation of increasing amounts of the guest salt.</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, two shoulders are found at 353 and 321 cm<SP>–1</SP> (Table 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" advantage="None">At <IT>n</IT> = 30, two other shoulders located at approximately 631 and 570 cm<SP>–1</SP> appear in the FT-IR and FT-Raman spectra, respectively (Table 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Upon further addition of the guest salt (m-Ut(750)<SB>10</SB>Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB>) the former shoulder shifts to 627 cm<SP>–1</SP> and the latter one vanishes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs20" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition two new shoulders situated at 363 and 309 cm<SP>–1</SP> emerge in the FT-Raman spectrum (Table 1).</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2">Two-dimensional spectroscopic correlation analysis</HEADER><P><s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to investigate in depth the changes of the spectral intensities occurring in <IT>δ</IT><SB>s</SB>(CF<SB>3</SB>) and <IT>ν</IT><SB>s</SB>(SO<SB>3</SB>) frequency envelopes as a function of salt concentration, we performed a 2D Correlation FT-IR and Raman spectroscopic study on the set of materials with 400 ≥ <IT>n</IT> ≥ 30.</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj10" novelty="New" advantage="None">The sample with <IT>n</IT> = 10 was excluded from this analysis because its vibrational spectrum exhibits crucial transformations originating from drastic reconfiguration of the polymer matrix.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The main goal of 2D correlation vibrational spectroscopy is to detect dynamic variations of spectroscopic signals induced by an external perturbation, which in the present case was the incorporation of different amounts of Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In dynamic vibrational spectra, typical changes are variations of band intensity, frequency shifts of the bands and modifications in the shape of the peaks.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The detected spectral change is then transformed in 2D spectra by means of a specialized correlation method, such as the one described in the Experimental section.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">As a result of this transformation, one obtains two 2D correlation spectra generally called synchronous and asynchronous maps.</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Correlation peaks appearing in the synchronous and asynchronous maps represent in-phase and out-of-phase variation tendencies of corresponding band intensities, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">It should be also stressed that 2D correlation analysis is a powerful tool for the determination of the number of spectral components in strongly overlapped profiles.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj11" novelty="New" advantage="None">To elucidate the question about the local coordination of the CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB><SP>–</SP> ions, it was important to examine the spectral region characteristic of the <IT>δ</IT><SB>s</SB>(CF<SB>3</SB>) mode, which has been found to be extremely sensitive to the environmental changes around the anion.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10a cit10b cit10c cit10d cit10f cit10g cit10h cit10i cit10j cit10k cit10l cit10m cit10n cit10o cit10p cit10q cit10r">10<IT>a</IT>–<IT>d</IT>,10<IT>f</IT>–<IT>r</IT></REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs21" novelty="None" advantage="None">The synchronous 2D correlation Raman spectra obtained for the series of monourethane cross-linked xerogels with 200 ≥ <IT>n</IT> ≥ 30 in the 770–750 cm<SP>–1</SP> frequency region (Fig. 8 (top)) displays a single peak located on the diagonal of 2D correlation map with the coordinate of 761 cm<SP>–1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None">We must note that the peaks at diagonal positions, designated as <IT>autopeaks</IT>, develop in the spectral intervals which demonstrate stronger intensity change with the external perturbation.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res29" novelty="None" advantage="None">Consequently, the 2D correlation analysis indicates that, as salt content rises, the strongest intensity change appears around 761 cm<SP>–1</SP>, <IT>i.e.</IT>, at a characteristic frequency of coordinated triflate species.</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res30" novelty="None" advantage="None">This means that, as more Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB> is introduced into the m-Ut(750) matrix, the concentration of the triflate environment responsible for the 761 cm<SP>–1</SP> component increases in the xerogels.</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" advantage="None">The growth of this event is clearly evidenced in the Raman spectra of the m-Ut(750)<SB><IT>n</IT></SB>Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB> compounds with 200 ≥ <IT>n</IT> ≥ 30 (Fig. 7 (right)).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs22" novelty="None" advantage="None">The asynchronous 2D correlation map derived for the same set of monourethanesil samples in the same range of frequencies is given in Fig. 8 (bottom).</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is believed that cross peaks (<IT>i.e.</IT>, off-diagonal peaks) in asynchronous 2D spectra usually indicate the lack of strong chemical interactions or direct connectivity between the functional groups.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">They appear rather due to a difference in reorientational rates of transition moments of the functional groups which are located in different local molecular environments.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">By extending lines from the spectral coordinates of the cross peaks to the corresponding diagonal positions, one obtains the frequencies at which the maximum variation of spectral intensities is observed.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res32" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus the map shown in Fig. 8 (bottom) suggests that there are three distinct components located at 761, 757 and 753 cm<SP>–1</SP> in the <IT>δ</IT><SB>s</SB>(CF<SB>3</SB>) band envelope.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="New" advantage="None">Based on these results we carried out curve-fitting of the <IT>δ</IT><SB>s</SB>(CF<SB>3</SB>) envelope.</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs23" novelty="None" advantage="None">The <IT>δ</IT><SB>s</SB>(CF<SB>3</SB>) region of the monourethanesils with 400 ≥ <IT>n</IT> ≥ 30 was decomposed into three components centered at about 762, 757 and 753 cm<SP>–1</SP> (Fig. 9, Table 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res33" novelty="None" advantage="None">The band at lowest frequency is associated with “free” anions,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF> whereas the other two are due to coordinated CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB><SP>–</SP> ions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs24" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the spectrum of the sample with <IT>n</IT> = 10 two additional peaks are seen at 769 and 765 cm<SP>–1</SP> (Fig. 9, Table 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res34" novelty="None" advantage="None">The latter event is assigned to coordinated anions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res35" novelty="None" advantage="None">The 769 cm<SP>–1</SP> feature must be characteristic of the crystalline compound.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs25" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 10 shows the contour of the asynchronous 2D correlation map constructed from the salt concentration perturbed FT-IR spectra of the monourethanesils with 200 ≥ <IT>n</IT> ≥ 30 in the 1045–1020 cm<SP>–1</SP> region.</annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs26" novelty="None" advantage="None">This map exhibits four cross peaks, two of positive and two of negative intensity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res36" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hence, in the investigated <IT>ν</IT><SB>s</SB>(SO<SB>3</SB>) envelope three spectral components centered at 1036, 1032 and 1026 cm<SP>–1</SP> may be resolved (Fig. 10).</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res37" novelty="None" advantage="None">Similar conclusions were obtained through curve-fitting (Fig. 6, Table 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res38" novelty="None" advantage="None">The most intense peak, located at 1032 cm<SP>–1</SP>, is attributed to the ‘free’ triflate anions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res39" novelty="None" advantage="None">The pair of events at 1036 and 1026 cm<SP>–1</SP> may be associated with coordinated anions in two different ionic environments.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19b cit20a">19<IT>b</IT>,20<IT>a</IT></REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res40" novelty="None" advantage="None">It must be noted at this stage that the band observed in the 1045–1020 cm<SP>–1</SP> spectral interval may be fitted with a good accuracy by a single Lorentzian peak (especially at low salt contents).</annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In two Raman studies of ion association in complexes formed between POE or poly(oxypropylene) and triflate salts containing mono-, di- and trivalent cations, it was shown that the 1032 cm<SP>–1</SP> band, characteristic of the “free” triflate ion, always demonstrated Lorentzian shape regardless the type of cation.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18a cit18b">18<IT>a</IT>,<IT>b</IT></REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res41" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, it is essential to remark that, while in the Raman spectra reported in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18a cit18b">refs. 18<IT>a</IT> and <IT>b</IT></REF> the half-width of the 1032 cm<SP>–1</SP> feature was about 5.5 cm<SP>–1</SP> (with the highest value of 7 cm<SP>–1</SP> detected in a material doped with Nd<SP>3+</SP> ions), in the spectra of the xerogels investigated in the present work the fit by a single Lorentzian curve produces a peak with half-width of 9.5 cm<SP>–1</SP> for the low concentration samples, which further increases up to 11.5 cm<SP>–1</SP> as the guest salt content rises.</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Under such conditions it is clear that fitting by a single Lorentzian shape may hide the presence of side bands of lower intensity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="New" advantage="None">Therefore, in the selection of the fitting parameters we took into account the three following factors: (i) the unexplainably large half-width found when the band was fitted by a single Lorentzian profile; (ii) the high probability of existence of differently coordinated triflate species; (iii) the results derived from the 2D correlation analysis performed in this frequency envelope (Fig. 10).</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="None" advantage="Yes">Since we do not use the curve-fitting data for the determination of the total integral intensities, but just to estimate frequency positions of the components, we believe that the present analysis is reliable.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3">Triflate ion bonding configurations</HEADER><P><s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this section we will attempt to deduce, on the basis of specific spectral triflate features, the bonding configurations of the anions in the m-Ut(750)<SB>10</SB>Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB> family of xerogels to gain more insight into the general picture of ionic association in these hybrids.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs27" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the 400 ≥ <IT>n</IT> ≥ 50 composition range, the characteristic <IT>ν</IT><SB>a</SB>(SO<SB>3</SB>) envelope contains three bands located at about 1286, 1275 and 1263 cm<SP>–1</SP> (Figs. 3 and 4).</annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res42" novelty="None" advantage="None">The 1275 cm<SP>–1</SP> band is attributed to “free” CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB><SP>–</SP> ions,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit9">8,9</REF> whereas the origin of the two other components is not straightforward.</annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is known that a strong interaction between the SO<SB>3</SB> group and the cation, such as that involved in a contact ion pair, lifts the double degeneracy of the <IT>ν</IT><SB>a</SB>(SO<SB>3</SB>) mode, thus leading to the appearance of two split bands.</annotationART></s> <s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">According to the observations of Bernson <IT>et al.</IT>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20a cit20b">20<IT>a</IT>,<IT>b</IT></REF> the typical <IT>ν</IT><SB>a</SB>(SO<SB>3</SB>) splitting values for contact ion pairs in polymer electrolytes containing lanthanide triflates range from 95 to 110 cm<SP>–1</SP>, depending on the type of polymer matrix, type of cation used, and salt concentration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of solvent-separated ion pairs, in which the strength of cation–anion interaction becomes essentially lower, the magnitude of the splitting was found to be <IT>ca.</IT> 40 cm<SP>–1</SP>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20b">20<IT>b</IT></REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the monourethanesils with 400 ≥ <IT>n</IT> ≥ 50 the splittings observed are significantly smaller (about 25 cm<SP>–1</SP>), thus suggesting that the species responsible for this effect can be neither contact ion pairs, nor solvent separated ion pairs.</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fact that the three-component profile is also detected in the spectra of the monourethanesils with extremely low salt content (<IT>n</IT> = 400 and 200), in which the formation of contact ion pairs is practically impossible, is consistent with our claim.</annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">We propose that the remarkably small <IT>ν</IT><SB>a</SB>(SO<SB>3</SB>) splitting produced by the m-Ut(750)<SB><IT>n</IT></SB>Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB> samples with 400 ≥ <IT>n</IT> ≥ 50 is a direct consequence of the weakness of the interaction existent between the CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB><SP>–</SP> and the Eu<SP>3+</SP> ions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">We may further speculate that this coordinating situation could involve CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB><SP>–</SP> species weakly bonded to Eu<SP>3+</SP> ions, which simultaneously interact with the carbonyl oxygen atoms of the urethane groups (A).</annotationART></s> <s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, the existence of CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB><SP>–</SP> ions hydrogen-bonded to the N–H groups cannot be excluded (B). </annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs28" novelty="None" advantage="None">When the salt content reaches <IT>n</IT> = 30, the behavior of the monourethanesil system suffers marked modifications.</annotationART></s> <s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs28" novelty="None" advantage="None">As was shown in Part 1,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF> at this particular composition new effects are produced: (1) a fraction of the N–H groups start to be free from hydrogen bonding interaction with the CO groups; (2) the lanthanide ions start to coordinate to the POE chains.</annotationART></s> <s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs29" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 4 shows that in the <IT>ν</IT><SB>a</SB>(SO<SB>3</SB>) region of the FT-IR spectrum of m-Ut(750)<SB>30</SB>Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB>, along with the 1284/1262 cm<SP>–1</SP> pair and the 1274 cm<SP>–1</SP> feature, new split components, which can be recognized as the 1295/1251 and 1317/1213 cm<SP>–1</SP> pairs, emerge (Table 1).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Bands at 1295 and 1251 cm<SP>–1</SP> were also detected in the spectra of poly(ethylene glycol)/La(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB> electrolytes.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20b">20<IT>b</IT></REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">These events were ascribed to the split components resulting from the presence of solvent separated ion pairs.</annotationART></s> <s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the monourethane cross-linked hybrids such spectral effect might appear due to the presence of “cross-link separated” ion pairs.</annotationART></s> <s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The POE chains probably contribute to the formation of the latter ionic aggregates.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The 1317/1213 cm<SP>–1</SP> pair observed in the FT-IR spectrum of the xerogel with <IT>n</IT> = 30 can be associated with contact ion pairs, since similar bands were seen at approximately the same position in the spectra of POE<SB><IT>n</IT></SB>Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB> electrolytes with <IT>n</IT> = 16 and .9<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20a">20<IT>a</IT></REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res43" novelty="None" advantage="None">At the highest salt concentration examined here (<IT>n</IT> = 10), the growth of the bands corresponding to the second and third coordinating environments just described and the reduction of those due to the “free” and weakly coordinated triflate ions are evident.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the <IT>ν</IT><SB>s</SB>(CF<SB>3</SB>) region of all the monourethanesils studied the appearance of the 1224 and 1237 cm<SP>–1</SP> features corroborates the claim that “free”<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF> and coordinated triflate ions<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9 cit20a cit20b">9,20<IT>a</IT>,<IT>b</IT></REF> exist within the whole range of salt concentrations investigated (Figs. 1 and 4, Table 1).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The existence of non-coordinated anions in the materials with 400 ≥ <IT>n</IT> ≥ 30 is also supported by the location of the <IT>ν</IT><SB>a</SB>(CF<SB>3</SB>) mode which is seen at approximately 1156 cm<SP>–1</SP>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The bands found at 1186, 1178, 1170, 1164 and 1156 cm<SP>–1</SP> in the <IT>ν</IT><SB>a</SB>(CF<SB>3</SB>) envelope of the FT-IR spectrum of m-Ut(750)<SB>10</SB>Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB> (Table 1) confirm that non-bonded anions subsist at this composition and strongly suggest that the anion is involved in four different coordinating environments in this salt-rich xerogel, a result that is in perfect agreement with the conclusions retrieved from the <IT>ν</IT><SB>a</SB>(SO<SB>3</SB>) region.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The presence of “free” anions in the doped monourethanesils (a conclusion drawn from the examination of the <IT>ν</IT><SB>a</SB>(SO<SB>3</SB>), <IT>ν</IT><SB>s</SB>(CF<SB>3</SB>) and <IT>ν</IT><SB>a</SB>(CF<SB>3</SB>) regions) is further confirmed by the appearance of the 1032 cm<SP>–1</SP> band, characteristic of the <IT>ν</IT><SB>s</SB>(SO<SB>3</SB>) vibration of the “free” triflate ion (Figs. 1, 2 and 6, Table 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The occurrence of two components on both sides of the 1032 cm<SP>–1</SP> feature in the spectra of the hybrids with <IT>n</IT> &gt; 10 (Fig. 6, Table 1) corroborates the results of the <IT>ν</IT><SB>a</SB>(SO<SB>3</SB>) region, which indicated that two anionic bonding environments exist in this salt concentration interval (Figs. 1, 3 and 4, Table 1)</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="143"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res44" novelty="None" advantage="None">It must be stressed that in the sample with <IT>n</IT> = 10 the number of <IT>ν</IT><SB>s</SB>(SO<SB>3</SB>) components that represent distinct anionic sites (<IT>i.e.</IT>, three) is in apparent contradiction with the information obtained from the analysis of the <IT>ν</IT><SB>a</SB>(SO<SB>3</SB>) band envelope which indicated the existence of four different anionic configurations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="144"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">This effect can, however, be explained on the basis of the conclusions of Petersen <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18b">18<IT>b</IT></REF>. who showed that the <IT>ν</IT><SB>s</SB>(SO<SB>3</SB>) mode of solvent separated ions appears at 1032 cm<SP>–1</SP>, typically ascribed to “free” CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB><SP>–</SP> ions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="145"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, we are led to suggest that the 1032 cm<SP>–1</SP> component discerned in the spectrum of the rich-salt hybrid with <IT>n</IT> = 10 most probably receives contributions from, not only the “free” anions, as usual, but also from the “cross-link separated” ion pairs.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="146"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con16" novelty="None" advantage="None">As it is beyond the scope of the present work to characterize the ionic aggregates responsible for the multicomponent <IT>ν</IT><SB>s</SB>(SO<SB>3</SB>) band profile of the m-Ut(750)-based compounds, we will simply consider that the two shoulders observed in the <IT>ν</IT><SB>s</SB>(SO<SB>3</SB>) region of the samples with 400 ≥ <IT>n</IT> ≥ 30 are originated from weakly coordinated CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB><SP>–</SP> ions (Table 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="147"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The 1042 cm<SP>–1</SP> (FT-IR)/1045 cm<SP>–1</SP> (Raman) component of m-Ut(750)<SB>10</SB>Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB> is tentatively attributed to the formation of the crystalline compound (Fig. 6, Table 1).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="148"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Considering the complicated behavior of the <IT>ν</IT><SB>s</SB>(SO<SB>3</SB>) vibration, it was proposed that the mode of symmetric CF<SB>3</SB> deformation, <IT>δ</IT><SB>s</SB>(CF<SB>3</SB>), is a much more reliable way of identifying differently coordinated CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB><SP>–</SP> ions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10a cit10b cit10c cit10d cit10f cit10g cit10h cit10i cit10j cit10k cit10l cit10m cit10n cit10o cit10p cit10q cit10r">10<IT>a</IT>–<IT>d</IT>,<IT>f</IT>–<IT>r</IT></REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="149"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">According to Frech <IT>et al.</IT>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10a cit10b cit10c cit10d cit10f cit10g cit10h cit10i cit10j cit10k cit10l cit10m cit10n cit10o cit10p cit10q cit10r">10<IT>a</IT>–<IT>d</IT>,<IT>f</IT>–<IT>r</IT></REF> although the CF<SB>3</SB> end of the anion is not expected to participate directly in the coordination process, cation–anion interactions affect the whole anion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="150"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs30" novelty="None" advantage="None">The <IT>δ</IT><SB>s</SB>(CF<SB>3</SB>) vibration is seen at about 752 cm<SP>–1</SP> when the ion is “free”.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="151"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">As this mode is non-degenerate, specific bonding geometries result in shifts to higher wavenumbers.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="152"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res45" novelty="None" advantage="None">The interpretation of the <IT>δ</IT><SB>s</SB>(CF<SB>3</SB>) envelope of the Eu<SP>3+</SP>-doped monourethanesils is not straightforward.</annotationART></s> <s sid="153"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The only reference found in the literature regarding the <IT>δ</IT><SB>s</SB>(CF<SB>3</SB>) region of lanthanide triflate electrolytes<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20b">20<IT>b</IT></REF> reports the presence of a dominating band centered at 762 cm<SP>–1</SP> and a less intense peak at 754 cm<SP>–1</SP> in the spectra of La(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB> dissolved in poly(ethylene glycol) methyl ether.</annotationART></s> <s sid="154"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The two events were assigned to ion pairs and “free” anions, respectively.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20b">20<IT>b</IT></REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="155"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res46" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the present case, the complexity of the band contour clearly suggests that the number of underlying components is much greater.</annotationART></s> <s sid="156"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The examination of the <IT>δ</IT><SB>s</SB>(CF<SB>3</SB>) region of the most concentrated monourethanesil allowed us to conclude about the existence of four coordinating sites.</annotationART></s> <s sid="157"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res47" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of the less concentrated xerogels, the 2D correlation analysis clearly showed the presence of two coordinating environments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="158"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con19" novelty="None" advantage="None">This finding means that, according to our spectral data, in samples with <IT>n</IT> = 10 and <IT>n</IT> &gt; 10 the anionic configurations deduced from the study of the <IT>δ</IT><SB>s</SB>(CF<SB>3</SB>) mode (<IT>i.e.</IT>, four and two, respectively) are identical to those derived from the other triflate regions analyzed above.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="159"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con20" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the low-frequency region of the spectra of the m-Ut(750)<SB><IT>n</IT></SB>Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB> composites, unmistakable evidences of the existence of unpaired and coordinated CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB><SP>–</SP> ions are apparent in the whole range of salt concentration (Table 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="160"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con21" novelty="None" advantage="None">The new shoulders detected in the spectra of the samples with <IT>n</IT> = 30 and 10 are tentatively associated with the crystalline complex formed at this composition (Table 1).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="161"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj12" novelty="New" advantage="None">It is finally instructive to mention that in the course of this investigation we recorded the FT-IR spectra of the monourethanesils in the temperature range between 20 and 85 °C (data not shown).</annotationART></s> <s sid="162"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con22" novelty="None" advantage="None">The spectra of all the samples were found to be temperature independent, an indication that the existing cation and anion coordinating environments are quite stable.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Conclusions</HEADER><P><s sid="163"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj13" novelty="New" advantage="None">Monourethane cross-linked poly(oxyethylene)/siloxane hybrids incorporating a wide range of europium triflate, Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB>, concentration (∞ ≥ <IT>n</IT> ≥ 10, where <IT>n</IT> is the molar ratio of (OCH<SB>2</SB>CH<SB>2</SB>) repeat units per Eu<SP>3+</SP> ion) were investigated by means of Fourier transform mid-IR and Raman spectroscopies to study the cation–anion interactions.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="164"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj14" novelty="New" advantage="None">This spectroscopic analysis relied essentially on the examination of the most informative bands of the triflate ion (in particular, the <IT>ν</IT><SB>a</SB>(SO<SB>3</SB>), <IT>ν</IT><SB>s</SB>(SO<SB>3</SB>) and <IT>δ</IT><SB>s</SB>(CF<SB>3</SB>) modes) at increasing salt concentration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="165"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="New" advantage="None">Two-dimensional correlation spectroscopic analysis was employed in the case of the <IT>ν</IT><SB>s</SB>(SO<SB>3</SB>) and <IT>δ</IT><SB>s</SB>(CF<SB>3</SB>) features that exhibited strong overlapped profiles.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="166"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con23" novelty="None" advantage="None">This work showed that in the m-Ut(750)<SB><IT>n</IT></SB>Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB> xerogels with 400 ≥ <IT>n</IT> ≥ 50 the triflate ions exist only as “free” and weakly coordinated species (O(triflate)⋯Eu<SP>3+</SP>⋯OC(urethane) and/or O(triflate)⋯H–N(urethane)).</annotationART></s> <s sid="167"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res48" novelty="None" advantage="None">At <IT>n</IT> = 30, in addition to these coordinating situations, two new ionic configurations appear: contact ion pairs and “cross-link separated” ion pairs.</annotationART></s> <s sid="168"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con24" novelty="None" advantage="None">These two environments are a consequence of the major modification undergone by the system involving the reconfiguration of the POE chains and the destruction of the hydrogen bonds established between N–H groups and carbonyl moieties or POE chains.</annotationART></s> <s sid="169"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con25" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the most concentrated sample analyzed (<IT>n</IT> = 10) direct cation–anion coordination becomes dominating and the formation of a crystalline polymer/salt complex is observed.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Experimental</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Synthesis</HEADER><P><s sid="170"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">See Part 1<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Fourier transform IR spectroscopy</HEADER><P><s sid="171"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">See Part 1<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Fourier transform Raman spectroscopy</HEADER><P><s sid="172"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">See Part 1<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Two dimensional (2D) correlation spectroscopic analysis</HEADER><P><s sid="173"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="New" advantage="None">In 2D spectroscopy, the variations in the spectra produced by an external sample perturbation are mathematically cross-correlated to construct a 2D correlation map, which allows to discriminate those vibration modes which selectively respond to the perturbation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="174"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Two kinds of 2D spectra, defined by two independent wavenumbers (<IT><IT>ν</IT></IT><SB>1</SB>, <IT><IT>ν</IT></IT><SB>2</SB>), are generated by cross-correlation analysis of dynamic fluctuations of spectral signals induced by an external perturbation: the synchronous and asynchronous spectra.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="175"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">While the synchronous 2D correlation spectrum represents the simultaneous (or coincidental) changes of spectral intensities measured at <IT><IT>ν</IT></IT><SB>1</SB> and <IT><IT>ν</IT></IT><SB>2</SB> within the interval between <IT>T</IT><SB>min</SB> and <IT>T</IT><SB>max</SB> of the externally defined variable <IT>t</IT>, the asynchronous one represents sequential (or successive) changes of spectral intensities measured at <IT><IT>ν</IT></IT><SB>1</SB> and <IT><IT>ν</IT></IT><SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="176"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="New" advantage="None">In the present work 2D correlation spectroscopic analysis was carried out using the following procedure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="177"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="New" advantage="None">First, the reference spectrum was subtracted from each of the experimental spectra in order to obtain the dynamic spectra (mean-centered procedure.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF>)</annotationART></s> <s sid="178"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="New" advantage="None">For practical reasons, in our calculations the average spectrum was used as a reference.</annotationART></s> <s sid="179"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="New" advantage="None">The resulting mean-centered dynamic spectra <IT>y</IT>(<IT><IT>ν</IT></IT>,<IT>t</IT>) represent the relative variations of spectral intensity at each wavenumber <IT><IT>ν</IT></IT> as a function of the lanthanide salt concentration <IT>t</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="180"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met14" novelty="Old" advantage="None">We then calculated, for the set of dynamic spectra, the complex correlation function 〈<IT>y</IT>(<IT><IT>ν</IT></IT><SB>1</SB>,<IT>t</IT>),<IT>y</IT>(<IT><IT>ν</IT></IT><SB>2</SB>,<IT>t</IT>′)〉 = <IT>Φ</IT>(<IT><IT>ν</IT></IT><SB>1</SB>,<IT><IT>ν</IT></IT><SB>2</SB>) + i<IT>Ψ</IT>(<IT><IT>ν</IT></IT><SB>1</SB>,<IT><IT>ν</IT></IT><SB>2</SB>) using the Hilbert transform algorithm developed by Noda.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="181"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met14" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The real and imaginary parts of this function correspond to the synchronous <IT>Φ</IT>(<IT><IT>ν</IT></IT><SB>1</SB>,<IT><IT>ν</IT></IT><SB>2</SB>) and asynchronous <IT>Ψ</IT>(<IT><IT>ν</IT></IT><SB>1</SB>,<IT><IT>ν</IT></IT><SB>2</SB>) 2D correlation maps of the dynamic spectra, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="182"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met15" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The synchronous 2D correlation intensities were defined by the equation and the asynchronous 2D spectra were determined using the expression where the <IT>H</IT><SB><IT>jk</IT></SB> is a Hilbert transformation matrix.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="183"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met15" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Here <IT>ν</IT> represents the IR or Raman wavenumber and <IT>n</IT> is the total number of dynamic spectra.</annotationART></s> <s sid="184"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">All the calculations were performed with the Matlab 6.0 software (The MathWorks Inc)..</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
