<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b309964d" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">The HOOH–HOO complex. A matrix isolation study</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The peroxy radical forms a cyclic complex with hydrogen peroxide, with both entities acting as hydrogen bond donors and as hydrogen bond acceptors.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The strength of the complex is very similar to that of the hydrogen peroxide dimer.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The peroxy radical participates in numerous oxidation reactions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Its interactions with stable molecules influences the stabilization of newly formed hot radicals and it may influence its reactivity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">We have used matrix isolation combined with infrared spectroscopy to study its interactions with small, stable molecules.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2 cit3 cit4 cit5 cit6">2–6</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In these experiments, we have observed weak bands, which we suspected to be due to a hydrogen peroxide peroxy radical complex, since hydrogen peroxide, which forms from the reaction between two peroxy radicals, is always present in our experiments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The addition of extra hydrogen peroxide to matrices containing peroxy radicals confirmed our suspicions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, a more complete assignment of the spectrum of the complex required studies of the hydrogen peroxide dimer <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF> and of the water hydrogen peroxide complex,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF> since water is another byproduct of the peroxy radical synthesis.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both hydrogen peroxide and the peroxy radical act as hydrogen bond donors<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2 cit9 cit10">2,9,10</REF> and as hydrogen bond acceptors,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2 cit11">2,11</REF> and both form cyclic complexes whenever possible.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">It therefore seems reasonable to expect their complex to have a cyclic structure, essentially the structure of the hydrogen peroxide dimer,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF> minus one of the two nonbonded hydrogens.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our spectra give clear evidence for this structure, we observe two strongly red shifted OH stretches and two strongly blue shifted HOO bends one from each complex component.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">A very recent calculation appears to support this structure.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">During the study of the HOOH–HOO complex, we noted that the positions of some of its bands were sensitive to the concentration of dopants in the matrix, shifting several wavenumbers between different experiments.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Experimental</HEADER><P><s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The experimental procedure has been described in earlier publications.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2 cit8 cit8">2,7,8</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">A brief description is given below.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Two separate deposition lines were used.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Their gas flows were regulated by Nupro needle valves.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In one volume argon (L′Air Liquide 99.9995%) was mixed with O<SB>2</SB> (L’Air Liquide, 999 995%).</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Ar/O<SB>2</SB> ratio was varied between 50/1 and 75/1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">This gas mixture was then swept over the urea–hydrogen peroxide adduct kept a fixed temperature as described by Pettersson <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The temperature of the adduct was +16 °C in most experiments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Deuterated hydrogen peroxide was prepared as described in .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">ref. 13</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="New" advantage="None">In a second volume argon was mixed with H<SB>2</SB>(AGA) or D<SB>2</SB> (L’Air liquide).</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Ar/hydrogen mixture was passed through a microwave discharge.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The gas mixtures were deposited on a CsI-window, cooled to 17 K by a Leybold RDK 10–320 closed cycle cryocooler.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Peroxy radicals formed on the surface of the growing matrix by the addition of hydrogen (deuterium) atoms from the discharge to molecular oxygen.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The deposition time was 2 h and the deposition rate 10 mmol h<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Infrared spectra were recorded, at 17 K, between 185 and 4000 cm<SP>−l</SP> with a Bruker 113 v spectrometer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">A resolution of 0.5 cm<SP>−1</SP> and an average of 512 scans was used in the mid-infrared while in the far infrared it was sufficient to use a resolution of 1 cm<SP>−1</SP> and 128 scans.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">An MCT detector was used in the mid-infrared and a liquid helium cooled Ge-bolometer in the far infrared.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp9" novelty="None" advantage="None">After the initial spectra had been recorded the matrix was irradiated with 266 nm radiation from a quadrupled Continuum NY 20 C YAG laser, and new spectra were recorded.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Assignment</HEADER><P><s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In complexes of the type studied here, the intramolecular vibrations of the complex components retain their original character in the complex.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, the perturbed <IT>i</IT>th fundamental of A in a complex with B will be denoted as <IT>ν</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB>(A–B).</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to indicate which hydrogens are engaged in the formation of the hydrogen bonds we write the complex with these hydrogens next to each other, for instance DOOH–HOO and OOH–HOOD denotes a complex where HOOD is H-bonded to HOO.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="New" advantage="None">It is possible to control the HOOH concentration in the matrices by changing the temperature of the urea complex.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is rather difficult to control the concentrations of HOOD and DOOD, since different preparations give different degrees of deuteration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is also hard to vary the peroxy radical concentration in a systematic way, since the efficiency of the microwave discharge, which produces the hydrogen atoms, varies between different experiments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Experiments with hydrogen through the discharge contain only HOO radicals and experiments with deuterium through the discharge contain DOO and only traces of HOO.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Bands are assigned to the hydrogen peroxide peroxy radical complex, if they appear only when hydrogen peroxide and peroxy radicals are simultaneously present in the matrix, if they have constant intensity ratios directly after deposition, independent of the concentrations of hydrogen peroxide and peroxy radicals, and if they decrease at the same rate when the matrix is irradiated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">It should be noted that the strongest bands which we assign to a hydrogen peroxide peroxy radical complex are too strong to be due to 1∶2 (2∶1) complex.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Two OH stretches at 3432 cm<SP>−1</SP> and 3206 cm<SP>−1</SP> have been observed as two weak bands in many previous experiments with peroxy radicals, see for instance Fig. 2 of .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">Ref. 2</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">When hydrogen peroxide is added to the matrix, they grow strongly as expected if they are due to a hydrogen peroxide peroxy radical complex (Fig. 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">When DOO is used instead of HOO, the 3432 band shifts to 3429 cm<SP>−1</SP>, the 3206 cm<SP>−1</SP> band disappears, and a new band appears in the OD stretching region at 2383 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">It therefore seems clear that the 3206 cm<SP>−1</SP> band is due to the OH stretch of HOO complexed to hydrogen peroxide.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The complex shift, −207 cm<SP>−1</SP>, is slightly larger than the corresponding shift of the peroxy radical water complex, −177 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Experiments with partially deuterated hydrogen peroxide show that the 3432 cm<SP>−1</SP> band is due to HOOH.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The corresponding band of DOOD complexed to HOO is found at 2536 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Also for the HOOH (DOOD) band the complex shift is relatively large, −156 cm<SP>−1</SP> (−110.0 cm<SP>−1</SP>), giving clear evidence for a hydrogen bond from hydrogen peroxide to the peroxy radical.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">At the same time as the 3432 cm<SP>−1</SP> and 3206 cm<SP>−1</SP> bands appear, bands are observed at 1428 cm<SP>−1</SP>, 1487 cm<SP>−1</SP> and 1496 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Deuteration experiments show that the 1428 cm<SP>−1</SP> band is due to HOOH and the 1487 cm<SP>−1</SP>, 1497 cm<SP>−1</SP> doublet is due to HOO.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both bands are strongly blue shifted from the HOO bends of hydrogen peroxide and the peroxy radical as expected for a cyclic, hydrogen bonded complex.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The OO stretch of the complexed peroxy radical is observed at 1121 cm<SP>−1</SP>, very close to the corresponding band of the peroxy radical water complex (1120 cm<SP>−1</SP>, <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">ref. 2</REF>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The non hydrogen bonded OH stretch of hydrogen peroxide is observed at 3574 cm<SP>−1</SP> and the corresponding HOO bend at 1284 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">A weak band at 868 cm<SP>−1</SP> is assigned to the OO stretch of complexed HOOH.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The corresponding bands of HOOH–DOO have been observed in experiments where D<SB>2</SB> was passed through the microwave discharge instead of H<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Experiments with partially deuterated hydrogen peroxide have made it possible to observe some of the intramolecular fundamentals of the D<SB>2</SB>O<SB>2</SB> and HDO<SB>2</SB> complexes with HOO (Table 1) and DOO (Table 2).</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The bands observed give clear evidence that both HOOD–DOO and DOOH–DOO exist.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition to the intramolecular fundamental bands, we observe a number of relatively weak bands which fulfill our criteria for assignment to the peroxy radical hydrogen peroxide complex.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The strongest of these, at 2926 cm<SP>−1</SP>, is probably due to the overtone of the HOO bend of complexed HOO.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The assignment of the mid-infrared spectrum is collected in Tables 1, 2 and 3.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have observed a number of intermolecular bands of the hydrogen peroxide complex (Fig. 2).</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The two bands with highest frequencies are observed in the region where the bolometer spectra and the MCT spectra overlap.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results in this region are in very good agreement.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Compared to mid-infrared bands of matrix isolated molecules, bands in the far infrared tend to be weaker and broader.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">One is closer to the phonon band in the far infrared, this makes relaxation a low order process and therefore decreases lifetimes of excited states.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Intermolecular vibrations, which are found in this region, involve the motions of the complex forming molecules as rigid entities which tends to make the coupling to the matrix stronger than in the mid-infrared where the vibrations tend to be localized in one of the complex forming molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is more difficult to obtain precisely matched sample and background spectra in the far infrared, where the wavelengths are comparable to for instance the matrix thickness.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The original spectra contain interference fringes from different optical elements.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Ideally these should cancel in the ratio between sample and background spectra.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Unfortunately even minute changes in for instance the cryostat position are sufficient to obliterate the cancellation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">This makes it harder to observe weak bands.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both hydrogen peroxide monomer and dimer have clear and strong far infrared bands, which partially obscure the bands of the peroxy radical hydrogen peroxide complex.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">The assignment is significantly aided by the fact that the hydrogen peroxide peroxy radical complex decomposes very rapidly when irradiated with 266 nm radiation, significantly faster than the hydrogen peroxide dimer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">The hydrogen peroxide monomer is hardly touched during the time it takes to eliminate the peroxy radical complex.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">The irradiation has the additional advantage that the base line is almost unchanged by the irradiation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">The assignment of the far infrared spectrum is collected in Table 4.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Discussion</HEADER><P><s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The appearance of two strongly red shifted OH stretches from the peroxy radical hydrogen peroxide complex clearly suggest that the complex is cyclic, with both components acting as hydrogen bond donors and as hydrogen bond acceptors (Fig. 3).</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" advantage="None">This conclusion is supported by the observation of two strongly blue shifted HOO bends, one from each component.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In fact the HOOH part of the mid-infrared spectrum of the HOOH peroxy radical complex is quite similar to the spectrum of HOOH in a dimer formed between HOOH and DOOD where there are no resonant interactions between the dimer components.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The shift of the bound OH stretch of HOOH is 25 cm<SP>−1</SP> more negative in the peroxy radical complex than in the DOOD complex, indicating that the peroxy radical is a better hydrogen bond acceptor than hydrogen peroxide.</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the HOO bends of HOOH, the shifts are larger in the HOOH–DOOD dimer than in the peroxy radical complex.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The high frequency bend is found at 1436 cm<SP>−1</SP> in the HOOH–DOOD dimer and at 1428 cm<SP>−1</SP> in the complex and the low frequency bend appears at 1291 cm<SP>−1</SP> in the dimer and at 1283 cm<SP>−1</SP> in the complex.</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None">For both bends, the complex shifts are smaller for the peroxy radical complex than for the mixed dimer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to understand this apparent discrepancy between the stretch shift and the bend shifts we note that the two OH stretches of hydrogen peroxide are almost independent, in HOOD the OH stretch almost coincides with the two OH stretches of HOOH.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res29" novelty="None" advantage="None">The two HOO bends are strongly coupled, in HOOD the HOO bend is found at 1343 cm<SP>−1</SP>, approximately midway between the two HOO bends of HOOH (1385 cm<SP>−1</SP> and 1271 cm<SP>−1</SP>) and the DOO bend is found at 981 cm<SP>−1</SP> close to the average of the two DOOD bends.</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The coupling between the bends depends on the dihedral angle between the HOO groups which may differ between the complex and the dimer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition the 1428 cm<SP>−1</SP> band is likely to be lowered somewhat by an interaction with the HOO radical bend at 1487 cm<SP>−1</SP> and 1496 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None"><IT>Ab initio</IT> calculations on the hydrogen peroxide dimer suggest that we should expect three intermolecular fundamentals above 200 cm<SP>−1</SP> for the HOOH–HOO complex, librations of the two complex components around their OO axis and the torsion of hydrogen peroxide.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The same calculations indicate that we should observe two torsion bands for the HOOH monomer since the trans barrier is low, and indeed we observe two bands for monomer HOOH, close to the expected positions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None">It seems reasonable to assume that the trans barrier of hydrogen peroxide complexed with a peroxy radical is relatively low so that there are two close low lying torsion states, a symmetric and an antisymmetric combination of the complexes with the free hydrogen of hydrogen peroxide above and below the plane of the other atoms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None">If the barrier is not too different for complexed HOOH compared to monomer HOOH, the next two torsion states are close to the maximum of the trans barrier and therefore strongly split.</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">We observe four far infrared bands for HOOH–HOO (Fig. 2).</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res30" novelty="None" advantage="None">The lowest band, at 227 cm<SP>−1</SP>, is close to a band at 219 cm<SP>−1</SP> of the hydrogen peroxide dimer, which we believe is due to the libration of HOOH in the dimer.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" advantage="None">We suggest that the 227 cm<SP>−1</SP> band of HOOH–HOO should be assigned to the libration of HOOH around its OO axis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The band at 557 cm<SP>−1</SP> appears to shift to slightly above 400 cm<SP>−1</SP> when DOO is substituted for HOO.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res32" novelty="None" advantage="None">The precise position depends on the isotopic composition of the complex partner.</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res33" novelty="None" advantage="None">We therefore assign the 557 cm<SP>−1</SP> band to the libration of complexed HOO around its OO bond.</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res34" novelty="None" advantage="None">This assignment implies that the 277 cm<SP>−1</SP> band and the 477 cm<SP>−1</SP> band are due to the HOOH torsion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">In HOOH monomer the corresponding bands are observed at 273.2 cm<SP>−1</SP> and at 373.5 cm<SP>−1</SP> respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The shifts are surprisingly different, but we do not think this automatically shows that the assignment is wrong.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the monomer calculation, the two lowest states were split by 10 cm<SP>−1</SP> and were approximately 300 cm<SP>−1</SP> below the trans barrier, the third lowest state was very close to the barrier and the next state approximately 100 cm<SP>−1</SP> above the barrier.</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None">If the barrier is lowered in the complex, the two upper states will be even further away from two interacting tunnel states than in the monomer and therefore even further apart than in the monomer.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con15" novelty="None" advantage="None">If we accept the assignment of the intermolecular fundamentals of HOOH–HOO, the assignment of the corresponding fundamentals of the HOOH–DOO complex is straight forward.</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res35" novelty="None" advantage="None">The bands at 485 cm<SP>−1</SP> and 272 cm<SP>−1</SP> are assigned to the torsion of HOOH and the 220 cm<SP>−1</SP> band to the libration of HOOH, the libration of DOO is observed at 415 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">We have made a number of experiments with partially deuterated hydrogen peroxide, both with HOO and DOO.</annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res36" novelty="None" advantage="None">In these experiments we observe a number of far infrared bands whose photolysis rates clearly shows that they are due to hydrogen peroxide peroxy radical complexes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res37" novelty="None" advantage="None">We found it difficult to control the H/D ratio sufficiently well to make it possible to avoid the presence of significant concentrations of HOOD in these experiments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res38" novelty="None" advantage="None">This makes the assignment very difficult, since the mid-infrared spectra indicate that there are two different isomers of the HOOD peroxy radical complex.</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con16" novelty="None" advantage="None">One therefore expects to find 12 bands due to the DOOD and HOOD peroxy radical complexes in a given experiment.</annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have tried to assign the observed bands guided by the results for HOOH and the assumption that the torsion frequencies are mainly determined by the mass of the free hydrogen of the complexed hydrogen peroxide.</annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res39" novelty="None" advantage="None">The assignment is collected in Table 4.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Two cyclic structures are found to represent local minima on the potential energy surface of HOOH–HOO in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">ref. 12</REF>, both at the B3LYP and QCISD levels of theory.</annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The hydrogen peroxide forms a hydrogen bond to the end oxygen of the peroxy radical in both structures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The most stable structure is a six-membered ring where the peroxy radical forms a hydrogen bond to the hydrogen peroxide oxygen, which binds the free hydrogen.</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The second minimum is a five-membered ring with a hydrogen bond from the peroxy radical to the hydrogen peroxide oxygen, which is bound to the hydrogen of the hydrogen bond.</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="New" advantage="None">It is interesting to compare the experimental complex shifts of HOOH–HOO with the calculated shifts of <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">ref. 12</REF> (Table 5).</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res40" novelty="None" advantage="None">The B3LYP calculations give very large shifts for the OH stretches of hydrogen peroxide and the peroxy radical for the six-membered ring structure, 1.4 and 1.8 times larger than the observed shifts respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res41" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the five membered ring structure the OH shift of the hydrogen peroxide is 0.50 of the observed shift and the OH shift of the peroxy radical is 1.5 times the observed shift.</annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res42" novelty="None" advantage="None">The calculated OO shifts of the peroxy radical are approximately 10 times larger than the observed shift for both structures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con17" novelty="None" advantage="None">We are therefore convinced that the B3LYP method gives a rather poor description of the complex.</annotationART></s> <s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res43" novelty="None" advantage="None">The complex shifts of the QCISD calculations are in reasonable agreement with the observations, the OH shifts of the OH bonds involved in the hydrogen bonds are somewhat smaller the the observed shifts but the general pattern of the shifts agrees well with the observations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res44" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is more difficult to choose between the two structures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res45" novelty="None" advantage="None">The largest difference in the calculated shifts is obtained for the HOOH torsion, which is calculated to be blue shifted in the five membered ring complex and red shifted in the six-membered ring complex.</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res46" novelty="None" advantage="None">Unfortunately it is impossible to compare the calculated torsions with the experimental torsion since the low trans barrier of the complex allows rapid tunneling in the torsionally excited state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con18" novelty="None" advantage="None">This makes the harmonic oscillator approximation used in the calculations completely unrealistic.</annotationART></s> <s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res47" novelty="None" advantage="None">The calculated bound OH shifts of the six-membered ring complex are both significantly closer to the observed shifts.</annotationART></s> <s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res48" novelty="None" advantage="None">Also most other calculated shifts of the six-membered ring are closer to the experimentally observed shifts that those of the five membered ring (Table 5).</annotationART></s> <s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Experiences from many other systems suggests that with few exceptions, only the most stable complex structure is observed, this seems to be the case also for the HOOH–HOO complex.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res49" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is difficult to compare the calculated intermolecular vibrations with the experimentally observed far infrared bands, since no description of the calculated bands is given in the paper and the calculations are done only for the HOOH–HOO isotopologue.</annotationART></s> <s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con20" novelty="None" advantage="None">It seems reasonable to assume that the highest calculated intermolecular fundamental at 647.6 cm<SP>−1</SP>(only the QCSID values for the six-membered ring complex are considered) corresponds to the observed HOO libration at 557 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res50" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both calculations and experiment agree that this is an intense band.</annotationART></s> <s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res51" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have difficulties in understanding the nature of the second largest calculated intermolecular fundamental at 544.6 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The librations of the two complex components involve only H-motions and are therefore expected to have high frequencies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The remaining intermolecular fundamentals will involve oxygen atom motions and have much lower frequencies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res52" novelty="None" advantage="None">The hydrogen bond from the peroxy radical to hydrogen peroxide is calculated to be stronger than the hydrogen bond from hydrogen peroxide to the peroxy radical.</annotationART></s> <s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res53" novelty="None" advantage="None">The hydrogen peroxide libration is therefore expected to be less than 0.7 of the peroxy radical libration, the calculated frequency is 100 cm<SP>−1</SP> larger than one expects from this argument.</annotationART></s> <s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con21" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is perhaps possible that the coupling between the hydrogen peroxide libration and the hydrogen peroxide torsion is very strong, giving one upper and one lower component both with significant torsion and libration contents.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res54" novelty="None" advantage="None">The hydrogen peroxide peroxy radical complex is clearly more strongly bound than the hydrogen peroxide dimer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The shift of the bound OH stretch of HOOH is −132 cm<SP>−1</SP> in the dimer and −156 cm<SP>−1</SP> in the peroxy radical complex.</annotationART></s> <s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res55" novelty="None" advantage="None">The complex shift of the OH stretch of the peroxy radical is −207 cm<SP>−1</SP> suggesting that the hydrogen bond from the peroxy radical to hydrogen peroxide is stronger than the hydrogen bond from hydrogen peroxide to the radical.</annotationART></s> <s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the hydrogen peroxide dimer the dissociation energy (<IT>D</IT><SB>e</SB>) was calculated to be 6.3 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> on the MP2 level.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="143"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con22" novelty="None" advantage="None">We believe that the the dissociation energy of the peroxy radical hydrogen peroxide complex is of the order of 6.5 to 7 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>, the calculations of <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">ref. 12</REF> gave 7.7 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> (<IT>D</IT><SB>e</SB>, corrected for BSSE).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="144"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res56" novelty="None" advantage="None">The shifts of several wavenumbers of some complex bands between different experiments is very surprising (Fig. 4).</annotationART></s> <s sid="145"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res57" novelty="None" advantage="None">Even more surprising is that the hydrogen peroxide dimer bands, which have very stable positions in experiments where only hydrogen peroxide is present in the matrix<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF> show shifts in these experiments, these shifts correlate with the shifts of the hydrogen peroxide peroxy radical complex bands.</annotationART></s> <s sid="146"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con23" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have previously noted a phenomenon, which we believe is related to the one observed here.</annotationART></s> <s sid="147"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the hydrogen peroxide monomer spectrum, in matrices with a low content of polar impurities, the OH stretch and the antisymmetric HOO bend have two relatively sharp components.</annotationART></s> <s sid="148"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None">When polar impurities are present, bands appear approximately midway between the two low concentration components.</annotationART></s> <s sid="149"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The low concentration components weaken and ultimately vanish at high impurity concentrations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="150"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">We suggested in an earlier publication that polar impurities introduced electric fields in the matrix, which strongly perturbed the hydrogen peroxide inversion.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="151"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The two components of the monomer bands are due to the inversion.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="152"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the dipole moment of hydrogen peroxide changes its direction upon inversion, the presence of an electric field may stabilize one of the two torsion minima and destabilize the other.</annotationART></s> <s sid="153"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con24" novelty="None" advantage="None">A similar mechanism is possible for the hydrogen peroxide peroxy radical complex, which should have a large dipole moment whose direction is determined by the orientation of the non hydrogen bonded hydrogen of hydrogen peroxide.</annotationART></s> <s sid="154"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con24" novelty="None" advantage="None">The electric field from a peroxy radical within 10 Å from a complex may inhibit the tunneling of the non bonded hydrogen and perhaps also shift its equilibrium dihedral angle, which in turn will influence the fundamentals directly involved in the hydrogen bond system of the complex.</annotationART></s> <s sid="155"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The equilibrium structure of the hydrogen peroxide dimer has <IT>C</IT><SB>i</SB> symmetry and consequently no dipole moment.</annotationART></s> <s sid="156"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res58" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the <IT>C</IT><SB>2</SB> symmetric isomer, which has the two non hydrogen bonded hydrogens on the same side of the plane of the heavy atoms has a relatively large dipole moment and is expected from <IT>ab initio</IT> SCF calculations to be approximately 50 cm<SP>−1</SP> higher in energy than the C<SB>i</SB> isomer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="157"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con25" novelty="None" advantage="None">A strong electric field may stabilize the <IT>C</IT><SB>2</SB> isomer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="158"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con26" novelty="None" advantage="None">More likely is that a polar molecule not too far from one of the non-hydrogen-bonded hydrogens of the <IT>C</IT><SB>i</SB> dimer inhibits the inversion of the dimer.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
