<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b312189e" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Observation and characterisation of the glycocalyx of viable human endothelial cells using confocal laser scanning microscopy<XREF TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" /></annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This paper describes the use of confocal laser scanning microscopy (CLSM) to observe and characterise the fully hydrated glycocalyx of human umbilical vein endothelial cells (HUVECs).</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Viable HUVECs in primary culture were studied at room temperature in HEPES-buffered, phenol red- and serum-free CS-C cell culture medium.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">A fluorescein isothiocyanate-linked wheat germ agglutinin (WGA-FITC) (2 μg ml<SP>−1</SP>, 30 min) was used to detect <IT>N</IT>-acetylneuraminic (sialic) acid, which is a significant component of the endothelial glycocalyx.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Single confocal sections, less than 1.3 μm thick, were collected at intervals of 0.5 μm, scanning through the entire <IT>z</IT>-axis of a series of cells.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Cell-surface associated staining was observed, which enabled the glycocalyx thickness to be deduced as 2.5 ± 0.5 μm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This dimension is significantly greater than that measured by electron microscopy, for glutaraldehyde-fixed cells (0.10 ± 0.04 μm).</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The specificity of WGA-FITC staining was demonstrated by treatments with several enzymes, known to degrade glycocalyx (heparatinase, chondroitinase, hyaluronidase and neuraminidase), of which neuraminidase (1 U ml<SP>−1</SP>, 30–60 min) was the most effective, removing up to 78 ± 2% of WGA-FITC binding to HUVECs.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Cell viability was assessed simultaneously with ethidium homodimer-1 staining and confirmed by standard colorimetric 3-[4,5]dimethylthiazol-2,5diphenyltetrazolium bromide (MTT) test.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">CLSM thus provides a useful approach for <IT>in situ</IT> visualisation and characterisation of the endothelial glycocalyx in viable preparations, revealing a thickness that is an order of magnitude greater than found in <IT>ex situ</IT> measurements on fixed cells.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="1.">Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">A single layer of endothelial cells forms a critical barrier between the blood and the interstitial fluid of most organs.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The luminal surface of the endothelium is exposed directly to the blood and is covered by an elaborate carbohydrate-containing, polyanionic surface coat called the glycocalyx.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">It includes plasmalemmal components such as the glycosylated ectodomains of integral membrane proteins, proteoglycans and glycolipids, as well as adsorbed plasma proteins such as albumin.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Many important normal and pathological vascular functions, such as capillary permeability,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">2</REF> receptor-mediated transcytosis,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF> transendothelial cell migration,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF> thrombosis,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF> inflammation,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF> blood coagulation,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF> oxygen transport<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF> and sensing of wall shear stress,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF> are dependent on interactions occurring at the level of the glycocalyx.</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Albumin, located within the luminal glycocalyx, has been shown to increase the anionic charge and volume exclusion of the glycocalyx, resulting in increased steric and electrostatic exclusion forces that reduce vascular permeability.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Several studies have used electron microscopy to demonstrate the presence of the glycocalyx in the microcirculation.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10 cit11 cit12">10–12</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="No">Conventional electron microscopy requires that cell specimens be dehydrated during the fixation procedure so that the total volume of extracellular material is significantly reduced or collapsed and compressed, leading to the distortion of the glycocalyx architecture.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">To eliminate this problem, we have chosen to develop methodology centred on confocal laser scanning microscopy (CLSM) to study the hydrated glycocalyx of viable, cultured endothelial cells derived from human umbilical vein.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">CLSM is a well established physical method for collecting three-dimensional images of cellular structures of living cells without destroying important functional features of studied specimens.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13 cit14">13,14</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, there are no reports on <IT>in situ</IT> observation of living endothelial glycocalyx with CLSM.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The glycocalyx layer has been visualised by lectin binding to living cells.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="New" advantage="None">We used a fluorescein isothiocyanate-linked wheat germ agglutinin (WGA-FITC), which binds selectively to <IT>N</IT>-acetyl-d-glucosaminyl residues, a constituent of heparan sulfate, the major saccharide of cell surface proteoglycans<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF> and to <IT>N</IT>-acetylneuraminic (sialyl) residues, making a significant contribution to the surface charge and representing a major component of the endothelial glycocalyx.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="New" advantage="None">Stringent concurrent screening for viability of the cells was undertaken for all experimental conditions used.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The CLSM analysis provided evidence of the extensive expression of the glycocalyx in cultured macrovascular endothelial cells in physiologically relevant conditions.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.">Materials and methods</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.1">Materials</HEADER><P><s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Unless stated otherwise, materials were obtained from Sigma Chemicals (Poole, UK).</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.2">Methods</HEADER><P><s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Human umbilical cords were obtained with full ethical approval within 12 h of birth from normal pregnancies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Human umbilical vein endothelial cells (HUVECs) were isolated by collagenase (0.3 mg ml<SP>−1</SP>) digestion<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF> and cultured in 35 mm diameter Petri dishes in medium 199 (M199) containing 20% fetal bovine serum, 0.05 mg ml<SP>−1</SP> gentamycin, 20 μg ml<SP>−1</SP> endothelial growth factor supplement and 90 μg ml<SP>−1</SP> heparin at 37 °C in 5% CO<SB>2</SB>/air.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The identity of endothelial cells in culture was confirmed by the presence of typical “cobblestone” monolayer morphology (shown by the phase contrast image, Fig. 1) as well as by the expression of von Willebrand factor, VCAM, and angiotensin converting enzyme (ACE), as determined by immunocytochemical staining and Western blotting.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">After 3 days in primary culture, at 70–80% confluency, the cells were washed twice with phosphate buffered saline (PBS), and WGA-FITC (2 μg ml<SP>−1</SP>), prepared in HEPES-buffered, phenol red- and serum-free CS-C (Sigma, C 1556) cell culture medium, was applied for 30–40 min.</annotationART></s></P><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.2.1">Confocal laser scanning microscopy</HEADER><P><s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Lectin binding (as WGA-FITC binding) was observed with a confocal laser scanning microscope (LSM 510, Axioplan 2, Carl Zeiss, Jena, Germany).</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp9" novelty="None" advantage="None">All CLSM images (1024 × 1024 pixels, 12 bit pixel depth) were acquired using a water immersion objective lens (Zeiss, Achroplan 63x/0.95NA W) with a 10× tube lens.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp10" novelty="None" advantage="None">To observe WGA-FITC binding, an argon laser (<IT>λ</IT> = 488 nm) was used in conjunction with a long-pass filter (<IT>λ</IT> = 505 nm).</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp11" novelty="None" advantage="None">For transmission images a HeNe laser was used (<IT>λ</IT> = 543 nm).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp12" novelty="None" advantage="None">For simultaneous assessment of cell viability, WGA-FITC and ethidium homodimer-1 were excited using Ar laser lines at <IT>λ</IT> = 488 and 514 nm, respectively, and fluorescence emission was measured with filter sets, band-pass <IT>λ</IT> = 505–550 nm and long-pass <IT>λ</IT> = 560 nm, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="New" advantage="None">Black level (background offset) was adjusted to eliminate autofluorescence from unstained cells.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp13" novelty="None" advantage="None">To achieve the optimum compromise between resolution and image intensity, the confocal aperture was set to give an optical slice of &lt;1.3μm (data from Zeiss).</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Under these conditions lateral resolution was sub-micron and axial resolution was ±0.65 μm.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Images were processed using the LSM Image Browser software (Zeiss).</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Average pixel intensities were calculated over the area corresponding to single cells (typically equivalent to 10–40 000 square pixels) using Scion Image software (Scion Corporation, USA).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp16" novelty="None" advantage="None">To discriminate between binding of WGA to sialic acid residues and binding to <IT>N</IT>-acetyl-d-glucosaminyl residues, a range of known glycocalyx-digesting enzymes<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12 cit18 cit19">12,18,19</REF> namely neuraminidase (1 U ml<SP>−1</SP> in CS-C, 30–60 min), hyaluronidase (from Streptomyces hyalurolyticus, 50 U ml<SP>−1</SP> in CS-C, 30–60 min), chondroitinase (1 U ml<SP>−1</SP> in CS-C, 60 min) and heparitinase (5 U ml<SP>−1</SP> in CS-C, 60 min), were added after a standard staining procedure with WGA-FITC (2 μg ml<SP>−1</SP> in CS-C, 30 min).</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp17" novelty="None" advantage="None">All the confocal microscopy analyses were carried out in an air-conditioned room, at 23 ± 0.5 °C.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Cell viability was simultaneously assessed with ethidium homodimer-1 (2.5 μM), which undergoes enhancement of fluorescence upon binding to DNA and RNA, which is only possible for cells with damaged plasma membranes.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Additionally, a colorimetric 3-[4,5]dimethylthiazol-2,5diphenyltetrazolium bromide (MTT) viability test was performed on cells growing as primary culture in 96-well plates, under conditions identical to those of the confocal analyses.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The tetrazolium ring of MTT is cleaved in active mitochondria, and so the reaction occurs only in living cells.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.2.2">Electron microscopy</HEADER><P><s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp20" novelty="None" advantage="None">HUVECs grown on cover slips were incubated in the presence or absence of neuraminidase (1 U ml<SP>−1</SP>) for one hour.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp21" novelty="None" advantage="None">Cells on cover slips were then fixed by immersion in freshly prepared solution comprising 2.5% glutaraldehyde and 0.3% ruthenium red in 0.1 M cacodylate buffer (pH 7.3), using a technique adapted from Hayat.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp22" novelty="None" advantage="None">After primary fixation, on ice for six hours, cells were washed in three changes of 0.1 M cacodylate buffer at 4 °C and post-fixed in 1% osmium tetroxide, 0.3% ruthenium red in 0.1 M cacodylate buffer for 30 min at 4 °C.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp23" novelty="None" advantage="None">Cells were washed again in three changes of cacodylate buffer and then distilled water, prior to dehydration with ethanol.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="New" advantage="None">This was followed by infiltration and embedding in Araldite resin.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp24" novelty="None" advantage="None">Resin surrounding the coverslips was trimmed and the block placed in liquid nitrogen to enhance cleavage between the glass coverslip and the overlying resin (which have different thermal contraction rates).</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="New" advantage="None">Glass fragments were gently removed from the overlying resin containing the cells.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp25" novelty="None" advantage="None">The cell layer was trimmed and 0.5 μm survey sections were cut and stained with 1% toluidine blue in 1% aqueous borax for light microscopy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp26" novelty="None" advantage="None">Cell rich areas of the block were trimmed and 50 nm thick sections were cut (perpendicular to the culture surface) and stained with 3% aqueous uranyl acetate and Reynolds' lead citrate solution.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp27" novelty="None" advantage="None">Digital micrographs were taken on a Philips 100CS microscope to show the disposition of any ruthenium red deposits on the surface of the HUVECs.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.">Results</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.1">WGA-FITC binding</HEADER><P><s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Cells incubated with 2 μg ml<SP>−1</SP> WGA-FITC showed clearly detectable fluorescence on the cell surface which appeared after 5 min and which increased to a maximum intensity after approximately 30 min of WGA-FITC incubation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Representative WGA-FITC staining and a corresponding transmission image of HUVECs are illustrated in Fig. 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">It can be seen that staining occurs heterogeneously over an area corresponding to that occupied by cells.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="New" advantage="None">Confocal microscopy allows a quasi-optical sectioning of fluorescing cells by eliminating fluorescence from sources below and above the focal plane.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp28" novelty="None" advantage="None">A number of single confocal sections, less than 1.3 μm thick, were collected at intervals of 0.5 μm through the entire <IT>z</IT>-axis of cells, labelled with WGA-FITC for 30 min.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">A typical set of results is shown in Fig. 3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The shape and intensity of the fluorescent pattern differed as a function of the level of cross-section scanning, from a small clearly defined area near to the top of the cell, to the diffused pericellular matrix of weaker intensity on the bottom, indicating that the staining is likely to be related to the cell surface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the laser intensity and scan time used, no significant photobleaching was observed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 4(a) shows a single optical slice near to the surface of the cell and a re-construction of the <IT>z</IT>-stack images as orthogonal projections in the <IT>x</IT>–<IT>z</IT> and <IT>y</IT>–<IT>z</IT> planes, through a cell, along planes passing through the green and red lines shown in Fig. 4.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">From these projections it can be seen that staining occurs in an arc over the cells, indicating surface localisation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Measurement of the glycocalyx thickness of the four cells visible in Fig. 4(a) from the orthogonal projections gave a value of 2.5 ± 0.5 μm (<IT>n</IT> = 4).</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The range in the thickness of glycocalyx measured for more than 20 cells in four separate experiments was 2.0 ± 1.2 μm.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.2">Enzyme treatment</HEADER><P><s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="New" advantage="None">Enzyme digestion was used to elucidate the specificity of WGA-FITC staining, and to obtain information about the types of WGA binding sites.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">Neuraminidase cleaves the O-glycosidic linkages between the terminal neuraminic (sialic) acids and the subterminal sugars.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Incubation of WGA-labelled HUVECs with a medium containing 1 U ml<SP>−1</SP> neuraminidase resulted in progressive reduction of the fluorescence (Fig. 4(b)).</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Reconstruction of <IT>z</IT>-axis intensity profile of cells after neuraminidase digestion reflected a clear diminishing of both the surface staining and its thickness (Fig. 4(b)).</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The variation in intensity of staining of FITC-WGA without enzyme treatment under similar conditions (60 min, same laser settings and number of confocal slices recorded) was less than 5% (data not shown).</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, we can be confident that the decrease in the intensity of staining with enzyme treatment is not significantly affected by photobleaching of the fluorophore or changes in the intensity of the laser during the time course of the experiment.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 5(a and b) show WGA-FITC staining before, (a), and after one hour incubation with neuraminidase, (b).</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">In Fig. 5(c) the decrease in staining is illustrated quantitatively along a line taken through a single cell, as shown in Fig. 5(a) and 5(b).</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The significant effect of neuraminidase treatment on the fluorescence intensity can clearly be seen.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 5(d) shows the average intensity over an area of 210 000 square pixels, recorded from images taken during 60 min of neuraminidase treatment.</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reduction in fluorescence intensity demonstrates a smooth trend.</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fluorescence was found to diminish by 64 ± 3% (<IT>n</IT> = 5) after 30 min and by 78 ± 2% (<IT>n</IT> = 2) after 60 min.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Electron microscopy examination of fixed endothelial cells stained with ruthenium red indicated the presence of glycocalyx, visible as a layer of dark material on the apical surface (Fig. 6(a)), with a thickness of 0.10 ± 0.04 μm (<IT>n</IT> = 6).</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In agreement with the <IT>in situ</IT> observations reported above, neuraminidase-treated cells which have been fixed lack any obvious glycocalyx (Fig. 6(b)).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results of fluorescence intensity measurements, after incubation with a series of enzymes, are summarised in Table 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The distribution of WGA-FITC signal after heparitinase (typical data shown in Fig. 7), hyaluronidase and chondroitinase ABC revealed relatively low levels of glycocalyx removal, so that reduction in average intensity was 21 ± 8% (<IT>n</IT> = 9), 13 ± 5% (<IT>n</IT> = 7) and 29 ± 3% (<IT>n</IT> = 9) of the control level (100%) after 60 min of heparitinase, chondroitinase and hyaluronidase treatment, respectively.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.3">Cell viability</HEADER><P><s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The aim of this study was to examine cells in a physiologically relevant environment, where the cells are likely to have retained normal functional characteristics.</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, the maintenance of cell viability was of paramount importance, particularly given the potential cytotoxic effect of laser illumination<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25">25</REF> and FITC-labelled lectins.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26">26</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="New" advantage="None">Cell viability was tested using two approaches.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="New" advantage="None">Firstly, the preincubation and continued presence of ethidium homodimer-1 (2.5 μM, 20 min), throughout all labelling and digestion procedures, demonstrated that all cells monitored maintained intact plasma membranes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="New" advantage="None">Secondly, cell viability assessed by MTT revealed no statistically significant differences between control and WGA-FITC, or control and WGA-FITC followed by neuraminidase-treated cells (P = 1, Mann–Whitney test, three independent cell populations, data not shown).</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">These data confirmed that HUVEC monolayers retained viability throughout all the procedures of WGA-FITC binding and neuraminidase treatment.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.">Discussion</HEADER><P><s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is well established that the luminal surface of the endothelium is lined with glycocalyx, a network of carbohydrate-rich membrane-bound molecules.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Electron microscopy studies have assessed the thickness of the endothelial glycocalyx as less than 100 nm.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12 cit27">12,27</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Recently, developed methods, such as <IT>in vivo</IT> visualisation by intravital microscopy, provided information about structures extending much further from the cell surface, averaging 0.6 μm.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28">28</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although it is still a matter of debate,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29">29</REF> it is possible that collapse of highly hydrated surface structures during chemical fixation of specimens for electron microscopy preparation may lead to a considerable underestimation of the real thickness of the glycocalyx.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The present study focused on using CLSM applied to isolated HUVECs, as a model to demonstrate non-invasively the <IT>in vitro</IT> expression of the glycocalyx.</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">By this approach we have shown that the apical surface of HUVECs is covered with an extensive layer of glycocalyx, with an estimated thickness on the micron scale.</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is worth noting that the CLSM procedure involved several washing steps, which may have removed plasma proteins associated with, and contributing to, the formation of the endothelial surface layer, which suggests that the thickness determined is unlikely to be overestimated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The relatively small molecular size of WGA (molecular weight 36 kDa, volume <IT>ca.</IT> 64 nm<SP>3</SP><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30">30</REF>) used as a probe for the dissection of cell surface associated molecules, rules out the possibility of it having a significant role in the observed glycocalyx thickness.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Interestingly, the comparative detailed electron microscopy examination with the cationic dye, ruthenium red, demonstrated considerably lower thickness of glycocalyx structures in HUVECs (0.10 ± 0.04 μm) consistent with earlier electron microscopy studies of endothelial cells.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12 cit27">12,27</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">This suggests that the preparation and measurement routine for electron microscopy results in significant peturbation of the glycocalyx layer thickness.</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The much larger dimension of the glycocalyx in HUVECs observed with CLSM may therefore be considered as a characteristic of the unperturbed monolayer.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition to the clear consequences of sample preparation procedures, the discrepancies in the measurements of the dimension of the glycocalyx in the present study, and data published earlier <IT>in vivo</IT>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF> might also partly arise from the structural heterogeneity of the endothelial glycocalyx in various species and vessels.</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">All known glycocalyx estimates have previously been carried out on animal blood vessels rather than human, and have shown considerable variations in composition and thickness, which depended on vascular tree, age of animals, and even the specific region of the vessel.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12 cit31">12,31</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">It would be reasonable to expect the glycocalyx morphology of cultured human endothelial cells to have its own unique characteristics.</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is also likely that glycocalyx thickness would be influenced by a variety of environmental factors such as density of cells, culture conditions and shear stress.</annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Henry <IT>et al.</IT> have estimated the glycocalyx thickness <IT>in vivo</IT> as 0.5 μm,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF> which is clearly less than our studies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Many factors could contribute to this difference eg, different species, <IT>in vivo</IT><IT>vs.</IT><IT>in vitro</IT> conditions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Additionally, the measurements of Henry <IT>et al.</IT> were made under physiological flow and it is not fully understand how this may affect the thickness of the glycocalyx, although it has been shown that flow-induced shear stress enhances glycosaminoglycan synthesis in vascular endothelial cells <IT>in vitro.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit32">32</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">WGA recognises sialyl residues, which are reported to be expressed at high concentration in umbilical endothelium.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Sialic acids are 9C monosaccharides that link to the terminal galactose, <IT>N</IT>-acetylgalactosamine, or other sialic acid residues in carbohydrate chains that are attached to glycoproteins or glycolipids.</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The hydrolysis of this linkage by neuraminidase is used as a common tool to identify the specific presence of sialic residues on a cell surface.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="Old" advantage="None">This standard procedure of using glycocalyx-degrading enzymes to demonstrate the targeted sites for WGA binding was considered appropriate to validate the new experimental approach.</annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">Due to their terminal location, sialic acids on the cell surface are among the first molecules encountered by other cells coming in contact with the cell.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit33">33</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">In addition, the carboxylate group at C-1 is deprotonated at physiological pH,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit34">34</REF> making sialic acid the only sugar in glycoproteins which bears a net negative charge.</annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">Sialic acids have also been shown to inhibit interactions between molecules and contribute to the anti-adhesive nature of luminal endothelium, including HUVECs.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit34">34</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the experiments reported herein, neuraminidase removed WGA-FITC labelling effectively, but not completely.</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The residual labelling could be ascribed to interaction with <IT>N</IT>-acetylglucosamine, a constituent of glucosaminoglycans such as heparan sulfate or hyaluronate, which are both expressed in HUVECs.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit35">35</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is supported by the observation of glycocalyx removal by heparitinase and hyaluronidase, which act on glycosidic bonds of <IT>N</IT>-acetylglucosamine, in heparan sulfate and hyaluronate molecules, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hyaluronidase also caused a marked removal of the fluorescent staining.</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Interestingly, however, the kinetics of the enzyme's action was different from that described by Henry <IT>et al.</IT><IT>in vivo</IT>, where hyaluronidase induced a highly pronounced effect in hamster vasculature, with the maximum achieved after one hour of systemic infusion.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Variation in the properties of the glycocalyx in different species, as well as different incubation temperatures, could explain the discrepancy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Low levels of chondroitin sulfate may explain the absence of chondroitinase-induced glycocalyx disruption on the cell surface in our study.</annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The lack of enzymatic effect may also be due to steric hindrance of the molecules in the heterogeneous glycocalyx structure.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="5.">Conclusions</HEADER><P><s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">In conclusion, we have developed a methodology for high resolution CLSM coupled with direct staining with fluorescently labelled lectin, WGA-FITC, to enable the visualisation of the sialic acid-enriched glycocalyx in viable HUVECs.</annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The specificity of the WGA-FITC staining was demonstrated by treatment with several enzymes known to degrade glycocalyx, from which neuraminidase was found to be most effective.</annotationART></s> <s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">By recording single confocal sections through the <IT>z</IT>-axis of cells the thickness of the hydrated glycocalyx was determined to be an order of magnitude greater than that found in <IT>ex situ</IT> measurements on fixed cells.</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met15" novelty="New" advantage="None">Viability was confirmed in the present studies using double labelling with ethidium homodimer-1 as an indicator of plasma membrane integrity, the MTT assay and demonstration of morphologically undisturbed monolayers throughout the imaging process.</annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None">These tests allow us to be confident that the measurements of glycocalyx relate to viable cell monolayers.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None">To our knowledge, this is the first report using CLSM for quantitative <IT>in situ</IT> analysis of the fully-hydrated structurally-intact glycocalyx in human macrovascular endothelium.</annotationART></s> <s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con15" novelty="None" advantage="None">There is scope to now use this technique to further investigate the effect of fluid-flow generated shear stress on the glycocalyx.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
