<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b313354k" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Raman spectroscopy of cryosolutions: the van der Waals complex of dimethyl ether with fluoroform</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Raman spectra in the 3200–350 cm<SP>–1</SP> range were obtained for solutions in liquid krypton, at 131 K, containing dimethyl ether, fluoroform and mixtures of them.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the spectra of the mixed solutions bands were detected that must be assigned to the 1∶1 complex between the ether and fluoroform.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fluoroform C–H stretching in the complex is detected at 18.7 cm<SP>–1</SP> above its value in monomer fluoroform, confirming the blue shifting hydrogen bonding in the complex.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Analysis shows that the Raman intensity of this mode is not significantly affected by complexation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The advantage of the complementarity of the IR and Raman spectra of cryosolutions is demonstrated by the detailed analysis of the methyl deformation modes of the ether.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Molecular cryospectroscopy using infrared (IR) spectroscopy to detect solutes in low temperature rare gas solutions has been proven to be a viable technique in the study of weak molecular complexes.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2">1,2</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast, Raman spectra of cryosolutions have been studied far less, and the Raman literature on the formation of weak complexes in cryosolution is virtually non-existent.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reasons for this are the weakness of the Raman effect and the low solubility of most compounds in typical cryosolvents.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">While the second drawback can be overcome in IR by using cells with longer pathlengths, the low concentrations call for the use of high sensitivity detection in Raman.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">State-of-the-art detectivity is offered by the use of a CCD camera, and we have used a detector of this type in this study.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">A complex which has recently drawn attention is the one formed between fluoroform and dimethyl ether (DME), F<SB>3</SB>CH·O(CH<SB>3</SB>)<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The complexation enthalpy of this complex was determined to be 12.6(3) kJ mol<SP>–1</SP> in liquid argon,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF> which puts it in the realm of weak complexes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The complex is held together by a hydrogen bond formed between the fluoroform hydrogen and the DME oxygen atoms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This interaction has been characterized by both calculation and experiment<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF> to belong to the class of blue shifting hydrogen bonds.</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The blue shift of the fluoroform C–H stretch, by 17.7 cm<SP>–1</SP> for F<SB>3</SB>CH·O(CH<SB>3</SB>)<SB>2</SB> in liquid argon, is accompanied by a decrease of the IR intensity of the fundamental stretching transition of the hydrogen bonded C–H bond.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This decrease, by an order of magnitude, makes the transition hard to detect in the IR spectra.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this study we have investigated the possibility of (i) recording Raman spectra of relatively dilute solutions, in a typical cryosolvent, of fluoroform and dimethyl ether, and (ii) observing the formation of a complex between them.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">In view of its unusual behaviour in IR, we have studied in some detail the Raman intensity of the fluoroform C–H stretch upon formation of the complex.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot3" novelty="None" advantage="None"><IT>Ab initio</IT> predictions of spectral intensities for complexes held together by blue shifting hydrogen bonds hitherto have exclusively concentrated on the IR spectra.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None">In view of our interest in the Raman characteristics of blue shifting hydrogen bonds we filled this gap by carrying out MP2 calculations of the Raman intensities of monomers and complex.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Experimental</HEADER><P><s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Dimethyl ether and fluoroform, with stated purities of 99+% and 98+%, respectively, were obtained from Sigma Aldrich.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The solvent gas, krypton, with stated purity of 99.998% was provided by L’Air Liquide.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="New" advantage="None">All compounds were used without further purification.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Raman spectra were obtained by using a Dilor XY spectrometer, consisting of a subtractive double <IT>f</IT> = 80 cm monochromator coupled to a single <IT>f</IT> = 80 cm spectrograph.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The scattered Raman signal was imaged onto a liquid nitrogen cooled charge-coupled device (P88231 EEV CCD) with a resolution of 770 × 1152.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The 514.5 nm line of a Spectra-Physics argon ion laser was used for Raman excitation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The power of the incident laser beam was set at 1 W. The polarization of the laser beam was controlled with a polarization rotator and measurements were made with the incident beam either perpendicular (“polarized spectrum” or parallel (“depolarized spectrum”) to the direction of measurement.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The light scattered at 90° was focused on the entrance slit, where a polarization scrambler was inserted to eliminate the intensity distortion by apparatus polarization.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The spectra were measured with resolutions of 1.5 and 0.8 cm<SP>–1</SP>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Raman cell consisted of a 70 cm long Pyrex tube with an outer diameter of 10 mm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The tube is sealed at the lower end to contain the solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp11" novelty="None" advantage="None">At the other end the tube is fused to a 1 L glass flask, which can be accessed <IT>via</IT> a Young PR10RA stopcock.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The tube is fitted on the outside with a PT 100 thermoresistor for temperature measurements.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The cell is dimensioned to be inserted into a Leybold exchange gas cryostat, using standard vacuum fittings.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp14" novelty="None" advantage="None">In a typical run the evacuated cell is filled at room temperature with the desired gas mixture to a pressure of 2 bar.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Cooling of the cell to a temperature below the normal boiling point of krypton then causes condensation of an amount of liquid that fills the cell to approximately 2 cm above the bottom of the tube, allowing convenient laser excitation of the sample.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Raman measurements in this study were made in the 3200–350 cm<SP>–1</SP> range, with the solutions kept in a 1 K temperature interval around 131 K. Full thermodynamic characterization of the complex equilibium requires spectra of the solutions to be recorded in a sufficiently wide temperature interval.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Due to the very limited liquid range of krypton at 1 bar, such a temperature study imposes the use of pressures inside the cell of up to 15 bars.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The present cell has not been designed to safely hold such pressures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Consequently, no variable temperature studies can be performed with it, so that the Raman spectra could not be used to determine the complexation enthalpy.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The previous cryosolution study of the complex<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF> in liquid argon focused on the fluoroform C–H stretch.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="New" advantage="None">For comparison, we have repeated that study using liquid krypton as solvent, and using concentrations similar to those for the Raman spectra.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="New" advantage="None">The latter are significantly higher than those used previously,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF> so that an IR cell with a pathlength of 1 mm had to be used.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The IR experiments were performed as described before.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="New" advantage="None">Theoretical information on the geometry of the complex and on its vibrational spectra was obtained by carrying out <IT>ab initio</IT> calculations, at the MP2 = FULL/6-31+G(d,p) level.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="Old" advantage="None">During the geometry optimization and the force field calculation, corrections for basis set superposition error were taken into account explicitly using the CP-corrected gradient techniques developed by Simon <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="Old" advantage="None">All calculations were performed using Gaussian.98<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="New" advantage="None">The Raman intensities were calculated by numerical differentiation of the dipole derivatives with respect to the electric field, using the FREQ = RAMAN and DENSITY = CURRENT keywords.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Results and discussion</HEADER><P><s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="New" advantage="None">Using <IT>ab initio</IT> calculations at the MP2/6-311++G(d,p) level, the structures of the monomers and of the 1∶1 complex have been optimized.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The resulting geometries are very similar to those obtained at the MP2/6-31++G(d,p) level<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF> and require no further comment.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The more important vibrational frequencies and corresponding IR and Raman intensities for these molecules have been collected in Table 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The intermolecular van der Waals modes of the complex are not listed, because they are not directly of interest to the present study.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the discussion of the spectra below, the fundamentals of the monomers are described by their number in the Herzberg system, as in Table 1, with the monomer indicated as as superscript.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The symmetry species of the normal coordinate is indicated, when deemed necessary, in parentheses.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The symmetry species for monomer DME have been derived with the heavy atom skeleton in the (<IT>y</IT>,<IT>z</IT>)-plane.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The point groups for DME and fluoroform are <IT>C</IT><SB>2v</SB> and <IT>C</IT><SB>3v</SB>, respectively, but the complex has the reduced symmetry <IT>C</IT><SB>s</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="New" advantage="None">To facilitate comparison, however, fundamentals of the complex are described by the symbol, including the symmetry species, of the corresponding monomer transition.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="New" advantage="None">The actual species for the complex can easily be derived using the correlations a<SB>1</SB>, b<SB>1</SB> → a′ and a<SB>2</SB>, b<SB>2</SB> → a″ for the DME moiety and a<SB>1</SB> → a′ and e → a′ + a″ for the fluoroform moiety.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The occurence of bands in the spectra of mixed solutions that are not present in either of the single monomer solutions allows the conclusion that a complex is formed between DME and fluoroform.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Raman frequencies of these observed complex bands are compared with the corresponding monomer frequencies in Table 2, together with the Raman, IR and <IT>ab initio</IT> complexation shifts.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Figs. 1 and 2 illustrate the new bands observed in the regions of (a<SB>1</SB>) and (a<SB>1</SB>), respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In both figures the top panel gives the Raman spectra while the lower panel gives the IR spectra.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met14" novelty="New" advantage="None">In order to allow direct comparisons of complex/monomer relative intensities, the spectra shown were recorded from solutions in which the concentration of the solute(s) was the same in both types of spectroscopy.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Raman spectra in Fig. 1 show the presence of a complex band in the spectrum of the mixed monomer solution at 3051.8 cm<SP>–1</SP>, on the high frequency side of the monomer (a<SB>1</SB>) band.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">With the highest DME mode observed at 2990.5 cm<SP>–1</SP>, the assignment of that complex band to a DME CH<SB>3</SB> stretching mode requires a complexation shift of more than 60 cm<SP>–1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In view of the weakness of the complex and of the weak perturbation of the DME methyl groups, such a shift is unrealistically high.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, we assign the 3051.8 cm<SP>–1</SP> band to (a<SB>1</SB>) in the complex.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Its frequency is 18.7 cm<SP>–1</SP> higher than the corresponding monomer band at 3033.1 cm<SP>–1</SP>, in very good agreement with the value of 17.7 cm<SP>–1</SP> determined at 92 K using IR spectroscopy in liquid argon.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, the 3051.8 cm<SP>–1</SP> Raman band clearly confirms the blue shifting hydrogen bond between DME and fluoroform.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The experimental conditions used in the present experiments are such that for the mixed solution the complex band is hardly visible in the IR spectrum, which exemplifies the above mentioned problem caused by the decrease of the IR intensity of the C–H stretch upon complexation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">From the relative intensities in the top panel then follows that the Raman intensity of this mode is affected much less.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="New" advantage="None">A more quantitative appreciation of this will be discussed in a following paragraph.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Other complex bands observed in the CH stretching region are compiled in Table 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">They are due to DME, but have not been assigned in more detail.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is because of the problems with the assignments of the DME fundamentals in this region.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Table 2 indicates that the highest and the lowest of the bands in this region appear at 2990.5 and 2811.7 cm<SP>–1</SP>.in the monomer, and at 2992.6 and 2811.7 cm<SP>–1</SP> in the complex.</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the depolarized Raman spectrum these bands are considerably weaker than in the polarized spectrum, which shows that they must be assigned as <IT>ν</IT>DME1(a<SB>1</SB>) and <IT>ν</IT>DME2(a<SB>1</SB>), respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The six complex bands found between <IT>ν</IT>DME1(a<SB>1</SB>) and <IT>ν</IT>DME2(a<SB>1</SB>) are also polarized in Raman, and, therefore, must be due to overtones or combination bands that derive their intensity from Fermi resonance with the a<SB>1</SB> fundamentals.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">These resonances do not permit meaningful comparison between the complexation shifts of the outer two complex bands and the (harmonic) <IT>ab initio</IT> results.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the complex band in the IR spectrum, shown in the lower panel of Fig. 2, is much sharper than the corresponding monomer mode: the measured full width at half height equals 1.0 cm<SP>–1</SP> for the complex band, against 5.0 cm<SP>–1</SP> for the monomer band.</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the Raman spectrum, top panel of Fig. 2, both monomer and complex bands are very narrow.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Because polarized Raman band widths of totally symmetric bands are predominantly determined by vibrational relaxation, this shows that the monomer IR contour is significantly broadened by rotational relaxation.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The <IT>ab initio</IT> results predict that for the Raman intensity in the monomer differs little from that in the complex, the ratio being 1.051.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">This ratio is in line with expectations for a mode of a weak complex that is localized in atoms not directly involved in the hydrogen bond.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met15" novelty="New" advantage="None">If the <IT>ab initio</IT> ratio is accepted to be correct, it can be used to transform the experimental band area ratio for this mode into the monomer/complex concentration ratio.</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The monomer/complex Raman band area ratio for the 698/694.7 cm<SP>–1</SP> doublet assigned to was determined from least squares band fitting to be 1.03(5).</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Combining this value with the <IT>ab initio</IT> Raman intensity ratio leads to a monomer/complex concentration ratio for the studied solution equal to 1.08(5).</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Also using least squares band fitting, the monomer/complex Raman band area ratio for in the same solution is calculated to be 0.99(7).</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None">With the above concentration ratio this can be transformed into the Raman intensity ratio for this doublet, resulting in a value of 0.92(11), which is in reasonable agreement with the ratio derived from the <IT>ab initio</IT> Raman intensities in Table 1, equalling 0.70.</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hence, always in the assumption that the <IT>ab initio</IT> intensity ratio for the doublet is valid, the above result confirms what was anticipated in the previous paragraph: in contrast with the IR intensity, the Raman intensity of the C–H bond stretching of fluoroform engaged in a blue shifting hydrogen bond with DME, does not significantly differ from that of the monomer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 1 then makes clear that blue shifting hydrogen bonding may escape detection in IR as a consequence of the intensity behavior, but that this is much less likely to happen when Raman spectroscopy is used.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The data in Table 2 show that complex bands have been observed for a number of other fundamentals.</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">It can be seen that in all cases the observed directions match the <IT>ab initio</IT> ones, and that also the quantitative agreement in general is good.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Over the years, dimethyl ether has been used as a model compound in numerous studies, many of which focus on the Lewis base properties of the compound.</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">It would seem that this popularity has led to a reliable assignment of all the normal modes of DME.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Inspection of the literature, however, shows that this is not the case.</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">For instance, in recent years, at least four different studies have reported on the IR spectra of matrix isolated monomeric DME.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7 cit8 cit9 cit10">7–10</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In two of these studies<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9 cit10">9,10</REF> a detailed assignment of the bands observed in the CH<SB>3</SB> deformation region, between 1500 and 1400 cm<SP>–1</SP> was given.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Of the six fundamentals expected in this region, spanning the representation 2a<SB>1</SB> + a<SB>2</SB> + b<SB>1</SB> + 2b<SB>2</SB>, five have been assigned by Asselin <IT>et al.</IT>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF> and four by Wrobel <IT>et al.</IT>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF> which differ from each other because the assignments of the b<SB>1</SB> and one of the b<SB>2</SB> fundamentals have been reversed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Their observed frequencies agree well with those of a somewhat older matrix study,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF> who identified and assigned five of the fundamentals.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In none of these studies, the IR forbidden <IT>ν</IT>DME9(a<SB>2</SB>) mode was assigned.</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">This mode was identified in the spectrum of solid DME isotopically diluted in DME-d<SB>6</SB>, by Allan <IT>et al.</IT>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF> at 1462.4 cm<SP>–1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although the positions of the bands in this environment differ somewhat from those in an argon matrix, detailed comparison suggests that this 1462.4 cm<SP>–1</SP> transition must correspond to the 1456 cm<SP>–1</SP> band observed in the argon matrices, which was assigned to a b<SB>1</SB> mode,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF> or to a b<SB>2</SB> mode<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF> in that environment.</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Raman spectra of solid DME isotopically diluted in DME-d<SB>6</SB> have also been reported.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although <IT>ν</IT>DME9(a<SB>2</SB>) is Raman active, it was not assigned, and the assignments proposed for the remaining five modes in this region disagree with those of the corresponding IR study.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hence, it is clear that the assignments of the methyl deformations have not yet converged, and this is another instance where the present study can contribute.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In Fig. 3 the methyl deformation region is shown in Raman, top panel, and in IR, lower panel, for a solution in liquid krypton.</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Obviously, the higher and lower bands, at 1474.8 and 1426.3 cm<SP>–1</SP>, respectively, are present in Raman as well as in IR.</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the Raman spectrum two more bands are observed, with maxima at approximately 1452.5 and at 1445.1 cm<SP>–1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Also in the IR spectrum two more bands are observed, at 1457.5 and 1454.8 cm<SP>–1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">The non-coincidence of the central Raman and IR doublets shows they are due to different fundamental modes of DME.</annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hence, in the combined spectra a total of six different transitions is observed, equal to the number expected in this region.</annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The assignment of the highest and lowest bands in this region to <IT>ν</IT><SB>3</SB>(a<SB>1</SB>) and <IT>ν</IT><SB>19</SB>(b<SB>2</SB>), respectively, is straightforward and requires no comment.</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">Apart from the IR forbidden <IT>ν</IT><SB>9</SB>(a<SB>2</SB>) mode, the <IT>ν</IT><SB>4</SB>(a<SB>1</SB>) is predicted, Table 1, to have significantly lower IR intensity than the other methyl deformation modes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None">We, therefore, assign the central ir doublet, in the predicted frequency order, to the transitions with the higher <IT>ab initio</IT> ir intensity, <IT>i.e.</IT> <IT>ν</IT><SB>18</SB>(b<SB>2</SB>) and <IT>ν</IT><SB>13</SB>(b<SB>1</SB>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The <IT>ab initio</IT> Raman intensity of <IT>ν</IT><SB>18</SB>(b<SB>2</SB>) suggests that this mode may contribute some intensity to the high frequency shoulder of the central Raman doublet, even when no separate maximum is observed for this mode.</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The components of that Raman doublet must be due to <IT>ν</IT><SB>4</SB>(a<SB>1</SB>) and <IT>ν</IT><SB>9</SB>(a<SB>2</SB>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con17" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contradiction with the predicted frequency order in Table 1, we prefer the assignment of <IT>ν</IT><SB>4</SB>(a<SB>1</SB>) to the intense low frequency component at 1445.1 cm<SP>–1</SP>, as this leads to a more satisfactory agreement with the predicted Raman intensities of these modes.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Conclusions</HEADER><P><s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con18" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the paragraphs above we have demonstrated the feasiblity of Raman cryospectroscopy, with solute concentrations in the 1 × 10<SP>–3</SP> mole fraction range, in the field of van der Waals molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The spectra recorded for mixtures of fluoroform and dimethyl ether confirm the blue shifting nature of the hydrogen bond between these monomers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con20" novelty="None" advantage="None">Finally, exploiting the sharpness of the vibrational bands in cryosolution, the use of combined IR and Raman spectra in removing uncertainties for some assignments has been illustrated.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
