<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b313362a" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Bi-directional photocurrent generation dependent on the wavelength of irradiation of a mixed monolayer assembly</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">A mixed self-assembled monolayer consisting of a ruthenium tris-bipyridine complex linked to viologen and a palladium phthalocyanine derivative was fabricated on a gold electrode by means of pendant thiol groups.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The direction of the photocurrent which is induced in the electrode when it is irradiated depends on the wavelength of the light used.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER /><P><s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The development of novel organic thin film devices based on the assembly of molecular components has been an exceptionally active field in recent times.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Self-assembled monolayers (SAMs) of donor (D)–acceptor (A) pairs on electrodes have attracted particular attention for application as photoelectric conversion devices.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2 cit3 cit4 cit5 cit6">1–6</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Photoinduced electron transfer between the donor and the acceptor is responsible for photocurrent generation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Implantation of light-harvesting molecules<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF> and fabrication of three-dimensional nanostructured assemblies by combining gold nanoparticles and thiol dyes<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit9 cit10">8–10</REF> have proven to be successful avenues for improving photocurrent generation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Until now, however, the development of devices based on SAMs has been directed towards the improvement of photoelectric conversion efficiency.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">One of the noteworthy advantages of self-assembly is that different molecules can be implanted on the electrode at the same time.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit7">1,7</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">This may allow SAMs to be exploited for new applications in photonic fields.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">We have developed a novel photoelectric conversion device which uses a mixed SAM composed of a linked ruthenium bipyridine–viologen disulfide<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF> and a palladium phthalocyanine thiol derivative (Fig. 1).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">The direction (cathodic or anodic) of the photocurrent induced in the monolayer can be reversed by altering the irradiation wavelength.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The syntheses of the linked ruthenium bipyridine complex–viologen disulfide [RuVS]<SB>2</SB><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF> and the phthalocyanine disulfide [PcS]<SB>2</SB><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF> have been described previously.</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The gold electrode was prepared by depositing a small amount of titanium and then gold on a glass plate by vacuum deposition.</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This gold electrode was immersed in a solution of [RuVS]<SB>2</SB> (5 × 10<SP>–4</SP> mol dm<SP>–3</SP>) in MeCN–CH<SB>2</SB>Cl<SB>2</SB> (1 ∶ 1 v/v) for 4 days.</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Then, the electrode was removed from the solution, rinsed with acetonitrile and dichloromethane, and then dried in air, to give an electrode modified with RuVS (denoted RuVS/Au).</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">An electrode modified with [PcS]<SB>2</SB> (PcS/Au) was also prepared by the same procedure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The electrode modified with both compounds, (RuVS + PcS)/Au (Fig. 1), was prepared from a solution containing identical concentrations (5 × 10<SP>–4</SP> mol dm<SP>–3</SP>) of [RuVS]<SB>2</SB> and [PcS]<SB>2</SB> by the same procedure as used for RuVS/Au.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The surface coverage of RuVS in RuVS/Au (5.5 × 10<SP>–11</SP> mol cm<SP>–2</SP>) was estimated by monitoring the reductive wave of the viologen moiety of RuVS, and the surface coverage of PcS/Au obtained from the absorption spectrum of PcS (1.6 × 10<SP>–11</SP> mol cm<SP>–2</SP>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">As to (RuVS + PcS)/Au, the surface coverage of each dye was evaluated from the reductive wave of the viologen moiety and from the adsorption ratio of RuVS and PcS on gold powder:<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit12">1,12</REF> 6.0 × 10<SP>–12</SP> mol cm<SP>–2</SP> for RuVS and 1.9 × 10<SP>–12</SP> mol cm<SP>–2</SP> for PcS.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reason for the lower coverage in the case of (RuVS + PcS)/Au is uncertain at present, but the photocurrent intensity correlates well with the surface coverage (<IT>vide infra</IT>).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Photocurrent measurements on the modified electrodes were carried out using a three-electrode photoelectrochemical cell consisting of the modified electrode (working), an Ag/AgCl (sat.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">KCl) electrode (reference), and a platinum wire (counter) in an aqueous solution containing 0.1 mol dm<SP>–3</SP> NaClO<SB>4</SB> under a nitrogen atmosphere in the presence of methylviologen (MV<SP>2+</SP>; 5 × 10<SP>–3</SP> mol dm<SP>–3</SP>) and triethanolamine (TEOA; 5 × 10<SP>–2</SP> mol dm<SP>–3</SP>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The light from a 150 W tungsten lamp was passed through a monochromator and irradiated a 0.28 cm<SP>2</SP> area of the modified electrode.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The photocurrent action spectra were measured by changing the excitation wavelength (Δ<IT>λ</IT> = ±16 nm).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">When the photocurrent action spectrum of RuVS/Au was measured at <IT>E</IT> = 0 mV, anodic photocurrents were observed in the 380–750 nm region.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The action spectrum showed a broad band around 450 nm, almost overlapping with the absorption band of RuVS in acetonitrile.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">This suggests that the ruthenium complex is the photoactive species and the anodic photocurrent generation is mainly due to photoinduced intramolecular electron transfer from the photoexcited ruthenium complex to the viologen moiety.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit4">1,4</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The oxidized ruthenium complex is reduced by TEOA.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the other hand, cathodic photocurrents were observed in the case of PcS/Au at <IT>E</IT> = 0 mV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The action spectrum also showed broad bands around 700 nm, corresponding to the absorption bands of phthalocyanine in toluene.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, the phthalocyanine moiety is the photoactive site and intermolecular photoinduced electron-transfer from the photoexcited phthalocyanine to MV<SP>2+</SP> in the bulk mainly induces the cathodic photocurrent generation in PcS/Au.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">A small amount of residual oxygen in the electrolyte solution may also contribute to some extent to the cathodic photocurrent generation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">These photocurrent mechanisms are shown in Figure 2.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">At <IT>E</IT> = –200 mV, the photocurrent from (RuVS + PcS)/Au was observed in the cathodic direction when exciting in the 400–750 nm region and the photocurrent action spectrum showed broad peaks around 630 and 700 nm; thus, the contribution from RuVS is negligible.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">At <IT>E</IT> = +400 mV on the other hand, the photocurrent was observed only in the anodic direction when irradiating in the 400–750 nm region, with a relatively large broad peak around 450 nm, meaning that the contribution from PcS is negligible.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">These results show that RuVS functions individually for anodic photocurrent generation at <IT>E</IT> = –200 mV, while PcS acts similarly for cathodic photocurrent generation at <IT>E</IT> = +400 mV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">At <IT>E</IT> = 0 mV, however, photocurrents were observed in both directions, depending on the irradiation wavelength, as shown in Fig. 3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The photocurrent action spectrum for (RuVS + PcS)/Au at <IT>E</IT> = 0 mV shows a broad anodic peak around 450 nm, corresponding with the absorption peak of RuVS, and two cathodic peaks around 630 and 700 nm, corresponding with the absorption peaks of PcS, with a cross-point (zero current) around 550 nm.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The photocurrent measurements summarized above indicate that two kinds of photoinduced electron-transfer pathways operate almost independently in the (RuVS + PcS)/Au monolayer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Intramolecular photoinduced electron transfer occurs from the photoexcited ruthenium complex to viologen in RuVS and intermolecular photoinduced electron transfer from the photoexcited phthalocyanine to MV<SP>2+</SP> (and residual oxygen) takes place in the bulk.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None">The photocurrent generated by PcS/Au was compared under three different experimental conditions in terms of the sacrificial reagents: (1) [MV<SP>2+</SP>] = 5 × 10<SP>–3</SP> mol dm<SP>–3</SP> under aerobic conditions, (2) [MV<SP>2+</SP>] = 5 × 10<SP>–3</SP> mol dm<SP>–3</SP> under a nitrogen atmosphere, and (3) without MV<SP>2+</SP> under aerobic conditions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ratio of the photocurrent at 700 nm for the three conditions (1), (2), and (3) is 20 ∶ 4 ∶ 7.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">These results indicate that oxygen is a good electron acceptor for the photoexcited phthalocyanine and the presence of oxygen promotes electron transfer from the photoexcited phthalocyanine to MV<SP>2+</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is likely that oxygen accepts an electron from MV<SP>+</SP>, regenerating MV<SP>2+</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In any case, one of these two pathways can be preferentially driven by irradiation at the appropriate wavelength, because the absorption bands of the ruthenium complex (around 450 nm; <IT>hν</IT><B>1</B>) and phthalocyanine (600–700 nm; <IT>hν</IT><B>2</B>) are widely separated from each other.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">At negative applied potentials, electron transfer from the electrode to the cation radical of phthalocyanine occurs easily in PcS (<IT>E</IT><SB>ox</SB> = +0.84 V <IT>vs</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Ag/AgCl), while that from the viologen moiety to the electrode becomes difficult in RuVS (<IT>E</IT><SB>red</SB> = –0.39 V <IT>vs</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Ag/AgCl).</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">At positive potentials, electron-transfer from the one-electron reduced viologen moiety to the electrode becomes favorable in RuVS.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Accordingly, the direction of the photocurrent in (RuVS + PcS)/Au at <IT>E</IT> = 0 mV reverses at ∼550 nm.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The bi-directional photocurrent response reported here arises as a result of the implantation of two separate and individually functioning photoinduced electron-transfer systems on the electrode.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">This novel photocurrent behavior is promising for applications in molecular photonic devices and photoelectric logic devices.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
