<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b313781c" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Collisions of excited Na atoms with N<SB>2</SB>, C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>2</SB> and N<SB>2</SB>O molecules. Surface-hopping calculation of the Na(3p) fine structure population</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">The results of optical collision experiments: fine structure population ratios and polarization alignment angles obtained from scattering of Na atoms which are optically 3s → 3p excited during the collision with N<SB>2</SB>, C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>2</SB> and N<SB>2</SB>O molecules, have been simulated numerically and analysed using quantum chemically computed potential energy surfaces, classical trajectory calculations and the semiclassical surface hopping method combined with a specially developed diabatization procedure.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="1">Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Optical collisions are scattering processes where the projectile is optically excited during its interaction with the target.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This paper is concerned with the optical collision experiments of Na atoms with a series of molecules which have been carried out in the past few years by Grosser and coworkers<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2 cit3">1–3</REF> following similar experiments with atomic targets.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit4 cit5">1,4,5</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The experiments can briefly be explained as follows.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The collisions take place in a crossed beam arrangement.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The collision complexes are excited with polarized laser light and a detection laser is used to separate the excited Na atoms from the background.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The excitation laser is detuned by a few 100 cm<SP>−1</SP> from the resonant 3s → 3p transition of Na, as a rule, but not always to higher frequency.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore optical transitions occur only at those geometries, the so-called Condon configurations, where the energy difference in the collision complex corresponds just to the detuned laser frequency.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Excitation probability as a function of detuning and polarization angle is recorded for a few selected scattering angles.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">From flight time measurement the velocity of the Na atoms after collision is obtained; this allows to reconstruct the kinematics of the observed scattering processes.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The goal of the experiments is to test the interaction potentials of excited Na with the target molecules and to obtain “snapshots” of the collision complexes, in particular of the direction of the 3p orbital after the process of optical excitation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The results are presented as polar diagrams of the probability as a function of an orientation angle; they are analysed with the aid of numerical simulations using quantum chemically calculated potential surfaces and classical trajectories.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2 cit3 cit6">2,3,6</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">A related experiment consists in measuring the ratio of excited Na atoms leaving the complex in the lower 3p<SB>1/2</SB> fine structure state compared to the sum 3p<SB>1/2</SB> + 3p<SB>3/2</SB>, the two levels being separated by spin–orbit interaction.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3 cit5 cit7">3,5,7</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Under the conditions the experiments have been carried out, the non-zero results for this ratio can be explained only by assuming non-adiabatic coupling effects between different excited electronic states.</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore precise knowledge of the interaction between the potentials is needed for a detailed understanding of the underlying process.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is the aim of the present work to explain the observed fine structure ratios as functions of the kinetic energy after the collision numerically by combining classical trajectory methods with a semiclassical surface hopping procedure.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2">Optical collisions</HEADER><P><s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Upon collision of an excited Na(3p) atom with a target molecule the degeneracy of the atomic 3p levels is removed to an extent depending on the separation and arrangement of the collision complex.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of a linear closed-shell target molecule as treated here three excited potential energy surfaces can be distinguished, two of <SP>2</SP>A′ (electronic) symmetry and one <SP>2</SP>A″.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The 3p charge distribution is no longer spherically symmetric as in the unperturbed atom.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In each of the excited components the 3p orbital is described by a real wave function and accordingly the excited Na atom has a quadrupole moment (of about −16.8 au).</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The interaction of Na(3p) with the target is determined by the interaction of this quadrupole with the molecular multipole moments as well as by the dispersion effect.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Quantum chemically the latter is an effect of electron correlation whereas the multipole interactions can be treated already on the Hartree–Fock (HF) level.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is important to have the correct orientation of the 3p atomic orbitals already in low order of the theoretical treatment.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="New" advantage="None">In our calculations we therefore choose a slightly distorted (fixed) geometry for the target molecules such that the HF multipoles correctly reproduce the experimental moments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="New" advantage="None">Alternatively the molecular moments obtained from a correlated wave function could be used; we hope that the experimental moments also account for the average over the configurations of the rotating and vibrating target molecule.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In a previous paper<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF> we have explained how a qualitative understanding of the excited potential surfaces can be obtained if the most important contributions to the multipole interactions are discussed.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">For every geometrical arrangement of the collision complex each one of the three 3p surfaces is characterized by the spatial orientation of the corresponding 3p orbital.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Whereas in the <SP>2</SP>A″ state the 3p atomic orbital is perpendicular to the plane defined by the linear target and the Na atom, the two <SP>2</SP>A′ states have in-plane 3p orbitals.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The expectation value of the 3p orbital direction after excitation leads to the so-called alignment angle, defined with respect to the center-of-mass (CM) trajectory of the incoming particle.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">With quantum chemistry the 3p direction angles can easily be obtained by calculating the 3s → 3p transition moment vectors; except for very close separations they are mutually orthogonal.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the descriptions of the experiments we also need the potential energy surface of the 3s ground state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this state the Na atom is approximately spherical; the surface is nearly structureless down to rather short distances where the Pauli repulsion sets in.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore on the three excited surfaces the spin–orbit interaction of the Na(3p) electron must be taken into account which contributes small corrections to the energies determined by the interaction of Na(3p) and the target molecule, in the order of the spin–orbit coupling constant of the Na(3p) state (11.5 cm<SP>−1</SP>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="New" advantage="None">Thus numerical simulation of the scattering experiments is carried out by running classical trajectories on the surfaces calculated with <IT>ab-initio</IT> quantum chemistry including electron correlation and the spin–orbit corrections.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="New" advantage="None">The polarization of the laser radiation is taken into account by projecting onto the 3s → 3p transition dipole vector.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="New" advantage="None">For this projection only the orientation of the transition vector is needed along the trajectories, not its value.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">Therefore our method to obtain the correct multipole interaction on the HF level is very useful and saving computer time.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The three potential surfaces derived from the Na(3p) components may penetrate each other at certain geometrical arrangements, <IT>i.e.</IT> change their energetic ordering.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">This situation favours non-adiabatic couplings.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Penetration of the two surfaces of <SP>2</SP>A′ symmetry leads to conical intersections.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The <SP>2</SP>A′ surfaces of the Na(3p) + HCCH system have such intersection points on the molecular axis, about 8 <IT>a</IT><SB>0</SB> off the position of the H atoms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of the N<SB>2</SB>, N<SB>2</SB>O (and CO<SB>2</SB>) target molecules, whose quadrupole moments are negative in contrast to HCCH, the penetration occurs on rings around the molecular axis with radii between 10 <IT>a</IT><SB>0</SB> (CO<SB>2</SB>) and 16.5 <IT>a</IT><SB>0</SB> (N<SB>2</SB>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Evidently the probability that a Na trajectory passes close to an intersection point such that non-adiabatic processes can be expected is much higher for a ring-shaped intersection line than in the case of only two axial intersection points.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3">Theory</HEADER><P><s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None">In this section we shall investigate the dynamics of the collision process taking place on the quantum chemically calculated potential energy surfaces.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The dynamics of nuclear motion is treated according to the concept of classical trajectories.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="New" advantage="None">The relative velocity of the colliding particles at large distance and the rotational temperature of the molecule are specified by the experimental setup.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="New" advantage="None">The impact parameter <IT>b</IT> and the initial rotational state of the molecule are determined by a random number generator for every trajectory.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="New" advantage="None">The bond distances and angles of the target molecule are kept fixed at linear geometry, thus the surfaces become two dimensional and only five coordinates remain describing the dynamics of the system in the center of mass system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="New" advantage="None">At a distance depending on the detuning of the laser frequency the collision complex is excited to one of the states of the 3p-manifold.</annotationART></s></P><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.1">Quantum chemical calculations</HEADER><P><s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The potential energy and transition dipole moment surfaces of the collision complexes Na + N<SB>2</SB> and Na + C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>2</SB> have been presented previously.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2 cit6">2,6</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Graphical representations of their transition vectors to the uppermost surfaces and of the Condon configurations for several detuning frequencies are shown below (Figs. 1 and 2).</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The value of the transition moments is practically constant for all transitions and every configuration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The direction of these vectors characterizes the surfaces and is important for the analysis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The sudden change of orientation in the figures indicates the position of the conical intersection where two surfaces penetrate each other.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="New" advantage="None">The quadrupole moments of the molecules were computed in HF approximation leading to the following results: 5.44 au for C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>2</SB> and −0.93 au for N<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met14" novelty="New" advantage="None">The quantum chemical calculations for the system Na + N<SB>2</SB>O have been performed in a similar way.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The surfaces are functions of only two geometrical parameters, the center of mass distance <IT>R</IT> between the atom and the target molecule and the angle <IT>ϑ</IT> between <IT>R</IT> and the molecular axis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fixed bond lengths are 2.18 <IT>a</IT><SB>0</SB> for NN and 2.17 <IT>a</IT><SB>0</SB> for NO.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">This corresponds essentially to shifting the central atom by 0.06 <IT>a</IT><SB>0</SB> towards the oxygen atom, as compared to the experimental geometry<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF> and yields a dipole moment of 0.07 au (0.17 D, O being the negative pole, exp.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">0.167 D) and a quadrupole moment of −2.85 au.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the calculations a 7s7p4d3f ANO (atomic natural orbitals) basis set from Widmark <IT>et al.</IT> has been used<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF> for the target molecule and a selfmade 8s6p4d3f basis for the Na atom.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The dipole vector surfaces have been calculated in HF approximation; the uppermost dipole vector surface is shown in Fig. 3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met15" novelty="Old" advantage="None">For the interaction energies we used the MCCEPA (multiconfiguration coupled electron pair approximation) program of Fink and Staemmler<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF> and single determinant (HF) reference functions.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met16" novelty="New" advantage="None">In order to justify the approximation for the orientation of the transition dipoles as introduced in section 2 we have carried out test calculations for the Na + N<SB>2</SB> and Na + N<SB>2</SB>O systems, evaluating the transition dipole vectors with correlated wave functions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">It turned out that although the values of the moments may change by up to 10 or 20% (mainly due to the reduced weight of the reference configurations in the correlated function) the orientation angles remain constant within 1° even for geometries close to a conical intersection where the electronic states are considerably mixed.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met17" novelty="New" advantage="None">The potential and transition dipole surfaces were interpolated by two-dimensional spline functions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met18" novelty="New" advantage="None">The derivatives of the potential resulted from local expansions for every grid point and subsequent interpolation by spline functions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">We found the achieved smoothness sufficient for our Monte Carlo based simulation method.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The surfaces can be obtained from the authors on request.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to simulate the population of the fine structure states the adiabatic potential surfaces have to be modified, so that they include the spin–orbit interaction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met19" novelty="New" advantage="None">This can be achieved approximately by diagonalizing the matrix for every point of the 3p-manifold.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod12" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the asymptotic region the three adiabatic energies <IT>e</IT><SB>1</SB>, <IT>e</IT><SB>2</SB> and <IT>e</IT><SB>3</SB> are degenerate and the correct splitting <IT>a</IT> with the spin–orbit coupling constant <IT>a</IT> = 11.5 cm<SP>−1</SP> results for Na(3p).</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met20" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Usually with positive detuning the optical excitation of the collision complex leads exclusively to the population of the highest of the 3p states.</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore under condition of strictly adiabatic dynamics all sodium atoms would be in the <SP>2</SP>P<SB>3/2</SB> state after the collision.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The involved surfaces however show conical intersections which lead to non-adiabatic transitions and to the population of the lower <SP>2</SP>P<SB>1/2</SB> state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met21" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In the asymptotic limit of infinite relative velocity of the colliding particles the <SP>2</SP>P<SB>1/2</SB>/<SP>2</SP>P<SB>3/2</SB> ratio is given by projection of the molecular state after excitation onto the final atomlike states <SP>2</SP>P<SB><IT>J</IT></SB>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus for high collision energy the relative <SP>2</SP>P<SB>1/2</SB> population is expected to approach 33%.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.2">The semiclassical trajectory surface-hopping method</HEADER><P><s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met22" novelty="Old" advantage="None">We use the semiclassical trajectory surface-hopping method developed by Preston and Tully<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12 cit13 cit14 cit15">12–15</REF> which will be reviewed shortly in the following.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod15" novelty="None" advantage="None">For every trajectory the probability of being on the excited surface number <IT>j</IT> is given by the squared absolute value of a time dependent coefficient <IT>c</IT><SB><IT>j</IT></SB>(<IT>t</IT>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The equation for the time derivative <IT>ċ</IT><SB><IT>j</IT></SB>(<IT>t</IT>) can be obtained by inserting the expansion for the electronic wave function <IT>Ψ</IT><SP>el</SP>(<IT>r</IT>,<IT>R</IT>(<IT>t</IT>)) into the time-dependent Schrödinger equation.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14 cit16">14,16</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The nuclear coordinates symbolized by <IT>R</IT>(<IT>t</IT>) are assumed to be functions of time <IT>t</IT> obeying classical equations of motion; <IT>r</IT> stands for the coordinates of the electrons.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod15" novelty="None" advantage="None">In general the resulting expression for <IT>ċ</IT><SB><IT>j</IT></SB>(<IT>t</IT>) contains matrix elements 〈<IT>ψ</IT><SB><IT>j</IT></SB>|<IT>H</IT><SP>el</SP>|<IT>ψ</IT><SB><IT>k</IT></SB>〉 of the electronic Hamiltonian as well as matrix elements of the nuclear coordinate derivatives 〈<IT>ψ</IT><SB><IT>j</IT></SB>|∂/∂<IT>R</IT>|<IT>ψ</IT><SB><IT>k</IT></SB>〉.</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met23" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Conventional quantum chemical programs yield adiabatic wave functions <IT>ψ</IT><SP>a</SP> that diagonalize the electronic Hamiltonian within the space of the electronic wave functions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met23" novelty="Old" advantage="No">The calculation of matrix elements of ∂/∂<IT>R</IT> with these wave functions (neglected in the Born–Oppenheimer approximation) is very time consuming.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the other hand these matrix elements become large in the region of a conical intersection or avoided crossing and are responsible for the radiationless transitions between different (adiabatic) electronic states.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met24" novelty="Old" advantage="None">A unitary transformation leads to a (quasi)-diabatic basis set <IT>ψ</IT><SP>d</SP> of electronic functions,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17 cit18 cit19 cit20">17–20</REF> which change as smoothly as possible with the nuclear coordinates and where the matrix elements of ∂/∂<IT>R</IT> are often assumed to be negligibly small.</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod16" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of only two involved states <IT>ψ</IT>d1 and <IT>ψ</IT>d2 this transformation is determined by the definition of an angle <IT>ϕ</IT> describing the mixing of the adiabatic states and depending on the nuclear coordinates.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod16" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the diabatic picture the matrix of the electronic Hamiltonian is no longer diagonal, but the matrix elements <IT>H</IT><SB>12</SB> = 〈<IT>ψ</IT>d1|<IT>H</IT><SP>el</SP>|<IT>ψ</IT>d2〉 can easily be calculated<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14 cit21">14,21</REF> as soon as the mixing angle is known.</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The expression for the off-diagonal element reads <IT>H</IT><SB>12</SB> = (<IT>E</IT><SB>1</SB> − <IT>E</IT><SB>2</SB>)sin <IT>ϕ</IT> cos <IT>ϕ</IT>, where <IT>E</IT><SB>1</SB> and <IT>E</IT><SB>2</SB> are the adiabatic energies; the corresponding diagonal expressions are <IT>H</IT><SB>11</SB> = <IT>E</IT><SB>1</SB>cos<SP>2</SP><IT>ϕ</IT> + <IT>E</IT><SB>2</SB>sin<SP>2</SP><IT>ϕ</IT> and <IT>H</IT><SB>22</SB> = <IT>E</IT><SB>1</SB>sin<SP>2</SP><IT>ϕ</IT> + <IT>E</IT><SB>2</SB>cos<SP>2</SP><IT>ϕ</IT>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod17" novelty="None" advantage="None">With <IT>a</IT><SB><IT>j</IT></SB> and <IT>b</IT><SB><IT>j</IT></SB> we denote the complex time-dependent coefficients of eqn. (2) in the diabatic and adiabatic basis respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Using the mixing angle <IT>ϕ</IT> the coefficients of the two different pictures can immediately be transformed into each other.</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Including the partial derivatives with respect to the nuclear coordinates the following system of differential equations is obtained<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16 cit21">16,21</REF> where the matrix elements <IT>H</IT><SB><IT>jk</IT></SB>(<IT>R</IT>(<IT>τ</IT>)) and 〈∂/∂<IT>R</IT>〉<SB><IT>jk</IT></SB>(<IT>R</IT>(<IT>τ</IT>)) are implicit functions of the runtime <IT>τ</IT> on the trajectory.</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met25" novelty="Old" advantage="None">These semiclassical equations and the classical equations of motion are solved simultaneously by numerical integration.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met26" novelty="Old" advantage="None">After transformation to (quasi)diabatic electronic wave functions the matrix elements 〈∂/∂<IT>R</IT>〉<SB><IT>jk</IT></SB> may be neglected for intermediate relative velocities <IT>Ṙ</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met27" novelty="New" advantage="None">However in our examples of optical collisions the correct <SP>2</SP>P<SB>1/2</SB> population for the asymptotic case of high velocity can only be obtained by maintaining the full operator.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met27" novelty="New" advantage="None">A simple approximation for 〈∂/∂<IT>R</IT>〉<SB><IT>jk</IT></SB> will be introduced in section 4.1.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The transition to the uppermost 3p surface takes place when a trajectory crosses the line (Condon configuration) corresponding to the appropriate energy difference defined by the detuning.</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod18" novelty="None" advantage="None">At this moment the time-dependent coefficients in the adiabatic picture are set to <IT>b</IT><SB>1</SB> = 1 and <IT>b</IT><SB>2</SB> = 0.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met28" novelty="New" advantage="None">Every trajectory is computed twice, corresponding to the two possibilities of excitation on the incoming and on the outgoing part of the path.</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met28" novelty="New" advantage="None">We denote these two cases with type 1 and type 2 respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met29" novelty="New" advantage="None">The (complex valued) diabatic coefficients <IT>a</IT><SB><IT>j</IT></SB> are computed by numerical integration using eqn. (3) and transformed to <IT>b</IT><SB>1</SB> = <IT>a</IT><SB>1</SB>cos <IT>ϕ</IT> + <IT>a</IT><SB>2</SB>sin <IT>ϕ</IT> and <IT>b</IT><SB>2</SB> = −<IT>a</IT><SB>1</SB>sin <IT>ϕ</IT> + <IT>a</IT><SB>2</SB>cos <IT>ϕ</IT> after every time step.</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met29" novelty="New" advantage="None">When the probability |<IT>b</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB>|<SP>2</SP> falls below 0.5 a random decision is made whether to hop to the other surface or not, and then the coefficients are reset accordingly.</annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met29" novelty="New" advantage="None">In the case of a hop the momentum of nuclear motion has to be corrected in order to ensure energy conservation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met29" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">Following this procedure several hops between the two in plane states including the spin–orbit correction (1) are possible per trajectory.</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">As is to be expected most hops occur not too far from the conical intersection.</annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met30" novelty="New" advantage="None">The number of trajectories ending in the two states <SP>2</SP>P<SB>1/2</SB> and <SP>2</SP>P<SB>3/2</SB> have to be weighted with the values of the impact parameter before being interpreted as probability.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.3">Diabatization</HEADER><P><s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the neighbourhood of a conical intersection the adiabatic wave functions are rapidly changing.</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is illustrated <IT>e.g.</IT> by the behaviour of the orientation of the transition moment vector to the higher <SP>2</SP>A′ state (shown in Figs. 1–3) which in fact maps the orientation of the Na(3p) orbital in the final state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Due to the orthogonality constraint the 3p orbital in the lower excited <SP>2</SP>A′ state (not shown) has an orientation rotated by 90°.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met31" novelty="New" advantage="None">Diabatic wave functions are obtained by a transformation of the mixed adiabatic states (in our case a 2 × 2 rotation) such that a suitable molecular property behaves as smoothly as possible.</annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met31" novelty="New" advantage="None">For that we compare the orientation of the 3p orbitals with the orientation of a classical 3p quadrupole <IT>Q</IT> in the field of the electric multipoles of the target molecule.</annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The classical quadrupole–dipole term of the interaction potential <IT>e.g.</IT> reads where <IT>μ</IT> is the dipole moment of the molecule.</annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod20" novelty="None" advantage="None">The position of the sodium atom relative to the molecule is given in polar coordinates (<IT>R</IT>,<IT>ϑ</IT>) and <IT>α</IT> is the direction angle of the Na quadrupole (with <IT>α</IT> = 0 defined as the direction of the vector connecting the molecule and the sodium atom).</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod21" novelty="None" advantage="None">Analogous expressions hold for the quadrupole-quadrupole interaction and for higher interaction terms; in general the potential <IT>V</IT>(<IT>R</IT>,<IT>ϑ</IT>,<IT>α</IT>) is a sum of such terms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">For energy calculations this approach would not be sufficient because the polarization effects are missing.</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">But as we need only orientation angles and since polarizabilities are essentially isotropic and do not affect the 3p orientation our approximation seems to be justified.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod22" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the classical picture we cannot distinguish two interacting electronic states.</annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod22" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hence there is no conical intersection, but there are two mutually orthogonal angles <IT>α</IT><SB>1</SB> and <IT>α</IT><SB>2</SB> corresponding to minimal and maximal interaction energy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met32" novelty="New" advantage="None">The angles <IT>α</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB> can be determined by the condition The direction <IT>α</IT><SB>1</SB> as a function of <IT>R</IT> and <IT>ϑ</IT> is also shown in Figs. 1 to 3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the asymptotic region far away from the conical intersection the angles <IT>α</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB> coincide with the two directions of the transition dipole moments to the ground state, but they behave smoothly also near the intersection points.</annotationART></s> <s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met33" novelty="New" advantage="None">Therefore we force the 3p orbitals of the diabatic wave functions to coincide with these classical angles everywhere.</annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In other words the deviation of the transition dipole vector direction to the highest 3p surface from the angle <IT>α</IT><SB>1</SB> can serve as a “diabatization angle” <IT>ϕ</IT> defining the transformation to the (quasi)-diabatic states.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that the classical orientation angles are only weakly dependent on the exact values of the molecular multipoles.</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">In all interaction terms (<IT>e.g.</IT> eqn. (4)) the Na quadrupole moment is only a factor which does not affect the <IT>α</IT> values of stationary energy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore it is rather the ratio of the molecular multipole moments than their absolute value which determines the orientation angles.</annotationART></s> <s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met34" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The function <IT>α</IT>(<IT>R</IT>, <IT>ϑ</IT>) has been approximated using the values of the molecular dipole and quadrupole moments given in section 3.1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met35" novelty="New" advantage="None">In addition in order to improve the agreement of the two angles in the areas where there is no mixing of the adiabatic states we have adjusted in a semiempirical way the hexadecupole terms for all three investigated molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Figs. 1 to 3 show the directions of <IT>α</IT><SB>1</SB> and of the transition dipole vectors for the three molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met36" novelty="New" advantage="None">The mixing angle <IT>ϕ</IT> has been determined as difference between these two directions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus in principle the transformation can directly be read from the figures.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In our examples with only two involved states a necessary condition for a considerable change of probability in (3) is that the absolute values of <IT>H</IT><SB>12</SB> and thus of sin <IT>ϕ</IT> and cos <IT>ϕ</IT> are not too small, and this is the case whenever the two adiabatic states are considerably mixed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">It can easily be seen in Figs. 1 to 3 that the necessary mixing angles around 45° are found only in rather restricted regions close to the conical intersections.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4">Results and discussion</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.1">Population of the Na(3p) fine structure states</HEADER><P><s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 4 shows the resulting fine structure populations for optical collisions of Na with the molecules N<SB>2</SB> and N<SB>2</SB>O for the rotational temperature 100 K and at a detuning value of 120 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met37" novelty="New" advantage="None">To facilitate comparison of our trajectory simulations with the experimental results<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF> (and Fig. 5), measured at a laboratory scattering angle of 18°, the abscissa is chosen to be the relative kinetic energy after collision.</annotationART></s> <s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met38" novelty="New" advantage="None">Our <SP>2</SP>P<SB>1/2</SB> fractions represented by solid lines were computed neglecting the matrix elements of ∂/∂<IT>R</IT> in the diabatic picture.</annotationART></s> <s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met38" novelty="New" advantage="None">Instead in order to ensure the correct asymptotic probability (33%) for high relative velocity a simple correction was applied: the matrix element 〈∂/∂<IT>R</IT>〉(<IT>R</IT>,<IT>ϑ</IT>) in (3) was assumed to be proportional to the radial derivative of the mixing angle <IT>ϕ</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met38" novelty="New" advantage="None">The proportionality constant <IT>f</IT> in <IT>Ṙ</IT>〈∂/∂<IT>R</IT>〉<SB>12</SB> ≈ <IT>fṘ</IT>∂<IT>ϕ</IT>(<IT>R</IT>,<IT>ϑ</IT>)/∂<IT>R</IT> was adjusted individually for N<SB>2</SB> and N<SB>2</SB>O at high velocities.</annotationART></s> <s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Maintaining the same constant in the full range of relative motion leads to the dashed curves in Fig. 4.</annotationART></s> <s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The error bars in the figures were determined by separate statistical test runs and do not represent any systematic error of our calculation method.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met39" novelty="New" advantage="None">A qualitative discussion of the results has to consider the position of the conical intersection as well as the Na-molecule distance at which the optical excitation occurs.</annotationART></s> <s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">For Na + N<SB>2</SB> the location of the conical intersection is definitely the most favorable for a high <SP>2</SP>P<SB>1/2</SB> fraction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="143"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our calculated percentage, which is slightly decreasing in the investigated range of collision energy, is in excellent agreement with measurement.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="144"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The relative contribution of type 2 trajectories on the <SP>2</SP><IT>P</IT><SB>1/2</SB> surface decreases from about 50% to about 25% with increasing relative velocity.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="145"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the Na + N<SB>2</SB>O system the 120 cm<SP>−1</SP> Condon line is situated at a radial distance which lies just inside the conical intersection.</annotationART></s> <s sid="146"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus less than 10% of the <SP>2</SP>P<SB>1/2</SB> trajectories are of type 2 except for very low collisional energy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="147"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The experimental population of the lower spin–orbit state is reproduced satisfactorily by our computations for this collision complex too.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="148"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Only excitations to the uppermost 3p surface were taken into account in the calculations for Na + N<SB>2</SB> and Na + N<SB>2</SB>O. In the case of Na + C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>2</SB> corresponding simulations lead to a population of the <SP>2</SP>P<SB>1/2</SB> state which is considerably much lower than according to the experiment.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="149"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The conical intersection is located in collinear geometry for C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>2</SB>, what means that much fewer trajectories pass through this region of strong mixing than for N<SB>2</SB> and N<SB>2</SB>O, where the non-adiabatic coupling is strong at T-shaped geometry.</annotationART></s> <s sid="150"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Further the Condon configuration for the detuning by 120 cm<SP>−1</SP> is situated clearly outside of the conical intersection region on the C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>2</SB> surface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="151"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">For that reason no non-adiabatic transitions to the <SP>2</SP>P<SB>1/2</SB> state can result from type 2 trajectories for C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="152"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The calculated <SP>2</SP>P<SB>1/2</SB> populations for Na + C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>2</SB> at a detuning value of 120 cm<SP>−1</SP> and for the rotational temperature 100 K are shown in Fig. 6.</annotationART></s> <s sid="153"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The low probability of non-adiabatic transitions in the case of Na + C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>2</SB> represented by the dashed curves is not able to explain the rather high measured <SP>2</SP>P<SB>1/2</SB> fraction.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="154"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">But in contrast to the other two investigated molecules the energy differences between the 3p surfaces are much smaller, so that excitations of the lower two 3p states are possible.</annotationART></s> <s sid="155"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">At a detuning of 120 cm<SP>−1</SP> the number of excitations to the uppermost surface is about three times higher than to each one of the lower surfaces.</annotationART></s> <s sid="156"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod23" novelty="None" advantage="None">After excitation to the lower one of the two mixed A′ surfaces most trajectories will contribute to the <SP>2</SP>P<SB>1/2</SB> population because of the low non-adiabatic transition likelihood.</annotationART></s> <s sid="157"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met40" novelty="New" advantage="None">The third state (A″) with the <SP>2</SP>P<SB>3/2</SB> asymptotic limit was assumed not to mix with the other two states.</annotationART></s> <s sid="158"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results represented by solid lines in Fig. 6 were obtained including excitations to all three surfaces and are in good agreement with experiment.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="159"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">A test calculation for Na + N<SB>2</SB>O showed that less than 15% of the excitations take place to the lower A′ state and many of these trajectories jump back to the uppermost surface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="160"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">So it seems reasonable to consider only excitations to the highest 3p surface except for the system Na + C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.2">Polarization and alignment</HEADER><P><s sid="161"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">As mentioned in section 2 the intensity of the Na(3s → 3p) transition depends on the polarization direction angle <IT>β</IT> of the excitation laser.</annotationART></s> <s sid="162"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Table 1 shows classical trajectory results for the scattering angle <IT>Θ</IT><SB>CM</SB> = 40° and several values of the detuning frequency.</annotationART></s> <s sid="163"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">A qualitative discussion of this method can be found in .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">ref. 2</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="164"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met41" novelty="New" advantage="None"><IT>β</IT> is measured relative to the incidence direction of the Na atom.</annotationART></s> <s sid="165"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">For example <IT>β</IT> = <IT>Θ</IT><SB>CM</SB> denotes the situation where polarization is parallel to the Na momentum vector after collision.</annotationART></s> <s sid="166"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">For all three examined molecules the weight of the type 1 trajectories is dominant, leading to an optimal polarization direction in backward direction (<IT>β</IT> &gt; 90°).</annotationART></s> <s sid="167"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">Figs. 1, 2 and 3 are useful for a qualitative understanding: For large detuning frequencies the transition dipole vector points more or less in radial direction towards the center of mass of the molecule for all possible Condon points.</annotationART></s> <s sid="168"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">The distance between the condon points for type 1 and type 2 trajectories decreases with increasing detuning, resulting in alignment angles near 90° and large alignment ratios.</annotationART></s> <s sid="169"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">For 120 cm<SP>−1</SP> detuning frequency the direction of the transition dipole vector shows more variation for Na + N<SB>2</SB>O and Na + C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>2</SB>, explaining the rather small alignment ratios.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="170"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met42" novelty="New" advantage="None">The calculated alignment results may be compared with measurements for Na + N<SB>2</SB> and Na + C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>2</SB><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2 cit3">2,3</REF> (and Table 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="171"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">While the experimental data are reproduced satisfactorily for the N<SB>2</SB> system the rotation of the alignment angle and the decrease of the alignment ratio at small detuning frequency are clearly underestimated for C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>2</SB> by our calculations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="172"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met42" novelty="New" advantage="None">In the case of C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>2</SB> excitations to all three surfaces of the 3<IT>p</IT>-manifold were included.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="5">Summary and conclusion</HEADER><P><s sid="173"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The presented results for the population of the Na(3p) fine structure states after an optical collision with a linear molecule are in good agreement with the experiment.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="174"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met43" novelty="New" advantage="None">Our simulations are based on quantum chemically calculated potential energy surfaces and dipole moment functions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="175"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Nuclear dynamics was treated in the framework of the semiclassical surface hopping method.</annotationART></s> <s sid="176"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met44" novelty="New" advantage="None">In order to test the effect of molecular vibration we introduced a harmonic potential for N<SB>2</SB> allowing the exchange of vibrational energy with the other degrees of freedom.</annotationART></s> <s sid="177"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" advantage="None">Neither for the population of the Na(3p) fine structure states nor for the alignment direction and ratio a significant change within the statistical uncertainty could be found.</annotationART></s> <s sid="178"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">We therefore conclude that our assumption of fixed molecular geometry is a reasonable approximation.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="179"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None">The analysis of the results for the <SP>2</SP><IT>P</IT><SB>1/2</SB> fraction after collision shows a sensitive dependence on the details of the energy surfaces, the non-adiabatic mixing of states and especially on the location of the conical intersections.</annotationART></s> <s sid="180"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met45" novelty="New" advantage="None">The experimentally observed dependence of the Na(3s → 3p) transition intensity on the polarization direction angle of the excitation laser may be understood qualitatively from the properties of the potential and dipole moment surfaces.</annotationART></s> <s sid="181"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None">The deviations between experiment and simulation are largest for small detuning frequencies.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="182"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The success of our simulations of the optical collision experiments is a strong indication for the correct understanding of the underlying physical processes.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
