<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b313261g" hasDoc="yes" version="1184" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Biomimetic synthesis of silica nanospheres depends on the aggregation and phase separation of polyamines in aqueous solution</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Long-chain polyamines extracted from the highly siliceous cell walls of diatoms are known to precipitate silica nanospheres from aqueous, silicic-acid containing solutions at near-neutral pH <IT>in vitro</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The same is true for synthetic polyamines such as polyallylamine.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the present contribution we show that the microscopic phase separation of polyallylamine in aqueous solution is strictly correlated with the silica precipitation activity of polyallylamine/silicic acid solutions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Multivalent anions such as phosphate or sulfate efficiently induce this microscopic phase separation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">At higher anion concentrations, macroscopic phase separation occurs.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast to the multivalent phosphate and sulfate ions, the monovalent chloride ions are much less efficient in polyallylamine aggregate formation.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Diatom cell walls are outstanding examples for nanoscale structured materials in nature.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">They consist of an amorphous composite material containing silica as well as certain biomolecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The latter are assumed to play a crucial role in diatom cell wall formation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Examples for such biomolecules are the so-called silaffins isolated from the diatom <IT>Cylindrotheca fusiformis</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">2</REF> as well as the long-chain polyamines extracted from the cell walls of species such as <IT>Nitzschia angularis</IT>, <IT>Stephanopyxis turris</IT>, and others.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both these classes of molecules were also shown to precipitate silica from aqueous solutions containing silicic acid <IT>in vitro</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The precipitates formed by the long-chain polyamines from <IT>S. turris</IT> consist of nanospheres exhibiting a surprisingly narrow size distribution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The particle diameter was shown to be strictly controlled by the concentration of phosphate ions added to the solutions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Initial NMR and dynamic light scattering experiments carried out on long-chain polyamines isolated from <IT>S. turris</IT> have shown that these molecules self-assemble in aqueous solutions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Silaffins from <IT>C. fusiformis</IT> behave very similarly.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is tempting to speculate that the aggregates (droplets) formed by the biomolecules in solution act as templates during cell wall formation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">A model based on phase separation processes could be developed which explains the pattern formation in diatom cell walls.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Inspired by these observations, a number of synthetic amino acids, peptides, and polyamines were shown to precipitate silica from aqueous solutions as well.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7 cit8 cit9 cit10 cit11">7–11</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">New opportunities for the so-called biomimetic silica synthesis are likely to arise from these discoveries.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">One particularly interesting example is polyallylamine (PAA), a commercially available compound.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">It exhibits a long-chain structure similar to the polyamines found in diatoms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Polyallylamine was also shown to catalyze the polycondensation of silicic acid<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF> and to precipitate silica.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The topic of the present paper is the detailed physico-chemical characterisation of PAA in aqueous solution especially with respect to the question whether or not an aggregation of the PAA molecules is a prerequisite for their silica-precipitating function as it is the case for the above-mentioned biomolecules extracted from diatoms.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Experimental</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Materials</HEADER><P><s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Polyallylamine hydrochloride (PAA) was purchased from Aldrich.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The PAA molecule exhibits a repeated unit (ru) of the following structure: [–CH<SB>2</SB>CH(CH<SB>2</SB>NH<SB>2</SB>˙HCl)–]<IT><SB>n</SB></IT> with <IT>n</IT> ∼ 160 corresponding to a molecular weight of <IT>ca.</IT> 15 kDa.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>NMR and dynamic light scattering experiments</HEADER><P><s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">NMR spectra were acquired on a DMX-500 spectrometer (Bruker, Karlsruhe, Germany) operating at 500 MHz <SP>1</SP>H resonance frequency.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The calibration of the <SP>31</SP>P NMR spectra was performed using H<SB>3</SB>PO<SB>4</SB> (85%) as an external reference.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Dynamic light scattering (DLS) experiments were carried out on a MALVERN HPPS5001 nanosizer.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the NMR and dynamic light scattering analyses, the polyallylamine hydrochloride was dissolved in millipore water.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">A concentration of 1 mM PAA was chosen.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">The desired concentration of orthophosphate ions (Pi) was obtained by the addition of the corresponding amount of sodium dihydrogen phosphate to the samples.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="New" advantage="None">The final pH value was adjusted to 5.8 by the addition of NaOH.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">Sulfate containing samples were prepared by the addition of sodium sulfate and chloride containing samples by the addition of sodium chloride.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Before the measurements, all solutions were allowed to equilibrate for at least 2 days.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER><IT>In vitro</IT> precipitation of silica and SEM analysis</HEADER><P><s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the silica precipitation experiments, a freshly prepared solution of 1 M tetramethoxysilane in 1 mM HCl was incubated at 20 °C for 15 min and immediately used as a source of monosilicic/disilicic acid.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">A typical precipitation assay contained in 50 µl: 0.2 mM polyallylamine and phosphate (5 to 25 mM).</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Silica formation was initiated by the addition of 2 µl silicic acid, prepared as described above.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp10" novelty="None" advantage="None">After 12 min at 20 °C, precipitated silica was collected by centrifugation (4 min, 12.000 rpm).</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The precipitate was washed twice with water, then suspended in water, applied to an aluminium sample holder, and air dried.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Silica precipitates were analyzed without sputter-coating with a LEO1530 field-emission scanning electron microscope equipped with energy dispersive X-ray analysis (EDXA, Oxford Instruments).</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Colorimetric determination of silica precipitates was performed by the molybdenum blue method<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF> after dissolving precipitated silica in 20 µl 2 M NaOH (85 °C, 5 min).</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Results and discussion</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>The influence of phosphate ions</HEADER><P><s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 1 summarizes the results of silica precipitation experiments carried out for samples containing various amounts of phosphate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The amount of silica precipitated from the PAA/silicic acid solution is plotted as a function of the phosphate concentration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Silica precipitation takes place only above a threshold value of <IT>ca.</IT> 0.3 [Pi]/[ru].</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Below, no silica precipitates at all indicating a crucial role of the phosphate ions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is interesting to note in this context that the PAA-induced silica precipitation experiments described by Patwardhan <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF>. were carried out in a phosphate-containing buffer solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, the particle diameter of the silica nanospheres precipitated by PAA is correlated with the phosphate concentration in complete analogy to the observations made for the long-chain polyamines extracted from <IT>S. turris.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The maximum particle diameter of <IT>ca.</IT> 3 µm strongly exceeds the maximum value of about 1 µm obtained for the polyamines from <IT>S. turris.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">A possible explanation for this behaviour is the much smaller size of the polyamines from <IT>S. turris</IT> (1.55 kDa molecular weight).</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the other hand, the particles precipitated by the synthetic polyallylamine exhibit a much broader size distribution than the nanospheres obtained by using polyamines from <IT>S. turris</IT>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to understand this behaviour, we have studied aqueous PAA solutions of various phosphate concentrations by dynamic light scattering (see Fig. 2).</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the absence of phosphate, aggregates of an average diameter of about 1 nm could be detected.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">For a single PAA molecule, one would expect a diameter of the same order of magnitude.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">This leads to the conclusion that the PAA molecules exist as single molecules (monomers) or small clusters in the absence of phosphate ions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Addition of phosphate results in a continuous but slow increase of the aggregate diameter up to about 5 nm at 0.25 [Pi]/[ru].</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note, that this phosphate concentration is close to to the above-mentioned threshold value of <IT>ca.</IT> 0.3 [Pi]/[ru] necessary for silica precipitation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">A rapid increase of the aggregate diameter is observed beyond this threshold value.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">At 0.31 [Pi]/[ru], aggregates of about 120 nm diameter could be detected.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Visual inspection shows that the samples become cloudy at this concentration which confirms the existence of larger aggregates (see Fig. 3).</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">If the phosphate concentration is further increased, the samples remain cloudy up to about 0.5 [Pi]/[ru].</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">DLS measurements show that the aggregate diameter increases up to almost 600 nm at 0.44 [Pi]/[ru] while a decreased value could be found at 0.5 [Pi]/[ru].</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">This decrease can be explained as follows: <SP>1</SP>H NMR studies show that more than 2/3 of the polyamine has disappeared from the part of the sample inserted into the NMR tube.<SUP TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" /></annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Obviously, this amount of polyamine already sediments at the bottom of the sample without forming a visible separate phase.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The decreased concentration of polyamine in the top part of the sample must be responsible for the decreasing diameter of the aggregates.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">At 0.63 [Pi]/[ru] and higher concentrations, the samples become clear after equilibration but exhibit a macroscopic phase separation: A separate phase containing the polyamine is formed at the bottom of the tube.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The aqueous phase on top does no longer contain a detectable amount of polyamine aggregates.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The observed aggregation and phase separation can be explained by the attractive electrostatic interactions between the positively charged polyamine molecules and the negatively charged phosphate ions<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF> and/or the formation of hydrogen bonds.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Comparison of Figs. 1 and 2 shows that the formation of the described large polyamine aggregates, <IT>i.e.</IT>, microscopic phase separation is correlated with the capability of the system to precipitate silica from a PAA/silicic acid solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">If, however, macroscopic phase separation takes place, <IT>i.e.</IT> for phosphate concentrations significantly exceeding 0.5 [Pi]/[ru], the solution looses its silica precipitation activity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">That means, microscopic phase separation is a necessary prerequisite for silica precipitation by the polyamine solution.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">In order to characterize the physico-chemical properties of this microscopically phase separated solution in more detail, extended <SP>31</SP>P and <SP>1</SP>H NMR spectroscopic studies were carried out.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">For all samples, only one single <SP>31</SP>P signal is observed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The chemical shift, <IT>δ</IT>, as well as the linewidth, Δ<IT>ν</IT><SB>1/2</SB>, (full-width-at-half-maximum) of this signal, however, change.</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The chemical shift is plotted as a function of phosphate concentration in Fig. 4 (top).</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">It remains almost constant up to about 0.3 [Pi]/[ru].</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Beyond this phosphate concentration, <IT>δ</IT> continuously decreases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None">At phosphate concentrations higher than 0.6 [Pi]/[ru], that means in the range of macroscopic phase separation, the chemical shift is again nearly constant and amounts to <IT>ca.</IT> 1.2 ppm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">As the solution in the NMR tube<SUP TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" /> is almost completely free of polyamine at high phosphate concentrations, the latter chemical shift value represents free phosphate ions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">From the observation that only a single signal is observed for all concentrations it is concluded that phosphate ions interacting with the polyamine rapidly exchange with free phosphate ions (on the time scale of NMR spectroscopy).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14 cit15">14,15</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The increased and constant chemical shift at low phosphate concentrations indicates that phosphate is preferentially bound to the polyamine molecules up to about 0.3 [Pi]/[ru].</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Above this concentration, an increasing amount of free phosphate exists which results in the described decrease of chemical shift.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The linewidth of the <SP>31</SP>P NMR signals (Fig. 4, bottom) also exhibits an interesting behaviour.</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None">From an initial value of about 4 Hz it increases up to about 12 Hz for 0.4 [Pi]/[ru].</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" advantage="None">At higher concentrations, Δ<IT>ν</IT><SB>1/2</SB> decreases until a constant value of 1.6 Hz is found for the aqueous part of the macroscopically phase-separated samples.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">This behaviour can be explained as follows: Due to the rapid exchange between phosphate bound to the polyamine aggregates and free phosphate, an average linewidth is observed.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14 cit15">14,15</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is known from the chemical shift analysis that the phosphate ions are preferentially bound to the polyamine aggregates at low phosphate concentrations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The linewidth, therefore, corresponds to the linewidth in the polyamine-bound state for low phosphate concentrations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since an increasing aggregate diameter (see Fig. 2) results in a lower correlation time of rotational diffusion, an increasing linewidth is expected for increasing phosphate concentrations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is in agreement with the experimentally observed behaviour up to 0.4 [Pi]/[ru] (Fig. 4, bottom).</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">For concentrations above 0.4 [Pi]/[ru], the influence of the increasing amount of free phosphate is observed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the linewidth of free phosphate is smaller than that of polyamine-bound phosphate, the measured average linewidth then decreases with increasing phosphate concentration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">After macroscopic phase separation took place, only free phosphate exists in the NMR samples giving rise to the small and constant linewidth of 1.6 Hz observed for high phosphate concentrations.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>The influence of sulfate and chloride ions</HEADER><P><s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">The influence of sulfate and chloride ions upon aqueous solutions of PAA was also investigated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The behaviour of sulfate, another multivalent anion, turned out be very similar compared to phosphate: The solutions become cloudy at about 0.3 [sulfate]/[ru] and exhibit macroscopic phase separation above 0.5 [sulfate]/[ru].</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None">This behaviour shows that the ability to phase-separate aqueous PAA solutions must not be considered to be a specific property of phosphate ions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is striking that both, phosphate and sulfate are multivalent anions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None">The question arises whether or not monovalent anions such as chloride can also be used to induce the described effects.</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 5 shows the diameter of the polyamine aggregates determined by dynamic light scattering as a function of chloride ion concentration.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Obviously, aggregates of increasing diameter are observed at increasing chloride concentrations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, even for the highest chloride concentration (<IT>ca.</IT> 20 [Cl]/[ru]), the obtained aggregate diameter of <IT>ca.</IT> 9 nm is almost two orders of magnitude smaller than the maximum aggregate diameter of <IT>ca.</IT> 600 nm observed for a phosphate concentration of only 0.44 [Pi]/[ru].</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs20" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is furthermore important to note that the macroscopic phase separation found for phosphate and sulfate does not occur for chloride ions even at about 20 [Cl]/[ru].</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">That means, the monovalent chloride ions are much less efficient in attracting the PAA molecules compared to the multivalent phosphate and sulfate ions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">In agreement with these observations, no silica is precipitated at all from the chloride-containing PAA solutions even at chloride concentrations up to <IT>ca.</IT> 20 [Cl]/[ru] which is far beyond the physiologically relevant level.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None">In summary, it can be stated that microscopic phase separation is necessary for the PAA-induced silica precipitation from silicic-acid containing aqueous solutions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None">This microscopic phase separation can be induced by the addition of multivalent anions such as phosphate or sulfate to the aqueous solutions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Polysilicic acid molecules may be adsorbed on and/or dissolved in the polyamine microdroplets thereby forming a coacervate which hardens by silica formation.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
