<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b315069k" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Calculations of PAH anions: When are diffuse functions necessary?<XREF TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" /></annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">The effect of including <IT>vs</IT>. excluding diffuse functions while calculating numerous parameters of PAH anions by various calculation methods is discussed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The omission of diffuse functions appears to have a negligible effect while calculating geometry parameters or total energy; thus, acceptable results may be obtained without them.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The conclusions for charge density appear to be the same; however, limited results make an unambiguous claim unachievable.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Calculating <SP>1</SP>H- and <SP>13</SP>C-NMR shifts undoubtedly requires the use of these functions.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">For some time now, computational chemistry has been an important tool for probing, observing, explaining and verifying what had been discovered experimentally.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">2</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">Calculations may verify or refute results still in question, or explain chemical, physical and other phenomena, whilst discovering previously unknown trends.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Combining experiment and theory results in a powerful and efficient instrument, enabling study of any kind of chemistry.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Theoretical chemistry, therefore, is an important tool, having a critical position as a companion to experimental results, playing a significant role in the advancement and development of today's chemistry in general, and the research in polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbon (PAH) anions, in particular.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">In this paper we are concerned with the necessity of diffuse functions in the calculation of large conjugated anions, especially PAH anions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">PAH anions have also been the focus of extensive research, as they exhibit extraordinary properties, pertaining to key questions of much interest in organic chemistry.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3 cit4 cit5 cit6">3–6</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The study of PAH anions is widespread, particularly in organic chemistry as they are models for charged graphite, fullerenes and other carbon-based compounds.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Additionally, interest in PAHs and their anions ranges from synthetic,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF> medicinal and biological<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF> chemistry, to environmental<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF> and interstellar<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF> chemistry.</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Theoretical characterization of PAHs and their anions is therefore critical to understanding their reactivity.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The heart of straightforward calculations is the proper choice of basis sets.</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Improvement of a calculation, in order to obtain more reliable and accurate results, closer to experimental values, is possible <IT>via</IT> a change in the calculation protocol.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">For instance, one may use an extended basis set, utilizing three or more lobes to describe an orbital; or employ polarization functions,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF> describing the change imposed on an orbital during the transition from free to bonded state.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Diffuse functions constitute a further effort to improve theory.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Just as the insertion of extra electrons into orbitals brings about their natural growth in order to reduce the Coulomb repulsion, so must a theoretical calculation allow for expression of such a change.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">Development of diffuse functions allowed orbital flexibility during calculation, allowing a more accurate description of the true, diminished electron repulsion, mainly for anions, and lowering the estimate of total energy, in accordance with the variation principle.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The use of diffuse functions originated from the calculation of atomic anions, such as for H<SP>−</SP>, F<SP>−</SP>, Li<SP>−</SP> and O<SP>−</SP>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The investigation of such anions demonstrated that without diffuse functions, even stable anions, such as O<SP>−</SP>, Cl<SP>−</SP> and F<SP>−</SP> are calculated to be unstable.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Calculating anions without diffuse functions generally overestimates mutual electron repulsion,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF> and even gives false interactions of each electron with itself.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Various small anions have been shown to commonly need diffuse functions for useful calculations.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Moreover, it has been shown that standard basis sets using <IT>only one</IT> set of diffuse functions for calculating properties of small anions may give inadequate results, indicating the necessity for double-diffuse functions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is important to note that in <IT>all</IT> these cases, assumptions regarding the necessity of diffuse functions were based on calculations of anions with <IT>point</IT> charges.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In such cases, the charge is almost entirely located on a <IT>single</IT> atom.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">These and other<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF> difficulties lead to the supposition that standard calculations are not appropriate for negative atomic and molecular anions, and eventually resulted in the inclusion of diffuse functions as a general prerequisite for reliable anionic calculations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">This pertained to small molecular anions, as well as to atomic anions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Duke's work<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF> on the methyl anion showed that the inclusion of diffuse functions proved to be critical for adequate representation of the anion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Even relatively small basis sets including diffuse functions, such as 3-21+G, were found to describe the geometries and proton affinities of small molecular anions, such as BeH<SP>−</SP>, BH<SB>2</SB><SP>−</SP>, NH<SB>2</SB><SP>−</SP> and OH<SP>−</SP>, fairly accurately.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">While calculating equilibrium geometries, the inversion barrier and other properties of CH<SB>3</SB><SP>−</SP> and CH<SB>3</SB> using <IT>ab initio</IT> methods, Driessler showed<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19">19</REF> that SCF values obtained using diffuse functions were substantially more accurate than previous results calculated without them.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Driessler's results reinforced Duke's,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF> also showing that, lacking diffuse functions, one obtains positive orbital energy for the highest occupied orbitals for negative anions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Davidson and Schaefer both independently confirmed this later on.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The necessity of diffuse functions in calculations and their contribution to various properties have been widely studied.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21 cit22 cit23 cit24 cit25 cit26a cit26b cit26c">21–26<IT>a–c</IT></REF> The importance of diffuse functions has been investigated with respect to polarizibility and dipole and quadruple moments,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21a cit21b cit21c">21<IT>a–c</IT></REF> relative,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22a">22<IT>a</IT></REF> binding<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22b cit22c">22<IT>b</IT>,<IT>c</IT></REF> and reaction<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21c cit22d">21<IT>c</IT>,22<IT>d</IT></REF> energies, as well as electronic interactions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The effect of diffuse functions on vibrational frequencies,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22b">22<IT>b</IT></REF> electron transfer,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF> hyperfine splitting constants<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25">25</REF> and conformational energy<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22d">22<IT>d</IT></REF> has also been studied.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The necessity of diffuse functions for calculating electron affinity has especially been examined.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21a cit22b cit24 cit25 cit26">21<IT>a</IT>,22<IT>b</IT>,24–26</REF> The relation between geometry and diffuse functions has also been analyzed,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21c cit22b cit25 cit26a">21<IT>c</IT>,22<IT>b</IT>,25,26<IT>a</IT></REF> although mostly for small and specific families of compounds.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Generally speaking, in almost all cases, the introduction of diffuse functions into the calculation improved calculation results substantially.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, while the use of larger and/or more complex basis sets usually yields more accurate results, this is almost always accompanied by a significant increase in calculation effort and time.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is <IT>particularly</IT> evident for large molecules, such as PAHs.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">A calculation with diffuse functions for PAHs is difficult and often quite impractical, since these large molecules may contain a sizeable number of atoms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Such calculations require augmented computational resources, calculation times can be larger by a full order of magnitude, and failures in convergence are common.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot4" novelty="None" advantage="None">At the same time, the actual necessity of diffuse functions for these types of molecules can be questioned.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The distribution of charge over a large spatial area reduces inter-electron repulsion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Additionally, charged PAHs may exhibit enhanced delocalization of π-electrons, for through this method, they attain aromatic stability.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None">Thus, an examination of the actual contribution and necessity of diffuse functions for several specific cases has been undertaken.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Is it possible that through size and delocalization PAH anions reduce inter-electron repulsion to such a degree that the use of diffuse functions is not necessary to accurately describe the system?</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot5" novelty="None" advantage="None">At the present time, the few DFT calculations performed on PAH anions have not extensively examined all parameters in this work.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26 cit27">26,27</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this paper, we present calculated results regarding the above question.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Computational details</HEADER><P><s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">All computations were carried out using the GAUSSIAN '98 program package,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28">28</REF> with the exception of NBO analyses,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29">29</REF> which employed JAGUAR 4.0 software.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30">30</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="New" advantage="None">All calculations of molecule parameters were carried out at a DFT level employing Becke's three-parameter hybrid density functional with the non-local correlation functional of Lee, Yang and Parr (B3LYP),<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit31 cit32">31,32</REF> and with Hartree–Fock methods.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="New" advantage="None">Four different basis sets were used: 6-31G*, 6-31+G*, 6-311G** and 6-311+G**;<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit33 cit34">33,34</REF> thus, each molecule was calculated with a total of eight different methods.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="New" advantage="None">All structures calculated were geometrically optimized within their highest symmetry point groups, and harmonic vibrational frequencies were computed to confirm that the stationary points correspond to minima.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="New" advantage="None">Only minimum energy structures were considered for NMR and NBO calculations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">NMR chemical shifts were derived from additional single point calculations employing the GIAO<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit35">35</REF> method as implemented in GAUSSIAN '98.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="New" advantage="None">The isotropy values obtained in this way were subtracted from the respective isotropy values obtained for optimized TMS<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit36">36</REF> (see ESI)<SUP TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" /> in order to obtain NMR chemical shifts.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Methodology</HEADER><P><s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj5" novelty="New" advantage="None">Primary parameters evaluated in this work are geometry (bond lengths and intramolecular angles), total energy, <SP>1</SP>H- and <SP>13</SP>C-NMR chemical shifts and charge density (on carbons and protons, though the density on carbons are of main interest).</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj5" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">While other properties, some more sensitive to diffuse functions, such as electron affinities, dipole moments and polarizabilities could also be examined, we nevertheless chose to focus on parameters central to PAH anion research generally, and particularly to systems previously studied in our laboratory.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit37">37</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj6" novelty="New" advantage="None">Various aspects, such as size, conjugation ability, charge states and systems with or without five- and six-membered rings were sampled.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj7" novelty="New" advantage="None">For these goals, calculations were made on a large series of different anions (mostly PAHs), namely, methyl (<B>1</B>), ethyl (<B>2</B>), <IT>n</IT>-propyl (<B>3</B>), iso-propyl (<B>4</B>), <IT>n</IT>-butyl (<B>5</B>), <IT>tert</IT>-butyl (<B>6</B>), formate (<B>7</B>), acetate (<B>8</B>), indenyl (<B>9</B>), fluorenyl (<B>10</B>) and cyclopentadienyl (<B>11</B>) anions (Scheme 1); and the acenaphthalene (<B>12</B>), pentalene (<B>13</B>), pyracylene (<B>14</B>), pyrene (<B>15</B>), phenanthrene (<B>16</B>), anthracene (<B>17</B>), tetracene (<B>18</B>), fluoranthene (<B>19</B>), indenofluoranthene (<B>20</B>), and cyclooctatetraene (<B>21</B>) dianions (Scheme 2).</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="New" advantage="None">Various comparisons were made in order to determine the effect of the use of diffuse functions on the different parameters calculated.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Results and discussion</HEADER><P><s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Taking indenyl anion (<B>9</B> and Scheme 3) as a general example, the results arising from calculations with diffuse functions are practically identical to those arising from calculations without these functions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit38">38</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="New" advantage="None">The comparisons typically performed weigh parameters for the four calculations performed with diffuse functions (HF/6-31+G*, HF/6-311+G**, B3LYP/6-31+G*, B3LYP/6-311+G**) against the analogous ones without them.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The largest difference relating to the molecular bond lengths, between results arising from the HF/6-31+G* calculation and those acquired from using the HF/6-31G* method is only 0.004 Å.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit38">38</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This corresponds to only 0.28% of the respective bond length.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit39">39</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">For all other comparisons (<IT>i.e.</IT> between other basis sets and calculation methods), the difference is at most the same value.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The largest difference in intramolecular angles (between the same two calculation methods and basis sets) was 0.194°, 0.15% of the respective angle.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Only the difference between B3LYP/6-31+G* calculated values and those obtained from B3LYP/6-31G* is larger; 0.202°, also 0.15% of its respective angle.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Examining the calculated total energy, one finds similar results: Δ<IT>E</IT> is 0.032 au between B3LYP/6-31+G* and B3LYP/6-31G*, and smaller still for all other three comparisons.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In comparison, the differences relating to charge densities and particularly to NMR shifts were somewhat larger.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The largest difference relating to charge density on carbons was 0.02 charge units (HF/6-31+G* <IT>vs.</IT> HF/6-31G*), equaling a 7.63% difference of charge density on the corresponding carbon atom.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The largest differences for NMR shifts were 7.60 ppm for carbons (B3LYP/6-31+G* <IT>vs.</IT> B3LYP/6-31G*), and 0.70 ppm for protons (HF/6-311+G** <IT>vs.</IT> HF/6-311G**).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit40">40</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the whole, most differences appear to be quite small, sometimes exceptionally so, to a point where they are insignificant.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">As we shall see, this appears to be the case in most instances for calculated PAH anions in the present work.</annotationART></s></P><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Geometry</HEADER><P><s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="New" advantage="None">By comparing the basis sets 6-31G* with 6-31+G* and 6-311G** with 6-311+G** for HF and B3LYP separately, and by plotting the maximum differences for each parameter against the number of atoms in the skeleton,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit41">41</REF> one can obtain four different figures for each calculated parameter.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 1 shows that the comparison between the B3LYP/6-311G** and 6-311+G** calculations,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit42">42</REF> methods that differ only by a single diffuse function, show highly different behavior for four different types of anions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Anions derived from regular saturated alkanes, such as the methyl and ethyl anions, have a fairly large difference for Δ<IT>r</IT><SB>max</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, without the use of diffuse functions, calculated geometries of small anionic molecules with significant charge density show considerable errors, reinforcing Duke<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF> and Driessler's<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19">19</REF> results. <IT>n</IT>-Propyl (<B>3</B>) and <IT>n</IT>-butyl (<B>5</B>) behave similarly.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the alteration of these anions to iso-propyl (<B>4</B>) and <IT>tert</IT>-butyl (<B>6</B>) give rise to a considerable reduction in Δ<IT>r</IT><SB>max</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The average figures are approximately three-fold smaller than those for their <IT>n</IT>-alkyl analogues.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The difference in connectivity of these sets of molecules is apparently significant to their stability.</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ability for hyperconjugation in these anions apparently disperses the charge in a much more effective way than in the <IT>n</IT>-alkyl anions; thus, the effect of diffuse functions in the calculation becomes less noticeable.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is important to note that comparisons for all other three pairs of basis sets show similar results.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The two models for resonance-stablized anions in this study, formate and acetate, indeed both show a much smaller Δ<IT>r</IT><SB>max</SB> than for <IT>n</IT>-alkyls, even ones with the same number of atoms in their skeleton.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">It can be rationalized that the negative charge is much less localized in these resonance-stabled anions compared with those of the <IT>n</IT>-alkyls, where the charge resembles more of a point charge.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Bond lengths in resonance stabilized molecules are therefore less susceptible to changes due to extra charge compared with <IT>n</IT>-alkyls, and parameters calculated with functions taking this charge into consideration are therefore less likely to be significantly different from those calculated without these functions.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">For cyclopentadienyl anion (<B>11</B>) and cyclooctatetraene dianions<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit43">43</REF> (<B>21</B>), Δ<IT>r</IT><SB>max</SB> drops off even further.</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the PAHs, Δ<IT>r</IT><SB>max</SB> is of the same order.</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is understandable, as most PAHs discussed here contain both aromatic stabilization (similar to the resonance stability of formate (<B>7</B>) and acetate (<B>8</B>) anions) <IT>and</IT> a large number of atoms in their skeleton.</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The order of magnitude of maximum bond length difference obtained for the indenyl anion, the smallest PAH studied, is already extremely small, and repeats itself for almost all other PAHs whose geometrical values were calculated in this work.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The only anomaly appears to be for the calculated differences of tetracene dianion (<B>18</B>), between 6-311G** and 6-311+G** in the Hartree–Fock method.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit38">38</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None">This may be due to the known fact that bond lengths in neutral tetracene deviate largely from each other: the longest bond being 1.452 Å, the shortest, 1.367 Å.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit44">44</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Bond lengths at the central ring of phenanthrene show similar magnitudes of Δ<IT>r</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Structural criteria are important in defining aromatic molecules.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit45">45</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Nevertheless, neither the aromaticity of tetracene nor that of phenanthrene<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit46">46</REF> is questioned, and in any case, this aberration does not recur for the other parameters calculated for tetracene.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">Intramolecular angles show the same trend as that seen for bond lengths.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 2 shows that the comparison between B3LYP/6-311G** and 6-311+G** methods.</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">While methyl anion has an average Δ<IT>α</IT><SB>max</SB> of about eight degrees, and the rest of the alkyls an average Δ<IT>α</IT><SB>max</SB> of ∼4–5, there is a decline in these figures when moving to the iso-alkyl anions (<IT>ca</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">0.7–1.4°) and furthermore when proceeding to the resonance-stabilized anions of formate (<B>7</B>) and acetate (<B>8</B>) (<IT>ca</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">0.57 a degree and less).</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">This interesting decline continues for the PAH anions, as no difference is greater than 0.43°.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">The acetate anion, containing only 4 atoms in its skeleton, shows a difference only slightly larger than that of pentalene dianion (<B>13</B>), the PAH with the largest Δ<IT>α</IT><SB>max</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">After reaching a minimal aromatic<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit41">41<IT>b</IT></REF> hydrocarbon size (<IT>ca</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">5 carbons) the introduction of additional carbons into the skeleton or even additional rings, does not appear to have much effect on the difference, as long as conjugation remains possible.</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Similar conclusions to the fact that calculated geometry related parameters of PAH anions are not affected greatly by the addition of diffuse functions have been achieved before, most recently by Schaefer and Schleyer,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26a">26<IT>a</IT></REF> although these conclusions have been made for smaller and more specific families of PAH anions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">Comparisons for all other pairs of basis sets showed similar results.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit38">38</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" advantage="None">No such correlations were found (for either bond lengths or intramolecular angles or any of the other parameters discussed in this work) when attempting to associate the differences with other factors, such as the total number of rings, the number of five-membered rings, or the ratio between the number of carbons to the number of rings.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Energy</HEADER><P><s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Energy is a clear case in which one <IT>cannot</IT> compare the absolute differences, as total energy varies <IT>considerably</IT> from molecule to molecule, <IT>especially</IT> when moving from small anions to PAHs, which have a very large number of wavefunctions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit47">47</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Using the B3LYP/6-311G** and B3LYP/6-311+G** methods, for instance, one calculates −39.829 au and −39.856 au for the methyl anion (<B>1</B>), respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The much larger hyperconjugated <IT>tert</IT>-butyl anion (<B>6</B>) has energies of −157.809 au and −157.836 au, calculated by the above two methods, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Lastly, the even larger PAH fluoranthene dianion (<B>19</B>) has energies of −615.775 au and −615.802 au, respectively.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit38">38</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None">The difference between the two calculation methods for all three molecules comes to approximately 0.027 au.</annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, one realizes immediately that this difference of 0.027 au does not carry the same significance for each anion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None">One cannot compare a difference of 0.027 au out of approximately −40 au with the same difference out of roughly −615 au.</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, in this case, the figures shown are those for <IT>relative</IT> Δ<IT>E</IT><IT>vs.</IT> the number of atoms in the skeleton.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res29" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 3 depicts the differences arising from the comparison between B3LYP/6-311G** and 6-311+G** methods.</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res29" novelty="None" advantage="None">As for geometry, comparable trends are found for all comparisons<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit38">38</REF> pertaining to Δ<IT>E</IT> as well.</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is important to note that unlike in the gas phase, where electrons of highly charged anions are considered to be unbound, in <IT>all</IT> calculations in this work, the electrons are restricted to be attached to the skeleton of the molecule.</annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Effectively, this means that values obtained here (regardless of basis set used <IT>and</IT> the existence of diffuse functions), only result in an <IT>estimate</IT> for the ground-state energy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None">In other words, the values should most probably only be considered <IT>qualitatively</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this regard, and with respect to the historical difficulties reported,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18 cit19 cit20">18–20</REF> it is highly important to note that <IT>all</IT> total energies for PAHs turn out to be negative, as expected from experiment.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con15" novelty="None" advantage="None">While most studies in the past concluded that diffuse functions are critical to the improvement of calculated energies,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22b cit22c cit22d">22<IT>b–d</IT></REF> these were based on knowledge mainly from <IT>atomic</IT> anions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res30" novelty="None" advantage="None">For PAHs, we conclude that the use of diffuse functions for calculating total energy improves the energy by only <IT>ca</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res30" novelty="None" advantage="None">0.01% or less.</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con16" novelty="None" advantage="None">These trends are in good agreement with conclusions reached by Schleyer and Schaefer for the more specific family of cyclopentadiene-annulated PAHs.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26a">26<IT>a</IT></REF></annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>NMR shifts</HEADER><P><s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa3" novelty="None" advantage="None">One of the main objectives of this work was to deduce conclusions regarding NMR shifts, as this is of utter importance and a main tool in examining aromaticity and aromatic-related properties in charged PAHs.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit48">48</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj8" novelty="New" advantage="None">Specifically, <SP>13</SP>C-NMR shifts are of more interest to our study, as these shifts show an empirical correlation between the additional charge each carbon obtains upon reduction and the shift change of each carbon introduced due to charging of the molecule.</annotationART></s> <s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj8" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">NMR shifts, therefore, show clear relationships to various important parameters, such as charge distribution, anisotropy, aromaticity,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit49a cit50">49<IT>a</IT>,50</REF> anti-aromaticity,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit49b cit49c cit49d cit49e cit50">49<IT>b–e</IT>,50</REF> the HOMO–LUMO energy gap and paramagnetism,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit49b cit49c cit49d cit49e">49<IT>b–e</IT></REF> and are of major importance to organic and theoretical chemists.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 4 shows the maximum differences, Δ<IT>δ</IT><SB>C max,</SB> between B3LYP/6-311G** and 6-311+G** methods <IT>vs.</IT> the number of atoms in the skeleton.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit41 cit51">41<IT>b</IT>,51</REF> Here, the difference must be viewed as the absolute difference, as NMR shifts (relative to TMS) may differ <IT>considerably</IT> from solvent to solvent, and the choice of solvent is arbitrary.</annotationART></s> <s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="New" advantage="None">Furthermore, the choice of TMS as a standard is arbitrary as well.</annotationART></s> <s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The above is <IT>especially</IT> true for <SP>13</SP>C-NMR, where the typical field is much larger; aromatic carbons typically resonate at 110–150 ppm, while aliphatic ones show resonances mainly in the 10–30 ppm region.</annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">While PAH anions generally produce a difference of 12 ppm or smaller, the differences for the small alkyl anions are less, and PAH anions give differences often larger than those calculated for the <IT>n</IT>-alkyl or iso-alkyl carbanions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit38">38</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" advantage="None">Δ<IT>δ</IT><SB>C max</SB> values typically in the order of 10 ppm surely are not negligible.</annotationART></s> <s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res32" novelty="None" advantage="None">Calculations utilizing B3LYP methods accentuate this fact.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit38">38</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con17" novelty="None" advantage="None">These findings are as expected, and agree with those of Jaszuński <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit52">52</REF>. that the use of diffuse functions for NMR shieldings are less important; larger basis sets with more flexible core functions should be employed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res33" novelty="None" advantage="None">Anthracene dianion (<B>17</B>) shows the largest difference, over 30 ppm in the 6-311G** <IT>vs.</IT> 6-311+G** comparison in the B3LYP method.</annotationART></s> <s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res33" novelty="None" advantage="None">This relatively large difference is an irregularity and is discussed later.</annotationART></s> <s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res34" novelty="None" advantage="None">In any case, this difference for the anthracene dianion (<B>17</B>) is <IT>far</IT> smaller in the other comparisons made.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit38">38</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res35" novelty="None" advantage="None">With respect to Δ<IT>δ</IT><SB>C max</SB>, there is no apparent decline in value in advancing from small aliphatic anions to π-conjugated systems.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the only physical parameter easily obtainable for comparison with calculated data is NMR shifts, evaluation of these experimental values with respect to those calculated is obviously called for and necessary.</annotationART></s> <s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res36" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 5 shows examples of correlations between experimental<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit53">53</REF><SP>13</SP>C-NMR values, and those calculated in this work with and without diffuse functions, for various PAH dianions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con19" novelty="None" advantage="None">While fairly small dissimilarities exist between the three graphs in each figure, the overall picture is clear: while some significant differences between calculated data with, and without, diffuse functions do occur, the <IT>pattern</IT> is replicated fairly well.</annotationART></s> <s sid="143"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res37" novelty="None" advantage="None">The square of the correlation factor between these two sets of data<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit54">54</REF> is 0.965 for the acenaphthalene dianion (<B>12</B>), and even higher values for <IT>R</IT><SP>2</SP>, of 0.999, 0.999 and 0.992 are obtained for the same comparison for the anions of fluorene (<B>10</B>), indene (<B>9</B>) and pyracylene (<B>14</B>),<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit38 cit54">38,54</REF> respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="144"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res38" novelty="None" advantage="None"><IT>R</IT><SP>2</SP> is largely of the same order of magnitude for comparisons between calculated data (either with diffuse functions or without) and experimental values.</annotationART></s> <s sid="145"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None"><IT>R</IT><SP>2</SP> is often even better for comparisons between experimental values and calculations made without diffuse functions than with calculations employing these functions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit38">38</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="146"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con20" novelty="None" advantage="None">This information clearly shows that while diffuse functions are essential in calculating <SP>13</SP>C-NMR shifts, calculated NMR shifts without diffuse functions may provide for assistance in experimental assigning.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit48c">48<IT>c</IT></REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="147"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res39" novelty="None" advantage="None"><SP>1</SP>H-NMR shifts show similar behavior with relation to the effect of diffuse functions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="148"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res39" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 6 shows the Δ<IT>δ</IT><SB>H max</SB> difference between B3LYP/6-311G** and 6-311+G** calculated methods.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit41 cit51">41<IT>b</IT>,51</REF> Δ<IT>δ</IT><SB>H max</SB> is frequently on the order of 1 ppm or more.</annotationART></s> <s sid="149"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res40" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is even a more critical error than for Δ<IT>δ</IT><SB>C max</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="150"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con21" novelty="None" advantage="None">Here, too, Δ<IT>δ</IT><SB>H max</SB> for PAH anions and other, non-aromatic anions seem to be on the same order of magnitude, again agreeing with the results of Jaszuński <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit52">52</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="151"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con22" novelty="None" advantage="None">This trend, which appears to be a major distinction from the other figures in general and from Δ<IT>δ</IT><SB>C max</SB> in particular, presumably reflects the fact that peripheral protons' NMR resonances are affected in a crucial way by anisotropic effects.</annotationART></s> <s sid="152"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con23" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is in sharp contrast to peripheral carbons, which are insensitive to anisotropic effects.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit55">55</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="153"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con24" novelty="None" advantage="None">These anisotropic effects may possibly explain the anomaly in anthracene, which, as well as many linear acenes, is customarily regarded as less stable than its angular counterpart.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit56">56</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="154"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Randić suggested<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit57">57</REF> that this is due to a smaller number of (4<IT>n</IT> + 2) π-electron conjugated circuits possible in such species.</annotationART></s> <s sid="155"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The linear systems cause significant dilution of the aromatic sextet.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit56a">56<IT>a</IT></REF> Schleyer proposed<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit58a">58<IT>a</IT></REF> that anthracene has only one resonant sextet located in the central ring.</annotationART></s> <s sid="156"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The NICS value for this ring is significantly larger than that of benzene; conversely, NICS values for the outer two rings are smaller than that of benzene.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit58">58</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="157"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The works of Ligabue <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit59">59</REF>. concerning density maps of anthracene, phenanthrene and triphenylene; and later on, of Ruiz-Morales<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit60">60</REF> on HOMO–LUMO gaps of PAHs, further supported Schleyer's conclusions.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="158"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con25" novelty="None" advantage="None">All of the above bring support to the fact that anthracene and anthracene dianion (<B>17</B>) may contain significant anisotropic effects.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit49b cit49c cit49d cit49e">49<IT>b–e</IT></REF> Thus, <SP>1</SP>H-NMR shifts are most affected and, as mentioned above, slightly less for <SP>13</SP>C-NMR.</annotationART></s> <s sid="159"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Non-magnetic related parameters, such as geometry (and energy to some extent), are hardly affected.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="160"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res41" novelty="None" advantage="None">Comparison to experimental<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit38 cit54 cit61">38,54,61</REF><SP>1</SP>H-NMR values (Fig. 7) gives rise to a similar image.</annotationART></s> <s sid="161"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res41" novelty="None" advantage="None">While <IT>R</IT><SP>2</SP> between a specific calculated data (either with diffuse functions or without) and experimental values varies from poor (indenyl, <B>9</B>) through fair (acenaphthalenyl, <B>12</B>) to quite good (fluorenyl, <B>10</B>),<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit62">62</REF> correlation factors between calculated data obtained with, and without, diffuse functions are good throughout.</annotationART></s> <s sid="162"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None"><IT>R</IT><SP>2</SP> between these two sets of data is 0.985 for the acenaphthalene dianion (<B>12</B>) and 0.995 and 0.981 for the anions of fluorene (<B>10</B>) and indene (<B>9</B>), respectively.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit63">63</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="163"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con26" novelty="None" advantage="None">This further supports the supposition that although diffuse functions are critical in calculating <SP>1</SP>H-NMR shifts, if calculation is meant only to assist in assignment, then one may possibly do so from calculated data excluding diffuse functions.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Charge density</HEADER><P><s sid="164"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res42" novelty="None" advantage="None">For charge density, the trends exhibited for geometry and energy are reiterated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="165"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res43" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 8 shows Δ<IT>ρ</IT><SB>max</SB> for the B3LYP/6-311G** and 6-311+G** comparison.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit41 cit51 cit64 cit65">41<IT>b</IT>,51,64,65</REF> As in the previous cases mentioned, also here one can see the distinction between the π-conjugated system/PAH region and the alkyl anion region.</annotationART></s> <s sid="166"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res44" novelty="None" advantage="None">Even the smaller PAHs have relatively smaller Δ<IT>ρ</IT><SB>max</SB> than the alkyl anions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="167"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res45" novelty="None" advantage="None">Similar trends are found for all other comparisons.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit38">38</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="168"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res46" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, since far fewer points appear on these graphs than on the corresponding ones for geometry and energy,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit51 cit64">51,64</REF> one should be cautious when drawing conclusions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="169"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con27" novelty="None" advantage="None">At any rate, NBO calculations apparently confirm the underlying working assumption; PAHs have a much smaller density of charge within their carbon-skeleton framework.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="170"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res47" novelty="None" advantage="None">Scheme 4 graphically shows that PAHs have a far less density of charge in their carbon skeleton due to their far larger size and π-conjugation ability.</annotationART></s> <s sid="171"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res48" novelty="None" advantage="None">These findings clearly indicate that the contribution of diffuse functions to the calculation of charge density in PAH anions would be quite small.</annotationART></s> <s sid="172"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con28" novelty="None" advantage="None">This contrasts the conclusions concerning small anions, as in the investigation of the hydride ion by Shore <IT>et al.</IT>, who showed<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit66">66</REF> that without diffuse functions, the local exchange approximation of the ground state failed, giving an incorrect ground state, with partial delocalization of the electrons.</annotationART></s> <s sid="173"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con29" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, one can, albeit vigilantly as mentioned above, conclude that the inclusion of diffuse functions in calculations of charge density does not cause the results obtained without them to change significantly.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>General</HEADER><P><s sid="174"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res49" novelty="None" advantage="None">From looking at all figures and data,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit38">38</REF> one can see some general trends common to all cases:</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="175"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res50" novelty="None" advantage="None">(i) For almost all parameters calculated, the difference between larger basis sets (6-311G** and 6-311+G**) is less significant than the difference between smaller ones (6-31G* and 6-31+G*).</annotationART></s> <s sid="176"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con30" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is understandable, as larger basis sets allow more flexibility in the calculation; consequently, allowing further flexibility using diffuse functions is of less importance in these cases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="177"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con30" novelty="None" advantage="None">When charge delocalization is present, inter-electronic repulsion is already being dealt with by larger basis sets and polarization functions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="178"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res51" novelty="None" advantage="None">The exception to this case is NMR differences: in these instances the differences follow no specific trend.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="179"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res52" novelty="None" advantage="None">(ii) Generally, <IT>n</IT>-alkyl and iso-alkyl anions exhibit the property that differences between two basis sets are larger for a B3LYP calculation than for the analogous calculations using HF theory.</annotationART></s> <s sid="180"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con31" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is in harmony with Truhlar's results<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22d">22<IT>d</IT></REF> on alkyls and other relatively small molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="181"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res53" novelty="None" advantage="None">Diffuse functions appear to be of much more significance for DFT than for Hartree–Fock in these cases.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="182"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res54" novelty="None" advantage="None">For PAHs, however, these differences are, on the whole, much smaller.</annotationART></s> <s sid="183"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res55" novelty="None" advantage="None">In fact, the differences between two B3LYP calculations are almost identical to those obtained from the same basis sets in HF.</annotationART></s> <s sid="184"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res56" novelty="None" advantage="None">For a sizeable number of occurrences, the difference is actually smaller for B3LYP calculations than for those calculated in the HF method.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="185"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="New" advantage="None">(iii) Since the differences reported are absolute values, it is noteworthy to examine trends within the differences (not only the maximum differences).</annotationART></s> <s sid="186"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res57" novelty="None" advantage="None">It should be pointed out at the start that all trends reported now are essentially the same regardless of the difference in basis sets or calculation methods.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="187"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con32" novelty="None" advantage="None">The addition of diffuse functions does not appear to result in a trend concerning the sign of the difference, <IT>i.e.</IT> calculations including diffuse functions give larger values than calculations excluding them roughly the amount of instances than <IT>vice versa</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="188"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res58" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the specific case of Δ<IT>r</IT>, PAH anions show a slight leaning towards <IT>negative</IT> differences, <IT>i.e.</IT> larger values for results obtained <IT>without</IT> diffuse functions than those obtained with them.</annotationART></s> <s sid="189"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In energy calculations, more than 95% of the cases show a negative difference for Δ<IT>E</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="190"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res59" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the total energy is a negative value, this means that in almost <IT>all</IT> cases, calculations made with basis sets containing diffuse functions give a better estimate<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit67">67</REF> of the energy compared to calculations made with basis sets omitting them.</annotationART></s> <s sid="191"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con33" novelty="None" advantage="None">This supports previous claims<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21a cit22b cit22d cit26a">21<IT>a</IT>,22<IT>b</IT>,<IT>d</IT>,26<IT>a</IT></REF> that diffuse functions are necessary for improving various energies calculated for anions.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="192"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res60" novelty="None" advantage="None">Most molecules show an equal amount of negative and positive differences for Δ<IT>δ</IT><SB>C</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="193"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res61" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, PAHs show a slight bias towards positive differences, <IT>i.e.</IT> the <SP>13</SP>C-NMR shifts obtained using diffuse functions are larger than those obtained without them.</annotationART></s> <s sid="194"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res62" novelty="None" advantage="None">For <SP>1</SP>H-NMR shifts, however, the picture is considerably different: the shifts are <IT>almost</IT><IT>always</IT> larger for calculations made using basis sets <IT>including</IT> diffuse functions compared with those obtained using basis sets excluding them.</annotationART></s> <s sid="195"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res63" novelty="None" advantage="None">In other words, Δ<IT>δ</IT><SB>H</SB> is almost always positive.</annotationART></s> <s sid="196"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res64" novelty="None" advantage="None">The picture <IT>vis-à-vis</IT> Δ<IT>ρ</IT> resembles that of Δ<IT>E</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="197"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con34" novelty="None" advantage="None">The use of basis sets containing diffuse functions almost always (&gt;95% of values calculated) results in more negative values than using the same method and basis sets excluding them.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Conclusions</HEADER><P><s sid="198"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Rightfully so, diffuse functions have widely been recognized for some time as a tool necessary for efficiently calculating various properties of anions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="199"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">High charge density affects numerous properties, such as bond length, energy, and electron affinity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="200"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, PAHs may use their size and, apparently more importantly, their π-system, for dispersion of charge over the carbon skeleton, reducing Coulomb repulsion and stabilizing themselves.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="201"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res65" novelty="None" advantage="None">Differences between using and not using diffuse functions while calculating parameters of geometry are considerably affected by the size of the molecule, but more so by the conjugational availability.</annotationART></s> <s sid="202"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con35" novelty="None" advantage="None">We conclude that the use of diffuse functions for calculating geometrical parameters for PAH anions in general is unnecessary and does not improve the calculated results significantly.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="203"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res66" novelty="None" advantage="None">Energy calculations are affected in much the same way.</annotationART></s> <s sid="204"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res67" novelty="None" advantage="None">PAH anions show little difference whether their energies were calculated including or excluding diffuse functions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="205"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con36" novelty="None" advantage="None">Diffuse functions almost always improve the calculated energy for PAH anions, although trivially.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit67">67</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="206"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con37" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is therefore of reduced importance using these functions when calculating total energy or geometrical parameters for PAH anions.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="207"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res68" novelty="None" advantage="None">The effect on NMR shifts is quite different.</annotationART></s> <s sid="208"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con38" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the most part, the absolute differences, Δ<IT>δ</IT>, are not insignificant, clearly demonstrating that diffuse functions are crucial in calculating NMR shifts, regardless of the nature of anion or nucleus in question.</annotationART></s> <s sid="209"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con39" novelty="None" advantage="None">If actual absolute values are desired (for instance, if no experimental data is available), then accuracy is available only to a certain degree.</annotationART></s> <s sid="210"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met14" novelty="New" advantage="None">If, however, the calculation is only meant to assist assignment, then, in most cases, <IT>regardless</IT> of whether <SP>13</SP>C- or <SP>1</SP>H-NMR shifts are being calculated, full assignment may be realized quite reliably through correlation between experimental and calculated values, without use of diffuse functions.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="211"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res69" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the whole, charge density calculations show that Δ<IT>ρ</IT> is always smaller for PAH anions than for smaller, aliphatic ones.</annotationART></s> <s sid="212"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con40" novelty="None" advantage="None">NBO calculations <IT>do</IT> appear to confirm the much lower charge density for PAH anions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="213"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con41" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, lack of results due to technical difficulties<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit64">64</REF> and for reasons stated in the computational details section<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit51">51</REF> prevent us from making unequivocal conclusions in this regard, and caution should be taken in attempting to extrapolate from the results presented.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="214"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con42" novelty="None" advantage="None">Some PAH anions exhibit irregularity regarding differences calculated; however, closer examination of these anomalies may provide insight as to why they are such, and chemical reasoning may elucidate aberrations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="215"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con43" novelty="None" advantage="None">Irregularity of various points on such figures may thus possibly be a tool for ascertaining specific and distinct chemical properties of particular anions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="216"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con44" novelty="None" advantage="None">Such comparisons may therefore assist in the realization of which properties are similar for PAHs and which are dissimilar.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Supporting information available</HEADER><P><s sid="217"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Isotropy values obtained for optimized TMS using the various methods (1 table), tables of data and statistics for indenyl anion exemplifying methodology (2 tables), tables of full data for all anions calculated with all comparisons made (21 tables), schemes for all parameters set for anions excluding indenyl anion (20 schemes), and all three analogous figures not presented in paper for all properties (18 total) are available.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
