<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b400183d" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the mechanism of the HCCO + O<SB>2</SB> reaction: Probing multiple pathways to a single product channel</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">We explore the mechanism of the HCCO + O<SB>2</SB> reaction using time-resolved Fourier transform spectroscopy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Utilizing an isotopically labeled reactant (<SP>18</SP>O<SB>2</SB>) and state-selective product detection, we determine the relative flux through different paths on the potential energy surface leading to a single asymptote: H + CO + CO<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the labeled reaction, the dominant isotopic products are C<SP>18</SP>O and <SP>16</SP>OC<SP>18</SP>O. Combined with data from the corresponding reaction in natural isotopic abundance, these results show that at least 85% of the reactive flux passes through a four-membered OCCO ring intermediate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">An alternative reaction path through an energetically allowed three-membered COO ring intermediate represents less than 15% of the total reactive flux.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The average energy deposited in vibration of CO and CO<SB>2</SB> is in reasonable agreement with a statistical model using the separate statistical ensembles method.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="I.">Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The measurement of total rate coefficients, product branching ratios, and product energy distributions are common methods in the elucidation of reaction mechanisms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Typically, each product branching ratio is interpreted as a measurement of the flux through one exit channel of the reaction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, it is possible that two energetically feasible paths on the potential energy surface (PES) lead to a single product channel.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Measuring the contribution of each allowed reaction path toward a given exit channel tests our understanding of both the PES itself, and the calculations carried out on that surface to predict kinetics and dynamics.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="No">In such cases it is usually quite difficult, if not impossible, to experimentally determine the contributions of these multiple reaction paths because they produce identical products.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">It is sometimes possible to measure contributions from multiple pathways if energy partitioning in a product molecule depends strongly on the different pathways, but this method may only be viable for the simplest cases.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2 cit3">1–3</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Isotopic labeling of reactants combined with isotope-specific detection of products offers the possibility of probing contributions of individual reaction paths in addition to more commonly measured product branching ratios.</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this paper, we use this concept to interrogate reaction paths in the HCCO + O<SB>2</SB> reaction.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ketenyl radical (HCCO) is a key intermediate in acetylene oxidation chemistry and consequently an important species in combustion of all hydrocarbons.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit5 cit6 cit7">4–7</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">HCCO is formed primarily <IT>via</IT> the reaction of C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>2</SB> + O C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>2</SB> + O(<SP>3</SP>P) → HCCO + H Δ<IT>H</IT><SB>0</SB> = −19.6 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit9">8,9</REF>→CH<SB>2</SB> + CO Δ<IT>H</IT><SB>0</SB> = −47.9 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Recent measurements of this reaction agree that HCCO + H is the dominant channel at room temperature.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10 cit11 cit12 cit13">10–13</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Experimental values of <IT>k</IT><SB>1a</SB>/<IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB> range from .085<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">(285 K), .083<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">(290 K), .080<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">(900–1200 K) to .064<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">(1500–2000 K), while a theoretical calculation predicts a <IT>k</IT><SB>1a</SB>/<IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB> ratio of 0.7,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF> with little temperature or pressure dependence.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The value of this branching ratio is critical in determining the mechanism behind “prompt” CO<SB>2</SB> formation in acetylene oxidation.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Prompt CO<SB>2</SB>, that is, the formation of CO<SB>2</SB> with the same time constant as the partially oxidized species CO, was first observed in Kistiakowsky's group in the 1960s.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15 cit16 cit17 cit18">15–18</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Eberius <IT>et al.</IT> observed further evidence of prompt CO<SB>2</SB> from measurements in lean C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>2</SB>/O<SB>2</SB> flames.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19">19</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Modeling results from Miller <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF>. successfully reproduced these experimental measurements under the assumption that CH<SB>2</SB> + CO is the dominant product channel of reaction (1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, in light of newer experimental evidence that HCCO + H is the major product channel of reaction (1), Klippenstein, Miller, and Harding<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF> recently proposed a new model for prompt CO<SB>2</SB> formation that centers on oxidation of HCCO HCCO + O<SB>2</SB> → H + CO + CO<SB>2</SB> Δ<IT>H</IT><SB>0</SB> = −110.4 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>,→OCHCO + O Δ<IT>H</IT><SB>0</SB> = −1.3 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>,→OH + CO + CO Δ<IT>H</IT><SB>0</SB> = −86.0 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF>.There are four measurements of the total rate coefficient for this reaction.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23 cit24 cit25 cit26">23–26</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Peeters <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF>. have suggested that the title reaction occurs though channel (2), while Murray <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25">25</REF>. presented tentative evidence that channel (4) is the major product channel.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Using variational transition state theory master equation calculations and direct trajectory simulations, Klippenstein <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF>. predicted that reaction (2) is the dominant product channel of the title reaction for a temperature range of 300–2500 K and pressures up to 100 atm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Shortly thereafter, Osborn directly observed the HCCO reactant and the CO and CO<SB>2</SB> products from the HCCO + O<SB>2</SB> reaction using time-resolved Fourier transform emission spectroscopy.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27">27</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The emission spectra indicated that the nascent CO and CO<SB>2</SB> products are highly internally excited.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">No emission from the OH radical was observable, implying that reaction (4) is not a major product channel.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">By comparison with a reference reaction that produces OH, the author concluded that the OH + CO + CO channel represents at most 10% of the reaction products<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27">27</REF> at 293 K. These results are in agreement with the detailed calculations of Klippenstein <IT>et al.</IT>, which predict that channels (3) and (4) are negligible at room temperature, but may make a small contribution at higher temperatures.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">A diagram of the PES for this reaction is presented in Fig. 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is important to distinguish between product channels (2)–(4) and reaction paths (A)–(F) on the PES.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">There are three reaction paths (A, C, and D) that lead to H + CO + CO<SB>2</SB> products.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">These paths involve either a four-membered OCCO ring (III) or a three-membered OCO ring (II) as reaction intermediates.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Similarly, there are two reaction paths (B and F) leading to OH + CO + CO.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Measuring the relative flux on these reaction paths through these intermediates is the focus of this paper.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Isotopic labeling has been widely applied in various fields of chemistry to determine the properties of chemical compounds and their origins and evolutions in reactions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28">28</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">This technique can provide important insights into reaction mechanisms and dynamics,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29 cit30 cit31 cit32">29–32</REF> where the same products may arise from several different pathways, although such studies are still scarce.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to further elucidate the reaction mechanism of HCCO + O<SB>2</SB>, we have studied this reaction comparing <SP>18</SP>O<SB>2</SB> with <SP>16</SP>O<SB>2</SB> reactants using time-resolved Fourier transform spectroscopy (TR-FTS).</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">As shown in Fig. 1, products arising from three-membered or four-membered ring intermediates are isotopically distinguishable.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="New" advantage="None">All the possible isotopic variants of CO and CO<SB>2</SB> can be easily separated by rotationally-resolved infrared spectroscopy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="New" advantage="None">The emission spectra of the isotopically labeled products provide a direct measurement of the reactive flux through different reaction pathways.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The vibrational distributions of the products from the emission spectra allow additional insight into the reaction dynamics.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="II.">Experimental</HEADER><P><s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">A detailed description of the experimental apparatus has been published previously.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27 cit33">27,33</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In short, helium is bubbled through a 273 K sample of ethyl ethynyl ether (HCCOC<SB>2</SB>H<SB>5</SB>) at 60 sccm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">This flow is combined with O<SB>2</SB> (100 sccm) and delivered to a Teflon-lined stainless steel flow cell through a 1.5 cm diameter Pyrex tube.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Ethyl ethynyl ether is photolyzed at 193 nm to produce HCCO + C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>5</SB> with near unit quantum yield.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit34">34</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The 193 nm photons from an unfocused ArF excimer laser are introduced into the cell about 1 cm below the gas mixture entrance.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Typical laser pulsewidth is 20 ns with a fluence of 24–30 mJ cm<SP>−2</SP> pulse<SP>−1</SP> at a 50 Hz repetition rate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Helium (100 sccm) is injected adjacent to the laser windows to minimize chemical deposition on the windows' surfaces.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The pressure of the cell is measured by a capacitance manometer, and maintained at 1.1 Torr through a closed-loop feedback valve throttling the pump.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp9" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to compare the <SP>16</SP>O<SB>2</SB> and <SP>18</SP>O<SB>2</SB> results without variations from long term laser power drift, back to back experiments are performed with either <SP>16</SP>O<SB>2</SB> or <SP>18</SP>O<SB>2</SB> flow under the same conditions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The gas manifold is back filled with helium and pumped out several times to reduce cross contamination before changing O<SB>2</SB> isotopes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The absorption cross section of ethyl ethynyl ether is 7 × 10<SP>−18</SP> cm<SP>2</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> at 193 nm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">From the flow rates of different gases, the total pressure of the cell and the absorption cross section of ethyl ethynyl ether at 193 nm, we estimate [HCCO]<SB>0</SB> ≅ 8 × 10<SP>13</SP> molecules cm<SP>−3</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The O<SB>2</SB> concentration is fixed at 1.26 × 10<SP>16</SP> molecules cm<SP>−3</SP>, ensuring pseudo-first-order reaction conditions and minimizing secondary reactions of HCCO.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Spectra taken without O<SB>2</SB> present have an equal flow of helium substituted for O<SB>2</SB> in order to maintain the same sample refreshing rate in the flow cell.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Time-resolved infrared emission is collected by Welsh collection optics,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit35">35</REF> made from a pair of 10 cm diameter silver-coated spherical mirrors.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The emission is sent into an evacuated Fourier transform spectrometer (Bruker IFS 66v/S) through a KBr window and focused onto a liquid nitrogen cooled InSb photodiode.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The signal is amplified and digitized by a 16-bit 200 kS s<SP>−1</SP> digitizer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Fourier spectrometer operates in step-scan mode.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit36">36</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Time traces of the emission signal are collected and averaged over four laser shots at each mirror position (∼10 000 mirror positions for a 0.115 cm<SP>−1</SP> resolution spectrum from 1800 to 2400 cm<SP>−1</SP>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The time-resolved interferograms at 5 μs intervals are later extracted from these traces and Fourier transformed into time-resolved spectra.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Data collection begins 20–25 μs prior to the photolysis laser pulse to provide a background noise measurement and a clear reaction starting point (<IT>t</IT> = 0).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Helium (99.999% Matheson), <SP>16</SP>O<SB>2</SB> (99.995% Matheson, natural isotopic abundance assumed: 99.76% <SP>16</SP>O<SB>2</SB>, 0.04% <SP>17</SP>O<SB>2</SB>, 0.20% <SP>18</SP>O<SB>2</SB>) and <SP>18</SP>O<SB>2</SB> (isotopic purity 99%, Isotek) gases are used without further purification.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="None" advantage="No">Unfortunately, the high cost of <SP>18</SP>O<SB>2</SB> severely limited the amount of signal averaging possible in these experiments, resulting in lower signal-to-noise ratios than we would normally accept.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="None" advantage="No">The limited supply of <SP>18</SP>O<SB>2</SB> also forced us to use a slower gas flow rate than previously utilized.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27">27</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The flow rate still ensures complete flushing of the laser interaction region between laser shots.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the cold gas filter effect (absorption of emission by ground state stable molecules) may perturb the populations slightly since the optical path of the Welch collection optics covers a large volume of the cell in addition to the laser interaction region.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp20" novelty="None" advantage="None">Ethyl ethynyl ether is obtained from Aldrich as a 40% solution in hexane and used without further purification.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hexane has a negligible absorption cross-section at 193 nm, and therefore does not affect the radical production method.</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that the C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>5</SB> cofragment produced by the photolysis laser will react with O<SB>2</SB>, but does not produce CO or CO<SB>2</SB>, and hence does not affect the present measurements<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit37">37</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="III.">Results and analysis</HEADER><P><s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">HCCO radicals produced from ethyl ethynyl ether photodissociation at 193 nm are internally excited and emit strongly in the 1800–2040 cm<SP>−1</SP> region.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27">27</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">This emission arises from the Δ<IT>υ</IT><SB>2</SB> = −1 asymmetric stretch bands of HCCO.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit38">38</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Unfortunately, HCCO absorbs very strongly at the photolysis wavelength (193 nm), dissociating to produce CH and vibrationally excited CO.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit39">39</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The infrared emission from HCCO and this photolytically-produced CO overlap with the emission produced by products of the HCCO + O<SB>2</SB> reaction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="New" advantage="None">Fortunately, CO from HCCO photodissociation can be easily removed by subtracting spectra taken with and without O<SB>2</SB> present.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">We observe that excited HCCO radicals are quenched in less than 15 μs, and that the quenching rate of HCCO is independent of O<SB>2</SB> and He concentration, indicating that the excited HCCO radicals are mainly quenched by hexane and/or ethyl ethynyl ether under the present experimental conditions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, vibrational relaxation of CO by O<SB>2</SB> and He is very slow.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, the background subtraction procedure is expected to completely remove the emission from the excited HCCO and photolytically-produced CO without introducing any bias to the signals from the HCCO + O<SB>2</SB> reaction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="New" advantage="None">All spectra are background subtracted using this method.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Because CH radicals are also produced in the photodissociation of HCCO, it is important to consider their effect on the system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although CH does react with O<SB>2</SB>, producing both CO and CO<SB>2</SB> with branching ratios of 0.5 and 0.3 respectively,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit40">40</REF> no evidence has been observed that the CH + O<SB>2</SB> reaction plays a significant role in CO and CO<SB>2</SB> production in the current experiments.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27">27</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Specifically, the rate coefficient for CH + O<SB>2</SB> at 300 K is 4.7 × 10<SP>−11</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit41">41</REF> corresponding to a rise time of ∼2 μs for products from this reaction at the O<SB>2</SB> concentrations in this experiment.</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">No production of CO or CO<SB>2</SB> is observed on this timescale.</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Instead, it is likely that most CH radicals react with ethyl ethynyl ether and/or hexane.</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reactions of CH with large hydrocarbons are extremely rapidly (1–2 orders of magnitude faster than the CH + O<SB>2</SB> reaction at room temperature)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit42">42</REF> and these reactions are unlikely to produce CO or CO<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the HCCO + O<SB>2</SB> reaction, CO and CO<SB>2</SB> are formed with significant vibrational excitation, such that their spectra overlap.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27">27</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Efficient cooling of CO<SB>2</SB>, by vibrational energy transfer to the bath gas, causes its spectrum to blue shift until at <IT>t</IT> = 300 μs it no longer overlaps the CO transitions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The HCCO + O<SB>2</SB> reaction has a half-life time of ∼80 μs<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24 cit25 cit26">24–26</REF> under the current experimental conditions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, at <IT>t</IT> = 300 μs the reaction is essentially complete.</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">To simplify quantification of the different isotopic products, we analyze spectra at this long delay time.</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that by observing both CO and CO<SB>2</SB>, we obtain two independent measurements of <SP>18</SP>O positions in the reaction products.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Emission spectra of the CO product from the HCCO + <SP>16</SP>O<SB>2</SB> and HCCO + <SP>18</SP>O<SB>2</SB> reactions at <IT>t</IT> = 300 μs are shown in Figs. 2 and 3 respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In both figures the upper panels show the experimental data along with a non-linear least squares fit<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit33">33</REF> and residuals of emission intensity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The lower panels show a narrower wavelength region to clarify the spectroscopic differences between C<SP>16</SP>O and C<SP>18</SP>O and the agreement between the experimental data and the fits.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">When we fit the emission spectra allowing contributions from both CO isotopes, we find the only detectable carbon monoxide products of HCCO + <SP>16</SP>O<SB>2</SB> and HCCO + <SP>18</SP>O<SB>2</SB> are C<SP>16</SP>O and C<SP>18</SP>O respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">An upper limit of the branching ratio of C<SP>16</SP>O in the HCCO + <SP>18</SP>O<SB>2</SB> reaction will be given later based on the signal-to-noise ratio of the data.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The validity of the background subtraction method is verified in the case of the HCCO + <SP>18</SP>O<SB>2</SB> reaction, where the entire C<SP>16</SP>O signal is removed upon background subtraction, implying that all C<SP>16</SP>O signals in the raw data arise from HCCO photodissociation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The vibrational distributions of CO derived from the fitting are shown in Fig. 4.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The emission spectra of CO<SB>2</SB> from the HCCO + <SP>16</SP>O<SB>2</SB> and HCCO + <SP>18</SP>O<SB>2</SB> reactions are shown in Figs. 5–7.</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 5 shows spectra acquired early in the reaction (<IT>t</IT> = 25 μs) that do not show any resolved rotational lines, but provide a good picture of the nascent vibrational energy of the CO<SB>2</SB> product.</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="New" advantage="None">The contributions from CO have been removed from Fig. 5 by a procedure described below.</annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">At <IT>t</IT> = 300 μs, CO<SB>2</SB> has cooled sufficiently that few vibrational bands are populated, and the emission bands are rotationally resolved, as shown in Figs. 6 and 7.</annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Rotational resolution is critical in determining the relative abundance of each CO<SB>2</SB> isotope.</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Only <SP>16</SP>OC<SP>16</SP>O emission is seen in the natural abundance case, and only <SP>16</SP>OC<SP>18</SP>O emission in the labeled reaction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">No emission from <SP>18</SP>OC<SP>18</SP>O is observed.</annotationART></s></P><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="A.">Quantitative measurement of isotope ratios</HEADER><P><s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The nonlinear least-squares fitting procedure for CO has been described in detail previously.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit33">33</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Transition energies are calculated from the spectroscopic constants for both C<SP>16</SP>O and C<SP>18</SP>O.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit43">43</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp21" novelty="None" advantage="None">Initially we fit spectra at <IT>t</IT> = 300 μs, where CO<SB>2</SB> emission does not overlap CO emission.</annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Rotational relaxation of CO is extremely fast and is expected to reach equilibrium in less than 1 μs under the current experimental conditions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit44">44</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">At <IT>t</IT> ≥ 5 μs, the rotational distribution for each vibrational band does in fact fit a rotational Boltzmann distribution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met14" novelty="New" advantage="None">The population of each vibrational level is allowed to vary independently during the nonlinear least-squares fitting to obtain the best fit to each experimental spectrum.</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met14" novelty="New" advantage="None">Either a fixed rotational temperature of 330 K for all vibrational bands is used, or the rotational temperature for each individual vibrational state is allowed to vary during the fitting procedure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The average fitted rotational temperature is 330 ± 50 K, and the quality of the fits is unchanged if the rotational temperature is fixed at this value.</annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">This rotational temperature is slightly higher than the ambient room temperature, which is expected considering the energy deposited in the system by the laser and the heat of reaction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Considering the enthalpy change (Δ<IT>H</IT> = <IT>hν</IT> − <IT>D</IT><SB>0</SB>(HCCO—C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>5</SB>) + |Δ<IT>H</IT><SB>0</SB>(ch.</annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">2)|) along with the heat capacities and mole fractions of the major species, we calculate a temperature increase of 25–35 K, depending on the value assumed for the heat capacity of HCCOC<SB>2</SB>H<SB>5</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None">This temperature change is in good agreement with the spectroscopic rotational temperature of CO derived from the fitting.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met15" novelty="New" advantage="None">Because C<SP>16</SP>O is not observed in the HCCO + <SP>18</SP>O<SB>2</SB> reaction, we evaluate the upper limit of C<SP>16</SP>O formation with an analysis similar to the one used for OH yield estimation.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27">27</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The absorption intensities of the <IT>υ</IT>′ = 1 ← <IT>υ</IT>″ = 0 transition of C<SP>16</SP>O and C<SP>18</SP>O show that the two isotopes have essentially equal Einstein <IT>A</IT> coefficients.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit45">45</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore the emission intensity of the two CO isotopes should be proportional to the absolute number densities of the emitting species.</annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Because the vibrational distributions of C<SP>16</SP>O and C<SP>18</SP>O can be approximately described by Boltzmann distributions with similar vibrational temperatures, the emission intensities are expected to be proportional to the total CO number density, including the ground vibrational state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the present experiments, the product of vibrational state population with the Einstein <IT>A</IT> coefficient is largest for the <IT>υ</IT>′ = 2 band, making it the most sensitive transition for CO detection.</annotationART></s> <s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met16" novelty="New" advantage="None">Beginning with the best-fit population distribution (which contains only C<SP>18</SP>O), we manually increase the population of C<SP>16</SP>O in the spectral simulation until several peaks originating in <IT>υ</IT>′ = 2 can be distinguished from the background.</annotationART></s> <s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">This analysis provides an upper limit of [C<SP>16</SP>O]/[C<SP>18</SP>O] &lt; 0.16 in the HCCO + <SP>18</SP>O<SB>2</SB> reaction.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">While emission from CO is rotationally resolved at all reaction times, CO<SB>2</SB> emission is rotationally resolved only at later times.</annotationART></s> <s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None">The fitting of CO<SB>2</SB> emission spectra is more complicated because of the presence of three vibrational modes, vibrational angular momentum, and the effect of nuclear spin.</annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met17" novelty="New" advantage="None">Given the 1800–2400 cm<SP>−1</SP> spectral window observed in these experiments, only transitions in the antisymmetric stretch bands, <IT>i.e.</IT> (<IT>mn</IT><SP><IT>l</IT></SP><IT>p</IT>) → (<IT>mn</IT><SP><IT>l</IT></SP><IT>p</IT> − 1), need be considered.</annotationART></s> <s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The spectroscopic constants for C<SP>16</SP>O<SB>2</SB>, <SP>16</SP>OC<SP>18</SP>O and <SP>18</SP>OC<SP>18</SP>O are adopted from <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit46 cit47">refs. 46 and 47</REF>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fitting of CO<SB>2</SB> spectra at long delay times (<IT>e.g.</IT>, 300 μs) indicates that only the lowest few vibrational states are populated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">The magnified regions in Figs. 6 and 7 clearly show that the different isotopes of CO<SB>2</SB> can be resolved.</annotationART></s> <s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">The only CO<SB>2</SB> isotope observed in HCCO + <SP>18</SP>O<SB>2</SB> is <SP>16</SP>OC<SP>18</SP>O. Our detection sensitivity for CO<SB>2</SB> is lower than for CO because so many more initial states are populated in the case of the triatomic molecule.</annotationART></s> <s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">Nevertheless, a similar analysis to that described above for CO indicates a limit of [<SP>18</SP>OC<SP>18</SP>O]/[<SP>16</SP>OC<SP>18</SP>O] &lt; 0.30.</annotationART></s> <s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None">This value is likely significantly overestimated due to the poor signal-to-noise ratio of the CO<SB>2</SB> emission spectra.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="B.">Nascent product state distributions</HEADER><P><s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to estimate the nascent product vibrational state distributions, the overlapping emission of CO and CO<SB>2</SB> at early times should ideally be separated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met18" novelty="New" advantage="None">However, a good approximation to the nascent CO product state distribution can be measured at <IT>t</IT> = 300 μs because CO cools very slowly due to collisions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met19" novelty="New" advantage="None">Using a process described below, we can also fit the CO distribution at early times when interference from CO<SB>2</SB> is substantial.</annotationART></s> <s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">The resulting CO vibrational distributions, shown in Fig. 4, can for simplicity be fit to a Boltzmann distribution, yielding temperatures of 8600 ± 900 K and 9500 ± 1000 K for C<SP>16</SP>O and C<SP>18</SP>O respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="143"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">The vibrational distributions of CO are similar for both C<SP>16</SP>O and C<SP>18</SP>O. The distributions on a Boltzmann plot are somewhat non-linear, with greater population in higher vibrational levels than a true vibrational temperature would allow.</annotationART></s> <s sid="144"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that the early time C<SP>16</SP>O distribution in Fig. 4 appears quite linear, while the population of higher vibrational levels of C<SP>16</SP>O seems to increase by <IT>t</IT> = 300 μs.</annotationART></s> <s sid="145"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">Most of this variation can be attributed to the less than optimal signal-to-noise ratio of the data.</annotationART></s> <s sid="146"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" advantage="None">As discussed above, the high cost of <SP>18</SP>O<SB>2</SB> limited signal averaging in the present experiments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="147"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met20" novelty="New" advantage="None">To facilitate comparisons between isotopes, the reaction using <SP>16</SP>O<SB>2</SB> is executed with the same limited averaging times.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="148"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None">Earlier data on the HCCO + <SP>16</SP>O<SB>2</SB> reaction,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27">27</REF> utilizing more signal averaging, provide a more precise representation of the C<SP>16</SP>O vibrational distribution, and display curvature in the Boltzmann plot that is intermediate between all the data presented in Fig. 4.</annotationART></s> <s sid="149"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None">While this distribution could be described as bimodal, we hesitate to draw conclusions based on bimodality without substantially more data collection over a range of total pressures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="150"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is important to note that curvature in the vibrational distribution has no impact on the isotope ratios discussed in section IIIA.</annotationART></s> <s sid="151"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the Boltzmann vibrational temperatures for the two CO isotopes are within mutual uncertainty, we conclude that different oxygen isotopes have little effect on the vibrational distribution of CO. The derived vibrational temperatures are consistent with the previous result of 8500 ± 800 K.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27">27</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="152"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp22" novelty="None" advantage="None">The much more rapid vibrational energy transfer from CO<SB>2</SB> requires that its nascent distribution be measured at the earliest reaction time with sufficient signal (<IT>t</IT> = 25 μs in this case).</annotationART></s> <s sid="153"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met21" novelty="New" advantage="None">To meaningfully fit the broad CO<SB>2</SB> emission at this early time requires both a robust method for removing the sharp features due to CO, and a spectroscopic model of highly excited CO<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="154"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp23" novelty="None" advantage="None">To remove the early-time CO spectral features, we first fit one CO spectrum at <IT>t</IT> = 300 μs, where CO<SB>2</SB> does not interfere.</annotationART></s> <s sid="155"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met21" novelty="New" advantage="None">We then separate all time-resolved spectra into two regions by determining where CO could contribute to the total emission (<IT>i.e.</IT>, near a known CO line) and where the emission must be solely due to CO<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="156"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Explicitly, these “separated” experimental spectra can be represented by the following equations, where <IT>I</IT>(<IT></IT>,<IT>t</IT>) is the emission intensity as a function of wavenumber and <IT>δ</IT> is the experimental root-mean-square (RMS) noise: Eqn. (6) retains all wavenumbers in the spectra where CO emission intensity is expected to be lower than the RMS noise.</annotationART></s> <s sid="157"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, contains emission solely from CO<SB>2</SB>, while has contributions from both CO and CO<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="158"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met21" novelty="New" advantage="None">The small gaps in are bridged using linear interpolation to obtain a continuous CO<SB>2</SB> emission spectrum for each delay time in the data sets.</annotationART></s> <s sid="159"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met21" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">This method is attractive because it does not require any <IT>a priori</IT> assumption as to the time-dependent shape of the broad CO<SB>2</SB> emission.</annotationART></s> <s sid="160"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met21" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">Because only the accurately known rovibrational line positions of CO are involved in this treatment, we obtain the least biased separation of CO and CO<SB>2</SB> emissions.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="161"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp24" novelty="None" advantage="None">Because the CO<SB>2</SB> emission spectrum at short delay times is not rotationally resolved, our spectroscopic model uses a resolution of 4 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="162"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">We assume a Boltzmann rotational distribution at 330 K and a Boltzmann vibrational distribution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="163"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">While the nascent CO<SB>2</SB> vibrational state distribution may be far from statistical, fast internal vibrational redistribution (IVR) of CO<SB>2</SB>, due to Fermi resonances and high vibrational state density,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit48">48</REF> is expected to redistribute the vibrational energy statistically among the three vibrational modes on a time scale less than our temporal resolution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="164"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fit has two parameters: vibrational temperature and total intensity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="165"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res29" novelty="None" advantage="None">The early spectra of CO<SB>2</SB> indicate that vibrational states as high as <IT>υ</IT><SB>3</SB> ∼ 18 can contribute to the wavelength region where we observe emission.</annotationART></s> <s sid="166"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res30" novelty="None" advantage="None">Because of the anharmonicity and rotation-vibration interaction constants related to the <IT>υ</IT><SB>3</SB> mode, the population of <IT>υ</IT><SB>1</SB> and <IT>υ</IT><SB>2</SB> (symmetric stretch and bend modes) cannot be neglected.</annotationART></s> <s sid="167"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The maximum quantum numbers for the <IT>υ</IT><SB>1</SB>, <IT>υ</IT><SB>2</SB>, and <IT>υ</IT><SB>3</SB> modes in the fit are 30, 65, and 25 respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="168"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">As in the rotationally resolved fitting, only (<IT>mn</IT><SP><IT>l</IT></SP><IT>p</IT>) → (<IT>mn</IT><SP><IT>l</IT></SP><IT>p</IT> − 1) transitions are included.</annotationART></s> <s sid="169"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met22" novelty="New" advantage="None">Emission spectra of CO<SB>2</SB> at <IT>t</IT> = 25–185 μs are fit using the low-resolution model.</annotationART></s> <s sid="170"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 5 shows representative experimental spectra and corresponding fits.</annotationART></s> <s sid="171"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" advantage="None">The residuals in Figs. 5–7 are generally comparable to the baseline noise away from spectral features.</annotationART></s> <s sid="172"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The increased residuals in the lower panel of Fig. 5 may indicate that our spectroscopic model of hot CO<SB>2</SB> is too simplistic, but we believe the data do not justify a more complex model.</annotationART></s> <s sid="173"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res32" novelty="None" advantage="None">The temporal evolution of CO<SB>2</SB> vibrational temperature is well fit by a single exponential curve as shown in Fig. 8.</annotationART></s> <s sid="174"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The vibrational temperatures obtained are 5900 ± 500 K and 6300 ± 500 K for nascent C<SP>16</SP>O<SB>2</SB> and <SP>16</SP>OC<SP>18</SP>O respectively by extrapolating the exponential fitting to <IT>t</IT> = 0.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="IV.">Discussion</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="A.">Reaction paths and their isotopic signatures</HEADER><P><s sid="175"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The possible outcomes of the HCCO + <SP>18</SP>O<SB>2</SB> labeled reaction can be considered with reference to Fig. 1 and the work of Klippenstein <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="176"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Kinetic isotope effects are expected to be negligible due to the small mass difference between the two oxygen isotopes, and the large exothermicity of the observed product channels.</annotationART></s> <s sid="177"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met23" novelty="New" advantage="None">In this case the isotopic labeling provides a means to distinguish different reaction paths without significantly affecting the reactivity of the system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="178"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">As O<SB>2</SB> approaches HCCO, a barrier at saddle point 1 (sp1) arises because the addition of O<SB>2</SB> breaks the resonance stabilization in HCCO.</annotationART></s> <s sid="179"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The initial adduct (I) can dissociate along two different reaction coordinates to yield H(<SP>18</SP>O)CC<SP>16</SP>O + <SP>18</SP>O (path E) or, with an energetically expensive H atom transfer, <SP>18</SP>OH + C<SP>16</SP>O + C<SP>18</SP>O (path F).</annotationART></s> <s sid="180"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Theoretical calculations indicate that these two pathways are of very minor importance at room temperature due to the high potential energy barriers sp2 and sp.3<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="181"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In light of these calculations, we expect that only paths A–D, which yield product channels 2 and 4, have the possibility to contribute at room temperature.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="182"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The unpaired electron on oxygen in the initial adduct (I) may attack either carbon atom, forming a three-member (II) or resonantly stabilized four-member (III) ring intermediate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="183"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The barrier to ring closing is higher for (II) than for (III), but the formation of a three-member ring involves less of an entropy penalty.</annotationART></s> <s sid="184"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is therefore not obvious which pathway will be more favorable.</annotationART></s> <s sid="185"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The dissociation of the three-member ring intermediate (II) occurs through C–C bond cleavage along path D. HC<SP>18</SP>O<SB>2</SB> (IV) is at most only marginally bound,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit49">49</REF> and will dissociate giving the final products H + <SP>18</SP>OC<SP>18</SP>O + C<SP>16</SP>O.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="186"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod12" novelty="None" advantage="None">In comparison, decomposition of the four-member ring intermediate may proceed through three different paths (A–C).</annotationART></s> <s sid="187"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod13" novelty="None" advantage="None">In all cases, O–O bond fission occurs first over sp5, leading to an <SP>18</SP>OCHC(<SP>18</SP>O)<SP>16</SP>O complex (the flat region near −94 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="188"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res33" novelty="None" advantage="None">The barrier to C–C bond fission in this complex is essentially zero, and it may dissociate directly <IT>via</IT> path A to HC<SP>18</SP>O + <SP>16</SP>OC<SP>18</SP>O. HC<SP>18</SP>O will almost certainly dissociate over sp8 due to the great exothermicity of this product channel, yielding finally H + C<SP>18</SP>O + <SP>16</SP>OC<SP>18</SP>O. However, the direct dynamics classical trajectory calculations of <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">ref. 21</REF>. provide evidence of two additional paths for decomposition of III.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="189"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Following O–O bond fission over sp5, the hydrogen atom may transfer to the unpaired electron on the <SP>16</SP>O atom.</annotationART></s> <s sid="190"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">If the C–C bond lives long enough for internal rotation about this bond, the H atom could also transfer to the <SP>18</SP>O atom in the CO<SB>2</SB> moiety.</annotationART></s> <s sid="191"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res34" novelty="None" advantage="None">In either case, after the H transfer the ensuing C–C bond fission leads to HOCO + CO (V), with isotope labels shown in Fig. 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="192"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The HOCO radical will almost certainly dissociate because of the great exothermicity of the reaction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="193"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">This dissociation, and the corresponding reaction OH + CO, has been studied extensively.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit50 cit51">50,51</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="194"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">There are two possible dissociation channels of HOCO: OH + CO and H + CO<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="195"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The OH + CO → HOCO reaction has a loose transition state, and may have a slight entrance barrier, while H + CO<SB>2</SB> → HOCO has a tight transition state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="196"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">High level <IT>ab initio</IT> calculations have located saddle points on the HOCO → CO<SB>2</SB> + H potential, which are 1.5 and 7.8 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> above the HO + CO asymptote for <IT>cis</IT> and <IT>trans</IT> HOCO respectively.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit52">52</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="197"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Variational transition state theory rate coefficient calculations<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit53">53</REF> predict that these two dissociation channels are almost equally important with 1 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> energy above the OH + CO asymptote.</annotationART></s> <s sid="198"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the OH + CO channel quickly becomes the dominant reaction channel and remains about an order of magnitude faster than H + CO<SB>2</SB> as energy increases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="199"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the reaction of HCCO + O<SB>2</SB> is highly exothermic, we expect that H + CO<SB>2</SB> would be a minor channel of HOCO dissociation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="200"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res35" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note, however, that path C cannot be distinguished from path A using the present isotopic labels.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="201"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res36" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, if we ignore the possibility of internal rotation about the C–C bond as (III) dissociates, the resulting isotopic intermediate is H<SP>16</SP>OC<SP>18</SP>O + C<SP>18</SP>O, which leads to <SP>16</SP>OH + C<SP>18</SP>O + C<SP>18</SP>O. At the other limit, if rotation about the C–C bond were facile as (III) dissociates, the final products would be a mixture of <SP>18</SP>OH + C<SP>16</SP>O + C<SP>18</SP>O and <SP>16</SP>OH + C<SP>18</SP>O + C<SP>18</SP>O with a relative ratio of 1∶1, as indicated in Fig. 1.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="B.">Contributions of each reaction path</HEADER><P><s sid="202"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="New" advantage="None">Given these possible paths on the potential energy surface, we now evaluate the constraints placed on the flux through these paths by the experimental data.</annotationART></s> <s sid="203"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Assuming that paths C, E, and F are negligible, as discussed above, we can draw the following connections between the product rate coefficients and the path-specific rate coefficients for this reaction: <IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB> = <IT>k</IT><SB>A</SB> + <IT>k</IT><SB>D</SB>,<IT>k</IT><SB>4</SB> = <IT>k</IT><SB>B</SB>,<IT>k</IT><SB>tot</SB> = <IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB> + <IT>k</IT><SB>4</SB> = <IT>k</IT><SB>A</SB> + <IT>k</IT><SB>D</SB> + <IT>k</IT><SB>B</SB>, where <IT>k</IT><SB>tot</SB> is the total rate coefficient.</annotationART></s> <s sid="204"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that <IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB>, the rate coefficient for H + CO + CO<SB>2</SB> production, may contain contributions from both the three- and four-member ring intermediates.</annotationART></s> <s sid="205"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The data place three constraints on these equations: two isotope ratios measured in this work, [C<SP>16</SP>O]/[C<SP>18</SP>O] &lt; 0.16 and [<SP>18</SP>OC<SP>18</SP>O]/[<SP>16</SP>OC<SP>18</SP>O] &lt; 0.30, and the limit on total OH production (<IT>k</IT><SB>B</SB>/<IT>k</IT><SB>tot</SB>) &lt; 0.10 from .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27">ref. 27</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="206"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The quantities we wish to obtain are the fractions of flux through the three- and four-member ring pathways: <IT>Φ</IT><SB>3-mem</SB> = (<IT>k</IT><SB>D</SB>/<IT>k</IT><SB>tot</SB>) and <IT>Φ</IT><SB>4-mem</SB> = 1 − <IT>Φ</IT><SB>3-mem</SB>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="207"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res37" novelty="None" advantage="None">The CO<SB>2</SB> isotopic ratio yields the most straightforward analysis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="208"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res38" novelty="None" advantage="None">Because only paths A and D produce CO<SB>2</SB>, we have [<SP>18</SP>OC<SP>18</SP>O]/[<SP>16</SP>OC<SP>18</SP>O] = <IT>k</IT><SB>D</SB>/<IT>k</IT><SB>A</SB> &lt; 0.3, and therefore <IT>k</IT><SB>D</SB>/(<IT>k</IT><SB>A</SB> + <IT>k</IT><SB>D</SB>) &lt; 0.23.</annotationART></s> <s sid="209"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res39" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the limit that 100% of the reaction produces CO<SB>2</SB> (<IT>i.e.</IT>, (<IT>k</IT><SB>B</SB>/<IT>k</IT><SB>tot</SB>) = 0) we have simply <IT>Φ</IT><SB>3-mem</SB> = <IT>k</IT><SB>D</SB>/(<IT>k</IT><SB>A</SB> + <IT>k</IT><SB>D</SB>) &lt; 0.23.</annotationART></s> <s sid="210"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res40" novelty="None" advantage="None">At the other limit, if 90% of the total reaction produces CO<SB>2</SB> (<IT>i.e.</IT>, (<IT>k</IT><SB>B</SB>/<IT>k</IT><SB>tot</SB>) = 0.1) the flux through the three-member ring becomes The conservative estimate based on the CO<SB>2</SB> isotope ratio is therefore <IT>Φ</IT><SB>3-mem</SB> &lt; 0.23.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="211"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res41" novelty="None" advantage="None">An evaluation based on the CO isotope ratios is somewhat more complicated because every possibility produces either one or two CO molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="212"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res42" novelty="None" advantage="None">If internal rotation of the CO<SB>2</SB> moiety about the C–C bond as (III) dissociates is slow, the H atom can only transfer to the <SP>16</SP>O atom along path B, and we have In the limit that <IT>k</IT><SB>4</SB> = <IT>k</IT><SB>B</SB> = 0, we obtain <IT>Φ</IT><SB>3-mem</SB> = (<IT>k</IT><SB>D</SB>/<IT>k</IT><SB>tot</SB>) &lt; 0.14, while for (<IT>k</IT><SB>B</SB>/<IT>k</IT><SB>tot</SB>) = 0.1 the result increases slightly to <IT>Φ</IT><SB>3-mem</SB> = (<IT>k</IT><SB>D</SB>/<IT>k</IT><SB>tot</SB>) &lt; 0.15.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="213"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res43" novelty="None" advantage="None">Finally, if internal rotation of the CO<SB>2</SB> moiety about the C–C bond as (III) dissociates is fast, the H atom may transfer with equal probability to <SP>16</SP>O or <SP>18</SP>O along path B. In this case 25% of the CO produced along path B is C<SP>16</SP>O, and we have As before, in the limit that <IT>k</IT><SB>4</SB> = <IT>k</IT><SB>B</SB> = 0, we obtain <IT>Φ</IT><SB>3-mem</SB> = (<IT>k</IT><SB>D</SB>/<IT>k</IT><SB>tot</SB>) &lt; 0.14, but in contrast, for (<IT>k</IT><SB>B</SB>/<IT>k</IT><SB>tot</SB>) = 0.1 the result decreases to <IT>Φ</IT><SB>3-mem</SB> = (<IT>k</IT><SB>D</SB>/<IT>k</IT><SB>tot</SB>) &lt; 0.10.</annotationART></s> <s sid="214"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res44" novelty="None" advantage="None">Overall, the conservative result from the CO spectra is <IT>Φ</IT><SB>3-mem</SB> &lt; 0.15, which is somewhat more restrictive than the result obtained from the CO<SB>2</SB> spectra, as expected from their worse signal-to-noise ratio.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="215"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con15" novelty="None" advantage="None">In summary, we find that at least 85% of the total reactive flux passes through the four-member ring intermediate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="216"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res45" novelty="None" advantage="None">Path A is the dominant reaction path, and H atom transfer during dissociation of (III) plays at most a minor role.</annotationART></s> <s sid="217"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con16" novelty="None" advantage="None">These results agree qualitatively with the rate constants and the 209 direct dynamic trajectories calculated by Klippenstein <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="218"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res46" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our reaction path analysis depends strongly on the signal-to-noise ratio of the data.</annotationART></s> <s sid="219"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The accuracy of our derived limits could be improved with better quality data, which is limited primarily by the cost of <SP>18</SP>O<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="C.">Vibrational energies compared with a statistical model</HEADER><P><s sid="220"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res47" novelty="None" advantage="None">The vibrational temperatures of CO and CO<SB>2</SB> extracted from the data are 9050 (average of C<SP>16</SP>O and C<SP>18</SP>O) and 6100 K (average of <SP>16</SP>OC<SP>18</SP>O and <SP>16</SP>OC<SP>16</SP>O) respectively, which correspond to average vibrational energies of 15.7 and 43.6 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> for CO and CO<SB>2</SB> respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="221"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met24" novelty="Old" advantage="None">We have modeled the energy partitioning in this channel using the separate statistical ensembles (SSE) method.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit54">54</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="222"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met24" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The SSE model is a refined phase space theory (PST), in which the vibrational branching is defined early in the dissociation, and the coupling between vibrations is assumed to be small for the remainder of the dissociation process.</annotationART></s> <s sid="223"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met24" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The rotational distributions are then statistically distributed using PST within each vibrational reservoir.</annotationART></s> <s sid="224"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The SSE model is usually applied to unimolecular photodissociation in which the products have no recombination barrier.</annotationART></s> <s sid="225"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac20" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the present reaction, while the barriers to decomposition of the four-membered ring intermediate are small, the overall reaction is exothermic, in contrast to unimolecular dissociation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="226"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Nevertheless, we have applied this model to the HCCO + O<SB>2</SB> reaction because it is straightforward to implement and provides a first assessment of the degree to which the system behaves statistically.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="227"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac21" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the HCCO + O<SB>2</SB> reaction, the four-membered ring intermediate dissociation along path A involves two bond cleavages.</annotationART></s> <s sid="228"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac21" novelty="None" advantage="None">According to Klippenstein <IT>et al.</IT>'s calculation,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF> the step-wise dissociation occurs with O–O bond fission prior to C–C bond fission.</annotationART></s> <s sid="229"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac21" novelty="None" advantage="None">The barrier height for O–O bond breaking (sp5) is less than 4 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> while there is no barrier for the subsequent C–C bond breaking.</annotationART></s> <s sid="230"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac21" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, the barrier to formation of the four-member ring intermediate (sp4) is even smaller than sp5.</annotationART></s> <s sid="231"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac21" novelty="None" advantage="None">While there is a small exit barrier (sp8) to dissociation of HCO,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit55">55</REF> this barrier is also small compared to the available energy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="232"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met25" novelty="New" advantage="None">It is worth noting that a modified statistical model was required to describe HCO dissociation at low and intermediate energies above the dissociation threshold<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit56">56</REF> because its low density of states leads to slow IVR.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit57">57</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="233"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp9" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, these nonstatistical effects are expected to be less important at high HCO internal energy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="234"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Because the excess reaction energy is significantly larger than all these barrier heights on the PES of the HCCO + O<SB>2</SB> reaction, the SSE method may still be applicable for the four-membered ring intermediate decomposition and subsequent HCO dissociation.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="235"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod16" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to evaluate the CO vibrational energy distribution, a two-step reaction mechanism was assumed for the four-membered ring intermediate: dissociation to HCO + CO<SB>2</SB> (VI), followed by HCO → H + CO.</annotationART></s> <s sid="236"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The available energy for the first step is the energy difference between the HCCO + O<SB>2</SB> reactants and HCO + CO<SB>2</SB>, 126.0 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="237"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The available energy for the second step is the internal energy of HCO minus the H—CO bond enthalpy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="238"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met26" novelty="New" advantage="None">The small exit barrier of HCO dissociation (sp8) is ignored in the SSE calculation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="239"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met27" novelty="New" advantage="None">For each HCO vibrational level, the corresponding CO vibrational state distribution is calculated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="240"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met28" novelty="New" advantage="None">The population of each vibrational state of CO is summed over all the possible HCO vibrational energies to obtain the final CO vibrational state distribution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="241"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp25" novelty="None" advantage="None">The vibrational frequencies for HCO are adopted from .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit58">ref. 58</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="242"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj5" novelty="New" advantage="None">The SSE method is only performed for <SP>16</SP>O isotopes in the current study.</annotationART></s> <s sid="243"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the model is only sensitive to the final product vibrational frequencies, and this frequency difference is small for <SP>16</SP>O and <SP>18</SP>O isotopes, the results of <SP>18</SP>O isotopes are expected to be very similar to <SP>16</SP>O.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="244"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res48" novelty="None" advantage="None">The predicted average vibrational energies from the SSE method are 48.2 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> for CO<SB>2</SB>, and 15.8 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> for CO, respectively, in reasonable agreement with the experimental values.</annotationART></s> <s sid="245"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The CO vibrational state distribution obtained from the SSE model is shown in Fig. 4.</annotationART></s> <s sid="246"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res49" novelty="None" advantage="None">The predicted product state distribution is in qualitative, but not quantitative agreement with experimental results.</annotationART></s> <s sid="247"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con18" novelty="None" advantage="None">One interpretation of the highly excited CO<SB>2</SB> and CO vibrational state distributions observed in this reaction is that the large geometry changes between the four-membered ring intermediate and the separated products lead to significant Franck–Condon excitation of product vibrational modes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="248"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con19" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the reasonable agreement between experiment and the SSE model implies that a statistical description is sufficient to explain the experimental results, due to the large exothermicity of the reaction and strong coupling between vibrational degrees of freedom as the intermediate dissociates.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="V.">Conclusions</HEADER><P><s sid="249"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa7" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have studied the reaction HCCO + <SP>18</SP>O<SB>2</SB> using time-resolved Fourier spectroscopy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="250"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con20" novelty="None" advantage="None">The observed C<SP>18</SP>O and <SP>16</SP>OC<SP>18</SP>O emission spectra indicate that the reaction occurs primarily through a four-membered ring intermediate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="251"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res50" novelty="None" advantage="None">Spectral fits yield the limits <IT>Φ</IT><SB>3-mem</SB> &lt; 15% and <IT>Φ</IT><SB>4-mem</SB> &gt; 85% for the total reactive flux through the two possible ring intermediates.</annotationART></s> <s sid="252"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con21" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hydrogen transfer during decomposition of the four-membered ring intermediate is a minor process.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="253"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res51" novelty="None" advantage="None">The CO and CO<SB>2</SB> products are found to be highly vibrationally excited with vibrational temperatures of 9050 ± 1400 K and 6100 ± 700 K respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="254"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con22" novelty="None" advantage="None">The average vibrational energy deposited in CO and CO<SB>2</SB> is reasonably well predicted by the separate statistical ensembles (SSE) method, implying that statistical rather than dynamical effects dominate this reaction mechanism.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
