<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b401234h" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Electrochemical impedance spectra for the complete equivalent circuit of diffusion and reaction under steady-state recombination current</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">We have analyzed the impedance model for diffusion and reaction in non-equilibrium steady-state, when large diffusion current flows in a thin film either due to homogeneous reaction or heterogeneous charge-transfer in a nanoporous film (photoelectrochemical solar cells).</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Besides the standard diffusion resistance, transport in non-equilibrium conditions introduces a current generator in the transmission line equivalent circuit, which is due to an inhomogeneous conductivity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Numerical simulation of impedance spectra shows that the effect of the current generator is rather large when the diffusion length is shorter than the film thickness.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="1.">Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The impedance spectroscopy technique is widely used in electrochemistry and solid-state electrochemistry, particularly for investigation of new and interesting systems such as nanostructured semiconductor electrodes and photoelectrochemical solar cells.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2">1,2</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Diffusion and diffusion-reaction phenomena appear often in these systems.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The impedance models are usually represented by a repetitive spatial arrangement (transmission line) involving resistances and capacitors.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">These elements pertain to the kinetic model that combines transport, reaction (or recombination) and charge accumulation processes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">With simplifying assumptions these models can be solved completely and the impedance responses, depending on system parameters, have been classified.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Frequently, significant deviations from the basic diffusion-reaction model spectra are observed in impedance measurements.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Different assumptions have been used in recent years in order to obtain more realistic model spectra: anomalous diffusion processes,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF> multiple trapping<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF> and non-uniform conductivity and capacitance.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6">5,6</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Very recently, Paasch<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7 cit8">7,8</REF> pointed out an effect that has been generally disregarded in the huge literature of diffusion impedances.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is a current generator that occurs in the transmission line equivalent circuit when steady-state current flows in the transport-reaction zone.</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">This element was derived by Sah in the transmission lines for solid-state electronics.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10 cit11 cit12">10–12</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">It has so far been neglected in solid-state electrochemistry, probably because the electrodes are usually blocking to steady-state current (<IT>e.g</IT>., in intercalation electrodes and conducting polymer films).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, strong steady-state diffusion currents become a quite important and even dominant feature in many applications.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">For example, TiO<SB>2</SB> nanostructured electrodes in dye-sensitized solar cells<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13 cit14 cit15">13–15</REF> provide strong diffusion-reaction (charge-transfer) currents at forward bias, and the same electrodes can be used in photocatalysis with a similar behaviour.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In these conditions, the concentration is strongly non-uniform, which complicates the equivalent circuit model, so that analytical solutions are not generally possible.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is necessary to investigate the impedance response of these systems considering the full theoretical model of diffusion-reaction including the current generators identified by Sah.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot3" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is particularly important to evaluate the extent to which, and in which conditions, the effects of non-homogeneity and current generators modify the results of the simpler equivalent circuits<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF> that are widely used.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">As a central example of electrochemical system in which diffusion and reaction are the dominant phenomena we will discuss the nanostructured semiconductor electrodes in contact with a redox electrolyte as shown in the schemes of Fig. 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">In this system electrons are injected either from photoexcited dye molecules adsorbed in the surface,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13 cit14 cit15">13–15</REF> or from the conducting substrate in which the film is deposited, applying a negative bias potential with respect to the Pt counterelectrode.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is widely believed that the displacement of electrons is governed mainly by diffusion, due to the effective shielding of large-scale electrical field by the conducting medium that permeates the nano-pores.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16 cit17 cit18">16–18</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of substrate-injected electrons, the concentration will decrease towards the outer edge of the electrode (where the electron flux <IT>J</IT><SB><IT>n</IT></SB> = 0) due to electron transfer across the oxide/electrolyte interface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">There are two main situations according to the strength of charge transfer with respect to electron transport, as shown in Fig. 1d.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">For low recombination, the electron diffusion length is much larger than film thickness and the concentration profile is nearly homogeneous.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the opposite case, the concentration decays rapidly near the injecting boundary.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Impedance models have been developed to treat these situations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The transmission line model used previously<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2">1,2</REF> is indicated in Fig. 1c.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">It corresponds to the expressionwhere <IT>R</IT><SB>t</SB> is the diffusion resistance, <IT>R</IT><SB>rec</SB> is the recombination resistance, <IT>ω</IT><SB>d</SB> = <IT>D</IT><SB><IT>n</IT></SB>/<IT>L</IT><SP>2</SP> is the characteristic frequency of diffusion in a finite layer (<IT>D</IT><SB><IT>n</IT></SB> being the electron diffusion coefficient), <IT>ω</IT><SB>k</SB> is the rate constant for recombination, <IT>ω</IT> is the angular frequency and .</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The model of eqn. (1) is valid for homogeneous elements in the transmission line.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, eqn. (1) considers only the modulation of the gradient of the Fermi level<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF> and not the current generators associated to position-dependent conductivity, as commented further below.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">With these simplifications, the transmission line model can be solved analytically.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the conditions of low recombination, <IT>R</IT><SB>t</SB> ≪ <IT>R</IT><SB>k</SB>, eqn. (1) reduces to the expression</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the other hand, in conditions of large recombination, <IT>R</IT><SB>t</SB> ≫ <IT>R</IT><SB>k</SB>, the general impedance of eqn. (1) becomes the Gerischer impedance,</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 2 shows the impedance shapes corresponding to the transmission line model of Fig. 1c.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The different shapes are obtained by changing only one parameter, the charge-transfer resistance <IT>R</IT><SB>rec</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Curves 1–5 are well described by eqn. (2), while curves 7–8 correspond to Gerischer impedance in eqn. (3).</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">All impedances show at high frequency a diffusion line of slope 1, which is implied by eqn. (1), <IT>Z</IT>(<IT>ω</IT>) ∝ (<IT>i</IT><IT>ω</IT>)<SP>−1/2</SP> at <IT>ω</IT> ≫ <IT>ω</IT><SB>k</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the conditions of low recombination (<IT>ω</IT><SB>k</SB> &lt; <IT>ω</IT><SB>d</SB>) for curves 1–3, the 45° line of diffusion is a minor feature at high frequencies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The impedance is largely dominated by the reaction arc, the second term in eqn. (2), with the characteristic frequency <IT>ω</IT><SB>k</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast, at high recombination <IT>ω</IT><SB>k</SB> &lt; <IT>ω</IT><SB>d</SB>, the impedance behaviour is similar to semi-infinite diffusion, curve .8<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The experimental impedance of nanostructured TiO<SB>2</SB> electrodes in solution, agrees qualitatively with the features of this model.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 3a shows an instance of eqn. (2), and Fig. 3b shows the Gerischer impedance that is measured when the rate of charge-transfer becomes large.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot4" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, it is evident in Fig. 1d that in the case when the difusion length is shorter than the film thickness, the distribution of electrons is strongly inhomogeneous.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot4" novelty="None" advantage="None">This should have a considerable influence in the measured impedance, both through the inhomogeneous impedance elements and the current generators.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to investigate this question, in this paper improved impedance models will be developed and discussed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None">We provide first a discussion of the physical origin of the complete equivalent circuit for diffusion-reaction of a single species.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thereafter we solve numerically the model in a variety of cases, varying both the materials and control parameters.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa4" novelty="None" advantage="None">We point out the main modifications to the standard model spectra.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.">The transport equations</HEADER><P><s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="New" advantage="None">We consider the statistics and transport of conduction band electrons.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The number density <IT>n</IT> is related to the electrochemical potential (or Fermi level) <IT></IT><SB><IT>n</IT></SB> by the Boltzmann distributionwhere <IT>k</IT><SB>B</SB><IT>T</IT> is the thermal energy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">According to non-equilibrium thermodynamics<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19">19</REF> one can formulate a linear phenomenological law that relates the irreversible flow to the thermodynamic force.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the flux of electrons in semiconductors the following relationship was formulated by Shockley<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF>The equilibrium condition is .</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">If we assume that the Galvani potential is uniform, as indicated in Fig. 1b by the homogeneous level of the lower edge of the conduction band, then <IT></IT><SB><IT>n</IT></SB> = <IT>μ</IT><SB><IT>n</IT></SB> + const, in terms of the chemical potential of electrons, <IT>μ</IT><SB><IT>n</IT></SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Eqn. (4) can be written as</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Then, by eqn. (5) the diffusion flux relates to the gradient of concentration as</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Eqn. (6) implies that the chemical capacitance<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF> for electrons (per unit volume) takes the formwhere <IT>e</IT> is the positive electron charge.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The meaning of eqn. (8) has been discussed elsewhere.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22 cit23 cit24">22–24</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The equation of conservation for diffusion, recombination and generation iswhere <IT>τ</IT><SB><IT>n</IT></SB> and <IT>n</IT><SB>0</SB> are constants for electron transfer (recombination), the lifetime and equilibrium concentration, respectively, and <IT>Φ</IT><SB>ph</SB> is the photogeneration rate.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">At <IT>x</IT> = 0 we place a reversible contact to a conducting substrate (Fig. 1b) so that <IT>V</IT>, the bias electrical potential, relates to chemical potential of electrons in TiO<SB>2</SB> as: −<IT>eV</IT> = <IT>μ</IT><SB><IT>n</IT></SB> − <IT>μ</IT><SB><IT>n</IT>0</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Using eqn. (6) we obtainAt the outer boundary of the film, <IT>x</IT> = <IT>L</IT>, we have the reflecting boundary condition</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the steady state, the excess electron concentration is determined by the equationwhich has been written using the electron diffusion length</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">From eqns. (10), (11) and (12) the following distribution of electrons in the porous network is found for <IT>Φ</IT><SB>ph</SB> = 0</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The diffusion current at the substrate/film interface gives the electrical current density</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.">Small signal perturbation</HEADER><P><s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The small signal perturbation techniques, such as electrochemical impedance spectroscopy, impose a small perturbation of a controlled physical quantity over a steady state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In general, this steady state will not be an equilibrium state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">For example, when <IT>V</IT> ≠ 0 eqn. (14) implies ∂<IT></IT>/∂<IT>x</IT> ≠ 0 at all <IT>x</IT> ≠ <IT>L</IT>, so that a steady-state current flows in the system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to analyze the evolution equations under a small perturbation, we express the different variables as a combination of a stationary and a (small) time dependent component: concentration, <IT>n</IT> + <IT>ρ</IT><SB><IT>n</IT></SB>(<IT>t</IT>), flux, <IT>J</IT><SB><IT>n</IT></SB> − <IT>i</IT><SB><IT>n</IT></SB>(<IT>t</IT>)/<IT>e</IT>, Fermi level, <IT></IT><SB><IT>n</IT></SB> − <IT>eφ</IT><SB><IT>n</IT></SB>, and photogeneration rate, <IT>Φ</IT><SB>ph</SB> + <IT>ϕ</IT><SB>ph</SB>(<IT>t</IT>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">We write the perturbation of both the flux, <IT>i</IT><SB><IT>n</IT></SB>, and the electrochemical potential, <IT>φ</IT><SB><IT>n</IT></SB>, in units of electrical current and electrical potential, respectively, for convenience of representation in transmission line.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="New" advantage="None">We begin the analysis of small modulated quantities by the phenomenological relationship for the electron flux, eqn. (5), that describes the exchange of electrons between two neighbour points.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">When it is linearized, eqn. (5) giveswhere we have defined the transport resistance (per unit volume), <IT>r</IT><SB>t</SB>, which is reciprocal to the electron conductivity</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The first term in eqn. (16) is the standard resistive component in the transport channel in transmission line models.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit9">1,9</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">As a remark, we wish to clarify the meaning of the “potentials” in the transmission lines drawn below.</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Consider the difference Δ<IT>φ</IT><SB><IT>n</IT></SB> between two points separated Δ<IT>x</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The first term in eqn. (16) can be written aswhere Δ<IT>R</IT> = <IT>r</IT><SB>t</SB>Δ<IT>x</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Eqn. (18) is a generalized statement of Ohm’s law with respect to the local difference of <IT>electrochemical potentials</IT>, Δ<IT>φ</IT><SB><IT>n</IT></SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Δ<IT>R</IT> is the resistance in a slab of thickness Δ<IT>x</IT>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the diffusion model (uniform Galvani potential) Δ<IT>φ</IT><SB><IT>n</IT></SB> corresponds to a local difference in modulated component of chemical potential.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">If the steady-state concentration, <IT>n</IT>, is uniform, the second term in eqn. (16) is zero and the small perturbation flux, <IT>i</IT><SB><IT>n</IT></SB>, will be driven by the difference of excess chemical potential, Δ<IT>φ</IT><SB><IT>n</IT></SB>, between two points.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">So the small perturbation component of diffusion flux is caused by two adjacent chemical capacitors, <IT>c</IT><SB><IT>μ</IT></SB>, that will be differently charged, Δ<IT>ρ</IT><SB><IT>n</IT></SB>, by the difference in Δ<IT>φ</IT><SB><IT>n</IT></SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is represented in equivalent circuit convention in Fig. 4a.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">This effect will also exist if <IT>n</IT> is non-uniform, although the chemical capacitance will have different values at neighbor points.</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, in this case the second term of eqn. (16) will not be zero, and another effect exists,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7 cit8 cit10 cit11 cit12">7,8,10–12</REF> as discussed below.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Assuming quasi-equilibrium, and linearizing eqn. (6), we get</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Then eqn. (16) can be written aswhere</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The second term in eqn. (20) was first identified by Sah.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10 cit11 cit12">10–12</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Obviously, eqn. (21) is nonzero only if the system is not in equilibrium steady state, ∂<IT></IT><SB><IT>n</IT></SB>/∂<IT>x</IT> ≠ 0, (or alternatively, <IT>J</IT><SB><IT>n</IT></SB> ≠ 0).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7 cit8">7,8</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">This contribution is related to the small perturbation of the prefactor of the phenomenological flux expression, eqn. (5), <IT>i.e.</IT>, the conductivity <IT>σ</IT><SB><IT>n</IT></SB> (through the carrier density, eqn. (17)).</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Indeed, when ∂<IT></IT><SB><IT>n</IT></SB>/∂<IT>x</IT> ≠ 0, a homogeneous change of the modulated component of Fermi level, <IT>φ</IT><SB><IT>n</IT></SB>, causes a change of the diffusion flux, which is represented by a current generator, −<IT>g</IT><SB><IT>σ</IT></SB><IT>φ</IT><SB><IT>n</IT></SB>, in eqn. (20) and Fig. 4b.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The conservation eqn. (9) governs the variation of carrier density at a given point.</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Eqn. (9) involves the time dependence through the term on the left.</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">In particular, we consider a small sinusoidal perturbation of angular frequency, <IT>ω</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Linearizing eqn. (9), taking the Laplace transform d/d<IT>t</IT>→i<IT>ω</IT>, and denoting the transformed variables by the same symbol, <IT>i.e</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None"><IT>φ</IT><SB><IT>n</IT></SB>(<IT>x,t</IT>)→<IT>φ</IT><SB><IT>n</IT></SB>(<IT>x,ω</IT>), we obtainwhere we have defined the recombination resistance (per unit volume)</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Eqn. (22) can be described as follows.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit22">1,22</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The first term is a capacitive current, the charging of the chemical capacitance.</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The second term is the recombination current.</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The third term is the photogeneration current.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that these currents do not represent transport currents, but the rates of creation and destruction of conduction band electrons.</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Further discussion of these terms is given in .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">ref. 22</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The last term in eqn. (22) describes the change in concentration by transport current from neighbor points.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Combining eqns. (20) and (22), the transmission line model of Fig. 5 is obtained.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.">Numerical results and discussion</HEADER><P><s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">With the aim of exploring the repercussion of the current generator on the overall response of a one-carrier system governed by diffusion and recombination/reaction with steady-state current different from zero, we have chosen a transmission line with completely reflecting boundary condition, as shown in Fig. 1c, in which the elementary line cell is that represented in Fig. 5.</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the sake of simplicity the photocurrent generator <IT>ϕ</IT><SB>ph</SB> has been neglected, <IT>i.e.</IT> simulations were done under dark conditions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="New" advantage="None">From eqn. (14) one can calculate the distribution of electrons for each value of the bias potential and thereby the circuit elements as a function of position.</annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="New" advantage="None">The chemical capacitance <IT>c</IT><SB><IT>μ</IT></SB> results from eqn. (8), transport resistance <IT>r</IT><SB><IT>t</IT></SB> from eqn. (17), current generator element <IT>g</IT><SB><IT>σ</IT></SB> from eqn. (21), and finally reaction resistance from eqn. (23).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The film thickness (0 ≤ <IT>x</IT> ≤ <IT>L</IT>) has been split into <IT>m</IT> slabs of equal width.</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="New" advantage="None">In order to check the resolution of the spatial discretization we compared the analytical value of the steady-state current [eqn.</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="New" advantage="None">(15)] and the current resulting from the application of the Fick’s law to the first cell of the transmission line.</annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Differences less than 0.1% are achieved for <IT>m</IT> = 1000 for several values of the diffusion length (0.1<IT>L</IT> ≤ <IT>L</IT><SB><IT>n</IT></SB> ≤ 10<IT>L</IT>) and the bias potential (0 V ≤ <IT>V</IT> ≤ 1 V).</annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">It was also verified that the low-frequency limit of the impedance, <IT>R</IT><SB>dc</SB> resistance, calculated by the derivative of eqn. (15) with respect of the bias potential, coincides with that obtained from the numerical simulation within the same accuracy.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 6 shows the results of the numerical simulation of the exact equivalent circuit, as compared to the impedance spectra resulting under equilibrium conditions (zero bias potential).</annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Simulations have been made for three different diffusion lengths, from much smaller to much larger than film thickness, and have been normalized to the dc resistance to facilitate comparison of spectral shapes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">As commented before, the models without current generators display patterns which in the cases <IT>L</IT><SB><IT>n</IT></SB> ≥ <IT>L</IT> consist of a transition from a purely diffusion impedance at high-enough frequencies (Warburg-like behavior) to a semicircle at lower ones, Fig. 6b and 6c.</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the diffusion length of order 3<IT>L</IT> there is no modification of the impedance pattern because the concentration profile changes slightly with respect to the equilibrium situation.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the contrary, as <IT>L</IT><SB><IT>n</IT></SB> decreases the effects of non-equilibrium and non-homogeneity become more visible in the impedance, Fig. 6a.</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The high-frequency diffusional line of the Gerischer impedance becomes heavily distorted.</annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">As previously commented, the bias potential has a great influence on the actual value of the dc resistance.</annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the normalized impedance spectra only undergo changes for bias potential values within the range of 0–100 mV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">For potentials larger than 100 mV normalized spectra exhibit patterns that coincide with that calculated for <IT>V</IT> = 100 mV.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj5" novelty="New" advantage="None">It is worth analyzing separately the repercussion of the current generator element <IT>g</IT><SB><IT>σ</IT></SB> on the whole impedance spectra with respect to the influence of the inhomogeneity of the other circuit elements with position <IT>x</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The effect of inhomogeneous circuit elements (without regarding current generators) was studied by others,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit25">5,25</REF> and it is exemplified in Fig. 7 in comparison with the complete equivalent circuit response.</annotationART></s> <s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">As observed, the inclusion of the current generator is absolutely necessary for an exact determination of the frequency response.</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Not only the value of the dc resistance changes but also the shape of the impedance spectra is altered.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The potential change produced by the inclusion of the current generator can be calculated by considering the Thèvenin equivalent of the current source as <IT>g</IT><SB><IT>σ</IT></SB><IT>r</IT><SB><IT>t</IT></SB>d<IT>x</IT>, which using eqns. (17) and (21) may be written as a specific parameter given byIt is observed that <IT>γ</IT> is a dimensionless parameter.</annotationART></s> <s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="Old" advantage="None">From eqn. (24) it is possible to define an average effect of the current generator for the whole film thickness by means of the following expression,</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">We point out that the average effect of the current generator depends on the concentration values at both limits of the diffusion layer and not on the particular concentration profile.</annotationART></s> <s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In case of equilibrium conditions <IT>n</IT> = <IT>n</IT><SB>0</SB>, constant along the film thickness, so that <IT></IT> = 0 as expected.</annotationART></s> <s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The effect increases as the ratio of concentrations at the boundaries becomes larger.</annotationART></s> <s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The variations of <IT>γ</IT> with position for different diffusion length and bias potential are summarized in Fig. 8.</annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The effect of <IT>γ</IT> is obviously higher as the diffusion length decreases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The variations of <IT></IT> with bias potential are displayed in Fig. 8e showing a saturation as the potential becomes larger.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="New" advantage="None">In order to indicate the significance of the average <IT></IT> defined by eqn. (25) we have calculated the increment of the dc resistance resulting from the transmission line calculations (without current generator) with respect to the exact simulation which considers <IT>g</IT><SB><IT>σ</IT></SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">By examining Fig. 9 one can realize that <IT></IT> is actually a measure of the dc resistance deviation Δ<IT>R</IT><SB>dc</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Errors as high as 60% could be committed in case of neglecting the effect of the current generators on the calculated impedance.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa5" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is also of interest to check to what extent the commonly used impedance expression of eqn. (1) is able to extract the main parameters of the diffusion-recombination model.</annotationART></s> <s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is known that eqn. (1) is equivalent to a transmission line with homogeneous elements (Fig. 1c) so that neither the effect of having an inhomogeneous distribution of circuit elements nor the repercussion of the current generators are taken into account in such a model.</annotationART></s> <s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">In Fig. 10, we show the variation of the diffusion coefficient resulting from fitting simulated spectra using eqn. (1): curves a and b for spectra which result from considering inhomogeneity only, and curves c and d for spectra generated using complete transmission line models, therefore including the current generator effect.</annotationART></s> <s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although quite good fits were obtained in all cases, the diffusion coefficient is overestimated and this deviation is more apparent for lower values of the diffusion length.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="5.">Conclusions</HEADER><P><s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj6" novelty="New" advantage="None">We have analyzed the impedance model for diffusion and reaction in a spatially restricted layer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The complete equivalent circuit in conditions of inhomogeneous carrier distribution requires considering the position-dependent impedance elements, as well as the current generators in parallel to the transport resistances.</annotationART></s> <s sid="143"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">As expected, these effects will be very small, with respect to the standard homogeneous transmission line equivalent circuit, when the diffusion length is much larger than the thickness of the diffusion zone.</annotationART></s> <s sid="144"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast, deviations of the impedance as large as 60% are found when the diffusion length is short.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
