<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b402614d" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Observation of low frequency vibrational modes in a mutant of the green fluorescent protein</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Coherent vibrational dynamics in a mutant of the green fluorescent protein are studied by diffractive optic ultrafast transient grating spectroscopy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Two low frequency (&lt;100 cm<SP>−1</SP>) modes are observed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">We propose that one at 95 cm<SP>−1</SP> may be associated with intramolecular torsional motion in the excited state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">The possible importance of such modes in understanding the very high quantum yield of the intact GFP is discussed.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER /><P><s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The green fluorescent protein (GFP) is a non-invasive genetically encodable fluorescence marker protein.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">It has found numerous and wide-ranging applications in molecular and cell biology.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fluorophore in wild-type (wt) GFP has been identified as 4′-hydroxybenzylidene-imidazolinone, formed through a cyclisation and oxidation reaction of three adjacent amino acid residues, Ser<SP>65</SP>–Tyr<SP>66</SP>–Gly<SP>67</SP>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2 cit3">2,3</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The resulting product is highly stable and strongly fluorescent.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The chromophore is protected from the environment by its location at the centre of an end capped <IT>β</IT>-barrel structure, and it is held in place by both covalent bonds and an extensive H-bonding network, involving the protein backbone and adjacent water molecules.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit5">4,5</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The stability and the high fluorescence yield of the chromophore are consequences of its interactions with the surrounding protein structure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">When the protein is denatured the fluorescence yield decreases by at least three orders of magnitude.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6 cit7">6,7</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, synthetic analogs of the GFP chromophore are essentially nonfluorescent in solution at room temperature.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">We investigated the radiationless decay of the GFP chromophore by ultrafast polarisation spectroscopy<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit9 cit10 cit11">8–11</REF> and time resolved fluorescence.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12 cit13">12,13</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The radiationless decay mechanism is ultrafast internal conversion, due to intramolecular motion about the bridging bond of the chromophore in its excited state.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit9 cit10 cit11">8–11</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The isomerization coordinate was shown to be near barrierless and, from the weak dependence of lifetime on medium viscosity, volume conserving.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11 cit12 cit13">11–13</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Recent theoretical calculations are in broad agreement with this mechanism, and provide additional information on the nature of the isomerization coordinate and excited electronic states.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14 cit15">14,15</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The outstanding challenge in developing a complete picture of the photodynamics of GFP is in understanding the nature of the protein–chromophore interactions which result in such a dramatic suppression of radiationless decay.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">It was proposed that in the excited state two coordinates are involved in coupling the ground and excited states,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13 cit15">13,15</REF> a two-state two-mode model.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">One co-ordinate involves ultrafast motion out of the Franck–Condon region along a high frequency stretching coordinate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">This stretching motion is coupled with motion along a low frequency torsional coordinate, which brings ground and excited states close in energy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This suggests that important information on the photodynamics can be obtained from vibrational spectroscopy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">There have been a number of studies of the vibrational spectroscopy of GFP and its isolated chromophore,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17 cit18 cit19 cit20 cit21">17–21</REF> but these have focussed on modes above 400 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">For example resonance Raman spectroscopy reveals a strong mode around 1560 cm<SP>−1</SP>, which may correspond to the initial stretching coordinate taking the chromophore out of the Franck–Condon region.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17 cit19">17,19</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, both theory and experiment suggest that low frequency torsional modes are important in understanding the radiationless decay mechanism.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13 cit15">13,15</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">These present a particular challenge to conventional Raman spectroscopy, because of experimental problems associated with scattered light, and fundamental problems involving thermal populations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus the important low frequency region of the GFP vibrational spectrum has not been investigated in any detail.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">While low frequencies are problematic for frequency domain spectroscopy they are quite readily observed by time domain ultrafast vibrational coherence spectroscopy.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22 cit23">22,23</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In this method a short coherent light pulse, the pump, excites the S<SB>0</SB> → S<SB>1</SB> transition of a solute.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The pulse impulsively excites coherent intramolecular motion whenever the pulse width is smaller than <IT>c</IT>/2π<IT>ν</IT>, where <IT>ν</IT> is the frequency of an intramolecular mode.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">Coherent motion in the sample may be either directly excited on the S<SB>1</SB> surface, or excited by impulsive stimulated resonance Raman scattering in S<SB>0</SB>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22 cit23">22,23</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">The resultant coherent vibrational motion in the sample modulates its optical properties, which are probed by a time delayed probe pulse.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">There exist two previous reports of coherent vibrational dynamics in GFP.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Boxer and co-workers reported ultrafast fluorescence of wtGFP, with 100 fs time resolution, and noted the appearance of a weak oscillatory signal in the first picoseconds;<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF> they did not extract a vibrational frequency.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">More recently Cinelli <IT>et al.</IT> reported ultrafast pump–probe spectroscopy with 10 fs time resolution on the EGFP mutant of GFP.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25">25</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">They found a strong oscillation damped on a 1 ps time scale, at the relatively high frequency of 497 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">This was assigned to vibrational dynamics in the excited state.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">In the following we describe a transient grating experiment with 60 fs time resolution, which is significantly lower than that of Cinelli <IT>et al.</IT>, so we cannot access modes with frequencies &gt;400 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">However, the signal-to-noise attainable with the background free TG measurement is very high.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">Thus we have been able to record coherent vibrational dynamics of lower amplitude and lower frequency than was accessible in earlier experiments.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">To optimise the signal-to-noise ratio we used a diffractive optics based TG technique, which amplifies the TG signal while reducing jitter.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Our experiment is based on the designs of Miller,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26">26</REF> Fleming<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27">27</REF> and their co-workers (Fig. 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Briefly the <IT>ca.</IT> 500 nm 1 μJ pulses from a non-collinear optical parametric amplifier (NOPA), pumped by a 1 kHz amplified Ti:sapphire laser (Clark MXR), were divided at a beam splitter into pump and time-delayed probe beams.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">These pulses had a width of 60 fs at the sample position.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The linearly polarised pump and probe pulses were combined with a 300 mm lens on the surface of an 80 groove mm<SP>−1</SP> transmission grating (Edmund Optics), which split each into two replicas.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The four beams were focussed onto the sample using a spherical mirror (radius 50 cm), <IT>via</IT> a folding mirror.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Beams 3 and 4 (pump) write a holographic grating in the sample.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="New" advantage="None">The decay of the grating is monitored by the intensity of the signal scattered from the time delayed probe pulse 1 in the direction 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The intensity is measured by a photodiode placed behind an analysing polarizer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The intensity of beam 3, and thus the formation of the grating, was modulated by a mechanical chopper.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The photodiode output was measured by a lock-in amplifier referenced to the chopper frequency.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The data presented below were measured in the homodyne configuration (with beam 2 blocked) and so report the square of the sample's third order nonlinear response function.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">A 100 mg ml<SP>−1</SP> solution of the EGFP mutant (S65T/F64L) of GFP (Clontech, used as received) was contained in a 1 mm pathlength cell.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In EGFP the anionic form of the chromophore dominates, which has a strong transition at 490 nm, nicely matching the output of the NOPA.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The absorbance was approximately unity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The high absorbance and absence of a measurable signal from the solvent suggest that the TG signal arises from sample dichroism.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="New" advantage="None">Before each TG measurement the pulsewidth from the NOPA at the sample position was carefully optimised by adjusting a dispersive prism pair.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">It should be noted that without such optimisation the coherent vibrational dynamics described below could not be reliably observed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Others have shown that the observation of vibrational coherences is dependent on the degree of chirp in the pulses.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The average of 50 TG measurements is shown in Fig. 2a.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Data were measured at 510 nm, on the low energy side of the S<SB>0</SB> → S<SB>1</SB> spectrum.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rise of the TG signal is limited by the laser pulsewidth, and reaches a maximum at <IT>t</IT> = 0.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The signal decays to a near constant level in &lt;200 fs.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Superimposed on this is an oscillatory component.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The oscillatory part of the response is assigned to coherent vibrational motion in EGFP.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="New" advantage="None">The non-oscillatory response can be fit to ultrafast (<IT>ca.</IT> 100 fs) and <IT>ca.</IT> 10 ps exponential relaxation times, plus a dominant constant term.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ‘constant’ is ascribed to the nanosecond excited state lifetime.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The remaining ultrafast and picosecond relaxation times are assigned to intramolecular vibrational redistribution and vibrational cooling in the excited state respectively.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28">28</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="New" advantage="None">Since we are mainly interested in the coherent vibrational dynamics we subtracted these exponential components from the experimental data to isolate the residual oscillatory response (Fig. 2b).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The dominant component in the residual data is an oscillation with a period of 370 ± 20 fs, or 95 cm<SP>−1</SP>, which persists for at least 2 ps.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The amplitude of the oscillation is not regular, but the data are well reproduced when a second component of approximately 35 cm<SP>−1</SP> is included (the lower frequency is not accurately determined, as data are available for at most two cycles).</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fit with these two components is shown as the solid line in Fig. 2b.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The same frequencies were extracted from measurements at 497 nm.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The frequencies reported in Fig. 2 are lower than any previously observed for GFP.</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">They are also lower than any frequency calculated for the ground state, though Tozzini <IT>et al.</IT> found deformation modes around 200 cm<SP>−1</SP> in their density functional theory and Car–Parrinello MD simulations.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">In a CASSCF calculation of the excited state of the GFP chromophore Olivucci and co-workers reported three modes lying between 100 and 160 cm<SP>−1</SP>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">These were associated with bending, torsion and pyramidalization in the bridging bonds.</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">These are the modes which appear to be involved in promoting ultrafast internal conversion in the chromophore.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is difficult to definitively assign the frequencies observed in Fig. 2 to either the ground or excited state, since both may be excited in vibrational coherence spectroscopy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the higher frequency oscillation is slow (370 fs) compared to the 60 fs pulsewidth.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This would favour an assignment to a vibrational mode in the excited state.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The poorly resolved low frequency mode may be in either the ground or excited state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The frequency seems too low to be associated with an intramolecular mode, and may reflect orientational (librational) motion of the chromophore, or some other slow dynamics, within the protein matrix.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">If, as we suggest, the higher frequency oscillation reflects the excitation of coherent intramolecular torsional motion in the excited state, then two factors are of note.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">First, the vibrational coherence survives the initial relaxation out of the Franck–Condon excited state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">This relaxation is responsible for a 2000 cm<SP>−1</SP> Stokes loss in &lt;100 fs in the free chromophore in solution,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF> but the Stokes shift is greatly reduced in the intact protein.</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Second the torsional mode in the intact protein is damped on the picosecond timescale, whereas in the free chromophore it promotes sub-picosecond internal conversion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">One possible mechanism for the suppression of radiationless decay in the protein is that protein–chromophore interactions lead to a modification of the torsional potential such that it is more harmonic and of higher frequency than in the free chromophore, and therefore couples less effectively with the ground state surface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Alternatively, the protein–chromophore interaction may modify the vibrational coordinate responsible for relaxation out of the Franck–Condon excited state in such a way that it cannot access that region of the potential energy surface from which ultrafast internal conversion occurs.</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Such explanations require further experimental and theoretical study.</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">A TG study of additional mutants of GFP is planned.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="New" advantage="None">In conclusion, we have used a sensitive diffractive optics based TG method to investigate the low frequency modes of a GFP mutant.</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">A mode at 95 cm<SP>−1</SP> is detected, which is lower in frequency than any previously reported mode in GFP.</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is tentatively assigned to excitation of torsional motion on the excited state surface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">The possible implications of this observation for understanding the enhancement of the fluorescence yield of the chromophore by the protein matrix are discussed.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
