<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b404632c" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">A detailed chemical reaction mechanism for the oxidation of hydrocarbons and its application to the analysis of benzene formation in fuel-rich premixed laminar acetylene and propene flames<XREF TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" /></annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the basis of existing detailed kinetic schemes a general and consistent mechanism of the oxidation of hydrocarbons and the formation of higher hydrocarbons was compiled for computational studies covering the characteristic properties of a wide range of combustion processes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Computed ignition delay times of hydrocarbon–oxygen mixtures (CH<SB>4</SB>-, C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>6</SB>-, C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>8</SB>-, n-C<SB>4</SB>H<SB>10</SB>-, CH<SB>4</SB> + C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>6</SB>-, C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>4</SB>, C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>6</SB>-O<SB>2</SB>) match the experimental values.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The calculated absolute flame velocities of laminar premixed flames (CH<SB>4</SB>-, C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>6</SB>-, C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>8</SB>-, n-C<SB>4</SB>H<SB>10</SB>-, C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>4</SB>-, C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>6</SB>-, and C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>2</SB>-air) and the dependence on mixture strength agree with the latest experimental investigations reported in the literature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">With the same model concentration profiles for major and intermediate species in fuel-rich, non-sooting, premixed C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>2</SB>-, C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>6</SB>- air flames and a mixed C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>2</SB>/C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>6</SB> (1:1)-air flame at 50 mbar are predicted in good agreement with experimental data.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">An analysis of reaction pathways shows for all three flames that benzene formation can be described by propargyl combination.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">With growing computing power modeling of various physical and technical systems becomes approachable or more realistic.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In the field of combustion research modeling provides a strong tool for the analysis of chemical and physical phenomena and predictions of properties of combustion systems.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Considerable progress has been made in the development of detailed reaction mechanisms being used in a manifold of scientific and industrial applications.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">One aspect is modeling of hydrocarbon fuel oxidation including soot formation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Soot emissions of combustion engines are suspected to cause cancer and research on soot formation is in the focus of both science and industry.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Warnatz and coworkers<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2 cit3 cit4">1–4</REF> have developed a widely-used mechanism for the oxidation of C1-C4-hydrocarbon fuels which is validated for flame speeds, ignition delay times and species concentration profiles.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The GRI-mechanism<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF> is an extensively tested mechanism geared to methane and natural gas oxidation including NO<SB><IT>x</IT></SB>-chemistry and used as reference mechanism in many computational studies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In 1987 Frenklach and Warnatz presented a kinetic model predicting PAH (poly-aromatic hydrocarbon) concentration profiles in sooting acetylene flames.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Ten years later Wang and Frenklach published a GRI based detailed reaction mechanism describing fuel oxidation, benzene formation and PAH mass growth<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF> being the most extensive study on soot formation in C2-flames.</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">This mechanism was moderately updated in .2000<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Benzene is commonly accepted to be a key species in PAH formation while the pathways to benzene are still discussed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Most studies<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9 cit10 cit11">9–11</REF> favour the combination of propargyl radicals C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>3</SB> + C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>3</SB> → A1 (reaction (R383), see mechanism in Table 1) to be the main source of benzene (A1, first aromat) while Wang and Frenklach<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF> demonstrated that in acetylene flames under certain conditions benzene formation can be described <IT>via</IT> alternative routes such as C<SB>4</SB>H<SB>5</SB> + C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>2</SB> → A1 + H, reaction (R449).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">An experimental investigation of Atakan <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF>. of a fuel rich propene flame indicates that additional reaction sequences <IT>via</IT> C<SB>6</SB>H<SB><IT>x</IT>,(<IT>x</IT>&gt;6)</SB> are involved in benzene formation.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In a modeling study<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF> of benzene formation for C2 and C3 low pressure hydrocarbon flames (acetylene, ethylene, and propene) Pope and Miller found that besides propagyl combination the reaction C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>3</SB> + C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>5</SB> (allyl) → A1 + H + H reaction (R*) contributes significantly to benzene formation.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The pioneering work of the named authors and many others has provided modeling tools for various aspects of hydrocarbon oxidation yet the application of every kinetic model is limted to its range of test cases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus it is desirable to provide a detailed reaction mechanism which is capable to predict flame structures, <IT>e.g.</IT> species concentration profiles, and global kinetic properties like flame speeds and ignition delay times simultaneously for a broad range of fuels.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Analysis of reaction pathways becomes more reliable with a larger set of test cases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore the aim of this study is to demonstrate that existing models can be improved when expanded to a broader range of targets.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">This approach is confirmed by a study of Qin <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF>. for C3 fuel-oxidation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="New" advantage="None">To obtain an optimal C3 data set, simultaneous optimisation of the kinetics of small and intermediate sized fuels was necessary.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">It will be shown that on the basis of the mechanisms of Warnatz and coworkers and Wang and Frenklach a kinetic scheme can be compiled that fulfils the demands named above.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The new mechanism predicts (a) the flame speeds of laminar premixed hydrocarbon–air flames for the fuels methane, ethane, ethylene, acetylene, propane, propene and butane in good agreement with the latest experimental data, (b) ignition delay times and species concentration profiles for various test cases of Warnatz’s mechanism in good agreement with experiments and (c) the concentration profiles of major and intermediate species in premixed, fuel-rich non-sooting acetylene– and propene–air flames and a mixed acetylene/propene–air flame including the propargyl radical and benzene.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">The reaction pathways leading to benzene are analysed by application of sensitivity and reaction flow analysis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="New" advantage="None">The results are compared with those of other experimental and computational studies with respect to the fuel, the temperature range and the vital role of the propargyl radical as a key intermediate in benzene formation.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The species concentration profiles or maximum concentration/position data are taken from flame chemistry studies by Atakan <IT>et al</IT>. obtained with molecular beam sampling mass spectroscopy The calculations were performed with the flame and ignition codes used in the Chemical Kinetics group in Lund<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit40">40</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Chemical model</HEADER><P><s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The detailed reaction mechanism consists of 569 reversible reactions and 96 chemical species.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The base for the C1-/C2- and C4-chemistry is the latest version of Warnatz’s mechanism.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The kinetic data relevant for benzene formation and destruction including additional species and C2–C4-reactions is based on the mechanism<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF> of Wang and Frenklach.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">The C3-chemistry is a new compilation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The species nomenclature of C1–C4-species corresponds to <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2 cit3">ref. 2 and 3</REF>, thermodynamic data were taken from the Sandia National Laboratories database.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">For species introduced with the chemistry of Wang and Frenklach’s mechanism the nomenclature corresponds to <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">ref. 16</REF> and thermodynamic properties are taken from .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">ref. 7</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The motivation to replace the GRI-C1-C2-chemistry in the original Wang–Frenklach-scheme is its limited reliability for fuels different from methane/natural gas as highlighted by the authors.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to predict simultaneously flame velocities, ignition delay times and species concentration profiles for various fuels and flame stoichiometries an unspecific, broadly validated C1–C4-chemistry is appropriate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="New" advantage="None">Due to the extended application area the new compilation of the chemical scheme demands some modifications of the kinetic data.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rate coefficients were taken either from literature or estimated based on analogous reactions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the most of the key reactions accounting for benzene and benzene precursor formation are identical with the model of Wang and Frenklach as described in .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">ref. 7</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None">Below those changes are discussed which have the greatest impact on the flame speeds of hydrocarbon flames and the species concentration profiles in the acetylene, propene, and the acetylene/propene flames.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">These reactions are listed for convenience in Table 1, where they are cited with their original source.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to keep the main body of the paper short the full mechanism and the thermodynamic data are given as an electronic supplement.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Results and discussion</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Flame speed</HEADER><P><s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Current values of flame speeds for hydrocarbons in air at atmospheric pressure differ significantly from older data.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the present study we adopted largely the experimental burning velocity data collected in the Princeton counterflow flames.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17 cit18">17,18</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The C1–C4 mechanism of Warnatz and coworkers, not validated against current flame speed data, overpredicts flame speeds for all fuel–air mixtures under study.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The key change of the Warnatz C1–C2-chemistry is the replacement of the kinetic data for the reaction <SP>3</SP>CH<SB>2</SB> + O<SB>2</SB> by the values reported by Dembrowsky and Wagner.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19">19</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The former rate coefficients<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF> and reaction pathways are recommended for temperatures up to 1000 K which is far below flame temperatures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The values of <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19">ref. 19</REF> are results of shock tube experiments between 1000–1800 K and thus more appropriate for modeling high temperature hydrocarbon oxidation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">They show in contrast to the old values a negative activation energy and the total rate is slower by one order of magnitude at 1000 K. The new experimental data for CH<SB>3</SB> + O features the branching path producing CO which effects strongly the mass flow in methane flames.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">This reaction has been extensively studied in the last decade<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21 cit22">21,22</REF> and the latest results of Hoyermann and coworkers<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF> are included in the mechanism:CH<SB>3</SB> + O → HCHO + HCH<SB>3</SB> + O → CO + H<SB>2</SB> + HThe reactionC<SB>2</SB>H<SB>5</SB> + H → CH<SB>3</SB> + CH<SB>3</SB>in Warnatz’s mechanism has already been identified by Egolofopoulos <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF>. to raise ethane flame speeds significantly, when comparing predictions of laminar burning velocities on the basis of different detailed mechanisms and the experimental data.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Using the rate coefficient for the backward reaction<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF>CH<SB>3</SB> + CH<SB>3</SB> → C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>5</SB> + Has recommended by Egolofopoulos reduces the flame speed by 2–4 cm s<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>5</SB> + H rate is calculated <IT>via</IT> the equilibrium constant.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 1 reflects the very good agreement between predicted and experimental flame speeds for methane and ethane.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">These above-named changes to the C1–C2-chemistry lead also to a good match between calculated and measured flame speeds for acetylene and ethylene flames.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Especially the agreement in the dependence of the flame speed and mixture strength for ethylene under fuel rich conditions, displayed in Fig. 2, shows that flame speed and flame structure predictions, as discussed below, did not add up to a conflict with flame structure calculations.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The overprediction of the acetylene flame speeds for fuel-rich mixtures is due to the added HCCO decomposition being also discussed in the flame structure part.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The named changes to the C1–C2 chemistry and the new C3-chemistry compilation implemented to predict acetylene-/propene-flame structures lead also to good agreement between calculated and measured flame speeds of propane, propene and butane flames displayed in Fig. 3.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Ignition delay times</HEADER><P><s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod11" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to prove the quality of the presented mechanism and its general applicability this scheme was chosen without further modifications for the calculation of ignition delay times of a variety of fuels.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">As demonstrated in Fig. 4 the absolute values and the temperature dependence (<IT>i.e.</IT> apparent activation energy) of the experimentally determined ignition delay times are well reproduced by the calculations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is noteworthy to state that the original Warnatz scheme gave similar results with minor deviations for propene and butane air mixtures.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Flame structure</HEADER><P><s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="New" advantage="None">The structure of laminar premixed fuel-rich acetylene-, propene- and acetylene/propene-air flames<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit34 cit12 cit35">34,12,35</REF> was analyzed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="New" advantage="None">In the following a comparison of predicted and measured species concentrations is given with emphasis on major and intermediate species relevant for benzene formation and PAH growth.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Where experimental data is available measured and predicted concentration profiles are displayed in figures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">For many species only positions and values of the maximum concentration are provided.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">These data are summarized for all species in Table 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="New" advantage="None">The experimental position data is slightly shifted to account for probe effects.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">A summary of the conditions of the three well-studied burner stabilized laminar premixed flames simulated in the present study is given in Table 3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The associated temperature profiles are shown in Figs. 5–7.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="New" advantage="None">For the present investigation the energy conservation equation was not solved explicitly and the temperature profiles were extracted from the experimental data.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">The profiles actually used in the calculations (dashed lines in Figs. 5–7) are raised by 100–200 K which is well within the uncertainity of the applied temperature diagnostics, <IT>T</IT>(OH-LIF), <IT>T</IT>(CO,H<SB>2</SB>-Raman).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">This leads to better results for the partial equilibrium determined C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>2</SB> concentrations in the post-flame region.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="New" advantage="None">The reaction pathways leading to benzene are traced back by application of reaction sensitivity and mass flow analysis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj5" novelty="New" advantage="None">An analysis of the main fuel consuming pathways is included.</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results are illustrated in flow diagrams.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Flame 1: Acetylene</HEADER><P><s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Good agreement between predicted and the experimental concentrations is found for the major species H<SB>2</SB>, H<SB>2</SB>O, CO. The calculated concentration of CO<SB>2,(<IT>x</IT>=12 mm)</SB> is overpredicted by approximately 60%.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The addition of the HCCO decomposition reactionHCCO → CH + COreduced the CO<SB>2</SB> concentration maximum by 30%.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">This effect is due to a decreased CO<SB>2</SB> formation <IT>via</IT> the competitive reactionHCCO + O<SB>2</SB> → H + CO + CO<SB>2</SB>which is a major source of CO<SB>2</SB> under fuel rich conditions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Its high sensitivity on CO<SB>2</SB> formation is due to a high HCCO channel fraction of the reaction C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>2</SB> + O (reaction (R111)) being the main fuel consuming path.</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">It should be noted that the influence of the HCCO decomposition reaction depends strongly on the thermodynamic properties of HCCO and the fuel/air ratio.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Moreover, it is not limited to acetylene flames: Our calculations for methane/air flames and a comparison of experimental results and GRI predictions<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit36">36</REF> show that CH concentrations are reduced for lean mixtures and raised for fuel rich mixtures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Additional kinetic and thermodynamic studies for this high sensitive reaction are desirable.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore the early formation of CO<SB>2</SB> in acetylene flames reported by Hoyerman <IT>et al</IT>. in 1972<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit37">37</REF> can be explained <IT>via</IT> the sequence of reactions (R111) and (R107).</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">In a recent experimental study using time-resolved FTIR it was demonstrated by Osborn<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit38">38</REF> that CO<SB>2</SB> is the main product for reaction (R107).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 8 shows that the concentrations of benzene, A1 and the benzene precursors C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>3</SB>, C<SB>4</SB>H<SB>3</SB>, C<SB>4</SB>H<SB>5</SB> are predicted in good agreement with experimental results.</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The maximum concentrations of C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>4</SB> and further C3 and C4 species are also predicted within the error margins given as 30% for major species (mole fraction &gt;10<SP>−3</SP>) and a factor of three for radicals and minor species (mole fraction&lt;10<SP>−3</SP>) by Atakan <IT>et al</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">(see Table 2).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The mass flow analysis of the reaction pathways from the fuel to benzene shows that C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>2</SB> is mainly consumed by the reactionsC<SB>2</SB>H<SB>2</SB> + O → <SP>3</SP>CH<SB>2</SB> + COC<SB>2</SB>H<SB>2</SB> + O → HCCO + H.C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>3</SB> is predominantly formed by the reactions of <SP>3</SP>CH<SB>2</SB> and <SP>1</SP>CH<SB>2</SB> with the fuel where <SP>3</SP>CH<SB>2</SB> and <SP>1</SP>CH<SB>2</SB> are the triplet and singlet methylenes respectively.C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>2</SB> + <SP>1</SP>CH<SB>2</SB> → C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>3</SB> + HC<SB>2</SB>H<SB>2</SB> + <SP>3</SP>CH<SB>2</SB> → C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>3</SB> + HThe rate coefficients of these C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>2</SB>/CH<SB>2</SB> reactions and other pathways (R196,197,209,210) to C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>4</SB>/C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>4</SB>P (allene/propyne) are fitted to give optimum results for C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>3</SB> and C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>4</SB> concentrations profiles for all three flames.</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The overall rate coefficients lie within the error range of the reported values.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10 cit20">10,20</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The importance of these reactions is also emphasized by Pope and Miller<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF> (see also notes added in proof).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit41">41</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The C<SB>4</SB>H<SB>5</SB> radical is mainly produced <IT>via</IT> the sequence of reactionsC<SB>3</SB>H<SB>3</SB> + CH<SB>3</SB> → C<SB>4</SB>H<SB>6</SB>C<SB>4</SB>H<SB>6</SB> + (H,OH) → i-C<SB>4</SB>H<SB>5</SB>, n-C<SB>4</SB>H<SB>5</SB> + (H<SB>2</SB>,H<SB>2</SB>O)This holds for all studied flames.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The potential benzene precursor n-C<SB>4</SB>H<SB>3</SB> is produced in all flames <IT>via</IT> the reactionsC<SB>4</SB>H<SB>2</SB> + H → n-C<SB>4</SB>H<SB>3</SB>C<SB>4</SB>H<SB>4</SB> + H → n-C<SB>4</SB>H<SB>3</SB> + H<SB>2</SB>As a result of reaction flow analysis benzene is almost exclusively formed by the propargyl combinationC<SB>3</SB>H<SB>3</SB> + C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>3</SB> → A1while R449 is the main consuming path boosted by the high benzene concentrations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">This changes when propargyl combination is omitted in the kinetic model.</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Another flow analysis revealed that benzene in this case is formed exclusively by n-C<SB>4</SB>H<SB>5</SB> + C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>2</SB> → A1 + H</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">A reaction sensitivity analysis (Fig. 9) at the position of the maximum concentration of benzene shows that the most sensitive reactions are the propargyl combination and radical/atom + fuel reactions on the path to C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>3</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">This applies for all three flames invesigated here.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Considering the acetylene flame in Wang and Frenklach’s study reaction (R449) was the major source for benzene.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Its concentration profiles could be reasonably well predicted even if the propargyl combination was excluded from the kinetic model.</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Here reaction (R449) is still among the most sensitive reactions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">But the computed A1 concentration profiles reach just 20% of the experimental value when reaction (R383) is neglected in the kinetic scheme.</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this simulation the n-C<SB>4</SB>H<SB>5</SB> concentration was at the upper limit of the stated experimental error and the predicted A1 concentration was compared to the lower experimental limit.</annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus benzene formation cannot be described without a predominant contribution from reaction (R383).</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj6" novelty="New" advantage="None">The A1 concentration profile was also simulated for the acetylene flame studied by Wang and Frenklach.</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">Here the concentration of A1 at the peak was reduced only by 30% when propargyl combination with <IT>k</IT><SB>383</SB> = 1 × 10<SP>11</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> mol<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP> is omitted (rate coefficient for 20 torr in Wang and Frenklach’s model).</annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">The maximum benzene mole fraction is predicted 30% lower than with Wang and Frenklach’s model but within the experimental error.</annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our simulation likewise showed that the benzene concentration is overpredicted in the post flame zone because of the persistent production <IT>via</IT> propargyl combination.</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">As already pointed out by Wang and Frenklach the formation and destruction of benzene depends strongly on temperature and thus on the thermodynamic properties of the species involved.</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is a critical point when simulating benzene concentration profiles and further kinetic studies are necessary for solving this problem.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 10 illustrates the reaction paths from the fuel to benzene identified by reaction and mass flow analysis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">The scheme is comparatively straightforward as the main benzene precursors are formed in one or two steps from the fuel molecule.</annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Flames 2 and 3 with different fuels show significantly more complex pathways but the route from acetylene is still an important route.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Flame 2: Propene</HEADER><P><s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" advantage="None">A very good match between the predicted and the experimental concentrations is found for the major species H<SB>2</SB>, H<SB>2</SB>O, CO, CO<SB>2</SB> and is displayed in Fig. 11.</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None">In case of the propene flame the CO<SB>2</SB> concentration profile is predicted within the experimental error of 30%.</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is due to the addition of the HCCO decomposition reaction (R103) discussed above which lowered the maximum CO<SB>2</SB> concentration again by 30%.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In Figs. 12 and 13 the mole fraction profiles of CH<SB>3</SB>, C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>2</SB>, C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>4</SB>, various C3/C4 and A1 species are displayed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res29" novelty="None" advantage="None">Profiles for species with mole fractions &gt;10<SP>−3</SP> are predicted in excellent agreement with the experimental data.</annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res29" novelty="None" advantage="None">This holds especially for intermediate species on the reaction paths leading to benzene (see Fig. 14).</annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res30" novelty="None" advantage="None">Even for radicals like C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>3</SB>, C<SB>4</SB>H<SB>3</SB> and C<SB>4</SB>H<SB>5</SB> maximum concentrations and profiles are simulated very close to the experimental values.</annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="New" advantage="None">The new compilation of the C3 chemistry was essential to achieve these results.</annotationART></s> <s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="None" advantage="Yes">It comprises large parts of Warnatz’s C3-chemistry but some modifications of key reactions were carried out which are very sensitive to the mass flow in propene flames.</annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac20" novelty="None" advantage="None">The C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>4</SB> isomer propyne, C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>4</SB>P, is central for simulating propene oxidation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac20" novelty="None" advantage="None">Most of its reactions are formulated analogously to those of allene.</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" advantage="None">The isomerization of allene and propyne explains the relative high C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>4</SB> mole fraction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="None" advantage="Yes">Especially these modifications enabled a simulation of the C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>4</SB> concentration profile.</annotationART></s> <s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res32" novelty="None" advantage="None">The experimental values are reproduced very well as seen in Fig. 9(d).</annotationART></s> <s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>4</SB> (allene/propyne) decomposition by C–H-bond breaking was described <IT>via</IT> the the backward reactionsC<SB>3</SB>H<SB>3</SB> + H → C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>4</SB>C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>3</SB> + H → C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>4</SB>PThe kinetic data are taken from Wang and Frenklach.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Some rate coefficients for H-atom abstraction reactions likeC<SB>3</SB>H<SB>5</SB> + H → C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>4</SB> + H<SB>2</SB>were slightly changed within the experimental error of the original reported values in order to predict simultaneously flame speeds for the same fuel.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj7" novelty="New" advantage="None">The importance of the reactions of C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>2</SB> with CH<SB>2</SB> for predicting benzene concentration profiles of all flames was discussed above.</annotationART></s> <s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj7" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">They are a vital part of the C3 chemistry derived here.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res33" novelty="None" advantage="None">The experimental flame structure analysis shows an earlier formation of species C<SB>6</SB>H<SB><IT>x</IT>,<IT>x</IT>&gt;6</SB> compared to benzene (A1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res34" novelty="None" advantage="None">A direct simulation with the Wang–Frenklach C6-chemistry resulted in C<SB>6</SB>H<SB>8</SB> concentrations which are almost two orders of magnitude too low.</annotationART></s> <s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res35" novelty="None" advantage="None">Even benzene concentrations were predicted one order of magnitude too low.</annotationART></s> <s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore additional chemistry was considered.</annotationART></s> <s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Obvious candidates for early C<SB>6</SB>H<SB><IT>x</IT>,<IT>x</IT>&gt;6</SB> formation are reactions of the species C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>6</SB> and C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>5</SB>, being abundant early in the flame.</annotationART></s> <s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod14" novelty="None" advantage="None">As already suggested by Atakan <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF>. the allyl combinationC<SB>3</SB>H<SB>5</SB> + C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>5</SB> → C<SB>6</SB>H<SB>10</SB>and the reactionC<SB>3</SB>H<SB>6</SB> + C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>3</SB> → C<SB>6</SB>H<SB>8</SB> + Hwere introduced, the latter analogously to C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>3</SB> + C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>3</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac21" novelty="None" advantage="None">This elementary reaction was studied by Knyazev <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit39">39</REF>. in detail.</annotationART></s> <s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="New" advantage="None">Adding the set of reactions (R384)–(R394), which is rather small, including some global reaction steps, allows the prediction of early C<SB>6</SB>H<SB><IT>x</IT>&gt;7</SB> formation and of accurate C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>3</SB>/A1 concentrations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">This opens a new pathway to C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>3</SB> and to benzene which is particular to the fuel propene as will be shown below.</annotationART></s> <s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="New" advantage="No">It should be noted that the considered allyl combination allowed a reasonable simulation of C<SB>6</SB>H<SB>10</SB> concentrations but does not significantly contribute to benzene formation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Further kinetic studies are needed to fully understand the mechanism of early C<SB>6</SB>H<SB>x</SB> formation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="143"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met14" novelty="New" advantage="None">Simulations were also performed with reaction (R*) added to the mechanism:<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF>C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>3</SB> + C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>5</SB> → A1 + H + HThough benzene concentrations in the propene flame could be predicted well even when reactions for C<SB>6</SB>H<SB>8</SB> build up, reaction (R384)–(R394), were omitted, there arise several drawbacks.</annotationART></s> <s sid="144"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res36" novelty="None" advantage="None">The C<SB>6</SB>H<SB>8</SB> maximum concentration is predicted much too low when reaction (R*) is added and the latter reactions are excluded.</annotationART></s> <s sid="145"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res37" novelty="None" advantage="None">The maximum position of C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>3</SB> is shifted to higher burner distances matching the experimental data less accurately.</annotationART></s> <s sid="146"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None">In Flame 1 and 3 reaction (R*) does not significantly contribute to benzene formation and the simultaneous prediction of benzene concentration profiles for all flames is no longer possible without major changes to the kinetic model.</annotationART></s> <s sid="147"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None">In principle reaction (R*) is a possible source of benzene in propene flames but it is not included in the mechanism for the reasons given above.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="148"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res38" novelty="None" advantage="None">The mass flow analysis shows that C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>6</SB> is mainly consumed by H-atom abstractionC<SB>3</SB>H<SB>6</SB> + H → C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>5</SB> + H<SB>2</SB>and H-atom additionC<SB>3</SB>H<SB>6</SB> + H → n-C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>7</SB>In the propene flame C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>3</SB> is again formed to a high extent by the reactions of <SP>3</SP>CH<SB>2</SB> and <SP>1</SP>CH<SB>2</SB> with acetylene.</annotationART></s> <s sid="149"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res39" novelty="None" advantage="None">Another source is H-atom abstraction from propyne, an intermediate in the stepwise abstraction route from propene to propargyl.C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>4</SB>P + (H,OH) → C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>3</SB> + (H<SB>2</SB>,H<SB>2</SB>O)A third important source of C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>3</SB> is connected to the early formation of C<SB>6</SB>H<SB>8</SB> as discussed above where C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>3</SB> is formed by the reverse of reaction (R391).C<SB>6</SB>H<SB>8</SB> + H → C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>6</SB> + C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>3</SB>Benzene is formed predominantly by propargyl combination.</annotationART></s> <s sid="150"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res40" novelty="None" advantage="None">A minor contribution is linked to the chemistry of C<SB>6</SB>H<SB>8</SB>, being formed early in the flame.</annotationART></s> <s sid="151"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res41" novelty="None" advantage="None">This additional reaction sequence is <IT>via</IT> C<SB>6</SB>H<SB>8</SB> formation, subsequent H-atom abstraction and n-C<SB>6</SB>H<SB>7</SB> decompostionC<SB>6</SB>H<SB>8</SB> + (H,OH) → n-C<SB>6</SB>H<SB>7</SB> + (H<SB>2</SB>,H<SB>2</SB>O)n-C<SB>6</SB>H<SB>7</SB> → A1 + HThe reaction sensitivity analysis (Fig. 13) at the position of the maximum concentration of benzene shows that the most sensitive reactions are the first and the last step of the pathway to benzene formation, <IT>i.e.</IT> propene H-atom abstraction und propargyl combination:C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>6</SB> + H → C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>5</SB> + H<SB>2</SB>C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>3</SB> + C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>3</SB> → A1Other sensitive reactions are related to reaction paths forming the intermediate C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>3</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="152"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The comparable high sensitivity of reactions (R258R) and (R383),C<SB>4</SB>H<SB>6</SB> → C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>3</SB> + CH<SB>3</SB>C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>3</SB> + <SP>3</SP>CH<SB>2</SB> → C<SB>4</SB>H<SB>4</SB> + Hshows that matching concentration profiles of C3 and C4-species simultaneously is essential (see Figs. 12(c–e) and 13).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="153"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">In Fig. 14 the results of the mass flow and reaction sensitivity analysis are illustrated by a reaction flow diagram.</annotationART></s> <s sid="154"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res42" novelty="None" advantage="None">In case of propene the propagyl radical cannot be formed directly from the fuel.</annotationART></s> <s sid="155"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res43" novelty="None" advantage="None">Compared with the case of acetylene this leads to a more complex mass flow to benzene with a higher number of reaction steps involved.</annotationART></s> <s sid="156"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res44" novelty="None" advantage="None">In particular the route <IT>via</IT> C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>2</SB>, the main route of the acetylene flame, consists of six steps but is still part of a main reaction path.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="157"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res45" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reaction paths <IT>via</IT> successive H-atom abstraction and the early formed C<SB>6</SB>H<SB>8</SB> are characteristic for a propene flame.</annotationART></s> <s sid="158"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res46" novelty="None" advantage="None">Reaction (R391R) in particular is a source of early formed propargyl and accounts for the high benzene concentrations compared to the acetylene flame.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Flame 3: Acetylene/propene (1:1)</HEADER><P><s sid="159"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj8" novelty="New" advantage="None">Since the mechanism derived here is developed and optimized for the oxidation of pure fuels its application to a blended fuel is a critical test.</annotationART></s> <s sid="160"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met15" novelty="New" advantage="None">No specific modifications to the kinetic scheme were carried out to predict the structure of a acetylene/propene flame.</annotationART></s> <s sid="161"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac22" novelty="None" advantage="None">In a recent flame study of C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>2</SB>/C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>6</SB>–O<SB>2</SB> in Ar the concentration profiles of some intermediates are reported, although major species like H<SB>2</SB> or CO are not included.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit35">35</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="162"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res47" novelty="None" advantage="None">Yet predictions of profiles and maximum concentrations of C1–C4 key species taken into account agree reasonably well with the experimental data and are displayed in Figs. 16–18 or listed in Table 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="163"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">It can be seen that calculated concentrations of the fuel C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>2</SB> and the radicals CH<SB>3</SB> and C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>3</SB> reach an almost constant level not detected in the experiment.</annotationART></s> <s sid="164"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res48" novelty="None" advantage="None">When predicting concentration profiles for the pure flames this concentration evolution is not observed but too much C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>3</SB> is predicted at high burner distances in the propene flame (Fig. 12).</annotationART></s> <s sid="165"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res49" novelty="None" advantage="None">In case of the acetylene/propene flame one of the fuel components (acetylene) is formed to a large extent from the degradation of the other component (propene) and is thus present in very high concentrations in the late flame and post flame zone (see Fig. 18).</annotationART></s> <s sid="166"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con16" novelty="None" advantage="None">This fuel to fuel interaction is probably not fully considered by the model and likely to cause the discrepancies seen in the C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>2</SB>, CH<SB>3</SB> and C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>3</SB> mole fraction profiles.</annotationART></s> <s sid="167"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con17" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the results show that the model developed for pure fuels can be applied to a fuel mixture without substantial drawbacks.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="168"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res50" novelty="None" advantage="None">Analysis of the reaction flow in the flame with the blended fuel yields the same reaction pathways from the fuel to benzene as seen for the pure fuel components, but relative distribution of different pathways are partially changed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="169"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res51" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reaction path to benzene <IT>via</IT> early formed C<SB>6</SB>H<SB>8</SB> dicussed above is no longer essential to predict benzene concentrations, a match with experimental results could be achieved even when this channel is omitted.</annotationART></s> <s sid="170"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res52" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is due to the the high contribution of C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>2</SB> reactions with methylene to benzene formation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="171"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res53" novelty="None" advantage="None">Acetylene is present in high concentrations in the flame zone because of the permanent C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>2</SB> production from C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>6</SB> degradation which is discussed above.</annotationART></s> <s sid="172"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 19 shows the results of the reaction sensitivity analysis at the maximum concentration of benzene.</annotationART></s> <s sid="173"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res54" novelty="None" advantage="None">The most sensitive reactions are those discussed for the pure flames.</annotationART></s> <s sid="174"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res55" novelty="None" advantage="None">Here the highest relative sensitivity is found for propargyl combination and not for a fuel radical reaction because the fuel concentrations are diluted in the blended fuel (see Figs. 9 and 15).</annotationART></s> <s sid="175"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res56" novelty="None" advantage="None">The high concentration of C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>2</SB> in the flame zone not only boosts benzene formation <IT>via</IT> C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>3</SB> but also <IT>via</IT> reaction (R449), n-C<SB>4</SB>H<SB>5</SB> + C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>2</SB>, although only half of the fuel comprises acetylene.</annotationART></s> <s sid="176"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore the relative sensitivity of reaction (R449) has the same value as in Flame 1.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="177"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res57" novelty="None" advantage="None">The flow diagram for the acetylene/propene flame (Fig. 20) is very similar to the propene flow diagram.</annotationART></s> <s sid="178"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res58" novelty="None" advantage="None">Here acetylene is both fuel and intermediate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="179"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res59" novelty="None" advantage="None">The path <IT>via</IT> n-C<SB>4</SB>H<SB>5</SB> is contributing as much to benzene formation as in case of the acetylene flame.</annotationART></s> <s sid="180"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res60" novelty="None" advantage="None">The minor route <IT>via</IT> C<SB>6</SB>H<SB>7</SB> of the propene flame is neglegible in the acetylene/propene flame.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Conclusions/summary</HEADER><P><s sid="181"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The mechanism presented here is capable to predict flame speeds, especially under fuel rich conditions, and ignition delay times for a large range of C1–C4 hydrocarbon fuels in good agreement with experimental data.</annotationART></s> <s sid="182"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met16" novelty="New" advantage="None">Cross-checking of this very broad range of targets is used to identify associated sets of sensitive reactions and to optimize the model.</annotationART></s> <s sid="183"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met16" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">This constitutes an important precondition for its application to flame structure studies, simulating concentration profiles of major species and key intermediates in fuel rich acetylene and propene flames in good agreement with the experiments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="184"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res61" novelty="None" advantage="None">The chemical structure analysis for fuel-rich C2–C3 laminar low pressure premixed flames shows fuel-dependent reaction pathways to benzene.</annotationART></s> <s sid="185"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con20" novelty="None" advantage="None">The propargyl radical is a key species for every reaction path found but its formation is fuel specific.</annotationART></s> <s sid="186"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res62" novelty="None" advantage="None">Benzene is produced in all flames predominantly by propargyl combination.</annotationART></s> <s sid="187"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res63" novelty="None" advantage="None">Acetylene addition to n-C<SB>4</SB>H<SB>5</SB> is a secondary benzene source in the acetylene and the mixed acetylene–propene flame.</annotationART></s> <s sid="188"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res64" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the propene flame the C<SB>6</SB>H<SB>7</SB> decomposition is a minor secondary source of benzene.</annotationART></s> <s sid="189"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The experimentally found early formation of C<SB>6</SB>H<SB>8</SB> in the propene flame is considered in the model.</annotationART></s> <s sid="190"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con21" novelty="None" advantage="None">Benzene formation <IT>via</IT> C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>5</SB> + C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>3</SB> is identified as a possible benzene source in propene flames.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
