<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b405211k" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Reactions of platinum clusters <SP>195</SP>Pt<IT><SB><IT>n</IT></SB></IT><SP>±</SP>, <IT>n</IT> = 1–24, with N<SB>2</SB>O studied with isotopically enriched platinum</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Cationic and anionic clusters <SP>195</SP>Pt<SB><IT>n</IT></SB><SP>±</SP>, 1 ≤ <IT>n</IT> ≤ 24, were generated by laser vaporization using an isotopically enriched platinum sample.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">The oxidation of the clusters by nitrous oxide under binary collision conditions was investigated as a function of charge and size in a Fourier transform ion cyclotron resonance mass spectrometer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The only reaction observed is sequential addition of an oxygen atom, with the loss of molecular N<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reaction rates as well as the number of reaction steps exhibit a strong and irregular dependence upon the number of atoms in the cluster and its charge.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">These results show that isotopically enriched samples allow for the investigation of large cluster sizes together with an unambiguous assignment of reaction products and quantitative determination of rate constants.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER /><P><s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Transition metals and their compounds, with their multitude of oxidation states, are efficient and frequently used catalysts.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reactions of ionic metal clusters, in particular those involving transition metals, with small gas phase molecules represent convenient, relatively simple models for heterogeneous catalysis, and for these reasons they were in the last two decades extensively investigated by mass spectrometry.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2 cit3 cit4 cit5">1–5</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Platinum, palladium and rhodium are useful dehydrogenation catalysts,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6 cit7">6,7</REF> but are also used extensively in removing toxic oxides such as carbon monoxide or nitrogen oxides from automotive exhaust.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit9">8,9</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Several groups have investigated dehydrogenation of simple hydrocarbons, such as methane, ethane, ethylene or acetylene on platinum cluster ions, and their reactions with various simple molecules, like CO, N<SB>2</SB>O or CH<SB>4</SB>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7 cit9 cit10 cit11 cit12 cit13 cit14 cit15 cit16 cit17 cit18 cit19 cit20 cit21 cit22">7,9–22</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have previously studied methane activation by gas phase Pt<SB><IT>n</IT></SB><SP>±</SP> cluster ions in the <IT>n</IT> = 1–9 size range.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Schwarz and coworkers succeeded, by mass-selecting the most intense peak, and then thermalizing the ions in argon collisions, in studying the reactions of <SP>195</SP>Pt<SB><IT>n</IT></SB><SP>+</SP> with N<SB>2</SB>O and other small molecules up to <IT>n</IT> = .5<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Larger clusters up to <IT>n</IT> = 30 have also been investigated in flow reactors,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11 cit21">11,21</REF> albeit without resolving the individual isotopomers, which made interpretation of the data somewhat difficult.</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Heiz <IT>et al</IT>. succeeded in depositing size selected platinum clusters with up to 20 atoms on surfaces and investigated their chemical reactivity.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23 cit24">23,24</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">While gas phase reactivity studies on metals like niobium or rhodium can easily be done for clusters of sizes ranging up to thirty atoms,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6 cit25 cit26">6,25,26</REF> large clusters of platinum and palladium have been studied in less detail.</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reason for this is that unlike rhodium or niobium, which are monoisotopic elements, both palladium and platinum have six stable isotopes each.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">For larger clusters, this very quickly leads to dilution of the signal among many isotopomers, and overlapping of the products with the reactants.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both effects together so far have limited the cluster sizes accessible in reactivity studies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">All works in which the reactivity was probed in the gas phase by mass spectrometry with at least unit mass resolution, have therefore been restricted to smaller clusters, with ten atoms or less.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7 cit9 cit14 cit19 cit20 cit22">7,9,14,19,20,22</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the present study we use isotopically enriched platinum (97.28% <SP>195</SP>Pt, Oak Ridge National Laboratories) to investigate the oxidation of <SP>195</SP>Pt+/−<IT>n</IT> clusters, <IT>n</IT> = 1–24, with N<SB>2</SB>O under binary collision conditions in a Fourier transform ion cyclotron resonance (FT-ICR) mass spectrometer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The platinum sponge was pressed into a disk and subjected to zonal melting.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The resulting pearl was rolled into a foil which was used as a target for our home-built laser vaporization source.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26 cit27 cit28 cit29">26–29</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this source, the firing of the laser is synchronized with a helium pulse from a home-built piezo-electric valve.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">From the laser generated plasma, cold clusters form in the supersonic expansion of the high pressure gas into high vacuum.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Ionic clusters are guided by a series of electrostatic lenses through several stages of differential pumping, and trapped and stored inside the ICR cell in the ultrahigh vacuum of the FT-ICR mass spectrometer (Bruker/Spectrospin CMS47X, 4.7 T, APEX III data station).</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">For each mass spectrum, clusters generated in 20 laser shots over a period of 2 s are accumulated in the cell.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">To study ion-molecule reactions, the pressure inside the ICR cell was raised from its base value of about 2 × 10<SP>−10</SP> mbar to a constant value of 2.0 × 10<SP>−8</SP> mbar by controlled admission of N<SB>2</SB>O (99.5%, Messer Griesheim) at room temperature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="New" advantage="None">Mass spectra were acquired after a series of varying reaction delays.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">A crude selection of a cluster size range was accomplished by adjusting the timing of the cell trapping, effectively selecting a fraction of ions within a certain time of flight window from the source to the ICR cell.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Relative rate constants were obtained by fitting the experimental data to pseudo-first order reaction kinetics, and converted to absolute rate constants and reaction efficiencies using the average dipole orientation (ADO) theory.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30 cit31 cit32">30–32</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="New" advantage="None">The advantage of using isotopically enriched platinum is exemplified by the <IT>n</IT> = 7 cluster in Fig. 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the top trace, obtained with a non-enriched sample, the intensity is distributed over at least seventeen isotopic peaks.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the bottom panel, obtained with the isotopically enriched target, a strong <SP>195</SP>Pt<SB>7</SB><SP>+</SP> peak is present.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The weak side peaks corresponding to <SP>194</SP>Pt<SP>195</SP>Pt<SB>6</SB><SP>+</SP> and <SP>195</SP>Pt<SB>6</SB><SP>196</SP>Pt<SP>+</SP> clusters exhibit intensities that are consistent with the specified enrichment grade of the sample.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">A typical mass spectrum of cationic clusters <SP>195</SP>Pt<SB><IT>n</IT></SB><SP>+</SP> with <IT>n</IT> = 10–21 after a reaction delay of 5 s is shown in Fig. 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reactions occurring are quite simple, and similar to those observed previously for smaller clusters:<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9 cit14">9,14</REF> Oxide clusters, <SP>195</SP>Pt<SB><IT>n</IT></SB>O<SP>+</SP> are formed with loss of N<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Apparent is a size-specific variation in reactivity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">While <IT>n</IT> = 11, 12, 15 and 20 are very reactive, <IT>n</IT> = 10, 13, 14, 19 and 21 show very little to no reactivity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">One can also see that in the case of <IT>n</IT> = 18, and to some extent <IT>n</IT> = 16, reaction with a second N<SB>2</SB>O occurs, resulting in the loss of another N<SB>2</SB> molecule, and formation of dioxide clusters, <SP>195</SP>Pt<SB><IT>n</IT></SB>O<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="New" advantage="None">More detailed insight and quantitative reaction rates are obtained by actually fitting the time-intensity profile to pseudo-first-order kinetics, as exemplified in Fig. 3. <SP>195</SP>Pt<SB>8</SB><SP>+</SP> is shown in the top panel.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this case, one can follow an exponential decay of the reactant cluster, and the oxide product, <SP>195</SP>Pt<SB>8</SB>O<SP>+</SP> reacts further with a second molecule of N<SB>2</SB>O, resulting in a dioxide cluster <SP>195</SP>Pt<SB>8</SB>O<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The figure also reveals that already at a nominal time <IT>t</IT> = 0 some product is present.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is due to reactions occurring during the cluster accumulation period.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">As a second example, in the bottom panel the exponential decay of the <SP>195</SP>Pt<SB>20</SB><SP>+</SP> cluster is shown, and concurrent growth of the only product, <SP>195</SP>Pt<SB>20</SB>O<SP>+</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reaction proceeds faster for <IT>n</IT> = 20 than for <IT>n</IT> = 8, but only one reaction step is observed.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Overall, the chemistry pattern found for all of the clusters, both anions and cations, within the range studied is quite simple.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">We do not observe any evidence for loss of a platinum atom from the cluster, which would in the present analysis lead to a curvature of the reactant ion decay in the semi-logarithmic plots of Fig. 3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">When reaction upon collision with N<SB>2</SB>O does occur, the N<SB>2</SB> molecule is lost, and the single oxygen atom adds to the cluster.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">While in some cases, <SP>195</SP>Pt<SB><IT>n</IT></SB>O<SP>±</SP> appears unreactive, in others it reacts further to form the respective dioxide, <SP>195</SP>Pt<SB><IT>n</IT></SB>O<SB>2</SB><SP>±</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In a few cases, also a third step resulting in <SP>195</SP>Pt<SB><IT>n</IT></SB>O<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> is detected, so that the reactions can be described by the simple equation pattern:Fig. 4 shows a graphical comparison of the observed rates, on a logarithmic scale, of the first reaction step, eqn. (1) for cations and anions as a function of cluster size.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Numerical data for the first reaction step are summarized in Table 1, and for the second, and in the few cases it is observed, third reaction step in Table 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">One finds that the rates of the reaction, as well as the number of oxidation steps observed in the time frame of the experiment vary appreciably, and in a seemingly random manner from cluster to cluster, and the reactivity pattern is also strongly dependent on the cluster charge.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Among the cations, the <IT>n</IT> = 6 and 20 clusters exhibit the fastest reaction according to eqn. (1), with rates above the ADO collision efficiency.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30 cit31 cit32">30–32</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This indicates that the collision probability for large clusters is higher than predicted by the ADO theory.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">In neither case does the primary product <SP>195</SP>Pt<SB><IT>n</IT></SB>O<SP>+</SP> react further, and after about five seconds, these clusters are almost completely converted to the primary product.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The clusters <IT>n</IT> = 7, 8, 11, 12, 15 exhibit an appreciable reactivity, with the primary product reacting further (2).</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the other hand, no reaction could be established for clusters <IT>n</IT> = 10, 14, 23, and upper limits for their reactivity are derived.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Also rather unreactive are very small clusters <SP>195</SP>Pt<SB><IT>n</IT></SB><SP>+</SP>, <IT>n</IT> ≤ 5, with <IT>n</IT> = 1, 2, and 5 reacting only marginally, and no detectable reaction for <IT>n</IT> = 2–4.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">For <IT>n</IT> = 15 and <IT>n</IT> = 18, also a third reaction step, according to (3), is observed, which is in both cases faster than the second step.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The negative cluster ions overall react somewhat slower than the cations, and the size dependence is considerably different.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Interestingly, the <IT>n</IT> = 6 cluster, which was the fastest reacting cluster among the cations, represents in fact a deep reactivity minimum among the anions, with the <SP>195</SP>Pt<SB>6</SB><SP>−</SP> cluster reacting twenty times slower than the neighboring <IT>n</IT> = 4,5,7,8 clusters.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The <IT>n</IT> = 4 cluster, which is completely unreactive among the cations, is in fact the fastest reacting anion, and also exhibits a fast second reaction step to form <SP>195</SP>Pt<SB>4</SB>O<SB>2</SB><SP>−</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs19" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the other hand, the <IT>n</IT> = 10 and 14 clusters, which appear completely inert as cations, are also as anions quite unreactive.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">To summarize the observations, one can understand the reactions as a decomposition of the nitrous oxide on the metal cluster surface, yielding an oxygen atom and molecular N<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">While the oxygen atom oxidizes the platinum, the weakly bound nitrogen is released.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs20" novelty="None" advantage="None">We do not observe stabilization of the undecomposed N<SB>2</SB>O on the surface, and see no trace of products containing nitrogen.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The nearly three orders of magnitude wide variation in the reaction rates between various clusters may reflect their structural differences, and the presence of differently efficient “sites” on the cluster surface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fact that anions and cations behave differently may suggest considerable differences between the structures of anions and cations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have previously succeeded in “soft-landing” otherwise reactive molecules such as benzene or methane on a cluster surface by exchanging them for weaker bound argon ligands,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF> and it might be interesting to try a similar experiment with N<SB>2</SB>O on platinum clusters.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">For small anions, <IT>n</IT> = 3–7, where our data overlap with earlier results of Hintz and Ervin,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13 cit14">13,14</REF> as well as for cations, <IT>n</IT> = 1–5, measured by Schwarz and coworkers,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF> there is good quantitative agreement in the measured rates.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Over the entire range of sizes explored, addition or subtraction of a single atom can change the reactivity by orders of magnitude.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Isotopically enriched platinum allows the quantitative investigation of size-dependent reactivities of platinum clusters.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The present work demonstrates the feasibility and the potential of this approach to further substantiate the notion introduced by Schwarz and coworkers that small platinum clusters can serve as model system for surface catalytic reactions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">They also indicate, however, that, as was previously shown for supported platinum clusters by Heiz <IT>et al</IT>.,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF> also in the gas phase “each atom counts”.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
