<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b406989g" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Crystal structure of cyanobacterial photosystem II at 3.2 Å resolution: a closer look at the Mn-cluster<XREF TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" /></annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">In the crystal structure of photosystem II (PSII) from the cyanobacterium <IT>Thermosynechococcus elongatus</IT> at 3.2 Å resolution, several loop regions of the principal protein subunits are now defined that were not interpretable previously at 3.8 Å resolution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The head groups and side chains of the organic cofactors of the electron transfer chain and of antenna chlorophyll <IT>a</IT> (Chl <IT>a</IT>) have been modeled, coordinating and hydrogen bonding amino acids identified and the nature of the binding pockets derived.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The orientations of these cofactors resemble those of the reaction center from anoxygenic purple bacteria, but differences in hydrogen bonding and protein environment modulate their properties and provide the unique high redox potential (1.17 V) of the primary donor.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None">Coordinating amino acids of manganese cluster, redox-active Tyr<SB>Z</SB> and non-haem Fe<SP>2+</SP> have been determined, and an all-<IT>trans</IT> β-carotene connects cytochrome <IT>b</IT>-559, Chl<SB>Z</SB> and primary electron donor (coordinates are available under PDB-code 1W5C).</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Photosystem II (PSII) is located in the thylakoid membrane of higher plants, algae and cyanobacteria and captures sun light with two antenna proteins CP47 and CP43, which transfer the excitation energy to the photochemical reaction center with primary electron donor P680 formed by chlorophyll <IT>a</IT> (Chl<IT>a</IT>) molecule(s).</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The excited primary donor is oxidized to P680<SP>+</SP>˙, and the released electron travels along the electron transfer chain (ETC) featuring two pairs of Chl<IT>a</IT>, one pair of pheophytin <IT>a</IT> (Pheo<IT>a</IT>) and two plastoquinones (Q<SB>A</SB> and Q<SB>B</SB>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">P680<SP>+</SP>˙ is re-reduced <IT>via</IT> redox-active tyrosine Tyr<SB>Z</SB> by an electron from a Mn-cluster that catalyzes the oxidation of water to atmospheric oxygen.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">After two cycles, doubly reduced and protonated Q<SB>B</SB> is released as plastoquinol Q<SB>B</SB>H<SB>2</SB> into the plastoquinone pool in the thylakoid membrane and oxidized at the membrane-intrinsic cytochrome <IT>b</IT><SB>6</SB><IT>f</IT> complex to Q<SB>B</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The electrons are transferred at the lumenal side of the membrane to soluble cytochrome <IT>c</IT><SB>6</SB> or plastocyanin and conveyed to photosystem I. Here the electrons are donated at the cytoplasmic (stromal) side to soluble ferredoxin that brings them to ferredoxin-NADP<SP>+</SP> reductase where the reducing equivalents finally convert NADP<SP>+</SP> to NADPH.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This whole process is associated with formation of a proton gradient across the membrane that drives synthesis of ATP.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Together with NADPH, it serves to reduce CO<SB>2</SB> to carbohydrates.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The structures of PSII subcore and PSII core complexes have been elucidated by electron diffraction<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">2</REF> and electron microscopy,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF> respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The crystal structure of oxygen-evolving PSII core from the thermophilic cyanobacterium <IT>Thermosynechococcus elongatus</IT> has been determined at 3.8 Å and 3.5 Å, respectively<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit5">4,5</REF> and that of <IT>Thermosynechococcus vulcanus</IT> at 3.7 Å resolution.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The structures show that PSII occurs as homodimer with the monomers related by a non-crystallographic twofold axis (pseudo-<IT>C</IT><SB>2</SB>).</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Experimental procedures</HEADER><P><s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">PSII from <IT>T. elongatus</IT> was purified and crystallized as described.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">X-ray diffraction data were collected at ESRF beamline ID14-2 (<IT>λ</IT> = 0.933 Å) at 100 K and anomalous diffraction data at the Fe-edge (<IT>λ</IT> = 1.7330 Å) and beyond the Mn-edge (<IT>λ</IT> = 1.910 Å) were collected at the MPG/GBF beamline BW6/DESY at 100 K. Fine-tuning of crystallization conditions and an improved cooling protocol yielded low mosaic crystals diffracting to 2.9 Å maximum resolution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">However, due to strong anisotropic diffraction the final dataset had to be truncated beyond 3.2 Å resolution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Data were processed with DENZO/SCALEPACK,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF> the orthorhombic space group is <IT>P</IT>2<SB>1</SB>2<SB>1</SB>2<SB>1</SB> and cell parameters are <IT>a</IT> = 127.5, <IT>b</IT> = 224.6, <IT>c</IT> = 305.6 Å.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Electron density maps calculated from experimental phases<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF> combined with phases derived from partial models were improved by solvent flattening, histogram matching and non-crystallographic symmetry averaging (CCP4 suite),<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF> and interpreted with O.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The atomic model of PSII contains <IT>ca.</IT> 38 000 atoms corresponding to nearly 70% of the expected total number of PSII atoms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Refinement of atomic coordinates against maximum-likelihood crystallographic target with CNS<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF> converged at <IT>R</IT>/<IT>R</IT><SB>free</SB> of 0.36/0.42.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Despite relatively good quality of electron density maps, reliable sequence assignment was only possible in regions with specific sequence landmarks (bulky amino acid side chains and coordination of cofactors).</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="New" advantage="None">Therefore, amino acid side chains of fragments of the structure where sequence assignment was ambiguous were modeled as poly-Ala or C<IT>α</IT>-trace, resulting in a final structure containing <IT>ca.</IT> 36 000 atoms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">All figures were drawn using DINO.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">See Table 1 for diffraction data.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Results and discussion</HEADER><P><s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="New" advantage="None">Here we describe the structure of <IT>Thermosynechococcus elongatus</IT> PSII at 3.2 Å resolution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Of the at least 14 membrane-intrinsic protein subunits in the monomer,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF> the six largest were identified: the reaction center proteins D1 and D2, core antennae CP43 and CP47, and α- and β-chains of cytochrome (cyt) <IT>b</IT>-559.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The remaining 12 transmembrane α-helices (TMH) belong to smaller subunits, some of which were tentatively assigned in previous structures based on biochemical data.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit5 cit6">4–6</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast to (5,6) no assignment of them was done in our present model, as the resolution does not allow a reliable tracing of side chains in these regions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Also, the comparison of other structures <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6">5,6</REF> with our electron density calculated at 3.2 Å resolution does not support their assignments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The membrane-extrinsic subunits PsbO, PsbU and PsbV (cyt <IT>c</IT>-550) were localized on the lumenal side of PSII (Fig. 1).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The core antenna subunits harbour 16 Chl<IT>a</IT> in CP47 and 13 in CP43 that are arranged in two layers near the cytoplasmic and lumenal sides of the membrane.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">All of them are in positions similar to the ones described by Fereirra <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">One additional Chl<IT>a</IT> in CP43 shown in (5) is not present in our electron density maps.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, one can not exclude that PSII contains several more Chl<IT>a</IT> molecules, which are not visible due to limitations of current experimental data.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The β-carotene located in PSII connects cyt <IT>b</IT>-559 and Chlz<SB>D2</SB> through Chl<SB>D2</SB> with the ETC, so that secondary electron donation to the primary donor is possible.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">This Car is found in a position similar to Car 48 reported in (5) but differs from the two Car given in (6).</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The presence of the other six Car molecules shown in (5), although possible, is not supported by our X-ray diffraction data.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Chl<IT>a</IT> and Pheo<IT>a</IT> in the ETC</HEADER><P><s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the Chl<IT>a</IT> pair P680, Chl<IT>a</IT> P<SB>D1</SB> is coordinated by D1-His198Nε and P<SB>D2</SB> by D2-His197Nε; the distance between the two Mg<SP>2+</SP> ions is 8.3 Å (instead of the previously reported 10 Å)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit6">4,6</REF> similar to the distance in (5,13).</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The interplanar separation of the chlorin heterocycles is 3.6 Å (Fig. 2).</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The environment of P<SB>D1</SB> and P<SB>D2</SB> is mainly hydrophobic with no evidence for direct H-bonding to protein.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">D2-Trp191, shown to be important for the high redox potential of P680<SP>+</SP>˙,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF> stacks with D2-His197 and is in van der Waals contact with P<SB>D2</SB>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Chl<SB>D1</SB> and Chl<SB>D2</SB> are found in positions equivalent to the two accessory bacteriochlorophyll <IT>b</IT> in purple bacteria reaction center (PbRC).</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast to PbRC, they are not coordinated by histidines,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF> but probably by water molecules H-bonded to D1-Thr179Oγ and D2-Val175O, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The binding pockets of Chl<SB>D1</SB> and Chl<SB>D2</SB> are both hydrophobic with two notable differences: first, in the Chl<SB>D1</SB> binding pocket there are three Met residues but none in the Chl<SB>D2</SB> pocket and second, there is no direct H-bond in the Chl<SB>D1</SB> pocket but one in the Chl<SB>D2</SB> pocket formed between D1-Gln199NεH and the carboxymethyl carbonyl oxygen of Chl<SB>D2</SB>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Pheo<SB>D1</SB> is located between TMH <B>c</B> of D1 and <B>d</B> of D2, while Pheo<SB>D2</SB> between TMH <B>c</B> of D2 and <B>d</B> of D1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both Pheo<IT>a</IT> are in van der Waals contact with non-polar side chains.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Pheo<SB>D1</SB> forms three H-bonds: between D1-Gln130NεH and the keto oxygen; D1-Tyr126OηH and carboxymethyl carbonyl oxygen; D1-Tyr147OηH and carboxyphytyl carbonyl oxygen.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Conversely, Pheo<SB>D2</SB> is not involved in any direct H-bond to the protein matrix.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although the arrangement and orientation of the cofactors constituting the two branches of the ETC are similar in PSII and PbRC, there are some notable differences.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Mg<SP>2+</SP>⋯Mg<SP>2+</SP> distance of P<SB>D1</SB>/P<SB>D2</SB> in PSII, 8.3 Å, is only 0.7 Å longer than that of the two bacteriochlorophyll <IT>b</IT> of P960 (7.6 Å),<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF> in good agreement with the structures published at lower resolution,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit13">5,13</REF> suggesting that P680 could likewise act as a special Chl<IT>a</IT> pair.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, according to the multimer model, the excited singlet state <SP>1</SP>P680* is rather delocalized over all four Chl<IT>a</IT> (P<SB>D1</SB>, P<SB>D2</SB>, Chl<SB>D1</SB>, Chl<SB>D2</SB>), and possibly could include the two Pheo<IT>a</IT> and the arrangement found in the structure does not contradict such model for the excited state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">This would allow these cofactors to act as a collective state, thereby promoting fast and efficient charge separation.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16 cit17">16,17</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The formed cation radical P680<SP>+</SP>˙ is localized on a monomeric Chl<IT>a</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF> that was identified as P<SB>D1</SB> by spectroscopic studies on D1-His198 mutants.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19">19</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">An increased distance between P<SB>D1</SB> and P<SB>D2</SB> also reduces electronic coupling, which in turn probably contributes to the higher midpoint redox potential for the primary donor in PSII compared to PbRC (1.17 V in P680<SP>+</SP>˙/P680 <IT>versus</IT> 0.52 V in P960<SP>+</SP>˙/P960),<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF> finally allowing electron abstraction from Tyr<SB>Z</SB> and the Mn-cluster.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The environment of P<SB>D1</SB>/P<SB>D2</SB> is more hydrophobic than that of P960, where three H-bonds have been identified.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">In PSII one H-bond is found to Chl<SB>D2</SB>, but none to the accessory bacteriochlorophyll <IT>b</IT> in PbRC.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None">These differences are likely to influence the redox potential of P680.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Environment of the Mn-cluster</HEADER><P><s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The cluster of four Mn cations located at the lumenal side of D1 is surrounded mostly by residues from this subunit and by some (not modeled) side chains from CP43 (Fig. 3A).</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Its electron density contoured at the 3.5 <IT>σ</IT> level is Y-shaped with dimensions 5 × 7 × 3 Å (Fig. 3B).</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">This changes at the 5.5 <IT>σ</IT> level to two distinct peaks, one larger and the other smaller harboring probably 3 and 1 Mn cations, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our X-ray diffraction data measured at and beyond the Mn-edge confirm the presence of Ca<SP>2+</SP> near the larger density peak of Mn, making interpretation in terms of a Mn–Ca-heteronuclear cluster<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF> possible.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">From this data the most probable of the four ions, which might be Ca<SP>2+</SP>, is Mn57 (Fig. 3).</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Assuming that all four cations are Mn would be in agreement with the 3 + 1 model structures derived from EPR and EXAFS data.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast to Ferreira <IT>et al</IT>.,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF> our electron density of the cluster accommodates only four metal ions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Such a model of the oxygen evolving centre (OEC) might be incomplete and explained by radiation damage occurring upon long exposure of crystals to X-rays during data collection.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The radiation, especially at low energies around the Mn-edge, is likely to promote intrinsic disorder or even loss of some metal ions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">The two models of OEC agree in terms of having two moieties: one smaller containing one cation and one larger containing three or more cations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The exact positions and identity of the cations are certainly affected by insufficient quality of data and different approaches in the interpretation of electron density.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Obviously, higher resolution (&lt;2.9 Å) data are necessary to complete a reliable model of the OEC, as the Mn-Mn distance is about 2.9 Å as derived from EXAFS.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The side chains of Asp170, Glu189, His332 and Glu333 of D1 are close enough for direct coordination of Mn cations (Fig. 3C and D), in agreement with mutation studies.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24 cit25">24,25</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Additional coordination could be provided by residues located in the loop <B>a</B>–<B>ab</B> and in the C-terminal region of D1, which are not clearly defined in the electron density.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con18" novelty="None" advantage="None">According to biochemical data the likely ligands would be His337, Asp342, Ala.344<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24 cit25">24,25</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Most of the protein ligands are in agreement to the recent 3.5 Å structure.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">Glu354 of CP43, proposed to coordinate Mn in (5) is close to the cluster but its side chain is not visible in our electron density.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Mn-cluster and phenolic TyrZOηH are bridged by the carboxylate of D1–Glu189 (Fig. 3C).</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Tyr<SB>Z</SB>OηH is separated by 13 Å from the central Mg<SP>2+</SP> of P<SB>D1</SB> (closest edge-to-edge distance 6.9 Å).</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con20" novelty="None" advantage="None">Extended H-bonding of Tyr<SB>Z</SB>OηH (Fig. 3C and D) supports the proposal that an H-bond network facilitates deprotonation of the Tyr<SB>Z</SB>OηH group.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26 cit27">26,27</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con21" novelty="None" advantage="None">The symmetry related Tyr<SB>D</SB> (D2-Tyr160) is found in a hydrophobic environment with two H-bonds to D2–His189 and D2–Gln164, as predicted by spectroscopy<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28 cit29">28,29</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>A word of caution</HEADER><P><s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con22" novelty="None" advantage="None">All thus far presented crystal structures of PSII from <IT>T. elongatus</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit5">4,5</REF> and <IT>T. vulcanus</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF> must be considered with caution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con22" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reason is that at resolutions in the range 3.2 to 3.8 Å the interpretation of electron density maps is only safe for polypeptide main chains whereas side chains can not be assigned unambiguously except if they are coordinated to ligands (Chl<IT>a</IT> or Fe<SP>2+</SP>) that could serve as landmarks, and this holds even for main chains in loop segments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">The best defined sections in the electron density are membrane-intrinsic parts of the main subunits D1, D2, CP43, CP47 and cyt <IT>b</IT>-559.</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">The electron densities of the small subunits located at the periphery of PSII are less well defined and consequently difficult to interpret, especially since these subunits do not bind marker groups, and the size of their side chains is more uniform compared to the large subunits.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con23" novelty="None" advantage="None">With this caveat we find that many sections of the 3.5 and 3.7 Å structures<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6">5,6</REF> may have been over-interpreted especially with respect to sequence assignment in loop segments and small subunits.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
