<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b411500g" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Rotational and ro-vibrational transitions of He<SB>2</SB>C<SP>2+</SP><XREF TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" /></annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None"><IT>Ab initio</IT> calculations of transition frequencies and line strengths have been calculated for the “forbidden” rotational spectrum and <IT>ν</IT><SB>2</SB> fundamental ro-vibrational of the <SP>1</SP>A<SB>1</SB> state of He<SB>2</SB>C<SP>2+</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the “pure” rotational spectrum, the vibration ground state transitions are very weak, with the intensity of the strongest line, 3<SB>31</SB>–4<SB>40</SB>, being only 2.15 × 10<SP>−22</SP> cm molecule<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">A group of significant line strengths is attributed to ro-vibrational transitions between (〈0,2,0〉 ←〈0,1,0〉) and (〈0,1,0〉 ← 〈0,0,0〉) bands.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">These band centers are calculated at 309.5 and 330.4 cm<SP>−1</SP> respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The strongest band is identified with the (〈0,2,0〉 ← 〈0,0,0〉) transition with a band center of 625.1 cm<SP>−1</SP> and line strength of 2.58 × 10<SP>−19</SP> cm molecule<SP>−1</SP> for the (4<SB>40</SB> ← 4<SB>41</SB>) transition.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="1.">Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Over the past several decades there has been considerable interest in using <IT>ab initio</IT> techniques in order to calculate the infrared spectra of molecular ions, which are of interest in ion-molecule reaction schemes pertinent to the production of interstellar molecules.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2 cit3 cit4 cit5 cit6">1–6</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The simplest molecular ion, H<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP>, has played a critical role in the synergy between theory<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2 cit4 cit7">2,4,7</REF> and experiment<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit9">8–9</REF> in unravelling the existence of this ion in interstellar space.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10 cit11">10–11</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is well known that helium is the second most abundant element in the interstellar medium.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Helium is involved in several important gas-phase reactions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The charge transfer recombination of multiply charged ionic species in collision with atomic helium is important in interstellar processes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">For example, more than eighty charge exchange reactions involving the He<SP>+</SP> have been identified in astrophysical plasmas.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Moreover, recent ion measurements from the Jovian magnetosphere have indicated the presence of helium, oxygen and sulfur ions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is therefore not surprising that the electronic structure of multiply charged seeded helide cations of form, He<SB><IT>n</IT></SB>X<SP><IT>m</IT>+</SP> (where <IT>n</IT> = 1 2, X = C,N,O and <IT>m</IT> = 1,2), have been extensively investigated using <IT>ab initio</IT> techniques by Hughes and von Nagy-Felsobuki.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6">5–6</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is hope that these calculations will assist the interstellar as well as the laboratory detection of these ions.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Of the triatomic seeded helides ions, He<SB>2</SB>C<SP>2+</SP> is the most likely candidate for detection in the interstellar medium.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The χ <SP>1</SP>A<SB>1</SB> state of He<SB>2</SB>C<SP>2+</SP> has been extensively investigated by Koch and Frenking<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF> and Hughes and von Nagy-Felsobuki.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit5">4–5</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">This state is predicted to be thermodynamically stable with a dissociation energy of <IT>ca.</IT> 57 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is lower in energy than the <SP>3</SP>B<SB>1</SB> state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Frenking and Cremer<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF> have also postulated that in this state the binding force of this ion is electrostatic in nature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">At the CCSD(T)_AE/cc-pCVTZ level of theory, Hughes and von Nagy-Felsobuki<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit5">4–5</REF> have determined that its optimised structural parameters (<IT>r</IT><SB>C–He</SB>; <IT>θ</IT><SB>He–C–He</SB>) are (1.570 Å; 84.1°), respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot3" novelty="None" advantage="None">These workers have also calculated the low-lying ro-vibrational states of this ion,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF> although so far no dipole moment surface or line strengths for the rotational and ro-vibrational transitions have been determined (such information would further assist the identification of this ion in a laboratory or interstellar setting).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">As our extension of our earlier work on the electronic structure of He<SB>2</SB>C<SP>2+</SP>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit5">4–5</REF> we wish to report the rotational and ro-vibrational spectrum of this ion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In doing so, we shall detail the most accurate ro-vibration transition frequencies, dipole moment surface and line strengths reported to-date, thereby assisting its laboratory and interstellar detection.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.">Computational procedure</HEADER><P><s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The potential energy surface used in the ro-vibrational calculations has been detailed elsewhere by Hughes and von Nagy-Felsobuki.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The potential energy function is a Padé (4,5) power series expansion, which has been embedded in the Eckart–Watson Hamiltonian, with the resultant eigenvalue problem solved with a variational methodology using an algorithm developed by Searles and von Nagy-Felsobuki.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The basic approach to the variational solution is the construction of a “full” three-dimensional vibration configuration basis set from 20 × 20 × 20 one-dimensional (1D) eigenfunctions (which are finite-element solutions of a 1D Hamiltonian expressed in terms of a single rectilinear <IT>t</IT> co-ordinate).</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The “full” ro-vibrational wave function is given by a linear combination of the products of the three 1D configurational bases functions (yielding 8000 vibration basis functions in total) together with a complete set of symmetric-top rotor functions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ro-vibrational matrix spanned by this trial basis set is then diagonalised yielding ro-vibrational eigenenergies and eigenfunctions.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The <IT>ab initio</IT> dipole moment surface (DMS) of a molecule is usually generated in conjunction with the calculation of the potential energy surface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The dipole moment calculations were performed in the centre-of-mass system using the QCSID_AE/aug-cc-pCVTZ level of theory.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None">A total of 75 <IT>ab initio</IT> points have been calculated on the <SP>1</SP>A<SB>1</SB> state of He<SB>2</SB>C<SP>2+</SP> hypersurface using the GAUSSIAN suite of programs.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">A table containing these points is available as electronic supplementary information (ESI).</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This discrete surface has been fitted to an analytical function generated using a fifth order power series, which was formulated by Gabriel <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF>. in the following manner,The functional form of the DMS is in terms of two bond lengths and included bond angle (<IT>ρ</IT><SB>1</SB> = <IT>R</IT><SB>1</SB> − <IT>R</IT><SB>1</SB><SP>e</SP>, <IT>ρ</IT><SB>2</SB> = <IT>R</IT><SB>2</SB> − <IT>R</IT><SB>2</SB><SP>e</SP>, <IT>ρ</IT><SB>3</SB> = <IT>θ</IT> − <IT>θ</IT><SP><IT>e</IT></SP>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The (<IT>χ</IT><SP>2</SP>)<SP>1/2</SP> for fifth order expansion is <IT>ca.</IT> 10<SP>−3</SP> au for all the <IT>μ</IT><SB><IT>x</IT></SB> and <IT>μ</IT><SB><IT>y</IT></SB> components.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The dipole moment function has been graphically inspected in order to ensure that the regions of electrical anharmonicity are within the expectation values of the <IT>ab initio</IT> dipole moment calculations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Table 1 gives a full description of the dipole moment function.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The general strategy in the evaluation of radiative properties has been detailed elsewhere.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19">19</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Nevertheless it is pertinent to point out some of the following features of the procedure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The transition probabilities spanned by the variational wave functions have been determined using the Harris <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF>. quadrature scheme.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The ro-vibrational transition probabilities have been transformed into the space-fixed co-ordinate system from the molecule-fixed framework, using the formulation as outlined by Zare<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF> and then appropriately evaluated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The transition probability evaluation procedure and ensuing results have been carefully benchmarked for H<SB>2</SB>O and are in excellent agreement with methodologies using more traditional algorithms.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19">19</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">All calculations have been performed using Compaq Alpha workstations under the UNIX operating system.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.">Results and discussions</HEADER><P><s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ro-vibrational wave function presented here differs significantly from that previously determined by Hughes and von Nagy-Felsobuki.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The latter variational calculation used a nodal cut-off criterion in order to select only 560 vibration configuration basis functions from a possible configuration list of 8000.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="New" advantage="None">The “pure” rotational and ro-vibrational transitional energies listed in Tables 2 and 3 have been calculated using the complete list of 8000 vibration basis functions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">The energy levels throughout these Tables are converged to ±0.02 cm<SP>−1</SP> (based on a study of the variation of the energy levels as a function of configurational size).</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hence, these are the most accurate energy levels reported to date in the literature.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Table 2 gives the “pure” rotational transitions associated with the ground electronic and vibrational state of He<SB>2</SB>C<SP>2+</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The limiting case for the rotational levels is Mulliken’s prolate symmetric-top.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="New" advantage="None">The rotational levels given in Tables 2 and 3 are assigned within this framework and are calculated up to the <IT>J</IT> = 4 level.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="New" advantage="None">The assignments of the ro-vibrational states in these tables are based on the expansion densities determined from the coefficients of the variational wave function.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="None" advantage="No">For the ro-vibrational states higher than the fourth excited rotational state, the resultant wave functions are heavily mixed due to basis functions, which belong to the same irreducible representation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="None" advantage="No">Hence, the assignment of a wave function in terms of a single diagonal representation becomes problematical for the more excited states.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="New" advantage="None">For simplicity we have restricted the analysis to energy levels whose wave functions (according to the expansion density analysis) have unequivocal assignments; that is, for wave functions which are not severely delocalised.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="New" advantage="None">Therefore, the assignments in Tables 2 and 3 are restricted to all transitions, up to and including the <IT>ν</IT> = 4 and <IT>J</IT> = 4 level.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">A comprehensive assignment of a more extensive list of transitions between delocalised states is available from the authors.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The ro-vibrational spectral line intensities of a transition from an initial state |<IT>i</IT>〉 to a final state |<IT>j</IT>〉 can be evaluated <IT>via</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF>where the usual definitions for <IT>k</IT>, <IT>h</IT>, <IT>c</IT>, <IT>R</IT>, <IT>T</IT> and <IT>N</IT><SB>A</SB> apply.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Here <IT>C</IT><SB>A</SB> is the isotopic abundance, <IT>g</IT><SB>nsi</SB> is the nuclear statistical weight of the initial state, <IT>ω</IT><SB><IT>ij</IT></SB> is the frequency of transition (cm<SP>−1</SP>), <IT>E</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB> and <IT>E</IT><SB><IT>j</IT></SB> are the energy of the initial state |<IT>i</IT>〉 and final state |<IT>j</IT>〉 in cm<SP>−1</SP>, <IT>Q</IT><SB>V</SB> and <IT>Q</IT><SB>R</SB> are the vibration and rotation partition functions, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="Old" advantage="None">For He<SB>2</SB>C<SP>2+</SP> the <IT>g</IT><SB>nsi</SB> value for the symmetric and anti-symmetric levels is 1 and 0, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The <IT>R</IT><SP>2</SP> term is the transition probability summed in terms of the Wigner rotation matrices, with the transition moment integrals evaluated using the Harris <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF>. quadrature scheme.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="New" advantage="None">It should be noted that in this work the ro-vibrational transition probability (<IT>R</IT><SP>2</SP>) is calculated exactly (<IT>i.e.</IT> by employing the “full” ro-vibrational wave function and the transformed DMS).</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">Therefore, there is no need to impose selection rules, such as Δ<IT>J</IT> = 0,±1, since these are reflected within the calculations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">According to the ro-vibrational selection rules, the total number of allowable transitions up to and including the <IT>v</IT> = 4 and <IT>J</IT> = 4 level is 1250.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">From <IT>ab initio</IT> calculations of He<SB>2</SB>C<SP>2+</SP> spectrum, many of these transitions are still not significant in terms of their intensities (<IT>i.e.</IT> well below 10<SP>−30</SP> cm molecule<SP>−1</SP>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, a number of these transitions are forbidden (<IT>i.e.</IT> the value of the line intensities are zero) due to the fact that the nuclear spin statistic of lower level is zero (<IT>e.g</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">512 transition are spin forbidden from this consideration alone).</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hence, for He<SB>2</SB>C<SP>2+</SP> the total number of transitions with intensities above 10<SP>−30</SP> cm molecule<SP>−1</SP> is 637.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 1 gives the ro-vibrational spectrum up to and including the <IT>v</IT> = 4 and <IT>J</IT> = 4 level using a line strength threshold of 1.0 × 10<SP>−30</SP> cm molecule<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Table 2 details the line strengths for all the “pure” rotational transitions up to <IT>J</IT> = 4 level associated with the ground electronic and vibrational state of He<SB>2</SB>C<SP>2+</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">From Fig. 1 and Table 2 it is evident that for the intensities of the “pure” rotational transition of the vibration ground state (with a transition energy less than 25.0 cm<SP>−1</SP>) are very weak (<IT>e.g.</IT> the intensity of the strongest line, 3<SB>3 1</SB>–4<SB>4 0</SB>, is only 2.15 × 10<SP>−22</SP> cm molecule<SP>−1</SP>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The next group of significant line strengths is attributed to ro-vibrational transitions between (〈0,2,0〉 ← 〈0,1,0〉) and (〈0,1,0〉 ← 〈0,0,0〉) bands.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The band centers are calculated to be 309.5 and 330.4 cm<SP>−1</SP> respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The strongest band is assigned to the (〈0,2,0〉 ← 〈0,0,0〉) transition, with the band center at 625.1 cm<SP>−1</SP> and a line strength of 2.58 × 10<SP>−19</SP> cm molecule<SP>−1</SP> (which is assigned to the 4<SB>4 0</SB>–4<SB>4 1</SB> transition).</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Table 3 details the dipole-allowed ro-vibrational transitions for He<SB>2</SB>C<SP>2+</SP> in the <IT>ν</IT><SB>2</SB> fundamental using a cut-off in intensity of greater than 1.0 × 10<SP>−20</SP> cm molecule<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Using the Einstein <IT>A</IT><SB><IT>ul</IT></SB> coefficient it also possible to calculate the fluorescence lifetime of a particular state in the absence of an external radiation field (where only spontaneous emission occurs).</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The fluorescence lifetime, <IT>τ</IT>f<IT>u</IT>, can be calculated <IT>via</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF>where the Einstein <IT>A</IT> coefficient is defined as</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Tables 2 and 3 list the Einstein <IT>A</IT> coefficients.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The selection rules discussed above lead to three or fewer possible decay routes for the levels presented in Tables 2 and 3 and so the radiative lifetimes using eqn. (2) can be easily determined.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
