<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b411005f" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Phytochromobilin C15-<IT>Z</IT>,<IT>syn</IT> → C15-<IT>E</IT>,<IT>anti</IT> isomerization: concerted or stepwise?</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">The C15-<IT>Z</IT>,<IT>syn</IT> → C15-<IT>E</IT>,<IT>anti</IT> isomerization of phytochromobilin that underlies the photoactivation of phytochrome, the plant photoreceptor responsive to red and far-red light, is investigated by means of quantum chemical methods.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">By calculating ground and excited-state potential energy surfaces for a phytochromobilin model comprising the full tetrapyrrolic skeleton, and taking into consideration rotations around the C14−C15 and C15C16 bonds constituting the methine bridge between pyrrole rings C and D, it is found that a stepwise <IT>Z</IT> → <IT>E</IT>, <IT>syn</IT> → <IT>anti</IT> mechanism is energetically preferable over a concerted <IT>Z</IT>,<IT>syn</IT> → <IT>E</IT>,<IT>anti</IT> mechanism.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In particular, on the basis of the calculated potential energy surfaces, it is proposed that the primary photochemical reaction involves a <IT>Z</IT> → <IT>E</IT> isomerization only, and that the subsequent <IT>syn</IT> → <IT>anti</IT> isomerization proceeds thermally.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="I.">Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Phytochromes make up a class of regulatory biliprotein photoreceptors in plants that monitor the quality and quantity of light in the environment and govern the adaptation of growth and developmental patterns in response to the prevailing light conditions by means of so-called photomorphogenic processes.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2 cit3">1–3</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The chromophore of phytochrome, phytochromobilin (PΦB, Fig. 1), is an open-chain tetrapyrrole which is covalently bound to a cysteine residue of the apoprotein through a thioether linkage.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Phytochromes exist in two thermostable forms: the physiologically inactive red-light absorbing form (Pr, <IT>λ</IT><SB>max</SB> = 660 nm) and the physiologically active far-red-light absorbing form (Pfr, <IT>λ</IT><SB>max</SB> = 730 nm).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">These two are photointerconvertible, and Pr/Pfr thus constitutes a photochromic system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Illumination with 660-nm light shifts the <IT>in vitro</IT> equilibrium between the two towards approximately 85% Pfr and triggers a physiological response <IT>in vivo</IT>, whereas illumination with 730-nm light yields about 99% Pr and cancels the physiological effect<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF>.The kinetics of the Pr → Pfr phototransformation has been extensively studied by a variety of time-resolved spectroscopic techniques,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6 cit7 cit8 cit9 cit10 cit11 cit12 cit13 cit14">6–14</REF> and a number of metastable intermediates states with lifetimes in the micro to millisecond regime and distinctive absorption characteristics (<IT>λ</IT><SB>max</SB>) have thereby been identified.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">It has also been established that only the first step of the reaction, formation of the lumi-R intermediate, requires light; the subsequent steps leading to Pfr take place in the dark (<IT>cf</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">ref. 14</REF>.).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">As for conformational changes of the protein and the chromophore during the phototransformation, a detailed understanding is still missing (<IT>e.g.</IT>, X-ray crystallographic structures are not available).</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In 1983, Rüdiger and co-workers recorded <SP>1</SP>H NMR spectra of chromopeptide fragments of phytochrome showing that while the chromophore in Pr has a <IT>Z</IT> configuration around the C15C16 bond (C15-<IT>Z</IT>), the chromophore adopts a C15-<IT>E</IT> configuration in Pfr.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Accordingly, they proposed that the primary photochemical reaction underlying the activation of phytochrome involves a <IT>Z</IT> → <IT>E</IT> isomerization of the chromophore around its C15C16 bond.</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In later studies resonance Raman (RR) techniques, which offer a means to investigate the <IT>in situ</IT> structure of chromophores in proteins, have been used to probe the conformation of PΦB at different stages of the photocycle.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16 cit17 cit18 cit19 cit20">16–20</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The consensus of these studies is that the configuration of PΦB indeed is C15-<IT>Z</IT> in Pr and C15-<IT>E</IT> in Pfr.</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, the C15-<IT>Z</IT> → C15-<IT>E</IT> photoisomerization appears to take place prior to the formation of the first intermediate (lumi-R),<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17 cit20">17,20</REF> which is in accordance with the observation that the lumi-R → Pfr conversion does not require light (<IT>cf</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">ref. 14</REF>.).</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Apart from implicating different configurations around the C15C16 bond, RR vibrational spectra also argue for different configurations with respect to the C14−C15 bond in Pr and Pfr (C15-<IT>syn</IT> and C15-<IT>anti</IT>, respectively).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16 cit19">16,19</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">This suggests that the geometry of the methine bridge between pyrrole rings C and D changes from C15-<IT>Z</IT>,<IT>syn</IT> to C15-<IT>E</IT>,<IT>anti</IT> during the course of the reaction (Fig. 1), <IT>i.e.</IT>, the conversion of Pr into Pfr involves a ‘two-fold’ isomerization of PΦB.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The isomerization about both a double bond and an adjacent single bond is commonly referred to as a ‘hula-twist’ isomerization.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">While the <IT>Z</IT> → <IT>E</IT> isomerization in all likelihood proceeds photochemically prior to the formation of lumi-R, the nature and starting of the <IT>syn</IT> → <IT>anti</IT> isomerization remain elusive issues.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">It has been argued that the primary photochemical reaction corresponds to the two isomerizations occurring simultaneously in a concerted fashion, as this mode may require less space in the protein pocket harbouring rings C and D.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit22">5,22</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the other hand, RR vibrational spectra of Pr, lumi-R, and Pfr suggest that the <IT>syn</IT> → <IT>anti</IT> isomerization is not initiated until <IT>after</IT> the formation of lumi-R, which implies that <IT>syn</IT> → <IT>anti</IT> proceeds thermally.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19">19</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The possibility that the protonation state of PΦB changes during the Pr → Pfr transformation is another issue that has attracted considerable interest.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">As for Pr, spectroscopic data from RR<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17 cit18 cit20">17,18,20</REF> and Fourier transform infrared (FTIR)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23 cit24">23,24</REF> studies unambiguously show that the chromophore is protonated (Fig. 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">In Pfr, on the other hand, the RR spectra due to Mizutani <IT>et al.</IT> favour a deprotonated chromophore,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF> while subsequent and arguably more reliable RR spectra recorded by Hildebrandt and co-workers using near-infrared Fourier transform techniques, which reduce the interference by inherent fluorescence on RR signals, suggest that the chromophore remains protonated throughout the Pr → Pfr transformation.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18 cit20">18,20</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">FTIR results are also indicative of the chromophore being protonated not only in Pr and Pfr, but also in all intermediates connecting these.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23 cit24">23,24</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In light of the above discussion, the main objective of the present work is to investigate the C15-<IT>Z</IT>,<IT>syn</IT> → C15-<IT>E</IT>,<IT>anti</IT> isomerization of PΦB using quantum chemical methods.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">By calculating ground and excited-state potential energy surfaces (PES) taking into account both concerted (<IT>Z</IT>,<IT>syn</IT> → <IT>E</IT>,<IT>anti</IT>) and stepwise (<IT>Z</IT> → <IT>E</IT> followed by <IT>syn</IT> → <IT>anti</IT>) reaction pathways, we will in particular herein be able to present valuable new information with regard to the nature and starting of the <IT>syn</IT> → <IT>anti</IT> isomerization (photochemical isomerization simultaneously with <IT>Z</IT> → <IT>E</IT> or thermal isomerization after <IT>Z</IT> → <IT>E</IT>).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">From relatively recent quantum chemical studies of the chromophore photoisomerization underlying the biological activity of the rhodopsin family of proteins, it has been suggested that only two electronic states of the chromophore (a retinal molecule) are of importance for this reaction; the ground state (S<SB>0</SB>) and the strongly absorbing first singlet excited state (S<SB>1</SB>).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25 cit26 cit27">25–27</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">This two-state model, which challenges a proposed three-state model involving the optically forbidden second singlet excited state (S<SB>2</SB>) as well,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28 cit29">28–29</REF> has later also been implicated in other photoisomerizations of conjugated protein-bound chromophores, including, <IT>e.g.</IT>, that of <IT>p</IT>-coumaric acid responsible for the activation of the bacterial photoreceptor photoactive yellow protein.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30">30</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is, consequently, of interest to explore whether a two-state model is applicable to PΦB isomerization as well.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">It should here be pointed out that the above studies<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25 cit26 cit27 cit30">25–27,30</REF> were carried out using multiconfigurational complete active space self-consistent field (CASSCF) methods, which constitute the most appropriate theoretical framework for the modeling of photochemical reactions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit31">31</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="No">However, such methods are inevitably marred by substantial computational demands, rendering them inapplicable to a molecular system as large as PΦB.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="No">Actually, even subjecting to CASSCF calculations a simplified PΦB model comprising only rings C and D is a prohibitively difficult task if many points on a PES are of interest (an active space consisting of 12 electrons and 12 orbitals is a recent estimate<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit32">32</REF> of the practical limit for asymmetric molecules).</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="New" advantage="None">The density functional theory (DFT)-based approach undertaken in this work, on the other hand, enables the necessary calculations, but provides a less accurate description in regions where two potential energy surfaces come close in energy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">None of the conclusions emerging from the present work is however affected by this shortcoming.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Finally, even though quantum chemical investigations of direct relevance for phytochrome are scarce, it is worth mentioning that calculated RR spectra of hexamethylpyrromethene (a dipyrrole) in fair agreement with experiments have been reported,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit33 cit34">33,34</REF> and that semiempirical calculations have yielded rather accurate electronic absorption spectra of PΦB<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit35">35</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="II.">Theoretical methods</HEADER><P><s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">All calculations were carried out with the Gaussian 03 suite of programs.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit36">36</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Ground-state geometries were optimized using the B3LYP hybrid density functional<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit37 cit38 cit39">37–39</REF> in conjunction with the 6-31G(d) basis set, excited-state geometries were optimized using the <IT>ab initio</IT> configuration interaction singles (CIS) method within the frozen-core approximation and employing the same basis set.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Vertical and adiabatic excitation energies were calculated on the basis of B3LYP ground-state and CIS excited-state geometries, respectively, using the Gaussian 03 implementation<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit40">40</REF> of time-dependent density functional theory (TD-DFT).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit41">41</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The TD-DFT single point calculations were carried out with the B3LYP functional, and made use of the 6-31G(d) basis set unless otherwise explicitly noted.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Due to the fact that PΦB contains 80 atoms and PES comprising in total &gt;200 structures had to be computed, simplified PΦB models were employed.<SUP TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" /> The principal model use, hereafter referred to as PΦB1, is shown in Fig. 2, and corresponds to a protonated chromophore.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17 cit18 cit20 cit23 cit24">17,18,20,23,24</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this model, the thioether linkage, the propionate side chains of pyrroles B and C, and the methyl group of each pyrrole are replaced by hydrogens.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is here appropriate to emphasize that the present study neglects the effect of the surrounding protein on the photochemistry of PΦB.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Even though this effect may be considerable, we are herein aiming at estimating <IT>relative</IT> reactivities of different isomerization pathways (on which similar influence from the protein to some extent may be expected), rather than estimating accurate <IT>absolute</IT> reactivities.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The C15-<IT>Z</IT>,<IT>syn</IT> to C15-<IT>E</IT>,<IT>anti</IT> isomerization was modeled as follows.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">First, the suitability of using PΦB1 in the modeling was explored by comparing calculated wavelengths of maximum absorption (vertical S<SB>1</SB> excitation energies) for PΦB1 in <IT>Z</IT>,<IT>syn</IT> and <IT>E</IT>,<IT>anti</IT> configurations with the corresponding <IT>λ</IT><SB>max</SB> as obtained for three larger models adding a) the missing propionate side chains of pyrroles B and C (PΦB2) b) the missing methyl group of each pyrrole (PΦB3) c) the missing propionate side chains of pyrroles B and C <IT>and</IT> the missing methyl group of each pyrrole (PΦB4).</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, optimized S<SB>0</SB> geometric parameters for PΦB1, PΦB2, PΦB3, and PΦB4 were compared.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="New" advantage="None">Next, basis set effects on excitation energies were investigated by calculating vertical excitation energies for the S<SB>1</SB> and S<SB>2</SB> states of PΦB1 in <IT>Z</IT>,<IT>syn</IT>, <IT>E</IT>,<IT>syn</IT>, <IT>Z</IT>,<IT>anti</IT>, and <IT>E</IT>,<IT>anti</IT> configurations using the 6-31G(d), 6-31G(d,p), 6-31+G(d), and 6-311+G(d,p) basis set.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="New" advantage="None">Subsequently, zero-point vibrational energy (ZPVE) corrections and thermal corrections to Gibbs free energies (<IT>G</IT><SB>corr</SB>) for optimized S<SB>0</SB>, S<SB>1</SB>, and S<SB>2</SB> structures of PΦB1 (<IT>Z</IT>,<IT>syn</IT>, <IT>E</IT>,<IT>syn</IT>, <IT>Z</IT>,<IT>anti</IT>, and <IT>E</IT>,<IT>anti</IT>) were obtained through B3LYP/6-31G(d) and CIS/6-31G(d) frequency calculations, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="New" advantage="None">Finally, S<SB>0</SB>, S<SB>1</SB>, and S<SB>2</SB> PES for PΦB1 taking into account variation in C13C14−C15C16 and C14−C15C16−C17 dihedrals were computed employing 99 ‘grid points’, each combining one value from C13C14−C15C16 = {−0, −30, −60, −75, −90, −105, −120, −150, −180°} with one value from C14−C15C16−C17 = {0, 30, 45, 60, 75, 90, 105, 120, 135, 150, 180°}.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="New" advantage="None">At each point, B3LYP/6-31G(d) and CIS/6-31G(d) geometry optimizations were carried out relaxing all other degrees of freedom.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">In order to obtain more accurate excited-state energies, TD-B3LYP/6-31G(d) single point calculations were then performed on the optimized CIS geometries.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="New" advantage="No">On the basis of the initial ‘benchmark’ calculations (commented upon in detail below), neither ZPVE nor thermal corrections for these grid point were accounted for.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="No">It should be noted that the use of DFT for optimizing ground-state structures and CIS − a Hartree–Fock (HF)-based method − for optimizing excited-state structures to some extent results in an unbalanced description of the PES.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">A more suitable approach in this respect would have been to either optimize the former (S<SB>0</SB>) at the HF level of theory, or to optimize also the latter (S<SB>1</SB> and S<SB>2</SB>) using DFT.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, since B3LYP in general improves significantly upon HF-derived ground-state molecular properties, and since CIS offers an efficient methodology for the calculation of excited-state geometries, we believe that the actual approach undertaken constitutes the best compromise between computational accuracy and efficiency.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="III.">Results and discussion</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>A. Evaluation of computational model and procedures</HEADER><P><s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results from the calculations comparing ground-state geometric parameters and wavelengths of maximum absorption for PΦB1, PΦB2, PΦB3, and PΦB4 are presented in Table 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">From the dihedral angles, we first and foremost note that the dipyrrolic moiety comprising rings C and D regardless of computational model and configuration is non-planar.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Even though the <IT>Z</IT>,<IT>syn</IT>, <IT>E</IT>,<IT>syn</IT>, <IT>Z</IT>,<IT>anti</IT>, and <IT>E</IT>,<IT>anti</IT> designations strictly speaking refer to configurations with the C14−C15C16−C17 and C13C14−C15C16 dihedrals equal to 180 and 0, 0 and 0, 180 and −180, and 0 and −180°, respectively, these designations will for the sake of simplicity refer to geometry-optimized configurations in this section.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Moreover, we observe (<IT>cf.</IT> PΦB1 and PΦB2) that none of the bond lengths, all of which one may expect to be of relevance for the isomerization, are sensitive to the exclusion of the propionate side chains of pyrroles B and C. This is also reflected by PΦB1 and PΦB2 having very similar <IT>λ</IT><SB>max</SB> (0.01 eV difference for both <IT>Z</IT>,<IT>syn</IT> and <IT>E</IT>,<IT>anti</IT>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">As for the influence of the methyl groups (<IT>cf.</IT> PΦB1 and PΦB3), a somewhat larger effect is observed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Yet, the absolute mean-deviation between the two sets of bond lengths is fairly small (&lt;0.01 Å), as are the differences in <IT>λ</IT><SB>max</SB> between PΦB1 and PΦB3 (0.05 eV for both <IT>Z</IT>,<IT>syn</IT> and <IT>E</IT>,<IT>anti</IT>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Even though an absolute comparison of calculated <IT>λ</IT><SB>max</SB>, representing the absorption by the chromophore in the gas phase, with experimental spectra, representing the absorption of phytochrome <IT>in vitro</IT>, for obvious reasons cannot be made, it is encouraging to note that the maximum absorption of the <IT>E</IT>,<IT>anti</IT> configuration throughout is red-shifted relative to that of <IT>Z</IT>,<IT>syn</IT>, which is in accord with the maximum absorption of Pfr being bathochromically shifted relative to that of Pr.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">We furthermore note that the calculated red-shifts essentially remain unaltered (0.07, 0.07, 0.07, and 0.10 eV for PΦB1, PΦB2, PΦB3, and PΦB4, respectively) upon enlargement of the computational model, and that these are in reasonable agreement with the experimental value of 0.18 eV.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Table 1 also lists HF ground-state and CIS excited-state bond lengths for PΦB1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The observed shortening and lengthening (relative B3LYP) of nominal double and single bonds, respectively, is a well-known deficiency of HF when applied to conjugated systems.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">By comparing HF and CIS bond lengths, we see that the bond alternation is less pronounced in the S<SB>1</SB> state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is a consequence of this state originating from a one-electron HOMO → LUMO π−π* transition.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The most notable geometric feature of the S<SB>2</SB> state (in comparison with HF S<SB>0</SB>) is the inversion of the C13C14 and C14–C15 bonds lengths, which is a result of this state including contributions from two π−π* transitions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since CIS due to the inclusion of only singly excited configurations in general seriously overestimates excitation energies for states having pronounced double-excitation character (<IT>e.g.</IT>, the S<SB>2</SB> state of PΦB1), it should be stressed that the S<SB>2</SB> geometries likely are less accurate than the S<SB>1</SB> ones.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Even though the fact that TD-DFT in general offers a significant improvement over CIS in reproducing transition energies for low-lying valence-excited states<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit40 cit42">40,42</REF> – including to some extent also those having appreciable double-excitation character<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit43">43</REF> – motivates the construction of excited-state PES using CIS geometries and TD-DFT energies, it is nevertheless important to emphasize that the S<SB>2</SB> PES presented below should be regarded as preliminary.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The observation that no inversion of the C13C14 and C14–C15 bonds is displayed in the S<SB>2</SB> state of the <IT>E</IT>,<IT>anti</IT> configuration can probably be attributed to the aforementioned shortcoming associated with the CIS methodology.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="Old" advantage="None">By subjecting the optimized S<SB>1</SB> geometries of PΦB1 to TD-B3LYP/6-31G(d) single point calculations, wavelengths of maximum emission were obtained as well (Table 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Depending on phytochrome size, the maximum fluorescence of Pr <IT>in vitro</IT> is located in the 672–692 nm (1.79–1.85 eV) region,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF><IT>i.e.</IT>, 0.03–0.09 eV below the absorption maximum at 660 nm (1.88 eV).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Encouragingly enough, the calculated 0.09 eV Stokes shift (difference between vertical excitation and emission energies) for <IT>Z</IT>,<IT>syn</IT> PΦB1 accounts rather satisfactorily for this feature of the photochemistry of phytochrome.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results from the calculations investigating basis set effects on electronic energies of PΦB1 are given in Table 2 together with calculated ZPVE and thermal corrections.</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is seen that using a larger basis set than 6-31G(d) has only a minor (≤0.4 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>) effect on relative ground-state electronic energies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Increasing the basis set does not significantly alter vertical excitation energies either, which is in accordance with recent TD-DFT studies on the absorption of the highly conjugated astaxanthin chromophore.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit44 cit45">44,45</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">At the 6-311+G(d,p) basis set level, the S<SB>1</SB> and S<SB>2</SB> excitation energies are lowered by 0.04 and 0.02–0.03 eV, respectively, with respect to the 6-31G(d) values.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The relative insensitivity of vertical excitation energies to the inclusion of diffuse s and p-functions on heavy atoms reflects the ‘valence-excited state’ nature of S<SB>1</SB> and S<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Considering differences in vertical excitation energies between different configurations (of particular relevance for the present work), basis set effects on both states throughout do not exceed 0.01 eV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Turning to the results from the frequency calculations, we note that ZPVE corrections and <IT>G</IT><SB>corr</SB> for the optimized ground-state structures differ within 0.3 and 0.2 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>, respectively, between the different configurations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">As for the optimized excited-state structures, the dependence of ZPVE correction (within 0.5 (S<SB>1</SB>) and 0.2 (S<SB>2</SB>) kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>) and <IT>G</IT><SB>corr</SB> (within 1.2 (S<SB>1</SB>) and 0.6 (S<SB>2</SB>) kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>) on conformation is not pronounced either.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None">These results indicate that the energetics of the PΦB1 isomerization can be assessed on the basis of electronic energies only.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Even though the effects of neglecting ZPVE corrections and <IT>G</IT><SB>corr</SB> for the individual states of course may add up when the states are considered simultaneously, the conclusions to be drawn from the present work are based on electronic energy differences that, we believe, are sufficiently large to marginalize such effects.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">Vertical S<SB>1</SB> and S<SB>2</SB> excitation energies for PΦB1 in <IT>Z</IT>,<IT>syn</IT>, <IT>E</IT>,<IT>syn</IT>, <IT>Z</IT>,<IT>anti</IT>, and <IT>E</IT>,<IT>anti</IT> configurations were in addition computed at the CIS/6-31G(d)//HF/6-31G(d) level of theory.</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">For both states, which respectively have HOMO → LUMO and {HOMO − 1 → LUMO/HOMO → LUMO + 1} character within the framework of CIS as well, this yielded considerably higher transition energies than did the TD-B3LYP/6-31G(d)//B3LYP/6-31G(d) calculations (0.8 and 2.3 eV higher for S<SB>1</SB> and S<SB>2</SB>, respectively).</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None">This finding is in accord with previously reported calculations on the electronic spectra of hexamethylpyrromethene indicating that CIS grossly overestimates excitation energies for pyrrole compounds.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit33">33</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con15" novelty="None" advantage="None">In summary, the results reported in Table 1 suggest that the approximation imposed by not including the thioether linkage, the propionate side chains, and the methyl groups in the computational model is sound, and also that PΦB1 is a reasonable model in that the calculated absorption red-shift induced upon <IT>Z</IT>,<IT>syn</IT> → <IT>E</IT>,<IT>anti</IT> isomerization, as well as the calculated Stokes shift for the <IT>Z</IT>,<IT>syn</IT> configuration, agree rather well with the corresponding experimental shifts as obtained for phytochrome.</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results given in Table 2, in turn, suggest that using a larger basis set than 6-31G(d) for calculating electronic energies is superfluous, and that the accounting for ZPVE and thermal corrections can be omitted.</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Finally, it should be noted that our conclusion that the computational procedure is suitable for calculating the relevant isomerization PES of course is directly dependent on the validity of the benchmark calculations also for distorted phytochromobilins along the isomerization path.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>B. Potential energy surfaces</HEADER><P><s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None">In the first part of this section, we will report S<SB>0</SB> and S<SB>1</SB> PES for PΦB1, and thereby propose a mechanism for the <IT>Z</IT>,<IT>syn</IT> → <IT>E</IT>,<IT>anti</IT> isomerization involving these two states only.</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="New" advantage="None">In the second part, we will present different cuts of the S<SB>2</SB> PES constituting further support for such a two-state model.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The S<SB>0</SB> and S<SB>1</SB> PES, and their difference, are shown in Fig. 3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Considering first the S<SB>0</SB> PES, we note that thermal <IT>Z</IT> → <IT>E</IT> isomerization of both the <IT>Z</IT>,<IT>syn</IT> and the <IT>Z</IT>,<IT>anti</IT> configuration is prevented by a high-energy barrier (&gt;35 and &gt;32 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>, peaking at <IT>β</IT> = 75°), as expected.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The barriers for <IT>E</IT> → <IT>Z</IT> isomerization are of a similar magnitude (&gt;34 and &gt;32 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> for <IT>E</IT>,<IT>syn</IT> and <IT>E</IT>,<IT>anti</IT>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">We furthermore observe that light does not seem to be an absolute requirement for <IT>syn</IT> → <IT>anti</IT> isomerization <IT>as such</IT>, as indicated by a barrier of ∼8 and ∼9 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> (peaking at <IT>α</IT> = −90°) for thermal isomerization of the <IT>E</IT>,<IT>syn</IT> and <IT>Z</IT>,<IT>syn</IT> configuration, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The barriers for <IT>anti</IT> → <IT>syn</IT> isomerization are likewise low (∼7 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> for both <IT>E</IT>,<IT>anti</IT> and <IT>Z</IT>,<IT>anti</IT>).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Turning to the S<SB>1</SB> PES, we recall that, as outlined in Section I, the primary photochemical reaction in phytochrome in all likelihood involves a <IT>Z</IT> → <IT>E</IT> isomerization of the chromophore.</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Moreover, it has been argued that also the <IT>syn</IT> → <IT>anti</IT> isomerization is part of the primary photochemical reaction and that the two isomerizations occur simultaneously in a concerted fashion,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit22">5,22</REF> whereas others have suggested that <IT>syn</IT> → <IT>anti</IT> is initiated <IT>thermally</IT> upon completion of <IT>Z</IT> → <IT>E</IT>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19">19</REF> thus favouring a stepwise process.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hence, it is interesting to note that – while photochemical <IT>Z</IT> → <IT>E</IT> isomerization of the <IT>Z</IT>,<IT>syn</IT> configuration is associated with a flat energy profile (maximum at <IT>β</IT> = 135° lying ∼4 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> above <IT>Z</IT>,<IT>syn</IT>) and a subsequent energy minimum region (at <IT>β</IT> = 90° lying ∼7 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> below <IT>Z</IT>,<IT>syn</IT>) enabling the system to decay to the S<SB>0</SB> PES and evolve to <IT>E</IT>,<IT>syn</IT> – the reaction path corresponding to a concerted <IT>Z</IT>,<IT>syn</IT> → <IT>E</IT>,<IT>anti</IT> photoisomerization has an unfavourable energy profile.</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">For example, the central {<IT>α</IT> = −90°, <IT>β</IT> = 90°} structure, the 9 structures covering the {−105 ≤ <IT>α</IT> ≤ −75°, 75 ≤ <IT>β</IT> ≤ 105°} region, and the 25 structures covering the {−120 ≤ <IT>α</IT> ≤ −60°, 60 ≤ <IT>β</IT> ≤ 120°} region lie ∼30, ∼17–32, and ∼11–32 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> above <IT>Z</IT>,<IT>syn</IT>, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, no S<SB>1</SB> → S<SB>0</SB> decay channel seems to exist along this path (<IT>cf.</IT> Fig. 3, S<SB>1</SB>−S<SB>0</SB> PES).</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con18" novelty="None" advantage="None">These findings strongly suggest that the photoactivation of phytochrome is less likely mediated by a concerted <IT>Z</IT>,<IT>syn</IT> → <IT>E</IT>,<IT>anti</IT> photoisomerization than by a stepwise <IT>Z</IT> → <IT>E</IT>, <IT>syn</IT> → <IT>anti</IT> mechanism involving a photochemical <IT>Z</IT> → <IT>E</IT> isomerization (∼4 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> barrier) followed by a thermal <IT>syn</IT> → <IT>anti</IT> isomerization (∼8 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> barrier).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The S<SB>1</SB> PES also suggests that an alternative mechanism (that has not been discussed in the experimental literature) involving consecutive <IT>syn</IT> → <IT>anti</IT> and <IT>Z</IT> → <IT>E</IT> photoisomerizations could be energetically feasible.</annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con20" novelty="None" advantage="None">The estimated barriers for these isomerizations are ∼6 and ∼3 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>, respectively, which effectively means that the calculations do not unambiguously show that photochemical <IT>Z</IT> → <IT>E</IT> followed by thermal <IT>syn</IT> → <IT>anti</IT> is the most probable route to the activation of phytochrome.</annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con21" novelty="None" advantage="None">Nevertheless, of the scenarios actually discussed in the experimental literature,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit19 cit22">5,19,22</REF> the calculations clearly show that photochemical <IT>Z</IT> → <IT>E</IT> followed by thermal <IT>syn</IT> → <IT>anti</IT> is energetically preferable over a concerted <IT>Z</IT>,<IT>syn</IT> → <IT>E</IT>,<IT>anti</IT> photoisomerization.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The decay process by which the excited system returns to the ground state is a key mechanistic element of photochemical reactions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">By means of CASSCF calculations, it has been shown that the decay channel in a number of systems corresponds to a conical intersection of the ground and excited-state potential energy surfaces.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25 cit46 cit47">25,46,47</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con22" novelty="None" advantage="None">Given that single-reference DFT methods in general fail to explicitly locate conical intersections,<SUP TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn2" /> the possibility that the decay along the photochemical <IT>Z</IT>,<IT>syn</IT> → <IT>E</IT>,<IT>syn</IT> path is governed by an actual S<SB>0</SB>/S<SB>1</SB> crossing cannot be excluded.</annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con23" novelty="None" advantage="None">This uncertainty is however irrelevant for distinguishing <IT>Z</IT>,<IT>syn</IT> → <IT>E</IT>,<IT>syn</IT> from <IT>Z</IT>,<IT>syn</IT> → <IT>E</IT>,<IT>anti</IT> as the most probable photoisomerization pathway.</annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The S<SB>1</SB>−S<SB>0</SB> PES shows that the two states are the closest in energy at {<IT>α</IT> = 0°, <IT>β</IT> = 75°} (∼11 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> apart) and {<IT>α</IT> = −180°, <IT>β</IT> = 75°} (∼12 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> apart).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">It has been suggested that the primary photochemical reaction in phytochrome takes place within picoseconds.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10 cit48">10,48</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is slower than the photoisomerizations underlying the biological activity of the rhodopsin family of proteins, which take place in the sub-picosecond regime and hence are essentially barrierless.</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Still, the barrier for PΦB photoisomerization should be very low.</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con24" novelty="None" advantage="None">Even though the prediction that ∼4 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> are needed for excited <IT>Z</IT>,<IT>syn</IT> to reach the decay channel is compatible with an isomerization occurring within a photochemically reasonable period of time, it is clear that the calculations, due to, <IT>e.g.</IT>, neglected interactions with the surrounding protein and limited computational accuracy, overestimate the barrier for photoisomerization.</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con25" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, a more elaborate quantum chemical treatment would require the explicit localization of excited-state stationary points and minimum energy path calculations.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25 cit26 cit27">25–27</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to, in turn, put the prediction that ∼8 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> are required for thermal <IT>E</IT>,<IT>syn</IT> → <IT>E</IT>,<IT>anti</IT> isomerization into an experimental perspective, it can be noted that an overall energy barrier of 17–20 kJ/mol (∼4–5 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>) for Pr → Pfr conversion has been derived through the monitoring of changes in Pr fluorescence <IT>in vitro.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit49">49</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con26" novelty="None" advantage="None">Even though the calculations once again appear to provide an overestimation, we believe that – considering the various approximations employed – the fair agreement between theory and experiment is rather encouraging.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Finally, as for the S<SB>2</SB> PES, we note that while an equal number (99) of S<SB>1</SB> and S<SB>2</SB> geometry optimizations were initiated, roughly one third of the latter were not successfully completed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj5" novelty="New" advantage="None">However, we are here primarily interested in the shape of the S<SB>2</SB> PES along the <IT>Z</IT>,<IT>syn</IT> → <IT>E</IT>,<IT>syn</IT> isomerization coordinate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj5" novelty="New" advantage="None">Rather than presenting a S<SB>2</SB> PES covering a lesser range than S<SB>1</SB>, we therefore focus our attention on the <IT>Z</IT>,<IT>syn</IT> → <IT>E</IT>,<IT>syn</IT> cut of S<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj5" novelty="New" advantage="None">This particular cut, as well as that along the <IT>Z</IT>,<IT>anti</IT> → <IT>E</IT>,<IT>anti</IT> coordinate, is shown in Fig. 4 together with the corresponding cuts of S<SB>1</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">We note that there are no signs of an S<SB>2</SB>/S<SB>1</SB> avoided crossing along the <IT>Z</IT>,<IT>syn</IT> → <IT>E</IT>,<IT>syn</IT> isomerization coordinate, as evidenced by the facts that the S<SB>2</SB>–S<SB>1</SB> energy gap increases (from ∼11 to ∼36 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> at <IT>β</IT> = 90°) as the system evolves towards the decay channel, and that the S<SB>2</SB> state throughout retains its character.</annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">The same features are observed along the <IT>Z</IT>,<IT>anti</IT> → <IT>E</IT>,<IT>anti</IT> coordinate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con27" novelty="None" advantage="None">These results indicate that the two-electronic state model involving only S<SB>0</SB> and S<SB>1</SB> previously assigned to, <IT>e.g.</IT>, the retinal photoisomerization in rhodopsins<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25 cit26 cit27">25–27</REF> is applicable to the PΦB photoisomerization in phytochrome as well.</annotationART></s> <s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con28" novelty="None" advantage="None">As emphasized in Section IIIA, the S<SB>2</SB> PES may be qualitatively incorrect due to the inadequacy of CIS in treating the PΦB S<SB>2</SB> state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con29" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, the proposed two-state model for PΦB photoisomerization should be regarded as a tentative model, rather than as a rigorously derived one.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="IV.">Conclusions</HEADER><P><s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="New" advantage="None">In order to gain some insight into the intrinsic mechanism governing the PΦB C15-<IT>Z</IT>,<IT>syn</IT> → C15-<IT>E</IT>,<IT>anti</IT> isomerization responsible for the photoactivation of phytochrome, we have in the present study subjected a simplified PΦB model to quantum chemical calculations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con30" novelty="None" advantage="None">By computing ground and excited-state PES for rotations around the C14–C15 and C15C16 bonds, it is found that a stepwise <IT>Z</IT> → <IT>E</IT>, <IT>syn</IT> → <IT>anti</IT> mechanism is energetically much more favourable than a concerted <IT>Z</IT>,<IT>syn</IT> → <IT>E</IT>,<IT>anti</IT> process.</annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con31" novelty="None" advantage="None">More specifically, on the basis of the calculated PES and in light of experimental observations,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19">19</REF> it is suggested that the primary photochemical reaction involves a <IT>Z</IT> → <IT>E</IT> isomerization only, and that the subsequent <IT>syn</IT> → <IT>anti</IT> isomerization occurs thermally.</annotationART></s> <s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con32" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, it is proposed that the <IT>Z</IT> → <IT>E</IT> isomerization proceeds solely through interactions between the S<SB>0</SB> and S<SB>1</SB> electronic states.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con33" novelty="None" advantage="None">While the elucidation of the intrinsic isomerization mechanism for an isolated chromophore in the gas-phase constitutes a natural first goal for quantum chemical studies, the ultimate goal is to be able to consider also (some of) the interactions with the surrounding protein.</annotationART></s> <s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con33" novelty="None" advantage="None">Of particular interest are then the molecular mechanisms responsible for the lowering of energy barriers, and whether the protein favours another reaction pathway than that proposed in this work.</annotationART></s> <s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con34" novelty="None" advantage="None">Future X-ray crystallographic structures of phytochrome will facilitate such studies.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
