<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b412680g" hasDoc="yes" version="1184" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Measurement of diffusion in Langmuir monolayers by single-particle tracking<XREF TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" /></annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">There is a great amount of literature available indicating that membranes are inhomogeneous, complex fluids.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">For instance, observation of diffusion in cell membranes demonstrated confined motion of membrane constituents and even subdiffusion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">In order to circumvent the small dimensions of cells leading to weak statistics when investigating the diffusion properties of single membrane components, a technique based on optical microscopy employing Langmuir monolayers as membrane model systems has been developed in our lab.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In earlier work, the motion of labeled single lipids was visualized.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="New" advantage="None">These measurements with long observation times, thus far only possible with this method, were combined with respective Monte-Carlo simulations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">We could conclude that noise can lead in general to the assumption of subdiffusion while interpreting the results of single-particle-tracking (SPT) experiments within membranes in general.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">Since the packing density of lipids within monolayers at the air/water interface can be changed easily, inhomogeneity with regard to the phase state can be achieved by isothermal compression to coexistence regions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Surface charged polystyrene latexes were used as model proteins diffusing in inhomogeneous monolayers as biomembrane mimics.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Epifluorescence microscopy coupled to SPT revealed that domain associated, dimensionally reduced diffusion can occur in these kinds of model systems.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">This was caused by an attractive potential generated by condensed domains within monolayers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Monte-Carlo simulations supported this view point.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Moreover, long-time simulations show that diffusion coefficients of respective particles were dependent on the strength of the attractive potential present: a behavior reflecting altered dimensionality of diffusion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The widths of those potentials were also found to be affected by the domain size of the more ordered lipid phase.</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In biological membrane systems, cells could utilize these physical mechanisms to adjust diffusion properties of membrane components.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="1.">Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Lateral transport plays a key role in biological processes such as, <IT>e.g.</IT> cellular signal transduction within the cell membrane and membrane formation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The transport of a signal mediated by components of a membrane can occur through lateral diffusion.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Reactions dependent on diffusion may proceed faster in the two dimensions of the membrane than in the three dimensions of the cytoplasm.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">2</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The two-dimensional liquid-crystalline membranes generally consist in a diverse amphiphilic lipid bilayer where proteins are differently integrated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Membranes seem to be relatively homogenous systems where lateral diffusion could be described easily.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, it was found that the cell membrane is inhomogeneous over different time and length scales.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Inhomogeneity was experimentally shown for the two main classes of membrane components, both for lipids and for proteins, by demonstration of restricted mobility.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The motion of proteins can be confined to regions of 100 nm to 1 μm size for a time from 3–35 s.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The actual size of these confinements for the lateral protein motion seems to be dependent on the cell type investigated.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit5 cit6 cit7 cit8">4–8</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Using optical tweezers, barrier free lengths for proteins of 1–10 μm were found.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Lipid diffusion within a membrane can be confined for times of less than a second to regions of 250–750 nm size within the cell membrane.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10 cit11">10,11</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, free diffusion was observed for lipids within a membrane, too.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, the diffusive speed of integral proteins in biological membranes is decreased by one order of magnitude up to immobility compared to the less complex model membranes.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Disturbing interactions of diffusing proteins with other structures within the membrane, <IT>e.g.</IT> with the membrane-associated cytoskeleton or ordered lipid domains, are supposed to be the reasons for this behavior.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7 cit14 cit15">7,14,15</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Membrane components coming into question as potential obstructions can be arranged according to their size.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Proteins (25–75% of membrane mass<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF>) can be considered as a first category of obstacles on a length scale of few nanometers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">As a second category, proteins with condensed lipid shells of a 10 nm diameter come into play.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Lipid rafts, as a potential third category, presumably have a size of 25–300 nm and represent mobile lipid organizations which differ with respect to their composition from their environment.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10 cit14 cit18 cit19 cit20 cit21">10,14,18–21</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">There are numerous indications that lipid rafts might play also a central role in diseases as, <IT>e.g.</IT> virus infections, Alzheimer and prion diseases.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Nevertheless, thus far these ordered domains could not be directly observed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Their occurrence was merely indirectly deducted, <IT>e.g.</IT>, from protein-clustering experiments.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hence, the biological membrane is currently considered to be an inhomogeneous fluid with structures on length scales of 1 nm to 10 μm which affect the lateral diffusion.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Diffusion of a laterally moving particle within the membrane can be described by the temporal scaling behavior of the mean square displacement (MSD) in dependence on the time Δ<IT>t</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF>〈<B><IT>r</IT></B><SP>2</SP>〉 = MSD(Δ<IT>t</IT>) = 4<IT>D</IT>Δ<IT>t</IT><SP><IT>α</IT></SP>where <B><IT>r</IT></B>(<IT>t</IT>) is the particle position at the time <IT>t</IT>, <IT>D</IT> the diffusion coefficient and <IT>α</IT> the scaling exponent.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">For normal Brownian diffusion, the exponent <IT>α</IT> remains 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Subdiffusive processes exhibit <IT>α</IT> &lt; 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Anomalous, non-Brownian diffusion was reported for different membrane components.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">For proteins in the plasma membrane, exponents in the range of <IT>α</IT> = 0.1–0.9 were found.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit24 cit25">5,24,25</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, evidence for the occurrence of subdiffusion by single-particle-tracking methods is often based on short trajectories where the scaling arguments can be inaccurate.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to understand the results on membrane diffusion experiments, computer simulation methods were developed and performed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Molecular dynamics calculations of the interactions of proteins, lipids and water molecules were carried out but the corresponding length scale is limited to very short distances (∼1 nm).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26">26</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The diffusion constants obtained (1–10 μm<SP>2</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>) agree with those from spectroscopic measurements.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Monte Carlo methods can give results regarding diffusion on length scales which correspond to those of fluorescence recovery after photobleaching (FRAP) and SPT data (in the range of 10<SP>−9</SP>–10<SP>−6</SP> m).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27 cit28 cit29 cit30">27–30</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Results of these simulations show, <IT>e.g.</IT> that a 10- to 100-fold decrease of the diffusion coefficient can arise from protein concentrations close to the percolation threshold.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">At protein concentration above the percolation threshold, only confined diffusion is found.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The former appears at long times normal whereas it may appear at short times as anomalous.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29">29</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The implementation of particle traps made the simulation of anomalous diffusion possible.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit31">31</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Increasing interest in understanding the basis of lipid and protein diffusion led to the development of various experimental models of the cell membrane, <IT>e.g.</IT> lipid vesicles with incorporated proteins,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit32">32</REF> planar supported bilayers,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit33">33</REF> with one or more membrane double layers on solid supports which were used for lipid and protein diffusion measurements.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit34 cit35">34,35</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Within the scope of earlier studies homogeneous one-component systems were investigated.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit36">36</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Later, full membrane extracts<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit37">37</REF> or multi-component systems in which phase separated lipids form obstructions for diffusion were studied.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit38">38</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Currently, the lipid raft mixtures have been frequently investigated by different methods.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit39">8,39</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Monolayers at the air/water interface have a critical advantage over cells and lipid vesicles regarding the investigation of diffusion by SPT techniques.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is the large observable area leading to long observation times.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Moreover, the packing density of a monolayer at the air/water interface can be conveniently varied at a constant temperature which is not possible for supported bilayers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">In Langmuir monolayers, a broad variable range of length scales within inhomogeneous structures is accessible.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the phase coexistence region <IT>e.g.</IT> in the liquid-expanded/liquid-condensed coexistence, inhomogeneities are characteristic and the size of occurring domains can be varied by altering the lateral pressure.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In the following section, recent achievements in developing the method of SPT on Langmuir monolayers are briefly summarized.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">To verify our experimental approach, at first the diffusion of lipids within homogeneous monolayers was studied.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">In a second step, the motion of carboxylated polystyrene beads within inhomogeneous monolayers was examined.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">This system mimics the interaction between negatively charged proteins and condensed membrane domains.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Already published features of these experimental models are reported concisely in the following.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The methods used for experiments and simulations of the model are described in Section 3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">New results on these models and interpretations are presented and discussed in significant extracts in Section 4.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.">Single-particle-tracking on monolayers</HEADER><P><s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In our lab, a technique was established enabling single-particle-tracking (SPT) experiments in monolayers at the air/water-interface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In order to obtain a highly unperturbed monolayer, air flow, convection in the subphase and vibrations of the system had to be minimized.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">For this purpose, a Langmuir film balance system was designed and built that reduces these effects by isolation of the liquid surface from the lab environment.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Tracking of the motion of a scattering gold nano particle bound to a single lipid molecule within a monolayer at the air/water interface over long time intervals by means of dark field microscopy was demonstrated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">DMPC monolayers were used which form homogeneous phases under standard conditions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit40">40</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">For this system, only normal diffusion can be expected according to the free-volume model for diffusion.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit41">41</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Pictures were recorded by use of an appropriate video microscopy system with a time resolution of 30 s<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Observation times for the tracking experiments ranged up to about 150 s.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The particle position per frame was determined applying modified IDL routines.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit42">42</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Due to the specific set-up, drift speed of the monolayer was reduced to &lt;1 μm s<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Nevertheless, for the calculation of the MSD due to pure diffusive motion the relative motion of two neighboring particles with position <B><IT>a</IT></B> and <B><IT>b</IT></B> was utilized.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="Old" advantage="None">For calculation of the MSD of the relative motion, the following relation was used<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit43">43</REF>where <B><IT>r</IT></B>(<IT>t</IT>) is the position of the particle at time <IT>t</IT>, δ<IT>t</IT> is the time between frames (successive images), Δ<IT>t</IT> is the time lag separating the locations such that <IT>n</IT>δ<IT>t</IT> = Δ<IT>t</IT>, with <IT>n</IT> the number of frames separating the locations, and <IT>N</IT> is the total number of steps in the trajectory.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">It was demonstrated that the measured diffusive speed of the lipid was independent on the size of the gold particle.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The scaling exponent was obtained by a linear fit of log(MSD) <IT>vs.</IT> log(Δ<IT>t</IT>) (<IT>cf.</IT> eqn. (3), below).</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">For DMPC at the air/water interface and different packing densities normal diffusion was found.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The diffusion coefficients were obtained by a linear fit of the data to eqn. (1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The diffusion coefficient <IT>D</IT> = (1.1 ± 0.2) μm<SP>2</SP> s<SP>−1</SP> was in good agreement with the results from other measurements obtained by ensemble methods, <IT>e.g.</IT> FRAP.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit44">44</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Further details are given in the respective previously published manuscript.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit43">43</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="Old" advantage="None">According to eqn. (1), the standard method to find the scaling exponent is a linear fit to:log(MSD(Δ<IT>t</IT>)) = <IT>α</IT> log(Δ<IT>t</IT>) + log(4<IT>D</IT>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Indications for the occurrence of subdiffusion were apparently found in the experiments with DMPC monolayers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since subdiffusion can be excluded for such a homogeneous system, an artifact due to basic problems of the data analysis had to be to considered.</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Correlation with noise inherent to all SPT measurements was initially noted.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit43">43</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The position of the particle was determined with a precision of 100 nm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The tracking routine employed finds the center of the particle using a weighted average of pixel intensities, taking the center of this average as the particle position.</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The position can be shifted by overlapping noise leading to an error in the particle position.</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Assuming a mean error of the particle position <IT>σ</IT>, the MSD is dependent on this noise:MSD = 4<IT>D</IT>Δ<IT>t</IT> + 2<IT>σ</IT><SP>2</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">To find the diffusion coefficient for Brownian motion, the linear plot gives <IT>D</IT> as the slope and 2<IT>σ</IT><SP>2</SP> as the intercept.</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The analysis of the logarithmic plot of the MSD which is used to determine whether a particle behaves subdiffusively is more complex since noise generates an initial slope resulting in an apparent scaling coefficient, <IT>α</IT><SB>app</SB> which might by expressed by</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In Fig. 1, a logarithmic plot of Brownian motion with an underlying diffusion coefficient of <IT>D</IT> = 1 μm<SP>2</SP> s<SP>−1</SP> and a varied positional error is displayed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Due to the logarithmic scale, noise appears large at short times whereas at long times the real character of the motion (normal diffusion) becomes obvious.</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Deviations from the noise-free behavior are significantly visible at short times.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">This observation was also supported by Monte Carlo simulations on comparable time scales.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="New" advantage="None">Random walks were used to simulate recorded measurements.</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Particle and noise intensity distributions were assumed to be Gaussian profiles according to experimental findings.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met14" novelty="New" advantage="None">The error of the position was determined by comparison of the underlying random walk and the trajectories yielded by the tracking routine.</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">A constant error was obtained which is dependent on the signal-to-noise ratio, the particle width and the tracking method.</annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the light of these findings, experimental results indicating subdiffusion on cell surfaces have to be re-evaluated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">It was concluded that a high fraction of these previously published data<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6 cit10">5,6,10</REF> can be explained by the interplay of normal diffusion and camera noise.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">In summary, long experimental observation times compared to those possible for SPT studies of the cell surface enabled us to demonstrate that (camera) noise can lead to the assumption of subdiffusion while interpreting the data of single-particle-tracking experiments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">More details are available in Martin <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30">30</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Direct observation of the effect of membrane inhomogeneities on diffusion of polystyrene beads within the model membranes was achieved by utilization of an experimental setup where dual band fluorescence microscopy was coupled to SPT (for details, <IT>cf.</IT> Forstner <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit45">45</REF>. and Section 3 of this paper).</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">A single trough for spreading the monolayer, compression and observation was used.</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met15" novelty="New" advantage="None">Two compartments were integrated for surface tension measurement and for observation of the monolayers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met15" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">This allowed us variation of the lateral pressure during observation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">In a first series of experiments, DMPE (1,2-dimyristoyl <IT>sn</IT>-glycerophosphoethanolamine) monolayers<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit46">46</REF> were spread on a physiological subphase (phosphate buffered saline, <IT>cf.</IT> Section 3).</annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The liquid expanded (LE) phase was visualized by fluorescently labeled lipids which partitionate preferably into this phase.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit47">47</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fluorescently labeled carboxylated polystyrene latexes mimicking negatively charged proteins (diameter 100 and 200 nm) were added to the subphase and were found to be localized at the air/water interface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The diffusion of the beads within the liquid-expanded (LE) lipid monolayer phase was observed for long time scales.</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Observation times of up to 20 min were achieved due to the relatively rigid properties of the DMPE liquid-condensed (LC) phase.</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Free and strikingly confined diffusion to the domain-edge were demonstrated in the LE phase.</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Domain-edge associated diffusion can be ascribed to an interaction between charged beads and domains.</annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Only normal Brownian diffusion has been found as determined from the scaling exponent which was <IT>α</IT> = 0.95 ± 0.05 for both free and domain-edge associated diffusion.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None">In the following sections, further measurements on bead diffusion in inhomogeneous membranes characterized in another inhomogeneous monolayer system are presented.</annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="New" advantage="None">The strength and the origin of the interaction between beads and domains is analyzed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Simulations were performed to support the interpretation of the experimental findings.</annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj5" novelty="New" advantage="None">Possible consequences for cellular membranes due to the mechanisms found are also discussed.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.">Materials and methods</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.1.">Materials</HEADER><P><s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp12" novelty="None" advantage="None">DMPE was purchased from Avanti Polar Lipids (Alabaster, Al, USA), methyl palmitate was from Fluka (Buchs, Switzerland).</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Salts for the subphase buffer, sodium chloride, monobasic and dibasic sodium phosphate were from Sigma-Aldrich Co. (Steinheim, Germany and St Lois, MO, USA) and of analytical grade.</annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Carboxylated fluorescent microspheres (FluoSpheres, yellow-green fluorescent (505/515), 200 nm diameter, were purchased from Molecular Probes Co. (Leiden, Netherlands)).</annotationART></s> <s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp15" novelty="None" advantage="None">According to the manufacturer, the surface charge was 0.073 milli-equivalent per gram (data sheet).</annotationART></s> <s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp16" novelty="None" advantage="None">All chemicals were used without further purification.</annotationART></s> <s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp17" novelty="None" advantage="None">For filtration of subphase solution, Anotop 25 0.2 μm filters were utilized.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.2.">Sample preparation</HEADER><P><s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Langmuir trough already mentioned in Section 2<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit45">45</REF> was covered by a steel lid with appropriate holes allowing for microscopical observation and measurement of the surface tension.</annotationART></s> <s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Holes in the lid were sealed against air flow, <IT>e.g.</IT> by a respective ring around the microscope objective and a dome over the Wilhelmy sensor system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp20" novelty="None" advantage="None">Within the trough, smaller observation and surface tension measurement areas were partially separated from the main part of the respective liquid surface by compartments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp21" novelty="None" advantage="None">As a subphase, about 100 ml of potassium-free phosphate buffered saline at pH = 7.5 (PBS, 50 mM NaCl, 50 mM phosphate, ionic strength, <IT>I</IT>, at 20 °C = 0.189 mol l<SP>−1</SP>) was prepared using Millipore water.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met16" novelty="New" advantage="None">The diluted aqueous suspension of microspheres was prepared for SPT experiments according to the following procedure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp22" novelty="None" advantage="None">20 μl of the microsphere suspension as obtained by the manufacturer were diluted in 40 ml of 100 mM PBS buffer, briefly vortexed and then centrifuged at 100 000 <IT>g</IT> for 5 min to ensure the sedimentation of bead conglomerates.</annotationART></s> <s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp23" novelty="None" advantage="None">20 ml of the supernatant were transferred into smaller (10 ml) glass bottles.</annotationART></s> <s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp24" novelty="None" advantage="None">Before each individual experiment, the bead suspension was briefly sonicated (&lt;60 s), to loosen possible weak conglomerates.</annotationART></s> <s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp25" novelty="None" advantage="None">35 μl of the diluted suspension were added to the subphase in the Langmuir trough.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp26" novelty="None" advantage="None">Consequentially, monolayers were prepared on the subphase as follows: The lipids (DMPE or methyl palmitate) were dissolved in chloroform (concentration ∼0.5 mM) and the resulting solution was then mixed with approx. 0.5–1% (related to DMPE or methyl palmitate concentration) of Texas-Red labeled DPPE (dihexadecanoyl phosphatidylethanolamine) from Molecular Probes (Leiden, Netherlands).</annotationART></s> <s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp27" novelty="None" advantage="None">This solution was spread on the aqueous surface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp28" novelty="None" advantage="None">The surface drift of the monolayers was reduced to 3–1 μm s<SP>−1</SP> depending on the phase state of the monolayer allowing for track lengths up to 20 000 to 35 000 steps.</annotationART></s> <s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp29" novelty="None" advantage="None">All measurements were performed at room temperature (<IT>ϑ</IT> ≈ 22 °C).</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.3.">Video microscopy</HEADER><P><s sid="143"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp30" novelty="None" advantage="None">The lipid monolayer and the fluorescent polysterol latex particles were visualized using an epi-fluorescence microscope (Olympus BX30M, Leeds Instruments Inc, USA) equipped with an Olympus 50 × 0.8 NA darkfield objective, a 100 W Hg-high pressure bulb (Osram HBO 103W/2) and a dual-band filter (51006 FITC/TR Chroma, Brattleboro, VT, USA).</annotationART></s> <s sid="144"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp31" novelty="None" advantage="None">Images were recorded by a SIT (Silicon Intensified Tube) Dage-MTI VE 1000 camera (Michigan City, IN, USA,) in PAL or NTSC mode (25 or 30 frames per second, respectively).</annotationART></s> <s sid="145"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp32" novelty="None" advantage="None">Data were transfered <IT>via</IT> a frame grabber card (Ni-Daq) connected to a suitable PC system.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.4.">Data analysis</HEADER><P><s sid="146"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp33" novelty="None" advantage="None">The video files (binary data) were analyzed using a tracking routine in IDL<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit48">48</REF> adopted for our system.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit43">43</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="147"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met17" novelty="New" advantage="None">A Gaussian fit of the pixel intensity was calculated.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit49">49</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="148"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met18" novelty="New" advantage="None">Other minor modifications of the programs were necessary to change from the NTSC to the PAL system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="149"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp34" novelty="None" advantage="None">Up to 50 particles were tracked at once with an estimated spatial accuracy of 100 nm.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30 cit43">30,43</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="150"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met19" novelty="New" advantage="None">The diffusion coefficients were obtained from a linear fit, the time exponents from logarithmic fits of different data evaluation programs (<IT>cf.</IT> Sections 1 and 2).</annotationART></s> <s sid="151"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp35" novelty="None" advantage="None">The length of the tracks was up to 30 min.</annotationART></s> <s sid="152"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met20" novelty="New" advantage="None">Immobile fluorescent microspheres within the LC phase (mainly nucleation seeds) were used to determine the collective drift of the surface, which was subtracted from trajectories of diffusing particles.</annotationART></s> <s sid="153"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met20" novelty="New" advantage="None">(<IT>cf</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit43">ref. 43</REF>., and this paper, Section 2).</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.5.">Simulations of random walks</HEADER><P><s sid="154"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met21" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Simulations of random walks can be performed applying pure obstructions in form of LC domains.</annotationART></s> <s sid="155"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met22" novelty="New" advantage="None">In this study, random walks were generated with fixed time steps to represent particle trajectories.</annotationART></s> <s sid="156"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met23" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Following the method described by Saxton,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28">28</REF> a probability distribution for the step size <B><IT>r</IT></B> was used.with δ<IT>t</IT> as the time between two steps, which equals 1/25 s due to the camera frame rate used in the experiments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="157"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met23" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The distribution is inverted to calculate the step size on a uniform random variable [0,1] and the direction is picked randomly from [0,2π].<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28">28</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="158"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met23" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In this fashion, a random walk with a diffusion coefficient <IT>D</IT> is obtained.</annotationART></s> <s sid="159"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met23" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In the random walks, generally a diffusion coefficient of 1 μm<SP>2</SP> s<SP>−1</SP> was applied.</annotationART></s> <s sid="160"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The simulation of motion within obstacles is obtained by a simple model for particle domain edge interaction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="161"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Particles bounce off the domain edge, the angle of incidence equals the angle of reflection.</annotationART></s> <s sid="162"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, when the particle is crossing the domain interface, the particle is reflected, traveling back into the fluid region.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="163"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met24" novelty="New" advantage="None">Additionally, the effect an interaction potential was added<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit50">50</REF> in order to include interactions between beads and domains.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="164"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">For a given energy profile <IT>U</IT>(<B><IT>r</IT></B>), the force on the particle <B><IT>F</IT></B>, the velocity of the particle <B><IT>v</IT></B>, and displacement of the particle Δ<B><IT>r</IT></B> are calculated from eqns. (7), (8) and (9).</annotationART></s></P><s sid="165"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None"><B><IT>F</IT></B>(<B><IT>r</IT></B>) = −d<IT>U</IT>(<B><IT>r</IT></B>)/d<B><IT>r</IT></B><B><IT>v</IT></B> = <B><IT>F</IT></B>/<IT>ξ</IT>Δ<B><IT>r</IT></B> = <B><IT>v</IT></B>δ<IT>t</IT></annotationART></s><P><s sid="166"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Here, <IT>ξ</IT> is the friction coefficient of the particle.</annotationART></s> <s sid="167"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In each step of the simulation the particle is displaced by Δ<B><IT>r</IT></B> with regard to the domain boundary.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="168"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met25" novelty="Old" advantage="None">For a linear relation of <B><IT>F</IT></B>(Δ<B><IT>r</IT></B>), the displacement Δ<B><IT>r</IT></B> can be calculated from the mean force acting on the particle, <IT>i.e.</IT> from the force at the midpoint of the step.</annotationART></s> <s sid="169"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met25" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The steptime Δ<IT>t</IT> was chosen such that the actual change in <B><IT>F</IT></B> was not more than 2% from a linear relation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="170"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met25" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In the neighborhood of the domain where a rapid change of <IT>U</IT>(<B><IT>r</IT></B>) occurs (<IT>cf.</IT> Fig. 2, Sections 4.2 and 4.3) time steps as small as 10<SP>−9</SP> s were necessary.</annotationART></s> <s sid="171"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met26" novelty="New" advantage="None">The random walk was then resampled at the experimental video rate.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="172"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met27" novelty="New" advantage="None">For simulating diffusion of particles within a liquid-expanded phase with liquid-expanded domains, a lattice of solid domains was used.</annotationART></s> <s sid="173"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac20" novelty="None" advantage="None">The basic tile is a fluid square with a circular solid circle in the center.</annotationART></s> <s sid="174"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac20" novelty="None" advantage="None">At an obstacle concentration of 12.5% (circular domains in 4 μm diameter separated by 10 μm) the diffusion of the particles is unchanged from free diffusion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="175"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac20" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the latter, the only interaction between probe particle and domain is reflection.</annotationART></s> <s sid="176"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">This was controlled by evaluation of trajectories with and without obstruction; no difference of diffusion coefficients was found.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.">Results and discussion</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.1.">Characteristics of bead diffusion in inhomogeneous membranes</HEADER><P><s sid="177"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met28" novelty="New" advantage="None">Single-particle tracking experiments were performed with polystyrene beads which are negatively charged due to dissociation of carboxyl groups exposed to the aqueous subphase.</annotationART></s> <s sid="178"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met28" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">This mimics the motion of associated proteins in a membrane.</annotationART></s> <s sid="179"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met29" novelty="New" advantage="None">The bead motion within the monolayers was followed by video microscopy as described above.</annotationART></s> <s sid="180"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met30" novelty="New" advantage="None">In order to generalize the nature of the model membrane, in a second series of experiments methyl palmitate was applied forming monolayers which are not charged due to the respective molecular structure.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="181"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although two structurally different lipid species, DMPE and methyl palmitate, were studied very similar results were obtained.</annotationART></s> <s sid="182"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, the results are presented and discussed together.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="183"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met31" novelty="New" advantage="None">Phase coexistence of liquid-expanded and liquid-condensed phases was generated by adjustment of the lateral pressure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="184"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp36" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is approximately the case at lateral pressures <IT>π</IT> &gt; 10 mN m<SP>−1</SP> and <IT>π</IT> &gt; 1 mN m<SP>−1</SP> for DMPE and methyl palmitate, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="185"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the polystyrene beads investigated in inhomogeneous monolayers under the experimental conditions, free and domain-edge associated diffusion was observed for both within DMPE<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit45">45</REF> and methyl palmitate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="186"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The bead motion close to the LC phase is illustrated in Fig. 2A, where the respective superimposed trajectory of a bead diffusing within LE phase and the inhomogeneous monolayer region under observation are shown.</annotationART></s> <s sid="187"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None">This behavior seems to be generally observed for these kinds of model systems.</annotationART></s> <s sid="188"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">As observed for DMPE<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit45">45</REF>, within the methyl palmitate monolayers only normal diffusion was found and as can be seen by the value of the scaling exponent <IT>α</IT> = 0.99 ± 0.24.</annotationART></s> <s sid="189"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results for <IT>α</IT> derived from individual experimental trajectories for particles within inhomogeneous methyl palmitate monolayers are summarized by the presentation in Fig. 3.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="190"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">For beads displaying diffusion confined to the domain boundary, reduced diffusion coefficients were found when compared to free diffusion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="191"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">For free diffusion (no interaction with the domain recognized) diffusion coefficients of 0.75 ± 0.10 μm<SP>2</SP> s<SP>−1</SP> and 1.31 ± 0.30 μm<SP>2</SP> s<SP>−1</SP> were obtained for DMPE and methyl palmitate, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="192"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">For domain-edge associated diffusion the respective values are 0.38 ± 0.05 μm<SP>2</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>, and 0.41 ± 0.12 μm<SP>2</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="193"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The diffusion coefficient measured for domain-associated bead motion is about one half of the diffusion coefficient of a freely in the monolayer diffusing particle.</annotationART></s> <s sid="194"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">A transition between two dimensional and one dimensional diffusion explains this since the relations MSD = 4<IT>D</IT>Δ<IT>t</IT> and MSD = 2<IT>D</IT>Δ<IT>t</IT> are valid for two-dimensional and for one-dimensional Brownian diffusion, respectively.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="195"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, particles which diffuse only in “one” dimension, <IT>i.e.</IT> along a line (<IT>i.e.</IT> the border of the domain), have a diffusion coefficient only half as large as freely diffusing particles in two dimensions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="196"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Further reduction of the coefficient might be explained by additional friction occuring during the movement along the domain border.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.2.">The interaction potential between beads and LC domains</HEADER><P><s sid="197"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The domain-associated diffusion shown in Fig. 2A for the methyl palmitate model system is apparently due to an attractive interaction between domains and charged beads.</annotationART></s> <s sid="198"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met32" novelty="New" advantage="None">A quantitative method to determine an interaction potential <IT>U</IT>(<B><IT>r</IT></B>) is based on the particle density <IT>ρ</IT>(<B><IT>r</IT></B>) as a function of the distance from the domain edge <B><IT>r</IT></B>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="199"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met32" novelty="New" advantage="None">In other words, <IT>ρ</IT>(<B><IT>r</IT></B>) is the amount of times a specific distance range [(<B><IT>r</IT></B> − Δ<B><IT>r</IT></B>), (<B><IT>r</IT></B> + Δ<B><IT>r</IT></B>)] from a condensed domain was visited during a track.</annotationART></s> <s sid="200"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met32" novelty="New" advantage="None">The size of Δ<B><IT>r</IT></B> was chosen to values equaling half of the bead diameter.</annotationART></s> <s sid="201"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Simulated random walks (<IT>cf.</IT> Section 3) indicated that a higher/lower Δ<B><IT>r</IT></B> is not feasible.</annotationART></s> <s sid="202"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met32" novelty="New" advantage="None">Assuming that the point density follows a Boltzmann distribution<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit51">51</REF> one can obtain <IT>U</IT>(<B><IT>r</IT></B>) from <IT>ρ</IT>(<B><IT>r</IT></B>), according to<IT>U</IT>(<B><IT>r</IT></B>) = −<IT>k</IT><SB>B</SB><IT>T</IT> log(<IT>ρ</IT>(<B><IT>r</IT></B>)) + <IT>C</IT>where the absolute energy can be set by choosing <IT>C</IT>. In order to calculate <IT>ρ</IT>(<B><IT>r</IT></B>), the amount of times the particle visited area units normalized to equal probabilities of being for the diffusing particle was determined.</annotationART></s> <s sid="203"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">An example for such an evaluation is given in Fig. 2B which corresponds to the diffusion experiment visualized in Fig. 2A.</annotationART></s> <s sid="204"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this experiment, a polystyrene bead within the LE phase close to a LC phase of a methyl palmitate monolayer clearly demonstrates domain-associated motion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="205"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The area close to the interface is obviously more frequently visited during the obversation time.</annotationART></s> <s sid="206"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met32" novelty="New" advantage="None">The density <IT>ρ</IT>(<B><IT>r</IT></B>) was calculated and the depth of the attractive potential <IT>U</IT>(<B><IT>r</IT></B>) was obtained setting the constant C so that <IT>U</IT>(<B><IT>r</IT></B>) converges to zero at large distances as depicted in Fig. 2B.</annotationART></s> <s sid="207"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met32" novelty="New" advantage="None">The maximal depth at a distance of 100 nm from the domain, corresponding to the polystyrene bead radius, was determined to <IT>U</IT> ≈ −4.6<IT>k</IT><SB>B</SB><IT>T</IT> by fitting the data using a dependence of <IT>U</IT>(<B><IT>r</IT></B>) ∼ 1/|<B><IT>r</IT></B>|.</annotationART></s> <s sid="208"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The attractive potentials between LC domains and polystyrene beads obtained by this evaluation method had a depth of −4.5 ± 1.0 <IT>k</IT><SB>B</SB><IT>T</IT> and −6.0 ± 2.0 <IT>k</IT><SB>B</SB><IT>T</IT> for DMPE and for methyl palmitate monolayers, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="209"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The variation of the attractive potentials calculated from our data of bead motion in DMPE monolayers is exemplarily illustrated in Fig. 4.</annotationART></s> <s sid="210"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac21" novelty="None" advantage="None">The experimental results of the DMPE system and the evaluation method are discussed in greater detail in a separate contribution<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit52">52</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.3.">Range of the attractive dipole–dipole interactions</HEADER><P><s sid="211"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac22" novelty="None" advantage="None">In earlier experiments studying the interactions of colloids with lipid domains which were performed employing larger sulfonated polystyrene beads (2.8 μm diameter) and pentadecanoic acid on different subphases, the attractive potentials found could be completely explained by dipolar interactions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit53">53</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="212"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met33" novelty="Old" advantage="None">We also use the approach of these authors in this paper.</annotationART></s> <s sid="213"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac22" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the former publication,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit53">53</REF> the diffusion of the particles was not characterized in detail.</annotationART></s> <s sid="214"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac22" novelty="None" advantage="None">The focus of interest was on the measurement of the strength of the bead–domain interaction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="215"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac22" novelty="None" advantage="None">This strength was reported to be firstly dependent on the electric field generated due dipolar difference within the monolayer between the solid phase and the surrounding fluid, Δ<IT>ρ</IT><IT><SB>μ</SB></IT>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit54">54</REF> and secondly dependent on the dipole moment of the beads, <IT>μ</IT><SB>b</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="216"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac22" novelty="None" advantage="None">The latter can be explained by a charge separation due to a counterion layer in the subphase nearby to the negatively charged sulfonated surface of the polystyrene beads used.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit55">55</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="217"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">We conclude that also the carboxylated beads used in this study have an analogous dipolar moment.</annotationART></s> <s sid="218"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is assumed that the electric field <B><IT>E</IT></B> of the domains in a distance from the domain, <B><IT>r</IT></B>, can be calculated from the dipole density difference as follows, where <B><IT>r</IT></B><SB>0</SB> is the radius of the domain and <IT>A</IT> is the area of the domain:For the permittivity <IT>ε</IT>, a value of 7 is used as in .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit53">ref. 53</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="219"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">This constant accounts for the dielectric properties within the monolayer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="220"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The interaction potential with the dipolar moment of a polystyrene bead, <IT>μ</IT><SB>b</SB>, is calculated as the product of <IT>μ</IT><SB>b</SB> and <B><IT>E</IT></B>(<B><IT>r</IT></B>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="221"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The dipolar moment of the bead is <IT>μ</IT><SB>b</SB> = π<IT>σa</IT><SP>2</SP><IT>λ</IT><SB>D</SB> where <IT>σ</IT> is the charge density on the bead surface, <IT>a</IT> is the diameter of the bead.</annotationART></s> <s sid="222"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None"><IT>λ</IT><SB>D</SB> is the Debye length approximated bywhere <IT>I</IT> is the ionic strength of the subphase used.</annotationART></s> <s sid="223"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">As already mentioned above, the potential found, <IT>U</IT>(<B><IT>r</IT></B>) shows a 1/<B><IT>r</IT></B> dependence.</annotationART></s> <s sid="224"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">This behavior is typical if the underlying electric field is generated by a semi-infinite dipolar plate given by:This situation applies to a small probe particle in front of a large domain.</annotationART></s> <s sid="225"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot3" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the size of domains within inhomogeneous biological membranes is assumed to be 300 nm and less, lying beyond the resolution of optical epifluorescent microscopy used in our experiments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="226"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj6" novelty="New" advantage="None">Therefore, the electric field of domains with decreased size, resembling the size of lipid raft microdomains, was calculated by us.</annotationART></s> <s sid="227"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met34" novelty="Old" advantage="None">For these calculations, an analytical approach published earlier<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit53">53</REF> can be used which was derived from eqn. (11).</annotationART></s> <s sid="228"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met34" novelty="Old" advantage="No">However, this approach is only exact for square domains and distances <B><IT>r</IT></B> &gt; 2 μm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="229"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met35" novelty="New" advantage="None">In our study, we used two different numerical methods for the calculation of such electric fields which were appropriate for varied domain sizes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="230"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met35" novelty="New" advantage="None">One approach we used summarizes over single lipid dipoles located on a hexagonal lattice forming as an entity a circular domain.</annotationART></s> <s sid="231"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">This method gave consistent results up to domain sizes of 100 nm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="232"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met36" novelty="New" advantage="None">The other method is a numerical integration of eqn. (11).</annotationART></s> <s sid="233"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met36" novelty="New" advantage="None">The integral is calculated within a 0.5 μm radius of <B><IT>r</IT></B>, with a d<B><IT>r</IT></B><SB>0</SB> that is a square of 10<SP>−3</SP> μm side length.</annotationART></s> <s sid="234"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met36" novelty="New" advantage="None">From 0.5–5 μm, d<B><IT>r</IT></B><SB>0</SB> is a square of 10<SP>−2</SP> μm side length.</annotationART></s> <s sid="235"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met36" novelty="New" advantage="None">From 5 μm to a cutoff length of 50 μm, d<B><IT>r</IT></B><SB>0</SB> is a square 0.1 μm side length.</annotationART></s> <s sid="236"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met36" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">This method leads to fields that are accurate to 5% beyond 10<SP>−2</SP> μm from the edge of a domain and can be used down to domain sizes of 10 nm diameter.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit56">56</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="237"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met37" novelty="New" advantage="None">For the resulting calculations, the domain radius <IT>R</IT> was varied from 0.25 nm (∼radius of a single lipid chain) to 100 μm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="238"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met38" novelty="New" advantage="None"><B><IT>E</IT></B>(<B><IT>r</IT></B>) was calculated for 50 nm &lt; <IT>r</IT> &lt; 20 μm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="239"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">These calculations indicated a transition in the functional dependence on the distance of the electrical field from a single dipole to the behaviour of an semi-infinite wall.</annotationART></s> <s sid="240"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">The transition occured at a domain size which is related to the size of potential lipid rafts.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="241"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">This behavior is illustrated in Fig. 5 which represents the distance dependence of the electric field on <IT>R</IT>, the domain radius.</annotationART></s> <s sid="242"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The exponent <IT>C</IT> for the dependence <B><IT>E</IT></B> ∼ <B><IT>r</IT></B><SP><IT>C</IT></SP> was depicted as a function of the exponentially growing domain radius <IT>R</IT>. For LC domains in a LE phase, a striking increase of <IT>C</IT> is observed in this representation at a domain size of 10 nm–1000 nm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="243"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, the width of the resulting potential affecting a mobile dipole within the membrane, which is in our experiments a charged latex bead, changes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="244"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" advantage="None">Some deviation from an ideal curve in the small domain size regime is caused by the use of a hexagonal lattice.</annotationART></s> <s sid="245"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None">These effects of irregularities of the domain border are, as expected, more eminent at small domain sizes.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="246"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None">In short, it can be concluded that the form of the potential and thus its range depend strongly on the size of the domains.</annotationART></s> <s sid="247"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con15" novelty="None" advantage="None">In analogy, this suggests for the liquid-ordered/liquid-disordered coexistence in cell membranes with rafts, that the cell might be able to change the range of the domain potentials easily, increasing its ability to influence diffusion processes drastically.</annotationART></s> <s sid="248"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con16" novelty="None" advantage="None">This change in size could be achieved by protein clustering processes or by specific fusion of membrane regions with vesicles containing raft lipids.</annotationART></s> <s sid="249"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, the cell might control signaling processes and protein reactions by simply growing or shrinking the domains or locally increasing the domain curvature.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.4.">Simulations of dipolar domain–bead interactions</HEADER><P><s sid="250"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac23" novelty="None" advantage="None">Simulated random walks can be extended far beyond the time scales of the experiments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="251"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac24" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, domain character and potential strength can be altered arbitrarily.</annotationART></s> <s sid="252"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to study the effect of varied dipolar interaction on diffusion of model proteins within membranes, simulations were carried out assuming varied potential strengths.</annotationART></s> <s sid="253"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met39" novelty="New" advantage="None">These simulations were performed under use of 4 μm domains on a 10 μm square lattice.</annotationART></s> <s sid="254"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The sole influence of obstacles on the diffusion coefficient under these conditions is negligible (<IT>cf.</IT> methods).</annotationART></s> <s sid="255"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met40" novelty="New" advantage="None">The strength of the potential based on dipolar interactions between domain and latex beads applied in these Monte Carlo simulations can be adjusted to fixed values by changing of one of the relevant constants <IT>μ</IT><SB>b</SB> or Δ<IT>ρ</IT><SB><IT>μ</IT></SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="256"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj7" novelty="New" advantage="None">The trajectories for random walks of 1 × 10<SP>6</SP> time steps demonstrated high similarity to the experimental results at the relevant potential depths of about 5 <IT>k</IT><SB>B</SB><IT>T</IT>. Domain-associated diffusion was also simulated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="257"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met41" novelty="New" advantage="None">From the trajectories, the long-time diffusion coefficient was determined by a linear MSD <IT>vs.</IT> Δ<IT>t</IT> plot.</annotationART></s> <s sid="258"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met41" novelty="New" advantage="None">The potential depth (at the minimal distance, |<B><IT>r</IT></B>| = 50 nm for 100 nm diameter beads) used was varied in the range from 0 to 20 <IT>k</IT><SB>B</SB><IT>T</IT>. The diffusion coefficient in the long-time limit shows a sharp transition for <IT>D</IT> from 1 μm<SP>−2</SP> s<SP>−1</SP> to about 0 around a potential depth of <IT>U</IT> = 6.6<IT>k</IT><SB>B</SB><IT>T</IT> (<IT>cf.</IT> Fig. 6).</annotationART></s> <s sid="259"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con18" novelty="None" advantage="None">From the graph, it can be concluded that the long-time diffusion constant is apparently very sensitive to the potential in which the particle diffuses.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="260"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the area of the steep decrease in Fig. 6 small variation of the parameters affecting the dipolar interactions in the experiment, <IT>e.g.</IT> by alteration of the packing density of the lipids or change in bead surface charge, should be able to induce significant change in the diffusive behaviour from one-dimensional to two-dimensional and <IT>vice versa</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="261"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con19" novelty="None" advantage="None">A change of the potential could be also induced by alteration of the particle nature or the subphase.</annotationART></s> <s sid="262"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None">Small changes in potential can be attributed in various ways to the variability in the bead dipole moment.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="263"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod11" novelty="None" advantage="None">For our experiments as well as for the study published by Nassoy <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit53">53</REF>. the relevant dipole interaction parameters of beads and domains are given in Table 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="264"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met42" novelty="New" advantage="None">Moreover, the theoretically achievable maximal attractive potentials are listed and compared to the experimentally observed values.</annotationART></s> <s sid="265"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac25" novelty="None" advantage="None">In Nassoy <IT>et al.</IT>’s work, considerably larger beads were chosen leading to dipolar bead moments that were orders of magnitude larger than for the beads we used.</annotationART></s> <s sid="266"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac25" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, these authors overestimated the dipolar density difference or excess dipolar density Δ<IT>ρ</IT><SB>μ</SB> since they used a value calculated for the dipolar density of the LC phase of pentadecanoic acid from the molecular dipole moment given for octadecanoic acid in an earlier reference.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit57">57</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="267"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac25" novelty="None" advantage="None">So, also the calculated potential dependencies as a function of distance from the domain edge must be considered as too high under the conditions assumed by these authors.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="268"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res29" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the systems investigated by us, a relatively good agreement can be found comparing the theoretically predicted maximal potentials to the ones obtained experimentally as summarized in Table 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="269"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Here, we rely on the values for Δ<IT>ρ</IT><SB><IT>μ</IT></SB> given by Miller <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit46">46</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="270"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res30" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the DMPE system, it is clearly possible to explain the behavior observed by pure dipolar attraction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="271"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">This approach results in potentials for the DMPE system of −6.3<IT>k</IT><SB>B</SB><IT>T</IT> calculated and (−4.5 ± 1.0)<IT>k</IT><SB>B</SB><IT>T</IT> measured.</annotationART></s> <s sid="272"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac26" novelty="None" advantage="None">For methyl palmitate monolayers, to the best of our knowledge no specific surface potential data are available in the literature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="273"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod13" novelty="None" advantage="None">We assume that the Δ<IT>ρ</IT><SB><IT>μ</IT></SB> value for these monolayers is within the range as given for various phospholipids in the cited reference publication.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit46">46</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="274"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" advantage="None">Again, the experimental and theoretically predicted values match relatively well (<IT>cf.</IT> Table 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="275"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res32" novelty="None" advantage="None">The error for the experimentally found potentials might be also considered as too low since the measurements are still away from equilibrium (Boltzmann) conditions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="276"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con20" novelty="None" advantage="None">A source for errors in calculating the maximal potential theoretically might be the depth the bead penetrates into the water subphase.</annotationART></s> <s sid="277"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac27" novelty="None" advantage="None">This depends strongly on the interaction between the bead surface (carboxyl coated polystyrene) and the aqueous subphase, the surface tension of the monolayer, and the bead–lipid interaction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="278"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res33" novelty="None" advantage="None">These factors are not well characterized for the latex beads used for our study.</annotationART></s> <s sid="279"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res33" novelty="None" advantage="None">Simple assumptions lead to estimates of the bead penetration of 35%–50% of the total bead diameter.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit55">55</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="280"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con21" novelty="None" advantage="None">The real penetration depth may be different.</annotationART></s> <s sid="281"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con22" novelty="None" advantage="None">Nevertheless, in our case surface interactions seem not to be more significant than for the system used by Nassoy <IT>et al</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="282"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con22" novelty="None" advantage="None">The lipid monolayer thickness is about 2 nm, which is very small compared to both the 2.0 × 10<SP>2</SP> nm and to the 2.8 × 10<SP>3</SP> nm used in our study studies and by Nassoy <IT>et al</IT>., respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="283"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con23" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, surface charges may vary between different beads and lead to a distribution of interaction strengths.</annotationART></s> <s sid="284"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con24" novelty="None" advantage="None">A possible way to address the question if dipolar interaction does explain also the strength of the interaction potential of smaller charged beads within inhomogeneous monolayers would be the use of model proteins that are much smaller by orders of magnitude.</annotationART></s> <s sid="285"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con25" novelty="None" advantage="None">The contribution of interface forces to interactions affecting diffusion should be considerably larger for, <IT>e.g.</IT> quantum dots, which have, with their hydrophilic shells, diameters on the order of magnitude of the monolayer thickness.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="5.">Conclusions</HEADER><P><s sid="286"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con26" novelty="None" advantage="None">The localization mechanism for diffusing probe particles which can be concluded from our experiments and simulations could enhance reaction kinetics in membranes by increasing the local concentration of reacting components and by restriction of diffusive transport to one dimension.</annotationART></s> <s sid="287"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con27" novelty="None" advantage="None">Clustering of proteins, assumed to occur in lipid rafts<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF> could be induced by such a mechanism.</annotationART></s> <s sid="288"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con28" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is conceivable that the speed of signal transduction is increased drastically by localization of the interacting messengers at the edge of a microdomain.</annotationART></s> <s sid="289"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con29" novelty="None" advantage="None">This mechanism is not described yet and could have a similar significance for reaction kinetics in membranes as the reduction of dimensionality from three to two dimensions which is achieved by integration of proteins into the membranes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="290"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con30" novelty="None" advantage="None">A related finding which agrees with our view point was reported in a previous publication describing attractive interaction of concanavalin A protein patches of 1 μm size on water subphases with LC domains within DMPE monolayers.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit58">58</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="291"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac28" novelty="None" advantage="None">The attractive interaction was explained by different electric polarization of the protein patches and the lipid environment.</annotationART></s> <s sid="292"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac28" novelty="None" advantage="None">Penetration of the LC phase boundary by the protein patches was not observed which was explained by packing constraints.</annotationART></s> <s sid="293"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac28" novelty="None" advantage="None">The concanavalin A patches have to be considered as macroscopic aggregations and are far away to serve as models for single membrane proteins diffusing in monolayers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="294"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac28" novelty="None" advantage="None">Another potential parameter affecting the diffusive behavior was demonstrated to be the size of ordered domains.</annotationART></s> <s sid="295"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con31" novelty="None" advantage="None">By the mechanism described in this work, the range of interaction between more ordered domains of potential lipid raft size scale and diffusing charged proteins could be influenced.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
