<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b312724a" hasDoc="yes" version="1184" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Aromaticity on the edge of chaos: An <IT>ab initio</IT> study of the bimodal balance between aromatic and non-aromatic structures for 10π-dihetero[8]annulenes<XREF TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" /><XREF TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn2" /></annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The computed geometries of a class of 10π-annulenes containing two heteroatoms, which exhibit an acutely sensitive balance between π and σ influences upon ring planarity, reveal that the recent KMLYP hybridisation of the exchange functional in the DFT method is qualitatively superior to the more commonly used B3LYP hybrid for modelling the aromaticity of such systems.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Aromaticity as a concept has been dominated for most of its history by the study of benzenoid systems containing single or fused six-membered rings, and the recognition in the 1920s that this motif was associated both with ring planarity and with an “aromatic sextet” of electrons.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Dewar in 1945 was the first to recognise unambiguous aromatic character in a larger (seven-membered) ring,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">2</REF> although the potential for aromaticity in the eight-membered ring cyclooctatetraene (<B>1</B>) had been considered much earlier, most revealingly by Penney<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF> in 1934 and Lennard-Jones in .1937<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The latter was apparently the first to conclude from Hückel-like calculations that this 8π system would exhibit strong bond alternation and relatively little stabilisation as a planar species.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Penney appears to have been the first to consider planar and buckled conformations, and his analysis of angular strain in the (CH<SB>2</SB>)<SB><IT>n</IT></SB> rings in particular is remarkably prescient of the theories of conformational analysis developed some 15 years later by Barton.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">By 1945 in a review of non-benzenoid aromatic hydrocarbons, Baker<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF> felt able to conclude that “it is doubtful if the instability of cyclooctatetraene can be explained on grounds of angular strain alone”, although it was not until 1965 that Breslow<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF> formalised this apparent instability with the term 4<IT>n</IT> “anti-aromatic”, invoking what had by then become known as the Hückel 4<IT>n</IT> + 2/4<IT>n</IT> rule<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF> of aromaticity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">We use term apparent instability because it has recently<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF> been argued in fact that such 4<IT>n</IT> “anti-aromatic” species are not destabilized electronically to any significant extent.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Angular ring strain is avoided in larger monocyclic rings which also follow the 4<IT>n</IT> + 2 rule such as [14] or [18] annulene <B>2</B><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF> by including transoid motifs to retain planarity or methano bridges<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF> to avoid close non-bonded contacts.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The [9]annulene monoanion <B>3</B> with <IT>D</IT><SB>9h</SB> symmetry appears to be the largest 10π annulene ring which is both planar and can accommodate all-cisoid motives.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Somewhat surprisingly however, given the rather controversial origins surrounding the aromatic/non-aromatic/anti-aromatic character of the 4<IT>n</IT><B>1</B>, less attention has been given to eight-membered rings involving instead 10 (and hence 4<IT>n</IT> + 2) rather than 8π electrons.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Whilst the angular strain may be considered similar to that of <B>1</B>, the presumption is that significantly more aromatic stabilisation will be present, hence tipping the balance towards planarity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The heterocyclic 10π 1,4-heteroannulenes <B>4</B> are one such a class for which a number of crystal structures have been reported.</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Remarkably, these exhibit wide variation in ring planarity and degree of bond alternation, in synchrony with the diatropic/non-diatropic NMR character of the molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">This suggests that the balance between planarising aromaticity and non-planarising angular strain in these systems is a fine one.</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">They may indeed be good examples of bimodal molecules where small changes to the substituents can invoke disproportionately large changes in their structure; a phenomenon which could be described as aromaticity on the edge of chaos.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">We considered that such bimodal molecules should serve as highly sensitive tests of modern quantitative electronic theories, since an accurate balance between ring strain, σ/π conjugation, bond delocalisation and associated electron correlation effects can often be a very difficult one to achieve in such theories.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Here we report a consistent set of calculations on such systems at two levels of theory, the standard B3LYP/6-31G(d) <IT>ab initio</IT> density functional procedure, and a newly reported<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF> rehybridisation known as KMLYP, in order to evaluate how sensitive the computed molecular geometries of such molecules are to variations in the computational method employed.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Computational procedure</HEADER><P><s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Calculations were performed using Gaussian 98 (Rev A11)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF> using standard optimization methods on all the known examples of ring system <B>4</B>–<B>6</B> for which crystal structures have been reported.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">To invoke the KMLYP functional, the following Gaussian route commands were used:<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF> #iop(5/45 = 10000557) iop(5/46 = 00000443) #iop(5/47 = 04481000)For reference, some calculations were also performed at the (computationally very much more expensive) MP2 correlated level.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">All final energies and geometries are available as electronic supplementary information (ESI).<SUP TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" /></annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Diatropic character was estimated using the NICS procedure as described by Schleyer and coworkers<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Results and discussion</HEADER><P><s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Schleyer and Wannere<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF> have recently suggested that the degree of bond length alternation in both [14] and [18] annulene (<B>2</B>) may be significantly greater than inferred from the hitherto accepted (1995) analysis of the X-ray structure.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Noting that the commonly used B3LYP/6-31G(d) <IT>ab initio</IT> density functional procedure associated little bond alternation with a poor prediction of the <SP>1</SP>H NMR shifts<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF> of <B>2</B>, they found that use of Kang and Musgrave's (KMLYP) rehybridisation<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF> of the density functional exchange terms predicted greater bond alternation but significantly also a much superior match between the computed <SP>1</SP>H NMR shifts at this geometry and experiment.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Following this suggestion, we considered it appropriate to also evaluate these two computational procedures for the bimodal series <B>4</B> to see if it represents an improved procedure for use when modelling molecules with aromatic properties.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The crystal structure of 1,4-dioxocine <B>4</B>, XYO, R6-(pyran-4-on-2-yl)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF> exhibits a non planar geometry, with an 81° dihedral angle for C3–O4–C5–C6 and an approximate <IT>C</IT><SB>2</SB> axis passing through the mid points of C2–C3 and C6–C7.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">At the B3LYP/6-31G(d) level only one minimum corresponding to an almost planar structure could be located (Table 1);<SUP TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" /> clearly this predicted geometry is qualitatively different from the crystal structure, and although crystal packing forces (no hydrogen bonding is possible) might explain the difference, there is little precedent for such large variation caused by this effect.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast, two minima were located at the KMLYP/6-31G(d) level; an essentially planar aromatic-like geometry equivalent to the B3LYP structure, and an apparent valence bond isomer (lower than the former by Δ<IT>G</IT> 1.4 kcal mol<SP>–1</SP> following zero-point and entropy corrections) which matches the twisted crystal structure with a predicted C3–O4–C5–C6 angle of 78°.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Similar results were obtained at the larger 6-311+G(3d,p) basis set level, indicating this result is not highly basis set dependent.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The differing electronic nature of these two isomers is also reflected in the diatropic NMR character, as quantified using NICS values<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF> (Table 1); the planar B3LYP and KMLYP forms indicating moderate diatropicity, the twisted KMYLP form indicating a non-diatropic system comprising almost orthogonal p<SB>π</SB>-p<SB>π</SB> overlap at <IT>e.g.</IT> O4–C5.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Two valence bond isomers are also located at the MP2 correlated level, the non-planar being lower by 0.8 kcal mol<SP>–1</SP>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">When the pyranonyl substituent is replaced by the modestly more electronegative chloroacetyl group, both B3LYP and KMLYP now concur, predicting the ring to be exactly <IT>planar</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF> (at both the 6-31(d) and 6-311+G(3d,p) basis set levels) and in essential agreement with the crystal structure; the small experimental non-planarity (Table 1) may indeed now be due to crystal packing effects.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">No non-planar valence bond forms could be located at either level, although this does not preclude their existence as very shallow stationary points.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Also of interest is the parent ring system (<B>4</B>, XYO, RH).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17b">17<IT>b</IT></REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Only a single planar minimum is predicted at B3LYP and KMLYP levels, with the NICS values indicating modest diatropicity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">MP2 optimisation results in location of two minima, the planar one being 2.6 kcal mol<SP>–1</SP> lower than the non-planar form.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Experimentally,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17b">17<IT>b</IT></REF> this system is reported as being planar in solution (from the <SP>2,3</SP>J<SB>HH</SB> coupling constants), with <SP>1</SP>H NMR shifts in a region (5.1–7.6 ppm) normally associated with diatropicity, but having a high olefin-like reactivity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is possible that both planar and non-planar valence isomers are present as an equilibrium mixture in solution, thus imparting dual characteristics to this molecule.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">We therefore highlight this ring system as being close to a bimodal system on the edge of aromatic chaos, with relatively small changes to substituents apparently capable of invoking large changes in the geometry and aromaticity.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Exact planarity from both (solid-state) experiment and calculation <IT>is</IT> a feature of the parent 1,4-dihydro-1,4-diazocine (<B>4</B>, XYNH) and the 1,4-bis(trimethylsilyl) derivative,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF> but not so when the <IT>N</IT>-substituent is an electron withdrawing ester group.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19">19</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Here again a significant difference between B3LYP and KMLYP is predicted, the latter appearing to be the more correct in terms of the computed bond lengths (no dihedral angles being reported for this system).</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The N-dimethylamide group is predicted as intermediate in planarity between <IT>N</IT>-alkyl and <IT>N</IT>-ester, although the X-ray structure<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19">19</REF> is quoted as being planar.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">This molecule may be particularly finely balanced between planar aromaticity and non-planar non-aromaticity and may again be a good example of a bipolar aromatic molecule.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None"><B>4</B>, XYN-mesyl at the KMLYP level also shows subtle behaviour; a non-planar stationary point appears as a near inflexion point during geometry optimization, but the final geometry is almost planar; at the MP2 level the non planar form is a genuine minimum.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Replacing a further ring carbon with a nitrogen heteroatom (<B>5</B>, XYN–CO<SB>2</SB>Me), Table 1) induces non-planarity which is more unambiguously predicted.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the mixed heteroatom series, planarity is both observed and computed for XO, YN-3,4,5-trimethoxyphenyl.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">With YN-Ts however, the crystal structure is described as “having considerable torsion”.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both MP2 and KMLYP optimizations result in location of such isomer (C3–O4–C5–C6 ≅93° and ≅82.5° respectively), although only with the former is the more stable the non-planar form (<IT>vis</IT> the similar KMLYP behaviour for <B>4</B>, XYN-Mesyl).</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The 1,4-dithiocine series (<B>4</B>, XYS)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21 cit22">21,22</REF> are all non-planar and equally well predicted with B3LYP and KMLYP, as is the oxathiocine (<B>4</B>, XO, YS).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The series <B>4</B>, XCH<SP>–</SP> are all predicted planar and are known<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25">25</REF> to be diatropic (Table 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The (as yet unknown) parent system for <B>4</B>, XO, YS, RH however shows another amplified difference between B3LYP and KMLYP.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Valence bond isomers were located at both levels; for the former, the planar aromatic form was 3.0 kcal mol<SP>–1</SP> lower, with KMLYP the non-aromatic form was 0.7 kcal mol<SP>–1</SP> more stable.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The existence of a locatable transition state between the two valence forms suggests these minima may not simply be artifacts of the single reference KMLYP (and MP2) procedures, but genuine (aromatic and non-aromatic) isomers straddling a Möbius-type<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26">26</REF> transition state (C3–O4–C5–C6 ≅38°/KMLYP) which represents the <IT>least stable</IT> configuration for the 4<IT>n</IT> + 2 π electrons present.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The analogy would be to planar <B>1</B> being the least stable 4<IT>n</IT> electronic configuration between two non-planar non-aromatic minima and hence a transition state connecting them.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The seven-ring analogue <B>6</B> (XYZNH) is predicted both slightly non-planar <IT>and</IT> diatropic; the only two known crystal structures of this 10π ring system (XYZNR<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27">27</REF> and XYZSe<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28">28</REF>) likewise reveal non-planarity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Finally, we note that only known example of a 6π four membered ring system (<B>7</B>, RCl, R′2,4,6-tri-t-butylphenyl) is also non-planar,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29">29</REF> but the origins of this are unlikely to be angular strain and are more likely associated either with poor p<SB>π</SB>p<SB>π</SB> overlaps or a high degree of electron repulsion in a small ring.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Conclusions</HEADER><P><s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">We argue here that molecules such as <B>4</B>–<B>6</B> are good examples of bipolar systems on the chaotic edge of aromaticity, where small changes of substitution on either the ring or the heteroatom can induce large (but predictable) changes to both the degree of delocalisation of the double bonds, reflected in the corresponding planarity and hence aromaticity of the system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">As such, they serve to provide challenging tests of modern quantitative electronic structure theories.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Of these, we suggest that the KMLYP/6-31(d) method appears capable of predicting this sensitivity more reliably than the older B3LYP treatment.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">We propose that synthesis and accurate structure determination of a more comprehensive set of substituted heteroaromatics such as <B>4</B> or <B>6</B> could serve as a novel type of reference library which could serve as the basis for developing even better hybridisations of density functional and other methods.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
