<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b403032j" hasDoc="yes" version="1184" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Density functional studies of the luminescence of Si<SB>29</SB>H<SB>36</SB></annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The molecular structures of the ground and the lowest excited state of a Si<SB>29</SB>H<SB>36</SB> cluster have been optimized at the density-functional-theory (DFT) level using the time-dependent perturbation-theory (TDDFT) approach for the excited state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The electronic absorption and emission energies for the fully optimized molecular structures have been calculated at the TDDFT level.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The excitation energy calculated for the equilibrium structure of the excited state using the Becke–Perdew (BP) functional was found to be 0.72 eV smaller than the vertical excitation energy for the ground-state structure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The calculated wavelength of the emitted light is 396 nm which agrees well with experiment as the silicon cluster emits blue light.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Small structural changes caused by the relaxation of the excited state introduce strains in the ground-state structure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The strain and the relaxation are found to contribute equally to the large red shift of the emitted light.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, the present calculations do not support the notion that the potential-energy surface of the excited state has a double-well structure.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="I.">Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">A more detailed understanding of light absorption and light emission processes requires information about the potential-energy surfaces of both the ground and the involved excited states.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">At absorption, the molecular system is excited from the ground state in its equilibrium geometry to an excited state and during the excitation process the molecular structure is approximately unchanged; the excitation is usually thought to be vertical.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the ground-state structure is not necessarily optimal for the excited state resulting in a relaxation of the molecular structure of the excited state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The deexcitation giving rise to the luminescence can probably be considered to occur vertically from the relaxed excited state structure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This simplified absorption-emission mechanism suggests that the emitted light is red shifted as compared to the absorbed one.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In photophysical studies of ultrasmall nano-sized Si particles, Nayfeh <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2 cit3 cit4 cit5 cit6 cit7 cit8 cit9 cit10 cit11">1–11</REF>. found that the absorption occurs in the ultra-violet (UV) region, whereas the excited Si particles emitted blue light with such a high intensity that one was able to observe the individual particles.</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Experimental and computational studies suggested that the Si nanoparticles most likely consist of 29 Si atoms which is a magic number for approximately spherically shaped clusters of <IT>T</IT><SB>d</SB> symmetry.</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Spectroscopic studies showed that the Si cluster is covered by hydrogens.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Si particles with carbon, nitrogen, or oxygen termination have also been prepared<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit8">5,8</REF> and studied computationally.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12 cit13">12,13</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The electronic absorption spectrum up to the ionization threshold has recently been calculated for the Si cluster at density-functional-theory (DFT) levels and the accuracy of the obtained excitation energies were checked using coupled-cluster response-theory (CC2) calculations.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">At the DFT level using the Becke–Perdew (BP) functional, the excitation energy of the first excited state is 3.85 eV which agrees well with the experimental excitation threshold of 3.7 eV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Calculations at the CC2 level and DFT calculations using a hybrid functional yielded somewhat larger excitation energies, whereas calculations at the coupled-cluster singles (CCS)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF> and the closely related configuration-interaction singles (CIS) levels<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6 cit7 cit8">6–8</REF> yielded an excitation threshold of about 6 eV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The calculations also showed that the silicon cluster of 1 nm size possesses a band structure consisting of more than one hundred excited states below the ionization threshold at about 8 eV.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Experimentally, the excited Si cluster is found to emit blue light which corresponds to an excitation energy of about 3 eV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, the relaxation of the excited state leads to a huge shift of about 0.7 eV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The large red shift of the luminescence has been explained by localized surface states in the Si nanocluster.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Based on empirical tight-binding and first-principle local-density calculations, Allan <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF>. proposed that such states exist under the form of self-trapped excitons at the Si–Si dimers on the nanocluster surface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Nayfeh <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF>. adopted their notion and examined various photoexcitation pathways involved in accessing and populating these molecular states.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">They found that the ground state has an all-confining single well, whereas the excited state has a double-well potential.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The inner minimum corresponds to a normal nonradiative delocalized excited state with a Si–Si distance of the surface dimer of 2.35 Å, while the outer minimum corresponds to a radiative and trapped excitonic surface state with a Si–Si interspacing of 3.85 Å.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit16">1,16</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this work, the molecular structure of the first excited state of the Si<SB>29</SB>H<SB>36</SB> cluster has been fully optimized at the time-dependent density-functional-theory (TDDFT) level.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">The corresponding emission spectrum as well as the absorption spectrum for the ground-state structure have been studied by employing TDDFT calculations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None">The potential-energy curve for a relaxation pathway of the first excited state of the Si<SB>29</SB>H<SB>36</SB> cluster has also been investigated.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="II.">Computational methods</HEADER><P><s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The molecular structure of the Si<SB>29</SB>H<SB>36</SB> cluster was optimized in the ground and the first excited state using the Turbomole program.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Structure optimizations were performed at the density-functional-theory (DFT) level<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF> using a gradient-corrected local-density approximation (BP)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19 cit20 cit21">19–21</REF> and triple-zeta valence quality basis sets augmented with polarization functions (TZVP).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Previous calculations showed that at least TZVP basis sets have to be used in order to obtain an accurate excitation spectrum.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The absorption and emission spectra were calculated using the time-dependent perturbation-theory approach (TDDFT).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23 cit24">23,24</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The molecular structure of the first excited state was fully optimized at the BP TDDFT level using the Egrad module of Turbomole.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25 cit26">25,26</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The molecular structure of the ground state of the Si<SB>29</SB>H<SB>36</SB> cluster belongs to the <IT>T</IT><SB>d</SB> point group, whereas the symmetry of the first excited state was found to be <IT>D</IT><SB>2d</SB>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="III.">Results</HEADER><P><s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The molecular structure of the Si<SB>29</SB>H<SB>36</SB> cluster is shown in Fig. 1, and the bond lengths of the ground and excited states are given in Table I. Structure changes (Δ<IT>R</IT>) due to the relaxation of the excited state are also given in the table.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">When the molecular structure of the Si cluster in the first excited state is assumed to belong to the <IT>T</IT><SB>d</SB> point group, the luminescence energy is red shifted by 0.26 eV as compared to the absorption threshold, while when the cluster is allowed to relax to a <IT>D</IT><SB>2d</SB> structure, the energy decreases by 0.72 eV yielding a deexcitation energy of 3.14 eV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, the wavelength of the emitted light is 396 nm; blue light is emitted as also detected experimentally.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2 cit3 cit4 cit5 cit6 cit7 cit8 cit9">1–9</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In Table I, one can see that the changes in the bond lengths are rather small.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The largest difference of 2.1 pm is obtained for the Si(2)–Si(4) bond.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Si(2) is attached to Si(1), which is the central Si atom, and to Si(4) which is a surface Si atom with only one attached hydrogen.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">See Fig. 1 for the atom numbering.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The bonds to the central Si(1) become 1.1 pm longer than for the ground state, while when the <IT>T</IT><SB>d</SB> symmetry is enforced on the excited state, the Si(1)–Si(2) bond becomes 3.3 pm longer than for the ground state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The changes in the bond lengths are remarkably small especially when one considers that the difference between the absorption and emission energies is as large as 0.72 eV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The calculations show that there are two equal sources to the huge red shift: the relaxation of the excited state and the energy shift due to the strain of the ground state.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In Table 2, the excitation energies of the first few dipole-allowed excitations are given.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the first three columns, the excitation energy and oscillator strengths obtained using the <IT>T</IT><SB>d</SB> structure of the ground state are given, while the remaining columns contain the corresponding data obtained using the optimized <IT>D</IT><SB>2d</SB> structure of the first excited state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The absorption and emission spectra obtained using the data of Table 2 are displayed in Fig. 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">As the emission spectrum is also constructed from calculated excitation energies and oscillator strengths, not all contributions to the emission are taken into account.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27">27</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="New" advantage="None">For the luminescence spectrum, the molecular structure of the 1b<SB>2</SB> state has been assumed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="New" advantage="None">Population of higher excited states leads to other molecular structures and different luminescence spectra.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">By optimizing the doubly degenerate 1e state one obtains a higher luminescence energy of about 3.5 eV, whereas for symmetry reasons, the three individual components of the 1t<SB>2</SB> state are identical.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">The relaxation pathway between the molecular structures of the ground and first excited states is difficult to compute.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">However, as a first guess one can assume that in the relaxation process the internal coordinates change linearly between the two extremes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The excitation energy plot shown in Fig. 3 is obtained from such an interpolation procedure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">As seen in the figure, the excitation energy is a smooth function decreasing from 3.85 eV for the ground-state structure and reaching 3.14 eV for the fully optimized structure of the excited state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The potential-energy curves for the ground and excited states along the same trajectory are shown in Fig. 4.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The potential-energy curves for both states are smooth functions with one single minimum each.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">No avoiding crossing yielding double minima of the potential-energy surface of the excited state, as previously proposed, can be seen in the figure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 4 shows that energy shift due to the relaxation of the excited state is equally significant to the red shift as the strain-energy contribution of the ground state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The chosen trajectory is not necessarily the exact pathway of the relaxation process.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the absence of a potential threshold along this trajectory for the excited state shows that the molecular structure of the excited state is, after excitation, relaxed without any barrier.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="New" advantage="None">In order to check whether the excited state has an outer potential minimum trapping an exciton state at the surface of the Si cluster, the optimization of the molecular structure of the first excited state was performed without any symmetry constraints <IT>i.e.</IT> in <IT>C</IT><SB>1</SB> symmetry starting from a structure with a long Si(3)–Si(5) distance of 3.18 Å.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, no outer potential minimum could be found in the reoptimization of the first excited state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">This, and the fact that the absorption and the emission energies are in close agreement with experimental data indicate that the potential-energy curve of the excited state does not possess any outer minimum.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The present calculations thus show that it is most unlikely that the potential-energy curve of the excited state has two minima separated by a barrier as previously suggested by Allan <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Instead, the small structural changes due to the relaxation of the excited state result in a lower energy for the excited state and simultaneously the energy of the ground state increases significantily due to the strain.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">These two contributions seem to be equally responsible for the obtained luminescence shift of 0.72 eV.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
