<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b413603a" hasDoc="yes" version="1190" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Statistical mechanical approach to competitive binding of metal ions to multi-center receptors</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">A microscopic site binding model to treat binding of several metal ions to multi-center receptors is proposed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The model introduces the appropriate parameterization in terms of microscopic complexation constants and metal–metal pair interaction energies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">The model is solved with statistical mechanical techniques, including direct enumeration or transfer matrices.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">We obtain microscopic and macroscopic complexation constants, microstate probabilities, and binding isotherms for chain-like receptors, including the long-chain limit.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Various examples to illustrate the usefulness of the model are given.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Interactions of metal ions with ligands represent an important topic in coordination chemistry.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the past, research mainly focussed on mono-center complexes containing a single metal ion and one or more ligands.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">More recently, attention shifted toward supramolecular multi-center assemblies, which result from the interactions between several ligands and metal ions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Researchers have focussed on the preparation and structural characterization of sophisticated metallo-supramolecular architectures, which can be obtained in high-yield by the simple mixing of the various components (<IT>i.e.</IT>, self-assembly).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">2</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the thermodynamic basis of the formation mechanisms of such complexes is poorly understood, and has not been addressed in much detail so far.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Proper understanding of these processes is essential for stimulating molecular programming, and for switching from the usual deductive chemical approach toward induction.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The latter bottom-up process necessitates an exploitation and modelling of the experimental kinetic and thermodynamic data on complexation reactions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this context, multi-metal supramolecular lanthanide complexes are particularly interesting, as the search for new receptors displaying selective binding along the 4f-block series provides a substantial database of macroscopic and microscopic stability constants.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The recent design of heterometallic f–f′ complexes evidencing large deviations from statistical distributions in solution demonstrates the need for mathematical models of multi-center complexation processes.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The partial rationalization of the formation of the heterobimetallic and trimetallic complexes represents a first step toward this goal.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6 cit7 cit8 cit9 cit10 cit11">6–11</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Examples of such complexes are shown in Fig. 1, and the structure of the ligands in Fig. 2.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The formation of metal–ligand complexes can be quantified in terms of chemical equilibria and the corresponding complexation constants.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="No">However, as soon as multi-center complexes are being considered, the number of constants becomes very large, and this approach becomes impractical.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">For this reason, a parameterization of these constants in terms of only a few chemically meaningful parameters is necessary.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Ercolani's work<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF> focusses exactly on this problem, as he attempts to express formation constants of multi-center complexes in terms of two intrinsic constants and symmetry numbers.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">A classical topic, where such questions arise, are acid–base equilibria of polyelectrolytes (<IT>i.e.</IT>, proton binding).</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the early fifties, Kirkwood,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF> Steiner,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF> and Marcus<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF> had shown how to formulate a site binding model for this situation, and this approach has been extended until recently.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16 cit17">16,17</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The free energy of a microscopic protonation state is expressed in terms of a small number of parameters.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Normally, these include microscopic binding constants for each site and site–site pair interaction energies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">For an infinite polyelectrolyte chain, the binding isotherms can be evaluated by standard techniques borrowed from statistical mechanics.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">For finite oligomers, one recovers the classical description in terms of chemical equilibria, and the corresponding protonation constants can be expressed in terms of microscopic binding constants and pair interaction energies.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">This parameterization appears to be the appropriate one to obtain the necessary simplification of the description of acid–base equilibria of polyprotic acids or bases.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18 cit19 cit20">18–20</REF> </annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">One encounters a similar problem, when one attempts to interpret the binding of metal ions by polyelectrolytes.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21 cit22 cit23 cit24 cit25">21–25</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Such charged macromolecules have linear or branched structures, and offer a large number of coordination sites.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Polyelectrolytes may therefore bind a larger number of metal ions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">For example, dendrimers have been reported to complex several hundreds of copper(ii) ions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Again, such systems cannot be described by a small number of complexation constants, and an alternative approach is needed.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">To approach such questions, microscopic site binding models have been proposed to address the competition between protons and multi-dentate metal binding to polyelectrolytes.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">In this publication, we develop this topic further and discuss a site binding model to describe binding of different metal ions to a multi-center receptor with well-defined binding sites, see Fig. 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">The receptor may consist of several preassembled ligands.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">This paper is structured as follows.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">First, we introduce the appropriate parameterization in terms of microscopic complexation constants and metal–metal pair interaction energies, elucidate the differences between microscopic and macroscopic equilibria in these systems, and extend the description to macromolecular receptors.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None">The model will be first discussed with simple examples, including small and infinitely large receptors.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="New" advantage="None">In the last section the applicability of the model to experimental binding constants is illustrated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The experimentally inclined reader is welcome to proceed to this section directly.</annotationART></s></P><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Binding of metal ions to a multi-center ligand receptor</HEADER><P><s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Consider a receptor with several binding sites, each of which can bind a single metal ion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Once the site is occupied with a metal ion, it can no longer bind any others.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">If a metal ion of type <IT>ω</IT> is bound to a site <IT>i</IT>, the corresponding element of the state vector <B><IT><B>s</B></IT></B>(<IT>ω</IT>)<IT>i</IT> is defined to be unity, and all the other elements are zero.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The state of all sites can be then described with a state vector <B><IT>s</IT></B><IT><SB>i</SB></IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">To a first approximation, the effective free energy of the metal-receptor complex can be written as a general linear and quadratic expression in the state variables, namely<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17 cit21 cit26">17,21,26</REF> where the chemical potential term can be related to the activity of metal <IT>α</IT><SB><IT>ω</IT></SB> as <IT>µ</IT>(<IT>ω</IT>)<IT>i</IT> = <IT>kT</IT> ln <IT>α</IT><SB><IT>ω</IT></SB><IT>K</IT>(<IT>ω</IT>)<IT>i</IT>, where <IT>K</IT>(<IT>ω</IT>)<IT>i</IT> is the microscopic association constant of the center <IT>i</IT> for the metal of type <IT>ω</IT>, and <IT>kT</IT> the thermal energy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have further denoted by <IT>E</IT>(<IT>ωη</IT>)<IT>ij</IT> the pair interaction energy between two metal ions <IT>ω</IT> and <IT>η</IT> occupying the sites <IT>i</IT> and <IT>j</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that the pair interaction energy is symmetric upon exchange of the indices <IT>ω</IT> and <IT>η</IT>, as well as <IT>i</IT> and <IT>j</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The free energy eqn. (1) is a straightforward generalization of the treatment of protonation equilibria.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16 cit17">16,17</REF> </annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Given the free energy of the metal–receptor complex, we can express the semi-grand canonical partition function as<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26">26</REF>where the sum extends over all possible states {<IT><B>s</B></IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB>}.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The binding isotherm for the metal <IT>ω</IT> and center <IT>i</IT> can be written as a thermal average over the state variable, namelywhere the thermal average of a function <IT>f</IT>({<B><IT>s</IT></B><SB><IT>i</IT></SB>}) is defined as.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The overall binding fraction of the metal <IT>ω</IT> can be expressed aswhere <IT>N</IT> is the total number of sites of the receptor.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">These isotherms obey the thermodynamic consistency relation </annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Macroscopic equilibrium constants</HEADER><P><s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Based on the present description, one can obtain expressions for equilibrium constants for the chemical equilibria between different species.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the sake of simplicity, let us consider two types of metal ions M<SP>(1)</SP> and M<SP>(2)</SP> only.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The generalization of the following arguments to an arbitrary number of metal ions is straightforward.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Commonly, solution equilibria are described in terms of macrospecies, where only the total number and type of metal ions are specified, but it is not specified to which site they are bound.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The formation of such macrospecies can be described in terms of a chemical reaction L + <IT>n</IT>M<SP>(1)</SP> + <IT>m</IT>M<SP>(2)</SP> ⇌ LM(1)<IT>n</IT>M(2)<IT>m</IT>which can be characterized in terms of macroscopic cumulative equilibrium constants <IT>β</IT><SB><IT>nm</IT></SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The latter can be obtained by expanding the partition function in terms of the activities <IT>a</IT><SB>1</SB> and <IT>a</IT><SB>2</SB>, and as the result one obtains the binding polynomial.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">From this expression, the probability of a macrospecies, or in other words its relative concentration, can be expressed as.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">From these macrospecies probabilities, the binding isotherms can be directly obtained as.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">These expressions reflect the basic fact that the overall binding isotherms depend on the probabilities of the corresponding macrostates.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Microscopic equilibrium constants</HEADER><P><s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Each macrospecies normally corresponds to a collection of several microspecies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">A microspecies is defined with a set of given state variable vectors {<B><IT>s</IT></B><SB><IT>i</IT></SB>}.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The probability of such a species (<IT>i.e.</IT>, its relative concentration) can be written as.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Let us express the macrostate probability in terms of the microstate probabilities where δ<SB><IT>n</IT>,<IT>m</IT></SB> is unity for <IT>n</IT> = <IT>m</IT> and zero otherwise.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">From this expression we find that the probability of the microspecies can be split into two terms, namely, <IT>p</IT>({<B><IT>s</IT></B><SB><IT>i</IT></SB>}) = π({<B><IT>s</IT></B><SB><IT>i</IT></SB>}|<IT>nm</IT>)<IT>P</IT><SB><IT>nm</IT></SB>(<IT>α</IT><SB>1</SB>,<IT>α</IT><SB>2</SB>)the macrostate probability <IT>P</IT><SB><IT>nm</IT></SB>(<IT>α</IT><SB>1</SB>,<IT>α</IT><SB>2</SB>), and the conditional microstate probability where the Kronecker's δ<SB><IT>n</IT>,<IT>m</IT></SB> is unity for <IT>n</IT> = <IT>m</IT> and zero otherwise.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">This conditional probability expresses the relative probability to find a given microstate within a particular macrostate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The important advantage of introducing this conditional probability is that this quantity is a constant and independent of the metal activities.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The entire concentration dependence is captured by the macrostate probability.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Equilibrium constants of microscopic equilibria can be discussed in this framework as well.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Recall that the binding state of the receptor is uniquely defined with a set of given state variable vectors {<B><IT>s</IT></B><SB><IT>i</IT></SB>}.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Consider now a chemical equilibrium between two species <IT>L</IT>({<B><IT>s</IT></B>′<SB><IT>i</IT></SB>}) ⇌ <IT>L</IT>({<IT><B>s</B></IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB>})the state vectors of which are identical with the exception of the elements <IT><B>s</B></IT><SB><IT>j</IT></SB>(<IT>λ</IT>)<IT>j</IT> = 0 and <IT><B>s</B></IT>′(<IT>λ</IT>)<IT>j</IT> = 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">This reaction corresponds to a microscopic equilibrium, where the site <IT>j</IT> eliminates a metal of type <IT>λ</IT>, but the binding state of the rest of receptor remains unchanged.</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The successive equilibrium constant for the reaction eqn. (16) can be obtained from the free energy difference of these states, and yields the result.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that the previously introduced binding constant <IT>K</IT>(<IT>λ</IT>)<IT>j</IT> corresponds to the inverse of the microconstant for the release of a metal of type <IT>λ</IT> from site <IT>j</IT> when all other sites of the receptor are empty.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Transfer matrix techniques</HEADER><P><s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Different binding states of receptors with a small number of sites can be enumerated by hand.</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Larger structures can be enumerated on a computer, even though the number of sites accessible with this technique remains limited to about 20–30.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Larger systems can be either treated by Monte Carlo simulation, or certain structures by transfer matrix techniques.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27">27</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In particular, the latter can be used to address systems in the limit of large number of sites in a straightforward fashion.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">To introduce the transfer matrix technique, consider a linear structure and nearest neighbor pair range interactions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27">27</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thereby, one introduces a recursion relation between the partition function of a chain with <IT>n</IT> sites and with <IT>n</IT> + 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to define this recursion, let us consider a restricted partition function for a sub-chain of length <IT>n</IT>, such that the values of the state vector of the last site are restricted to given values <B><IT>s</IT></B>, namely where δ<SB><B><IT>s</IT></B>,<B><IT>s</IT></B>′</SB> is unity when <B><IT>s</IT></B> = <B><IT>s</IT></B>′ and zero otherwise.</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">By arranging the elements of the restricted partition function <IT>Ξ</IT><SB><IT>n</IT></SB>(<B><IT>s</IT></B>) into a column vector <B><IT>Ξ</IT></B><SB><IT>n</IT></SB>, the transfer matrix <B><IT>T</IT></B> can be defined as <B><IT>Ξ</IT></B><SB><IT>n</IT> + 1</SB> = <B><IT>T</IT></B><B><IT>Ξ</IT></B><SB><IT>n</IT></SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Adopting this notation, we assume that the sites are numbered from the left to the right.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">As will be discussed in the following, transfer matrices have simple forms for nearest neighbor pair interactions.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The recursion relation eqn. (19) can be initiated with the partition vector for the first site <B><IT>Ξ</IT></B><SB>1</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, it is usually more practical to generate this restricted partition function by the application of the transfer matrix to a suitably chosen generating vector <IT><B>V</B></IT><SB>g</SB> such that <B><IT>Ξ</IT></B><SB>1</SB> = <B><IT>T</IT></B><IT><B>V</B></IT><SB>g</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">As will be exemplified below, the advantage of introducing this vector is its simple structure.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The partition function of the entire chain can be then obtained by summing over all the states of the sub-chain.</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Again, this operation can be formulated in a matrix notation, by defining a terminating vector <IT><B>V</B></IT><SB>t</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Usually this vector contains unit entries, and one can write eqn. (20) as a scalar product <IT>Ξ</IT> = <B><IT>V</IT>̃</B><SB>t</SB><B><IT>Ξ</IT></B><SB><IT>N</IT></SB>where <B><IT>V</IT>̃</B><SB>t</SB> denotes the transposed (row) vector.</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The partition function can be now written in a compact fashion as <IT>Ξ</IT> = <B><IT>V</IT>̃</B><SB>t</SB><B><IT>T</IT></B><SP><IT>N</IT></SP><IT><B>V</B></IT><SB>g</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Based on this formulation, many properties of finite and infinite chains can be obtained in a straightforward way.</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">For example, the long chain limit is typically dominated with the largest eigenvalue <IT>λ</IT> of the transfer matrix <B><IT>T</IT></B>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The partition function is asymptotically given by <IT>Ξ</IT> ∼ <IT>λ</IT><SP><IT>N</IT></SP> for <IT>N</IT> → ∞If the largest eigenvalue cannot be found analytically, it can be easily calculated numerically.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The binding isotherms are then obtained from eqn. (5).</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Binding of a single metal ion</HEADER><P><s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">This situation is completely analogous to the situation of proton binding discussed in detail elsewhere.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14 cit15 cit16 cit17">14–17</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Nevertheless, it is important to understand this case for our discussion of the multicomponent case.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">For this reason, a few major features will be summarized here.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this situation, the state vector has only one element, and the index <IT>ω</IT> can be suppressed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the situation of identical sites and nearest neighbor interactions the free energy is given by where <IT>µ</IT> is a chemical potential term, and <IT>E</IT><SB><IT>ij</IT></SB> is the pair interaction energy between the sites <IT>i</IT> and <IT>j</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Due to Coulombic forces between charged metal ions, the interactions are repulsive and <IT>E</IT><SB><IT>ij</IT></SB> &gt; 0.</annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The chemical potential term <IT>µ</IT> can be related to the metal ion activity <IT>a</IT> and the microscopic binding constant <IT>K</IT> of the metal to a binding center when all other centers are empty by <IT>µ</IT> = <IT>kT</IT> ln <IT>aK</IT>. </annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Let us now consider three examples.</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The first two concern small receptors, and the last one the infinite linear chain.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The situation of a symmetric receptor with three equivalent sites is simple to discuss, see Fig. 3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since all the sites are equivalent, there is only one type of the metal–receptor complex, and the microstate is equivalent to the macrostate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The microscopic binding constant to bind a metal ion to the site will be denoted as <IT>K</IT>, which is the inverse of the microconstant to remove it.</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The macroscopic formation constant <IT>β</IT><SB>10</SB> involves a statistical factor of 3, since there are three sites on which the metal ion can bind to the receptor.</annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">When two metal ions bind to the receptor, there is again only one type of the metal–receptor complex, and the microstate is also equivalent to the macrostate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The macroscopic formation constant <IT>β</IT><SB>20</SB> involves the square of the microconstant, as two metal ions are being bound, the statistical factor of 3, and the pair interaction parameter <IT>u</IT>, which is related to the pair interaction energy <IT>E</IT> by <IT>E</IT> = −<IT>kT</IT> ln <IT>u</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The inverse microconstant for removing a metal ion involves the binding constant <IT>K</IT> and one pair interaction <IT>u</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The macroconstant <IT>β</IT><SB>30</SB> for the fully occupied receptor involves the cube of the microconstant, three pair interactions, and no statistical factor.</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">When we remove a metal ion of the fully occupied receptor, we overcome the binding constant and two pair interactions, obtaining the inverse of <IT>Ku</IT><SP>2</SP>. </annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The second example involves a linear receptor, with two equivalent terminal sites, and one central site, see Fig. 4.</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">There are two possible microstates, when one binds one metal ion to the receptor, namely either to the terminal site or to the central site.</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">We assume that the microconstant of these sites is the same for all sites, and will be denoted by <IT>K</IT>. The inverse of this value corresponds to the microconstant for the removal of the metal ion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since these constants are the same for all three sites, the conditional probability to find the microspecies with the central site occupied is 1/3, while when the terminal site is occupied 2/3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The latter factor of two arises since there are two equivalent terminal sites.</annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The macroconstant <IT>β</IT><SB>10</SB> is given by three times the microconstant <IT>K</IT>, since each species contributes in the same way.</annotationART></s> <s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">One also obtains two microspecies when the receptor binds two metal ions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the first species, one terminal site and one central site are occupied.</annotationART></s> <s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">This microspecies invokes a nearest neighbor pair interaction, denoted by the parameter <IT>u</IT>, and the square of the microconstants.</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">To remove a metal ion from this species, the inverse microconstant involves a factor <IT>K</IT> and we eliminate a pair interaction, which involves a factor <IT>u</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the other microspecies, both terminal sites are occupied.</annotationART></s> <s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">For this species, which has a symmetry number of 2, it may be necessary to consider the typically weaker next neighbor pair interaction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, this interaction will be neglected here.</annotationART></s> <s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The microconstant to remove a metal ion is now given by the inverse of <IT>K</IT>. Summing up the contributions of both species, we thus find the macroconstant <IT>β</IT><SB>20</SB> and the conditional probabilities of each microspecies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The receptor fully occupied with metal ions invokes two nearest neighbor pair interactions, and thus invokes a factor <IT>u</IT><SP>2</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">From these considerations, we obtain the conditional microstate probabilities and the macroconstants shown in Fig. 4.</annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">To remove a metal ion, there are two different microconstants as the terminal site involves only one pair interaction, and the central one two.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of linear chain, one can use the transfer matrix technique to obtain these results.</annotationART></s> <s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of a single metal ion, equivalent sites, and nearest neighbor interactions, the transfer matrix is given by<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16 cit21 cit27">16,21,27</REF> where we have introduced the reduced activity <IT>z</IT> = <IT>α</IT><IT>K</IT>.The two supplementary (transposed) partition vectors are <IT><B>V</B></IT>̃<SB>g</SB> = (1,0) and <B><IT>V</IT></B>̃<SB>t</SB> = (1, 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The partition functions can be evaluated by inserting these quantities into eqn. (22).</annotationART></s> <s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">For example, for a chain with three sites (<IT>N</IT> = 3) one obtains <IT>Ξ</IT> = 1 + 3<IT>z</IT> + (1 + 2<IT>u</IT>)<IT>z</IT><SP>2</SP> + <IT>u</IT><SP>2</SP><IT>z</IT><SP>3</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Inserting eqn. (26) in eqn. (27) and comparing term-by-term with eqn. (8) the macroscopic binding constants <IT>β</IT><SB><IT>n</IT>0</SB> follow, in agreement with Fig. 4.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Let us now consider the long chain limit as the last example.</annotationART></s> <s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">This model is equivalent to the so-called Ising model, which is amply discussed in the statistical mechanics literature.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27">27</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The largest eigenvalue of eqn. (25) can be evaluated analytically as.</annotationART></s> <s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">With eqns. (23) and (5), an analytical expression of the binding isotherm of a linear chain follows <IT>θ</IT>(<IT>z</IT>) = [2 + (<IT>λ</IT>(<IT>z</IT>)/<IT>z</IT>)(1 − <IT>zu</IT>)/(1 − <IT>u</IT> + <IT>λ</IT>(<IT>z</IT>)<IT>u</IT>)]<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that this isotherm is identical to the case of proton binding to a polyelectrolyte.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15 cit16 cit21">15,16,21</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="143"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the absence of interactions (<IT>E</IT> = 0 or <IT>u</IT> = 1), this isotherm reduces to the familiar Langmuir isotherm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="144"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">This behavior of this isotherm is shown in Fig. 5.</annotationART></s> <s sid="145"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the absence of interactions, the isotherm has the classical sigmoidal shape in the semi-logarithmic representation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="146"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">With increasing repulsive interactions, it develops a two-hump structure with an intermediate plateau at <IT>θ</IT> = 1/2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="147"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The intermediate plateau originates from the stabilization of an intermediate structure, where a bound metal ion alternates with an empty site, see Fig. 6(a).</annotationART></s> <s sid="148"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">With attractive interactions, a sharp transition takes place.</annotationART></s> <s sid="149"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Within this transitions, the metal ions cluster together, see Fig. 6(b).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="150"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">For repulsive interactions, the first hump in the binding isotherm is located at log <IT>a</IT> = log <IT>K</IT>, while the second hump at log <IT>a</IT> = log <IT>K</IT> −2<IT>ε</IT> where <IT>ε</IT> = −log<SB>10</SB><IT>u</IT> = <IT>E</IT>/(<IT>kT</IT>ln10).</annotationART></s> <s sid="151"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The location of these humps is simply understood.</annotationART></s> <s sid="152"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Initially, the metal ions bind to the empty sites, and thus with the microconstant log <IT>K</IT>. Beyond the plateau, the metal ions must bind between two occupied centers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="153"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">They have to overcome two pair interactions, and thus bind with a microconstant of log <IT>K</IT> − 2<IT>ε</IT>. </annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Competitive binding of several metal ions</HEADER><P><s sid="154"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj5" novelty="New" advantage="None">Let us now present the treatment of two types of metal ions using the three examples already discussed.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="155"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj6" novelty="New" advantage="None">The first example is the symmetric receptor with three equivalent sites.</annotationART></s> <s sid="156"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the presence of two metal ions, three types of complexes form.</annotationART></s> <s sid="157"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Complexes will form only with the first metal ion, provided the activity of the second metal ions is small, see Fig. 3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="158"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The same complexes form with the second metal ion, when the activity of the first metal ion is small.</annotationART></s> <s sid="159"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the intermediate situation, one obtains mixed complexes shown in Fig. 7.</annotationART></s> <s sid="160"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Obviously, there are only mixed complexes with two or three metal ions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="161"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Due to symmetry, the microspecies are again equivalent to the macrospecies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="162"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The complex with two different metal ions involves one pair interaction energy <IT>E</IT><SP>(12)</SP>, and this interaction will be abbreviated with the parameter <IT>u</IT><SB>12</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="163"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The macroconstant <IT>β</IT><SB>11</SB> is obtained by realizing that the microspecies has a symmetry number of six.</annotationART></s> <s sid="164"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The microconstants to remove each metal ion can be again evaluated by considering the affinities of the metal ions to the sites and by considering the pair interaction, and their inverse values are given in Fig. 7.</annotationART></s> <s sid="165"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">There is one complex involving three metal ions, with one from one kind and two from the other kind.</annotationART></s> <s sid="166"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">This complex involves three pair interactions, namely one between the same metal ions, and two between different ones.</annotationART></s> <s sid="167"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The macroconstants <IT>β</IT><SB>12</SB> and <IT>β</IT><SB>21</SB> of both complexes follow by taking into account the symmetry number of three.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="168"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Let us now consider the second example of the linear receptor with three sites, which has two equivalent terminal sites and one central site.</annotationART></s> <s sid="169"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the matter of illustration, let us assume that the affinity of the terminal and central sites are the same.</annotationART></s> <s sid="170"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Again, three types of complexes will form.</annotationART></s> <s sid="171"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Complexes with the first metal ion for sufficiently low activity of the second metal ion, complexes with the second metal ion for sufficiently low activity of the first metal ion, and mixed complexes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="172"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The complexes with one metal ion has been discussed above, see Fig. 4, while Fig. 8 summarizes the mixed complexes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="173"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">There are three nonequivalent microstates, each of which has a symmetry number of two.</annotationART></s> <s sid="174"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Either one metal ion occupies the central site, and a nearest neighbor pair interaction has to be considered in this case.</annotationART></s> <s sid="175"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">This case leads to two microstates.</annotationART></s> <s sid="176"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Alternatively, both metal ions occupy the terminal sites.</annotationART></s> <s sid="177"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">These three microspecies have to be considered, when the macroconstant <IT>β</IT><SB>11</SB> of the complex with two different metal ions is evaluated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="178"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The inverse values of the various microconstants to remove the respective metal ions are also indicated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="179"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">When three metal ions are bound, two sites are occupied by one type of the metal ion, and the remaining site with the second type.</annotationART></s> <s sid="180"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Two macrospecies are possible, depending whether there are two metal ions of type one or of type two.</annotationART></s> <s sid="181"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">In either situation, we have two microstates, depending on the fact whether the two terminal sites are occupied with the same metal ion or with two different ones.</annotationART></s> <s sid="182"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The macroconstants <IT>β</IT><SB>12</SB> and <IT>β</IT><SB>21</SB> are again obtained by considering the pair interactions and the symmetry numbers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="183"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The microconstants follow as above.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="184"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The transfer matrix formalism can be extended to competitive metal binding to linear receptors in a straightforward fashion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="185"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Consider two metal ions and assume nearest neighbor interactions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="186"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The transfer matrix reads where we have introduced the abbreviations <IT>z</IT><SB><IT>ω</IT></SB> = <IT>α</IT><SB><IT>ω</IT></SB><IT>K</IT><SP>(<IT>ω</IT>)</SP> and <IT>u</IT><SB><IT>ωη</IT></SB> = exp(−<IT>E</IT><SP>(<IT>ωη</IT>)</SP>/<IT>kT</IT>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="187"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The generating and terminating vectors are given by <B><IT>Ṽ</IT></B><SB>g</SB> = (1,0,0) and <B><IT>Ṽ</IT></B><SB>t</SB> = (1,1,1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="188"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Again, the properties of short chains can be evaluated analytically.</annotationART></s> <s sid="189"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">For example, the trimer (<IT>N</IT> = 3) is now described with a partition function.</annotationART></s> <s sid="190"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Again, by equating the coefficients of eqn. (32) with eqn. (8) one obtains the macroscopic binding constants <IT>β</IT><SB><IT>nm</IT></SB>, as shown in Figs. 4 and 8.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="191"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">In long chain limit, the largest eigenvalue cannot be evaluated analytically in the general case.</annotationART></s> <s sid="192"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, an analytical solution is possible if we specialize to the important case of equal pair interactions, namely <IT>u</IT><SB>11</SB> = <IT>u</IT><SB>12</SB> = <IT>u</IT><SB>22</SB> = <IT>u</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="193"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The solution can be expressed in terms of the solution of the linear chain for a single metal ion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="194"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Some algebra leads to the closed form of the adsorption isotherm where <IT>θ</IT>(<IT>z</IT>) is the mono-component isotherm given by eqn. (29) evaluated at <IT>z</IT> = <IT>z</IT><SB>1</SB> + <IT>z</IT><SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="195"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the absence of interactions, this isotherm reduces to the competitive Langmuir isotherm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="196"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the general case, when <IT>u</IT><SB>11</SB> ≠ <IT>u</IT><SB>12</SB> ≠ <IT>u</IT><SB>22</SB> the isotherm can be found numerically by evaluating the largest eigenvalue of the transfer matrix.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="197"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Figs. 9 and 10 illustrate the main features of these isotherms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="198"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the top of both figures, the binding isotherm for the first metal ion is shown as a function of its activity for fixed activities of the second metal ion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="199"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the bottom, the isotherm for the second metal is shown in the same representation.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="200"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results for the analytically soluble case with equal interaction parameters are shown in Fig. 9.</annotationART></s> <s sid="201"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">At low activities of the second metal ion, the receptor fills up through the alternating full-empty configuration discussed above, see Fig. 6(a).</annotationART></s> <s sid="202"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">At high activities of the second metal ion, the second metal exchanges with the first one.</annotationART></s> <s sid="203"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">This process follows the one-to-one exchange isotherm since there is no difference in the interactions between the two metal ions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="204"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">As a consequence, a disordered intermediate structure is formed (Fig. 6(c)).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="205"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">An example of unequal interaction parameters is shown in Fig. 10.</annotationART></s> <s sid="206"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">At low activities of the second metal ion, the receptor again fills up through the alternating full–empty configuration (Fig. 6(a)).</annotationART></s> <s sid="207"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">At high activities of the second metal ion, on the other hand, the second metal exchanges with the first one following an effective repulsive interaction between both metal ions, and leading to an intermediate plateau.</annotationART></s> <s sid="208"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The intermediate structure is again alternating (Fig. 6(d)).</annotationART></s> <s sid="209"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The binding isotherm of the second metal shows an interesting transition region, as the isotherm becomes steep in the intermediate activity regime.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="210"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">When both components are in excess, one can show that the model can be again reduced to the linear chain model with the effective pair interaction energy <IT>E</IT> = <IT>E</IT><SP>(11)</SP> + <IT>E</IT><SP>(22)</SP> − 2<IT>E</IT><SP>(12)</SP>or equivalently.</annotationART></s> <s sid="211"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The normalized activity now is <IT>z</IT> = <IT>z</IT><SB>1</SB><IT>u</IT>212/(<IT>z</IT><SB>2</SB><IT>u</IT>222) for the first metal ion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="212"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Depending on the magnitude of the individual interactions, at intermediate loading one can obtain random arrangements for <IT>E</IT> = 0, alternating arrangements for <IT>E</IT> &gt; 0, or clustering of the same metal ions for <IT>E</IT> &lt; 0 (see Fig. 6).</annotationART></s> <s sid="213"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the situation shown in Fig. 9 a random structure forms (<IT>E</IT> = 0), while in the one shown in Fig. 10 the alternating structure forms (<IT>E</IT> = 15 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> &gt; 0).</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Illustrations</HEADER><P><s sid="214"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj7" novelty="New" advantage="None">Multi-center complexes of lanthanides provide good examples for the mechanisms discussed here.</annotationART></s> <s sid="215"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj7" novelty="New" advantage="None">For this reason, we shall focus on those, but applications to other complexes should be envisioned as well.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Trimetallic inositol complexes</HEADER><P><s sid="216"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj8" novelty="New" advantage="None">As a first example, consider trimetallic complexes of 1,3,5-triamino-1,3,5-trideoxy-<IT>cis</IT>-inositol (taci) <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chemL1">L1</XREF>H<SB>3</SB> with Nd<SP>3+</SP>, Sm<SP>3+</SP>, and Eu<SP>3+</SP> (see Fig. 1 and 2).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="217"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod11" novelty="None" advantage="None">These complexes form in water according to the equilibrium 2<XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chemL1">L1</XREF>H<SB>3</SB> + <IT>x</IT>Nd<SP>3+</SP> + <IT>y</IT>Sm<SP>3+</SP> + (3 − <IT>x</IT> − <IT>y</IT>)Eu<SP>3+</SP> ⇌ [Nd<SB><IT>x</IT></SB>Sm<SB><IT>y</IT></SB>Eu<SB>3−<IT>x</IT>−<IT>y</IT></SB>(<XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chemL1">L1</XREF>)<SB>2</SB>]<SP>3+</SP> + 6H<SP>+</SP>where <IT>x</IT>, <IT>y</IT> = 0, 1, 2, 3 with <IT>x</IT> + <IT>y</IT> ≤ 3 and <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chemL1">L1</XREF><SP>3−</SP> corresponds to the deprotonated ligand.</annotationART></s> <s sid="218"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The measured equilibrium constants<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF> are reported in Table 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="219"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod12" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to apply the site binding model, which treats the binding of metal ions to one receptor, we consider the conditional equilibrium 2<XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chemL1">L1</XREF><SB>tot</SB> + <IT>x</IT>Nd<SP>3+</SP> + <IT>y</IT>Sm<SP>3+</SP> + (3 − <IT>x</IT> − <IT>y</IT>)Eu<SP>3+</SP> ⇌ [Nd<SB><IT>x</IT></SB>Sm<SB><IT>y</IT></SB>Eu<SB>3−<IT>x</IT>−<IT>y</IT></SB>(<XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chemL1">L1</XREF>)<SB>2</SB>]<SP>3+</SP>where <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chemL1">L1</XREF><SB>tot</SB> refers to all solution species of the ligand.</annotationART></s> <s sid="220"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="New" advantage="None">We choose pH 8 as reference.</annotationART></s> <s sid="221"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="New" advantage="None">From the known ionization constants of <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chemL1">L1</XREF>H<SB>3</SB>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28">28</REF> one can evaluate the conditional constants of these equilibria.</annotationART></s> <s sid="222"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">These conditional constants are given in Table 1, and only those will be considered further.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="223"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The site binding model introduces three microscopic binding constants <IT>K</IT><SP>(Nd)</SP>, <IT>K</IT><SP>(Sm)</SP> and <IT>K</IT><SP>(Eu)</SP> and six pair interaction energies <IT>E</IT><SP>(<IT>ωη</IT>)</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="224"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod13" novelty="None" advantage="None">We simplify the interaction energy matrix further by assuming that the diagonal elements <IT>E</IT><SP>(<IT>ωω</IT>)</SP> and off-diagonal elements <IT>E</IT><SP>(<IT>ωη</IT>)</SP> (<IT>ω</IT> ≠ <IT>η</IT>) are the same, respectively, leaving us with two pair interaction energies to be determined.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="225"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since only the complexes with three lanthanide ions exist, one cannot estimate both interaction energies independently.</annotationART></s> <s sid="226"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod13" novelty="None" advantage="None">For this reason, we set the diagonal term <IT>E</IT><SP>(<IT>ωω</IT>)</SP> = 18.7 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="227"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod13" novelty="None" advantage="None">This value can be estimated from interaction of an effective charge near +2, which are obtained from <IT>ab-initio</IT> calculations,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29">29</REF> and calculated for the distance of 3.61 Å invoking the Coulomb law in water.</annotationART></s> <s sid="228"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod13" novelty="None" advantage="None">With this value, the model contains four adjustable parameters, which we extract by non-linear least squares fit from the constants of the nine complexes containing one or two different metal ions (see Table 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="229"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">We obtain three microscopic constants log <IT>K</IT><SP>(Nd)</SP> = 10.56, log <IT>K</IT><SP>(Sm)</SP> = 12.20, and log <IT>K</IT><SP>(Eu)</SP> = 12.64.</annotationART></s> <s sid="230"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The off-diagonal pair interaction turns out to be <IT>E</IT><SP>(<IT>ωη</IT>)</SP> = 19.4 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> (<IT>ω</IT> ≠ <IT>η</IT>) and recall that we set <IT>E</IT><SP>(<IT>ωω</IT>)</SP> = 18.7 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="231"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fit cannot be substantially improved by allowing for further variation in the interaction parameters.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="232"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">To test the predictive capabilities of the model, we have calculated the constant of the ternary complex [NdSmEu(<XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chemL1">L1</XREF>)<SB>2</SB>]<SP>3+</SP> (see Table 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="233"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The experimental value of its common logarithm is 25.90 and the model predicts 25.98.</annotationART></s> <s sid="234"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This result can be considered as very satisfactory, since the model was calibrated on binary systems only.</annotationART></s> <s sid="235"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The model therefore captures the interactions between the different lanthanide ions properly.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="236"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">From this model description, we can extract various properties of interest.</annotationART></s> <s sid="237"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Naturally, once the macroscopic constants are known, the macrostate probabilities can be computed (see Fig. 11).</annotationART></s> <s sid="238"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The macrostate probabilities are displayed as a function of the free concentration ratio [Sm<SP>3+</SP>]/[Nd<SP>3+</SP>], where the free concentrations have been set equal to the activities for simplicity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="239"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The total concentration of the three metals was set to 0.1 M and the overall mole fraction <IT>x</IT><SB>Eu</SB> of the Eu<SP>3+</SP>-ion was fixed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="240"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the absence of Eu<SP>3+</SP>, one observes the classical evolution from the [Nd<SB>3</SB>(<XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chemL1">L1</XREF>)<SB>2</SB>]<SP>3+</SP> complex, through the mixed binary complexes [Nd<SB>2</SB>Sm(<XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chemL1">L1</XREF>)<SB>2</SB>]<SP>3+</SP> and [NdSm<SB>2</SB>(<XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chemL1">L1</XREF>)<SB>2</SB>]<SP>3+</SP>, to the [Sm<SB>3</SB>(<XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chemL1">L1</XREF>)<SB>2</SB>]<SP>3+</SP> complex (see Fig. 11(a)).</annotationART></s> <s sid="241"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">At <IT>x</IT><SB>Eu</SB> = 0.01, various mixed complexes appear, in particular the mixed ternary complex [NdSmEu(<XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chemL1">L1</XREF>)<SB>2</SB>]<SP>3+</SP> (see Fig. 11(b)).</annotationART></s> <s sid="242"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">At <IT>x</IT><SB>Eu</SB> = 0.1, binary complexes not containing Eu<SP>3+</SP> disappear, and the evolution is dominated by the complexes [Eu<SB>3</SB>(<XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chemL1">L1</XREF>)<SB>2</SB>]<SP>3+</SP>, [Eu<SB>2</SB>Sm(<XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chemL1">L1</XREF>)<SB>2</SB>]<SP>3+</SP>, [EuSm<SB>2</SB>(<XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chemL1">L1</XREF>)<SB>2</SB>]<SP>3+</SP> and [Sm<SB>3</SB>(<XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chemL1">L1</XREF>)<SB>2</SB>]<SP>3+</SP> (see Fig. 11(c)).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="243"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The microscopic picture is very simple in this case, as each macrostate consists of a single microstate (see Fig. 12).</annotationART></s> <s sid="244"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, as the pair interaction energies between different metal ions are somewhat larger than between the same metal ions, the microscopic constants increase with increasing number of different neighboring metal ions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="245"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">This effect leads to a destabilization of the metal ions in the mixed complexes (see Fig. 12).</annotationART></s> <s sid="246"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Moreover, one observes that Nd<SP>3+</SP> is bound the weakest in the complex, Sm<SP>3+</SP> is intermediate, and Eu<SP>3+</SP> is bound the strongest.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Linear bimetallic and trimetallic helicates</HEADER><P><s sid="247"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj9" novelty="New" advantage="None">As a second example, consider the monometallic and bimetallic helicates of the general formula [La<SB><IT>x</IT></SB>Eu<SB><IT>y</IT></SB>(<XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chemL2">L2</XREF>)<SB>3</SB>]<SP>3(<IT>x</IT>+<IT>y</IT>)+</SP> (<IT>x</IT>, <IT>y</IT> = 0, 1, 2) and trimetallic helicates of the formula [La<SB><IT>x</IT></SB>Eu<SB>3−<IT>x</IT></SB>(<XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chemL3">L3</XREF>)<SB>3</SB>]<SP>9+</SP> (<IT>x</IT> = 0, 1, 2, 3, see Fig. 1 and 2).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7 cit8">7,8</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="248"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod15" novelty="None" advantage="None">To analyze the formation constants, we assume that the bimetallic and trimetallic complexes have equal interactions, and thus we use the whole series to extract the microscopic parameters.</annotationART></s> <s sid="249"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The formation constants to be analyzed are summarized in Table 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="250"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">We note that the complexes [La<SB>2</SB>(<XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chemL3">L3</XREF>)<SB>3</SB>]<SP>6+</SP> and [Eu<SB>2</SB>(<XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chemL3">L3</XREF>)<SB>3</SB>]<SP>6+</SP> have been also described, but their structure is probably rather different, and they are not considered here.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF> </annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="251"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod16" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to simplify the structure of the model, let us consider the equilibrium constant of the exchange reaction [LaLa(<XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chemL2">L2</XREF>)<SB>3</SB>]<SP>6+</SP> + [EuEu(<XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chemL2">L2</XREF>)<SB>3</SB>]<SP>6+</SP> ⇌ 2[LaEu(<XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chemL2">L2</XREF>)<SB>3</SB>]<SP>6+</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="252"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod16" novelty="None" advantage="None">This exchange constant has been shown to be 4 within experimental error,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF> meaning that the fraction in eqn. (41) can be well approximated by unity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="253"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod16" novelty="None" advantage="None">In other words, the pair interaction energies obey the mixing rule.</annotationART></s> <s sid="254"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The off-diagonal terms are now simply approximated by an arithmetic average of the corresponding diagonal terms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="255"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that this mixing rule imposes no effective interactions in the saturated state (<IT>cf</IT>. eqn. (36)).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="256"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The site binding model now contains the following parameters.</annotationART></s> <s sid="257"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod17" novelty="None" advantage="None">These include microscopic binding constants for both metal ions to the terminal site <IT>K</IT>(La)t and <IT>K</IT>(Eu)t and to the central site <IT>K</IT>(La)c and <IT>K</IT>(Eu)c.</annotationART></s> <s sid="258"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod17" novelty="None" advantage="None">When we consider nearest neighbor interactions only, we now have two pair interaction energies, namely <IT>E</IT><SP>(LaLa)</SP>, <IT>E</IT><SP>(EuEu)</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="259"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The cross term <IT>E</IT><SP>(LaEu)</SP> is obtained from eqn. (42).</annotationART></s> <s sid="260"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod17" novelty="None" advantage="None">These six parameters can be extracted from the nine constants given in Table 2.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="261"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The experimental equilibrium constants can be described with the site binding model extremely well (see Table 2).</annotationART></s> <s sid="262"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The resulting parameters are the microscopic constants for the terminal sites log <IT>K</IT>(La)t = 16.70 and log <IT>K</IT>(Eu)t = 19.10.</annotationART></s> <s sid="263"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the central site we have log <IT>K</IT>(La)c = 17.91 and log <IT>K</IT>(EuEu)c = 21.08.</annotationART></s> <s sid="264"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The nearest neighbor pair interaction energies are <IT>E</IT><SP>(LaLa)</SP> = 47.5 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> and <IT>E</IT><SP>(EuEu)</SP> = 69.5 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="265"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Independent fit of the off-diagonal terms gives a value of the off-diagonal terms, which is very close to the value predicted by the mixing rule eqn. (42), and leads to no improvement to the fit.</annotationART></s> <s sid="266"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Consideration of a next nearest neighbor interaction energy gives equally no effect.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="267"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Based on these model parameters, various macroscopic and microscopic properties of these helicates can be predicted.</annotationART></s> <s sid="268"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 13 shows the macroscopic properties of the trimetallic helicates with the formula [La<SB><IT>x</IT></SB>Eu<SB>3−<IT>x</IT></SB>(<XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chemL3">L3</XREF>)<SB>3</SB>]<SP>9+</SP> (<IT>x</IT> = 0, 1, 2, 3).</annotationART></s> <s sid="269"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The macrostate probabilities, which are normalized to the total concentration of the saturated complexes, are shown in Fig. 13a.</annotationART></s> <s sid="270"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">As the concentration ratio [Eu<SP>3+</SP>]/[La<SP>3+</SP>] is increased, one goes through the characteristic sequence of the macrospecies [La<SB>3</SB>(<XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chemL3">L3</XREF>)<SB>3</SB>]<SP>9+</SP>, [La<SB>2</SB>Eu(<XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chemL3">L3</XREF>)<SB>3</SB>]<SP>9+</SP>, [LaEu<SB>2</SB>(<XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chemL3">L3</XREF>)<SB>3</SB>]<SP>9+</SP> and [Eu<SB>3</SB>(<XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chemL3">L3</XREF>)<SB>3</SB>]<SP>9+</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="271"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 13(b) shows the relative fraction of metal bound in the trimetallic helicates.</annotationART></s> <s sid="272"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">One observes that the exchange between Eu<SP>3+</SP> and La<SP>3+</SP> occurs in a relatively narrow concentration range.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="273"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">For each mixed complex (macrospecies), there are two possible structures (microspecies), each of which has always a fixed relative fraction within the macrostate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="274"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 14 summarizes their microscopic properties.</annotationART></s> <s sid="275"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">The macrospecies [La<SB>2</SB>Eu(<XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chemL3">L3</XREF>)<SB>3</SB>]<SP>6+</SP> consists of the two microspecies, the dominant asymmetric complex [EuLaLa(<XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chemL3">L3</XREF>)<SB>3</SB>]<SP>9+</SP> and the symmetric minority complex [LaEuLa(<XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chemL3">L3</XREF>)<SB>3</SB>]<SP>9+</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="276"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the other hand, in the macrospecies [LaEu<SB>2</SB>(<XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chemL3">L3</XREF>)<SB>3</SB>]<SP>9+</SP> the symmetric complex [EuLaEu(<XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chemL3">L3</XREF>)<SB>3</SB>]<SP>9+</SP> is dominant, while the asymmetric complex [LaEuEu(<XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chemL3">L3</XREF>)<SB>3</SB>]<SP>9+</SP> is in minority.</annotationART></s> <s sid="277"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">This observation is consistent with NMR results, since the two minority complexes could not be detected.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF> </annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="278"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">The microconstants to remove the respective metal ions from each site are summarized in Fig. 14.</annotationART></s> <s sid="279"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">One observes that the terminal metal ions are much more tightly bound that the central ones.</annotationART></s> <s sid="280"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">This effect is mainly caused by the additional electrostatic repulsion between the sites.</annotationART></s> <s sid="281"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">One further observes that the binding of La<SP>3+</SP> is weakened through the presence of neighboring Eu<SP>3+</SP> ions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="282"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" advantage="None">The same trend can be also observed for Eu<SP>3+</SP>, as its binding is also weakened by the presence of neighboring La<SP>3+</SP> ions.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Conclusion</HEADER><P><s sid="283"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this paper, we have presented a microscopic site binding model treating binding of several metal ions to preassembled multi-center receptors with well-defined binding sites within a statistical mechanical framework.</annotationART></s> <s sid="284"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None">We introduce the appropriate parameterization in terms of microscopic complexation constants and metal–metal pair interaction energies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="285"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None">From this model, the distinction between microscopic and macroscopic equilibria in these systems enters in a natural way.</annotationART></s> <s sid="286"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">With the present approach one can not only treat receptors with a small number of binding sites, but also macromolecular receptors capable of binding a large number of metal ions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="287"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res29" novelty="None" advantage="None">This situation is illustrated with linear chains.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="288"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res30" novelty="None" advantage="None">The applicability of the model has been illustrated with examples of lanthanide complexes, namely mixed trimetallic <IT>cis</IT>-inositol complexes and multi-metallic helicates.</annotationART></s> <s sid="289"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">In both situations, we find that consideration of pair interactions is important to obtain an acceptable description of the data.</annotationART></s> <s sid="290"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the general structure of the pair interaction matrix is not obvious at this point.</annotationART></s> <s sid="291"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">While for multi-metallic helicates a simple mixing rule appears to represent a reasonable approximation of the off-diagonal elements of the matrix, for the inositol complexes deviations from this rule are observed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="292"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Further experimental data sets are necessary to settle such questions in detail.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="293"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" advantage="None">Predictive capabilities of the site binding model were illustrated with the inositol complexes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="294"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, one can predict binding constants of metal complexes from a limited set of experimental data.</annotationART></s> <s sid="295"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res32" novelty="None" advantage="None">The example of the multi-metallic helicates did show that from a homologous series one can obtain a sufficient number of experimental quantities in order to fix the model parameters.</annotationART></s> <s sid="296"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None">In both cases, the model is able to predict all details of the microscopic equilibria, including microstate probabilities and microscopic equilibrium constants.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="297"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None">An analogous formulation can be applicable when the receptor undergoes conformational transitions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="298"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the parameters considered must be interpreted as thermal averages over the different conformational states.</annotationART></s> <s sid="299"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Moreover, more long-range interactions and eventually higher order interactions (<IT>e.g.</IT>, triplets) must be considered.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="300"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The present formulation certainly represents an appropriate way to treat binding of several metal ions to one type of multi-center receptor.</annotationART></s> <s sid="301"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con17" novelty="None" advantage="None">In most situations, however, the receptor is composed of different ligands, which have to assemble in order to form the complex.</annotationART></s> <s sid="302"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con18" novelty="None" advantage="None">As long as all complexes are composed of the same number of ligands (<IT>e.g.</IT>, helicates) the present approach applies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="303"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con19" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the other hand, when the complexes contain different numbers of sub-units, the present approach must be generalized in order to incorporate this situation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="304"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con19" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the protein literature,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30">30</REF> this problem is referred to as aggregation of ligands, but a useful parameterization of this problem is not known.</annotationART></s> <s sid="305"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">These aspects will be the subject of future studies.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
