<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b414641g" hasDoc="yes" version="1184" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Infrared spectrum of the NH<SB>4</SB>-<IT>d</IT><SB><IT>n</IT></SB><SP>+</SP> cation trapped in solid neon</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The NH<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP> cation has been stabilized in solid neon in sufficient concentration for the identification of both of its infrared-active vibrational fundamentals, which appear within a few wavenumbers of the gas-phase band centers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Systematic alteration of the concentrations and positions of introduction of NH<SB>3</SB> and H<SB>2</SB> in the discharge sampling experiments demonstrated that the highest yield of NH<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP> resulted when both the NH<SB>3</SB> and the H<SB>2</SB> were introduced downstream from a discharge through pure neon.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this configuration, each of these molecules can be ionized by excited neon atoms and their resonance radiation (16.6 eV to 16.85 eV), but fragmentation is minimized.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both infrared-active vibrational fundamentals of ND<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP> and several fundamentals of each of the partially deuterium-substituted isotopomers of NH<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP> were also identified.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Evidence is presented for complexation of NH<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP> with an H atom or with one or more H<SB>2</SB> molecules.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="I.">Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Because of the chemical and biological importance of the ammonium cation, NH<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP>, there have been many observations of its infrared absorption spectrum in the strongly interacting environments of ionic crystals and polar solvents.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast, studies of its spectroscopic behavior in the absence of these interactions are sparse.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The first gas-phase observations of NH<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP> were concurrent studies by Crofton and co-workers<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2">1,2</REF> and by Schäfer and co-workers,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3 cit4">3,4</REF> which yielded the assignment of the infrared-active stretching fundamental, <IT>ν</IT><SB>3</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The other infrared-active fundamental of gas-phase NH<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP>, <IT>ν</IT><SB>4</SB>, was later observed in diode laser studies.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6">5,6</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Crofton and co-workers<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">2</REF> also analyzed the <IT>ν</IT><SB>3</SB> band of ND<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP>, and, in a study of the zero-kinetic-energy photoelectron spectrum of ND<SB>4</SB>, Signorell and co-workers<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF> obtained the rotational constant of ground-state ND<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP> with an uncertainty of 0.004 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Except for the analysis of one vibrational fundamental of NH<SB>3</SB>D<SP>+</SP> by Nakanaga and Amano,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF> there have been no experimental studies of the partially deuterium-substituted ammonium cations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The CCSD(T)/cc-pVTZ <IT>ab initio</IT> calculations, including anharmonic corrections, by Martin and Lee<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF> of the vibrational fundamentals of NH<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP> and all of its deuterium-substituted isotopomers provide tentative information regarding the spectroscopic properties of these species.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Experiments in this laboratory have led to the stabilization of a number of small molecular ions in concentration sufficient for infrared identification.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the study of the infrared spectrum of NH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF> a weak absorption appeared near the position of the <IT>ν</IT><SB>4</SB> fundamental of gas-phase NH<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP>, 1447.22 cm<SP>−1</SP>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6">5,6</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to determine whether this peak was indeed contributed by NH<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP> and, if so, to optimize the conditions for NH<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP> production, further studies were conducted using several different sampling configurations and introducing additional H<SB>2</SB> into the system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">As will be shown in the following discussion, not only did these studies confirm the identification of NH<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP>, but they yielded the first spectroscopic identification of <IT>ν</IT><SB>4</SB> of ND<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP> and of many of the vibrational fundamentals of the partially deuterium-substituted isotopomers.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="II.">Experimental details<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF></HEADER><P><s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ammonia samples used for these studies were the same as had been used for the previous series of experiments<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF> concerned with the identification of isotopomers of NH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">These samples were freed of relatively volatile impurities by freezing at 77 K and pumping on the resulting solid.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The H<SB>2</SB> and D<SB>2</SB> (Matheson Gas Products, Inc)., HD (97%, Cambridge Isotope Laboratories, Inc)., and neon (Spectra Gases, Inc., Research Grade, 99.999%) were used without further purification.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Sample mixtures were prepared using standard vacuum procedures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">A number of initial experiments were conducted in order to establish optimal conditions for the stabilization of NH<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP> and its isotopomers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">For these studies, the concentrations of the reactants were varied.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The concentrations which will be given in the description of the initial experiments were representative.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The optimum Ne : H<SB>2</SB> : NH<SB>3</SB> mole ratio was found to be 400 : 6 : 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">After this had been established, more detailed isotopic substitution studies were conducted at a Ne : H<SB>2</SB>-<IT>d</IT><SB><IT>m</IT></SB> : NH<SB>3</SB>-<IT>d</IT><SB><IT>n</IT></SB> mole ratio of 400 : 6 : 1 or 400 : 5 : 1.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Isotopically enriched ammonia undergoes significant isotopic exchange with ammonia which has previously been adsorbed on the walls of deposition line.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The extent of isotopic enrichment improved as a series of experiments on a given isotopically enriched sample proceeded.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Flowing some of the sample mixture through the deposition system and cell before the cell was cooled for the experiment enhanced the extent of isotopic enrichment.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">A Helitran (APD Cryogenics.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Inc). continuous transfer liquid helium cell maintained at 4.3 K was used for all of the experiments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The deposition configuration has previously been described,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF> as has been the setup used for microwave excitation.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In typical ion production experiments, pure neon is subjected to a microwave discharge while it passes through a quartz tube that has a coarse pinhole in the end.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The molecule of interest, mixed with a large excess of neon, is introduced into the cell slightly beyond the discharge tube, and the excited neon atoms and their resonance radiation interact with the molecule outside the pinhole and on the cryogenic surface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In some of the preliminary experiments, the two deposition lines were interchanged, so that the ammonia-containing mixture passed through the microwave discharge and additional neon was introduced into the sample without exposure to the discharge.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In a few experiments, a small concentration of H<SB>2</SB> was added to the neon sample flowing through the discharge tube.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The absorption spectra of the sample deposits were obtained using a Bomem DA3.002 Fourier transform interferometer with transfer optics that have been described previously.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Observations were conducted with a resolution of 0.2 cm<SP>−1</SP> between 400 and 5000 cm<SP>−1</SP> using a globar source, a KBr beamsplitter, and a wide-band HgCdTe detector cooled to 77 K. Data were accumulated for each spectrum over a period of at least 15 min.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The resulting spectrum was ratioed against a similar one taken without a deposit on the cryogenic mirror.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Under these conditions, the positions of the prominent, nonblended atmospheric water vapor lines between 1385 and 1900 cm<SP>−1</SP> and between 3620 and 3900 cm<SP>−1</SP>, observed in a calibration scan, agreed to within 0.01 cm<SP>−1</SP> with the high-resolution values reported by Toth.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16 cit17">16,17</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Based on previous investigations, with this experimental configuration the standard uncertainty (type B) in the determination of the positions of absorption maxima for molecules trapped in solid neon is ±0.1 cm<SP>−1</SP> (coverage factor, <IT>k</IT> = 1, <IT>i.e.</IT>, 1<IT>σ</IT>).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Information on photoinduced changes in the matrix sample was obtained by exposing the deposit to various wavelength ranges of visible and ultraviolet radiation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">For a few studies, a tungsten background source was used with a 780 nm (Schott glass type RG780) or a 630 nm (Corning glass type 2403) short-wavelength cutoff filter.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since no changes were detected in the product spectra under those irradiation conditions, most of the sample irradiations were conducted using a medium-pressure mercury arc with a filter of Corning glass type 3384, 3389 or 7740 or without a filter to provide a short-wavelength cutoff of approximately 490, 420, 280 or 250 nm, respectively.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="III.">Results and discussion</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="A.">Stabilization of NH<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP></HEADER><P><s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The initial experiments were focused on determining the conditions that produce the greatest intensity of the product absorption which was previously detected<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF> at 1442.5 cm<SP>−1</SP> when a Ne : NH<SB>3</SB> sample was codeposited with a beam of discharged neon atoms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results of these experiments are summarized in Fig. 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">The initial strategy was to pass the Ne : NH<SB>3</SB> mixture, rather than pure neon, through the microwave discharge and, to improve the isolation of the products in the solid deposit, diluting the discharged material with an approximately equal amount of pure neon that had not been excited in the discharge.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Similar conditions have been used in many laboratories to produce molecular fragments for spectroscopic study.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">As is shown in trace (a), a weak absorption at 1442.5 cm<SP>−1</SP> resulted.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">When a mixture with a greater concentration of NH<SB>3</SB> was used, as in trace (b), a somewhat more intense product absorption appeared.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the isolation properties of the neon matrix would be likely to degrade at still higher concentrations of NH<SB>3</SB>, the introduction of H<SB>2</SB> was next tried.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The first such study, shown in trace (c), involved passing a Ne : H<SB>2</SB> : NH<SB>3</SB> = 400 : 4 : 1 mixture through the microwave discharge.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Further enhancement of the 1442.5 cm<SP>−1</SP> absorption resulted.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">When, as in trace (d), a still higher concentration of H<SB>2</SB> was present in the sample mixture, the 1442.5 cm<SP>−1</SP> peak and satellite absorptions at 1441.2 and 1440.9 cm<SP>−1</SP> grew still more.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the experiments of traces (b) through (d), a new absorption at 3357.5 cm<SP>−1</SP> appeared and grew in prominence.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">It was not feasible to increase the H<SB>2</SB> concentration in the mixture passed through the discharge tube beyond about 2.5%, the value employed for the experiment of trace (d); at higher concentrations spontaneous warmups of the deposit frequently occurred.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The experiment of trace (e) more closely followed the procedure which has typically been used for ion production studies in this laboratory.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Ne : NH<SB>3</SB> mixture was introduced into the system downstream from the discharge region.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">A Ne : H<SB>2</SB> = 39 mixture was passed through the microwave discharge, providing a source not only of excited neon atoms and their resonance radiation but also of H atoms and undissociated H<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although care had been taken to match the sample size and deposition time in the other experiments in this comparison, only a limited amount of liquid helium was available to conduct the experiment shown in trace (e).</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Despite the smaller sample size, both the absorption pattern near 1442.5 cm<SP>−1</SP> and that near 3357.5 cm<SP>−1</SP> were more prominent than in the earlier studies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Finally, an experiment was conducted using an undischarged Ne : H<SB>2</SB> : NH<SB>3</SB> = 400 : 6 : 1 sample mixture and passing pure neon through the microwave discharge.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">As is shown in trace (f) of Fig. 1, the absorptions of interest were approximately doubled in intensity, compared to those of trace (e).</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Subsequent experiments were conducted using the same sampling configuration and approximately the same concentrations in the sample mixture as had been used for the experiment of trace (f).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The assignment of the absorption at 1442.5 cm<SP>−1</SP> to the <IT>ν</IT><SB>4</SB> fundamental of NH<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP> is supported not only by its proximity to the gas-phase band center of that species but also by the enhancement in its intensity as hydrogen is added to the system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The absorption at 3357.5 cm<SP>−1</SP> and a less intense absorption at 3361.0 cm<SP>−1</SP> that grow at a rate proportional to that of the structured 1442.5 cm<SP>−1</SP> absorption in the experiments summarized by Fig. 1 lie suitably close to the 3343.14 cm<SP>−1</SP> gas-phase band center<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2 cit3 cit4">1–4</REF> of <IT>ν</IT><SB>3</SB> of NH<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP> for the corresponding assignment.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">A series of molecular beam studies by Dopfer, Maier and co-workers, recently reviewed by Bieske and Dopfer,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF> have shown that the H-stretching vibrational band centers of complexes of the rare gases with protonated molecules are often shifted to appreciably lower frequencies because of proton sharing with the rare gas atom.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the proton affinity of NH<SB>3</SB> is relatively high, and the <IT>ν</IT><SB>3</SB> band center of gas-phase NH<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP> complexed to a single neon atom appears at 3344.0 cm<SP>−1</SP>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19">19</REF> very close to the band center for the uncomplexed cation.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">When both NH<SB>3</SB> and H<SB>2</SB> are present in the sample deposit, the detailed structure of the infrared absorptions of the NH<SB>3</SB> differs from that characteristic of simple Ne : NH<SB>3</SB> deposits.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20 cit21">20,21</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">This phenomenon is attributed to complex formation between H<SB>2</SB> and NH<SB>3</SB>, previously reported by Moroz and co-workers.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Further discussion of perturbations to the spectrum of NH<SB>3</SB> is beyond the scope of the present study.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the experiment of Fig. 1(f), as well as in the other experiments here reported, the presence of H<SB>2</SB> or its isotopomers greatly inhibits the stabilization of NH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> or its isotopomers.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">All of the absorptions shown in Fig. 1 except that of NH<SB>3</SB> at 3350 cm<SP>−1</SP> were somewhat diminished in intensity when the sample was exposed for a few minutes to mercury-arc radiation of wavelength longer than 490 nm and were destroyed when a 420 nm cutoff filter was instead used or the filter was removed during the irradiation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The absorptions of ammonia showed little or no change as a result of this irradiation.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="B.">Isotopic dependence of the NH<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP> absorptions</HEADER><P><s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Still further support for the assignment of the 1442.5 and 3357.5 cm<SP>−1</SP> neon-matrix absorptions to the two infrared-active vibrational fundamentals of NH<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP> has been obtained from experiments on isotopically substituted samples.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, these experiments have yielded the first infrared spectroscopic data for several isotopomers of NH<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">As is shown in Table 1, the 1442.5 and 3357.5 cm<SP>−1</SP> neon-matrix absorptions also agree well with the positions obtained for these two vibrational fundamentals of NH<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP> in the CCSD(T)/cc-pVTZ calculations including anharmonic corrections by Martin and Lee.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although these workers obtained vibrational fundamental frequencies for all of the <SP>14</SP>NH<SB>4</SB>-<IT>d</IT><SB><IT>n</IT></SB><SP>+</SP> species, estimates of their relative intensities were not reported.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="New" advantage="None">Since these would also be helpful in the assignments and since some of the experiments were conducted using ammonia samples which were enriched in nitrogen-15, we performed calculations for the various isotopomers of the ammonium cation at the RMP2/6-311++G(3<IT>df</IT>,3<IT>pd</IT>) level using the Gaussian 98 program package.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The intensities estimated for the vibrational fundamentals of the <SP>14</SP>NH<SB>4</SB>-<IT>d</IT><SB><IT>n</IT></SB><SP>+</SP>species by these calculations are included, in parentheses, in Table 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Assignments of observed absorptions are also summarized.</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The observations leading to these assignments are described in the following discussion.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">NH<SB>3</SB>D<SP>+</SP> should have two relatively prominent deformation fundamentals, one only slightly shifted from the triply degenerate deformation fundamental of NH<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP>, the other near 1278.6 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The latter spectral region is shown in Fig. 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">As is shown in trace (a), from the same experiment on a Ne : H<SB>2</SB> : NH<SB>3</SB> sample as that illustrated in Fig. 1(f), when the sample was not enriched with deuterium no absorption appeared between 1265 and 1280 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None">In another experiment in which HD was substituted for H<SB>2</SB>, shown in trace (b) of Fig. 2, a weak, photosensitive new absorption appeared at 1277.3 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The absorption pattern near 1442.5 cm<SP>−1</SP> was unchanged from that obtained using H<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the NH-stretching region, a photosensitive absorption with a high frequency shoulder appeared at 3353.7 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs19" novelty="None" advantage="None">In still another experiment using D<SB>2</SB> instead of H<SB>2</SB>, shown in Fig. 2(c), the 1277.3 cm<SP>−1</SP> absorption appeared with slightly lower intensity and was accompanied by several photosensitive lower frequency absorptions, the most prominent of them at 1274.8, 1273.1, 1272.4 and 1270.9 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Because of the facile isotopic exchange of ND<SB>3</SB> in the vacuum system, spectra obtained in experiments with more extensive deuterium enrichment are quite complicated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs20" novelty="None" advantage="None">Various spectral regions in which most of the product absorptions appear are shown in Figs. 3–8.</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs20" novelty="None" advantage="None">Each of these figures shows the results from the same set of four experiments, arranged in the order of increasing deuterium enrichment.</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs21" novelty="None" advantage="None">The traces labeled (a) were obtained for the same sample as that used for Fig. 1(f) and for Fig. 2(a), with no deuterium enrichment.</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs22" novelty="None" advantage="None">The traces labeled (b) were obtained in an experiment on a Ne : H<SB>2</SB> : ND<SB>3</SB> : NH<SB>3</SB> = 400 : 5 : 0.7 : 0.3 sample, those labeled (c) in a study of a Ne : H<SB>2</SB> : ND<SB>3</SB> = 400 : 5 : 1 sample, and those labeled (d) in a study of a Ne : D<SB>2</SB> : ND<SB>3</SB> sample.</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs23" novelty="None" advantage="None">The latter sample achieved the highest extent of deuterium enrichment attained in this series of experiments.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs24" novelty="None" advantage="None">As is shown in Fig. 3(d), highly structured, photosensitive absorption appeared between 1085 and 1097 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs24" novelty="None" advantage="None">The strongest absorption maximum was at 1092.0 cm<SP>−1</SP>, but absorptions at 1093.6 and 1093.1 cm<SP>−1</SP> were only slightly weaker.</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs24" novelty="None" advantage="None">Other relatively prominent absorptions appeared at 1091.6, 1089.7, 1088.3 and 1086.8 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The 1092.0 cm<SP>−1</SP> absorption and its satellites lie close to the 1094.9 cm<SP>−1</SP> position calculated for the previously unreported <IT>ν</IT><SB>4</SB> fundamental of ND<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">(Here and in the following discussion, all of the calculated positions for isotopomers of the ammonium cation – summarized in Table 1 – are those obtained in the study by Martin and Lee.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF>)</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The photosensitive absorption at 1103.4 cm<SP>−1</SP>, most prominent in traces (b) and (c) of Fig. 3, also lies close to the absorption of NHD<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> which is calculated to appear at 1101.0 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Photosensitive absorptions at 1099.6 and 1094.6 cm<SP>−1</SP> may possibly be contributed by the same fundamental of NHD<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs25" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the 1130 to 1150 cm<SP>−1</SP> spectral region, shown in Fig. 4, a sharp, photosensitive absorption appeared at 1139.9 cm<SP>−1</SP> in the experiments with a moderate extent of deuterium enrichment.</annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs26" novelty="None" advantage="None">This peak was accompanied by less well defined, photosensitive peaks at 1133.5 and 1131.6 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The correlation of the 1139.9 cm<SP>−1</SP> peak with the 1140.6 cm<SP>−1</SP> peak calculated for NHD<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> is evident.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs27" novelty="None" advantage="None">The 1260 to 1280 cm<SP>−1</SP> spectral region is shown for these four samples in Fig. 5, which may be compared to the related observations for samples prepared using HD or D<SB>2</SB> illustrated in Fig. 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the experiments of Fig. 5(b) and 5(c), as in those of Fig. 2(b) and 2(c), the most prominent photosensitive product absorption appears at 1277.3 cm<SP>−1</SP>, very close to the 1278.6 cm<SP>−1</SP> position calculated for one of the vibrational fundamentals of NH<SB>3</SB>D<SP>+</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">Within the experimental error, the most prominent satellite absorptions, at 1273.2 and 1272.5 cm<SP>−1</SP>, correspond with relatively prominent peaks in the experiment of Fig. 2(c).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs28" novelty="None" advantage="None">As is shown in Fig. 6, a sharp, photosensitive absorption appears at 1365.9 cm<SP>−1</SP> in the spectrum of samples with an intermediate extent of deuterium substitution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">This peak corresponds well with the most intense deformation fundamental of NH<SB>2</SB>D<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP>, calculated to appear at 1363.5 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs29" novelty="None" advantage="None">Satellite absorptions also appear at 1363.4 and 1357.0 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs30" novelty="None" advantage="None">The 1430 to 1450 cm<SP>−1</SP> spectral region is shown for this set of samples in Fig. 7.</annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs31" novelty="None" advantage="None">The photosensitive absorption at 1442.5 cm<SP>−1</SP> and its less intense companions at 1441.2 and 1440.9 cm<SP>−1</SP> decrease rapidly in intensity as the extent of deuterium substitution of the sample grows.</annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs32" novelty="None" advantage="None">A weak, photosensitive absorption appears at 1447.9 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">Possibly this absorption is contributed by a deformation vibration of NH<SB>3</SB>D<SP>+</SP>, detectable at the concentration of NH<SB>3</SB>D<SP>+</SP> achieved in the experiments shown in Fig. 7(b) and 7(c) but not in the experiments of Fig. 2(b) and 2(c).</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, this identification is tentative.</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the experiments of Fig. 7(b) and 7(c), a weak, sharp, photosensitive absorption also appeared at 1425.0 cm<SP>−1</SP>, close to the 1426.9 cm<SP>−1</SP> position calculated for a deformation fundamental of NHD<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs33" novelty="None" advantage="None">The 2500 cm<SP>−1</SP> spectral region, characteristic of the ND-stretching vibrations of both uncharged deuterium-substituted ammonia and the fully and partially deuterium substituted ammonium cation, shows a very complicated absorption spectrum.</annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">The most prominent photosensitive peak in the highest deuterium enrichment study lies at 2502.1 cm<SP>−1</SP>, in good agreement with the calculated position of 2492.0 cm<SP>−1</SP> and the gas-phase band center<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">2</REF> observed at 2495.0 cm<SP>−1</SP> for <IT>ν</IT><SB>3</SB> of ND<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" advantage="None">The 3340 to 3370 cm<SP>−1</SP> absorption region, shown in Fig. 8, includes several NH-stretching absorptions of NH<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP> and its partially deuterium-substituted isotopomers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs34" novelty="None" advantage="None">In trace (a), the most prominent absorption is the photosensitive peak at 3357.5 cm<SP>−1</SP>, which has a less intense companion at 3361.0 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs35" novelty="None" advantage="None">The major peak acquires a lower frequency counterpart at 3354.2 cm<SP>−1</SP> when some deuterium is introduced into the ammonia molecule, as in traces (b) and (c).</annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None">The assignment of that absorption to NH<SB>3</SB>D<SP>+</SP> is consistent with the calculations and with the identification<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF> of the gas-phase band center of <IT>ν</IT><SB>4</SB> of NH<SB>3</SB>D<SP>+</SP> at 3341.08 cm<SP>−1</SP>, 2.06 cm<SP>−1</SP> below the position of the NH<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP> stretching absorption.</annotationART></s> <s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although the peak at 3350.0 cm<SP>−1</SP> did not decrease on mercury-arc irradiation of the deposits of traces (a) and (b), it did decrease in the experiment of trace (c), suggesting that in the latter experiment much or all of the absorption at that frequency arises from NH<SB>2</SB>D<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the experiments of traces (b) and (c), a photosensitive absorption (not shown in Fig. 8) also appeared at 3306.4 cm<SP>−1</SP>, a position appropriate for its assignment to the second NH-stretching fundamental of NH<SB>2</SB>D<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Experiments were also conducted on samples prepared using <SP>15</SP>NH<SB>3</SB> and <SP>15</SP>ND<SB>3</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res29" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results were analogous to those already described, except that each of the absorptions is shifted to a slightly lower frequency.</annotationART></s> <s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs36" novelty="None" advantage="None">In Table 2, the observed shifts are compared with those obtained from RMP2/6-311++G(3df,3pd) calculations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp12" novelty="None" advantage="None">To correct for anharmonicity, each vibration calculated for the nitrogen-15 substituted cation was scaled by a factor derived from the ratio of the observed vibrational frequency for the nitrogen-14 substituted species to the corresponding calculated value.</annotationART></s> <s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res30" novelty="None" advantage="None">None of the observed isotopic shifts deviated from the calculated shift by more than 0.9 cm<SP>−1</SP>, providing further support for the proposed assignments.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="C.">Processes which occur in the matrix</HEADER><P><s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results of all of the earlier studies in this laboratory using a beam of pure neon that had been passed through a microwave discharge are consistent with ion production by interaction of a suitable precursor with excited neon atoms and their resonance radiation, in the 16.6 to 16.85 eV energy range.</annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since those energies, for the first group of excited states of the neon atom, exceed the first ionization energy of both NH<SB>3</SB> (10.17 eV <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11 cit24">11,24</REF>) and H<SB>2</SB> (15.43 eV <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25">25</REF>), the two reactionsH<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP> + NH<SB>3</SB> → NH<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP> + HandH<SB>2</SB> + NH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> → NH<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP> + Hmay both occur in the region between the pinhole in the discharge tube and the cryogenic surface, as well as on the surface itself.</annotationART></s> <s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, because of the large disparity between the values of the first ionization energies of H<SB>2</SB> and NH<SB>3</SB>, collisional charge exchange between H<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP> and NH<SB>3</SB> is likely to occur.</annotationART></s> <s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, Reaction (2) would be likely to predominate.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Early gas phase studies<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26 cit27">26,27</REF> determined a relatively slow rate (<IT>k</IT> = 5 × 10<SP>−13</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>) rate for Reaction (2) at room temperature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">This rate increased as the temperature was raised, permitting estimation of an activation energy of 8.8 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> (2.1 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">When the reaction mixture was cooled, it was found<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28 cit29">28,29</REF> that the rate levels off between 80 and 100 K. At lower temperatures, the rate increases again.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30 cit31">30,31</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Studies of isotopically enriched samples determined<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29 cit32">29,32</REF> that the rate of the reaction between D<SB>2</SB> and NH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> is only about 10% as great as that for H<SB>2</SB> and NH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Several laboratories<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit32 cit33 cit34 cit35">32–35</REF> have also studied the comparative yields of NH<SB>3</SB>D<SP>+</SP> and NH<SB>2</SB>D<SP>+</SP> in the D<SB>2</SB> + NH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> system for various NH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> vibrational energies and center-of-mass collision energies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although NH<SB>3</SB>D<SP>+</SP> is always the predominant product, at higher collision energies some NH<SB>2</SB>D<SP>+</SP> is also formed.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Herbst and co-workers<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit36">36</REF> obtained good agreement between their calculated rate coefficients and the values derived from the experimental data for a mechanism that postulated the initial formation of a NH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP>⋯H<SB>2</SB> complex, bound by 5.9(1.3) kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>, or 1.4(3) kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>, which has a long lifetime at low temperatures and decomposes by tunneling.</annotationART></s> <s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The exit channel complex, NH<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP>⋯H, is bound by less than 3 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> and readily decomposes to form NH<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP> + H. Their model is consistent with the observed reaction rates for the deuterium-substituted species.</annotationART></s> <s sid="143"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Herbst and co-workers also calculated the rates for the three-body reaction (which also involved a helium atom) and found that the results were compatible with other observations.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30">30</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="144"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The three-body reaction differs by collisional stabilization of the NH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP>⋯H<SB>2</SB> complex, which is found still to be able to undergo tunneling to form the products on a time scale shorter than that of the observations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="145"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">These conditions are likely to predominate during matrix depositions and in solid neon.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="146"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The structure observed for the vibrational fundamentals of the NH<SB>4</SB>-<IT>d</IT><SB><IT>n</IT></SB><SP>+</SP> species may arise in part from the trapping of the molecules in various types of site in the solid neon.</annotationART></s> <s sid="147"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Site splittings have been observed for NH<SB>3</SB><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20 cit21">20,21</REF> and for many other molecules trapped in the solid rare gases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="148"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, other phenomena must be invoked to explain the disparity between the absorption patterns observed for <IT>ν</IT><SB>4</SB> of NH<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP> and ND<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="149"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The complicated vibrational absorption patterns observed in the present series of experiments might arise from molecular rotation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="150"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Simple uncharged molecular hydrides usually can rotate in a neon matrix.</annotationART></s> <s sid="151"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rotation of ammonia in solid neon has previously been studied.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20 cit21">20,21</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="152"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">High-resolution infrared observations<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit37">37</REF> of a very dilute Ne : CH<SB>4</SB> sample suggested that although CH<SB>4</SB>, which is geometrically similar to NH<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP>, can rotate in argon and the heavier rare-gas matrices, it cannot rotate in solid neon.</annotationART></s> <s sid="153"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Beginning with the high-resolution observations by Momose and co-workers,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit38">38</REF> the rotation of CH<SB>4</SB> in solid parahydrogen has been extensively studied.</annotationART></s> <s sid="154"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">At 4.8 K, the most prominent absorption of each of the two infrared-active vibrational fundamentals of CH<SB>4</SB> is contributed by the R(0) transition.</annotationART></s> <s sid="155"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Other components of the rotational structure are symmetrically placed about it, with spacings of approximately 5 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="156"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although, with appropriately smaller spacings, a similar pattern of absorptions is observed for ND<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP>, the pattern for NH<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP> is quite different.</annotationART></s> <s sid="157"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" advantage="None">Whether NH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> and other ions of the simple hydrides can rotate in a neon matrix is not known with certainty.</annotationART></s> <s sid="158"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, there is abundant evidence that the rotation of uncharged hydride molecules is suppressed in the presence of an ion field.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="159"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, other explanations for the observed structure must also be considered.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="160"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">A major contributor to the observed structure is likely to be complexation of NH<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP> by other species present in the matrix.</annotationART></s> <s sid="161"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res32" novelty="None" advantage="None">The interaction energy for the NH<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP>⋯NH<SB>3</SB> pair<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit39">39</REF> is relatively large, but in the present experiments the probability of collisional interaction between NH<SB>3</SB> and NH<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP> is much smaller than that between H<SB>2</SB> and NH<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="162"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">At the H<SB>2</SB> concentrations necessary to obtain an appreciable yield of NH<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP>, the stabilization of that species with one or more nearest neighbor H<SB>2</SB> molecules is highly probable.</annotationART></s> <s sid="163"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Calculations by Urban and co-workers<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit40">40</REF> indicate that up to eight H<SB>2</SB> molecules can complex with NH<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="164"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The first solvation shell is filled by four H<SB>2</SB> molecules, each oriented with its axis perpendicular to that of the NH bond with which it interacts.</annotationART></s> <s sid="165"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">At the MP4 level, the solvation energy of each of these four H<SB>2</SB> molecules is approximately 10 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> (2.4 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="166"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">When deuterium atoms are introduced into the system, interactions with HD and with D<SB>2</SB> will also occur, resulting in small changes in the infrared absorption pattern.</annotationART></s> <s sid="167"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res33" novelty="None" advantage="None">Because of the several possible interactions, the absorption pattern in the deuterium-substitution experiments may become quite complex, as is observed.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="168"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The calculations by Herbst and co-workers<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit36">36</REF> indicate that the transition state for the reaction between NH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> and H<SB>2</SB> rearranges into a weakly bound NH<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP>⋯H complex, raising the possibility that this entrance channel complex may also contribute to the observed spectrum.</annotationART></s> <s sid="169"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Some of the H atoms are likely to be formed with sufficient kinetic energy to escape from the site of their production.</annotationART></s> <s sid="170"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the presence of an abundance of neon atoms will encourage collisional deactivation of the initially formed complex.</annotationART></s> <s sid="171"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs37" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results of calculations of the positions of the vibrational fundamentals of NH<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP> and ND<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP> complexed with a single H or D atom, performed at the UMP2/6-311++G(3df,3pd) level using the Gaussian 03 program package,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit41">41</REF> are summarized in Table 3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="172"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res34" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reduction in symmetry from <IT>T</IT><SB>d</SB> to <IT>C</IT><SB>3v</SB> because of complex formation leads to a splitting of approximately 40 cm<SP>−1</SP> in the infrared-active NH-stretching vibration and 8 cm<SP>−1</SP> in the infrared-active deformation vibration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="173"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res34" novelty="None" advantage="None">The magnitudes of these splittings are independent of whether an H atom or a D atom participates in the complex.</annotationART></s> <s sid="174"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res35" novelty="None" advantage="None">The calculated splitting of the deformation vibration could explain some of the observed structure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="175"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res35" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, a lower frequency component of the NH-stretching fundamental was not identified.</annotationART></s> <s sid="176"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res35" novelty="None" advantage="None">Such an absorption may have been obscured by one of the prominent absorptions of the photolytically stable NH<SB>3</SB>⋯(H<SB>2</SB>)<SB><IT>n</IT></SB> species which appeared in these experiments at 3314, 3319 and 3333 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="177"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, the contribution of infrared absorptions of the exit channel complex to the observed spectrum remains uncertain.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="178"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">As in the earlier study of the infrared spectrum of NH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF> the identity of the anion(s) which provide for the requisite overall charge neutrality of the sample deposit is not revealed by the present experiments, presumably because these species are weak infrared absorbers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="179"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">A leading candidate would be NH<SB>2</SB><SP>−</SP>, which is calculated<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit42">42</REF> to have its bending vibration fundamental in the same spectral region as that of <IT>ν</IT><SB>4</SB> of NH<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="180"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the two stretching fundamentals of NH<SB>2</SB><SP>−</SP> are calculated<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit42 cit43">42,43</REF> to lie between 3100 and 3200 cm<SP>−1</SP> and to be much more strongly infrared absorbing than the bending fundamental.</annotationART></s> <s sid="181"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs38" novelty="None" advantage="None">The experimentally determined band centers of these stretching fundamentals lie at 3121.93 and 3190.29 cm<SP>−1</SP>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit44 cit45">44,45</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="182"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs39" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the present experiments, no new absorptions were detected in that spectral region.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="IV.">Conclusions</HEADER><P><s sid="183"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res36" novelty="None" advantage="None">A considerably higher yield of NH<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP> is obtained in cryogenic sampling experiments when NH<SB>3</SB> and H<SB>2</SB> are introduced into the system downstream from neon atoms that are excited in a microwave discharge than when either molecule is introduced into the discharge region.</annotationART></s> <s sid="184"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since extensive atomization occurs in discharges, the predominant source of NH<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP> in these experiments is believed to be the reaction of NH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> with H<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="185"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs40" novelty="None" advantage="None">The neon-matrix shifts in the infrared-active vibrational fundamentals of NH<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP> are smaller than 0.5%.</annotationART></s> <s sid="186"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res37" novelty="None" advantage="None">These experiments have yielded the first identifications of the <IT>ν</IT><SB>4</SB> vibrational fundamental of ND<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP> and of several of the vibrational fundamentals of each of the partially deuterated ammonium cations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="187"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Complexation of H atoms and of H<SB>2</SB> with the NH<SB>4</SB>-<IT>d</IT><SB><IT>n</IT></SB><SP>+</SP> is believed to be a major contributor to the satellite absorptions which appear close to each of the fundamental absorptions of the NH<SB>4</SB>-<IT>d</IT><SB><IT>n</IT></SB><SP>+</SP> species trapped in the neon matrix.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
