<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b415247f" hasDoc="yes" version="1184" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Creation of permanent lattice defects <IT>via</IT> exciton self-trapping into molecular states in Xe matrix</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Electronic excitation is shown to affect the structural properties of the Xe matrix at low temperatures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">The lattice defect creation was studied using the selective vacuum ultraviolet (VUV) spectroscopy methods.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">The samples were excited by synchrotron radiation in the range of excitonic absorption.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None">The temporal evolution of the intensity distribution in the band of molecular type self-trapped exciton luminescence was analyzed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">A direct evidence for the creation and accumulation of point lattice defects in solid Xe <IT>via</IT> the excitonic mechanism was obtained for the first time.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The model of permanent lattice defect creation and transformation is discussed.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Physics and chemistry in cryomatrices is an active research field and rare-gas matrices have been used frequently in studies over many years.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2 cit3 cit4 cit5 cit6 cit7">1–7</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Defects of structure are of substantial importance in the kinetics of solid-state chemical reactions and have a pronounced effect on the efficiency of formation and stability of radicals and ionic species in cryogenic solids.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The part of the defects in the accumulation of matrix-isolated species has already been discussed in earlier studies<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit8">1,8</REF> and the well-known “matrix-site” effect often involves lattice imperfections.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Whereas in the case of “matrix-site” effect the defects adversely affect guest optical spectra causing a band broadening, the presence of defects, which can be seen as charge traps, is favourable for stabilization of ionic species in cryomatrices.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">To cite an example, the stabilization effect of structural defects on the intrinsic ionic species Rg<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP>, so-called self-trapped holes (STH), in cryomatrices was recently found in the experiments carried out at Bondybey’s Laboratory.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9 cit10">9,10</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Another interesting example to mention is the influence of local matrix morphology on the formation of neutral ground-state chemical compounds involving rare-gas atoms.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">A special type of lattice defects is an electronically induced point defect–Frenkel pair.</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">These defects are created in different classes of wide-gap insulators<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF> and even in narrow-gap materials.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The basis for the physics of electronically induced lattice rearrangement is a concentration of the excitation energy released in the relaxation process within a volume about that of a unit cell followed by the energy transfer to the surrounding matrix.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rare-gas solids are characterized by extremely small binding energies in comparison with the energies of electronic excitations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The difference in energies is of the order of 10<SP>2</SP>–10<SP>3</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">This peculiarity in conjunction with the strong electron–phonon interaction followed by the self-trapping of excitons and holes<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12 cit14 cit15">12,14,15</REF> results in a high quantum yield for the electronically induced processes, making the rare-gas matrices excellent objects for studying the topic under consideration.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Despite the aforementioned attractive properties of the rare-gas solids the experimental study into electronically induced defect creation was undertaken not so long ago.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The first efforts were concentrated on defect creation <IT>via</IT> self-trapping of excitons into atomic states that is the case for solid Ne.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16 cit17">16,17</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">These high-resolution spectral studies revealed a creation and accumulation of point defects in the Ne lattice under irradiation by slow electrons.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The self-trapping of excitons into atomic states is suggested to be a stimulating factor.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The direct experimental proof of this mechanism of defect creation was provided by a recent study carried out with synchrotron radiation.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results obtained in combination with the activation spectroscopy study<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19 cit20">19,20</REF> supported the theoretical model<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21 cit22">21,22</REF> of the evolution of atomic self-trapped excitons (A-STE) into permanent lattice defects—Frenkel pairs of the second neighbour configuration.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The spectroscopic investigation of lattice defect creation in the case of exciton self-trapping into molecular states, as occurred in solid Xe, Kr and Ar, is a rigorous task.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast to the case of exciton self-trapping into atomic states the luminescence spectra of molecular self-trapped excitons (M-STE) have a shape of broad bands stemming from the electronic transition from the <SP>1,3</SP>Σ+u to a repulsive part of the ground state <SP>1</SP>Σ+g (the well-known M bands.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12 cit14 cit15">12,14,15</REF>)</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The design of a special cryogenic cell<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF> for sample growth enabled us to grow samples of high crystal quality and to reveal the internal structure of the M bands.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">It has been shown that the M band in all rare-gas solids consists of two components—M<SB>1</SB> (related to the molecular centers in the defect sites) and M<SB>2</SB> (related to the molecular centers formed in the regular lattice at the exciton self-trapping).</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The interpretation was supported by the recent experiments on selective excitation by synchrotron radiation.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The existence of these two components in the M bands provides a way for application of the sensitive VUV luminescence spectroscopy method to characterize the samples and to study the electronically induced defect creation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Even in our first studies<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23 cit25">23,25</REF> slow electrons were used for the excitation in order to prevent the knock-on defect creation—formation of defects by elastic collisions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The accumulation of radiation-induced defects was detected in all heavy rare-gas solids—Ar, Kr and Xe.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23 cit25 cit26 cit27">23,25–27</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The comprehensive study performed in pure and doped Kr matrices<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28">28</REF> permitted us to suggest mechanisms of defect creation <IT>via</IT> exciton self-trapping into molecular states.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="New" advantage="None">However, the direct proof of the excitonic mechanism requires experiments with state-selective excitation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">The synchrotron radiation providing an intense VUV light tunable through the range of excitonic absorption of rare-gas solids is best suited to such an experiment.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="New" advantage="None">This paper reports the results of a synchrotron radiation study into permanent lattice defect creation in the Xe matrix <IT>via</IT> excitonic mechanism.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="New" advantage="None">The experimental findings are compared with the results obtained under electron beam irradiation, and discussed in relation to the suggested model of defect creation.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Experimental</HEADER><P><s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Investigation of electronically induced lattice rearrangement requires definite experimental conditions—first, high quality samples with low concentration of initial defects and impurities, then subthreshold excitation of the samples using slow particles of energy deficient to produce defects <IT>via</IT> knock-on mechanism or photons of appropriate energy, and finally, excitation of the samples at low temperatures to exclude the conventional thermally-activated defect creation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The study to be described was performed at the SUPERLUMI station of the Hamburger Synchrotronstrahlungslabor HASYLAB at DESY.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The set-up designed for luminescence experiments in the VUV range is given elsewhere,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29">29</REF> so only essential details are mentioned here.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The samples of required quality were grown in a special closed cell mounted on a He-flow cryostat holder in an ultrahigh vacuum (UHV) environment (10<SP>−10</SP> mbr).</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">High-purity Xe gas (99.9996%) was used, and the gas handling system was operated under UHV conditions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The samples were condensed from the vapour phase at elevated temperature under isobaric conditions (<IT>P</IT> = 1000 Pa) with a constant cooling in the temperature range 125–110 K. Then the temperature was controllably reduced at a constant rate of 0.1 Ks<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">After the sample preparation and cooling, the cell was removed and the free-standing cryocrystal of 1 mm thickness was studied.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The polycrystalline samples thus produced were optically transparent.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The intense luminescence of free excitons indicated their high quality.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The samples were then subjected to prolonged irradiation by the VUV light.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The selective excitation was carried out with a bandpass of Δ<IT>λ</IT> = 0.25 nm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The excitation energy was chosen in the range of the <IT>n</IT> = 2 term of the Γ(3/2) excitonic series.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The luminescence analysis was performed with Δ<IT>λ</IT> = 2 nm by using a 0.5 m high-flux Pouey VUV monochromator equipped with a multisphere plate detector.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The entire M band was periodically recorded during exposure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The following decomposition of the M band into M<SB>1</SB> and M<SB>2</SB> subbands yielded the dose dependence of the defect component and the regular one.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj5" novelty="New" advantage="None">The influence of the annealing at 60 K on the intensity distribution in the M band was examined.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="New" advantage="None">To probe the defects we used thermally stimulated luminescence (TSL).</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The electron-hole pairs were generated by a short-term exposure to the VUV radiation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">On completion of the irradiation the spectrum of the TSL was recorded.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">For comparison, we replicated the experiments with excitation by an electron beam following the identical procedure of the sample growing.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The experiments were performed at the Laboratory of Condensed System Spectroscopy at the Verkin Institute for Low Temperature Physics &amp; Engineering NASU.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The samples were grown in a closed cell with an electromagnetic shutter mounted on a L-He cryostat holder in the vacuum chamber.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">After the sample preparation and its cooling, the shutter was open providing the free access for the electron beam and emerging luminescence.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">We used electrons of 1 keV energy, deficient to create defects by knock-on collisions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The irradiation was performed under steady state conditions with a current density of 50 μA cm<SP>−2</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The dose was increased with exposure time.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The sequence of luminescence spectra was recorded using a normal incidence 1 m VUV monochromator with a bandpass of Δ<IT>λ</IT> = 0.16 nm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The irradiation and measurements were performed at low temperature (15 K) in order to exclude the conventional thermal mechanism of defect creation and to avoid the annealing of the defects produced.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Results and discussion</HEADER><P><s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 1 demonstrates the internal structure of the M band in solid Xe and its temporal evolution under excitation by slow electrons.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The shape of the M band profoundly varies with exposure time.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">These changes are caused by the intensity redistribution between the two components of its internal structure—M<SB>1</SB> and M<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Each of the subbands approximated by the Gaussian is depicted in Fig. 1.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The dose dependence of the subband intensity is shown in the insert of Fig. 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The intensity of the M<SB>2</SB> subband related to the exciton self-trapped in the regular lattice remains constant.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The distinct enhancement of the defect subband M<SB>1</SB> upon irradiation indicates an increase in the number of defect sites, <IT>i.e.</IT> accumulation of permanent lattice defects.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The existence of the two subbands points to a branching of the relaxation channels.</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Ionizing radiation (electrons in our case) creates primary excitations—free electron-hole pairs.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Three channels of “indirect” exciton creation were found under selective excitation above the band gap energy <IT>E</IT><SB>g</SB>: (i) recombination of electron-hole pairs, (ii) inelastic scattering of electrons, and (iii) excitonic side bands of valence or inner-shell excitation.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30">30</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Free excitons can be then self-trapped in the regular lattice or trapped in some defect site.</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The method of lattice defect detection developed in our studies<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16 cit17 cit23">16,17,23</REF> is in fact a modification of the sensitized luminescence method.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The excitation energy is transferred to the defects by free excitons followed by their trapping and radiative decay yielding the M<SB>1</SB> subband.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Apparently, both kinds of defects—the initial structural defects and the defects created <IT>via</IT> electronic excitation—contribute to the M<SB>1</SB> subband.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The contribution of the initial defects can be easily found by extrapolating the dose dependence of the M<SB>1</SB> subband intensity to zero.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj6" novelty="New" advantage="None">Let us take up possible channels of electronically induced defect creation keeping in mind that the key point for this process is the relaxation energy release in a confined region of the crystal.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">As was already mentioned, two efficient channels of electronic excitation self-trapping exist in the lattice of heavy rare-gas solids–formation of STEs and STHs.</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The secondary electrons produced under excitation well above <IT>E</IT><SB>g</SB> for the most part remain in the solid, and hence each hole has, in the mean, its counterpart—an electron elsewhere.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Taking into account the fact that the electrons are characterized by free-like behavior<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF> in rare-gas solids, in other words, they are highly mobile, one can expect an efficient recombination on the electron thermalization.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">If a part of the electrons is trapped in some defect sites, STHs remain stable in the lattice at temperatures low enough to prohibit the release of the electrons from their traps.</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The exciton self-trapping caused by exciton–phonon interaction was found in all rare-gas solids and reported in a number of books, reviews and papers.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12 cit14 cit15 cit31 cit32 cit33 cit34 cit35">12,14,15,31–35</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The relevant relaxation processes involving the self-trapping of holes and excitons can be given by the reactions:Rg<SB>H</SB><SP>+</SP> + Rg → Rg<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP> + Δ<IT>E</IT><SP>+</SP>(STH) → Rg<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP>+ e → Rg* + Rg + Δ<IT>E</IT>(<IT>DRec</IT>)Rg<SB>E</SB>* + Rg → Rg<SB>2</SB>* + Δ<IT>E</IT>*(M-STE) → <IT>hν</IT> (M-STE) + Rg + Rg + Δ<IT>E</IT>(<IT>D</IT>)We take Rg<SB>H</SB><SP>+</SP> and Rg<SB>E</SB>* to denote a free hole and free exciton, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The first stage of these reactions corresponds to the self-trapping of holes (1) and excitons (2) followed by the formation of vibronically hot charged (STH) and neutral (M-STE) dimers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that STH and M-STE might be considered as “matrix isolated” molecular centers within its own host crystal.</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">While relaxing through the vibronic levels, the positively charged dimer STH can recombine with a thermalized electron into a repulsive electronic state yielding two Rg atoms separated energetically (a so called dissociative recombination <IT>DRec</IT>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">At both relaxation stages an essential amount of energy Δ<IT>E</IT><SP>+</SP>(STH) and Δ<IT>E</IT>(<IT>DRec</IT>) is released in the vicinity of STH, which can be spent on the lattice defect creation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The efficiency of this defect creation channel <IT>via</IT> recombination depends on the rate of electron thermalization and is not expected to be high.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of exciton self-trapping by reaction (2) the relaxation energy is transferred to the surrounding atoms at both stages—in the excited state of the M-STE and in the ground state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The energy release during the M-STE vibronic cooling Δ<IT>E</IT>*(M-STE) is about 0.45 eV <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit36">36</REF> which is higher than the binding energy per atom in solid Xe (172.3 meV .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF>)</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">After the radiative transition (<IT>hν</IT> (M-STE)) of the relaxed M-STE to a repulsive part of the ground state potential, the excess energy Δ<IT>E</IT>(<IT>D</IT>) = 0.86 eV is shared between two dimer atoms, in other words, there appear the two “hot” atoms with a 0.43 eV kinetic energy available for the defect creation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In accordance with this consideration, the mechanisms of exciton-induced defect creation can be classified as an “excited state” mechanism and a “ground state” one.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28">28</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to distinguish clearly the recombination (1) and excitonic (2) channels of defect creation the direct experiments with selective excitation into the exciton band were performed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">First of all, the origin of the M<SB>1</SB> and M<SB>2</SB> subbands was verified using the advantages of the selective excitation by synchrotron radiation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The shape of the M band in the luminescence spectrum of solid Xe measured at different excitation energies—below the bottom of the lowest exciton band <IT>n</IT> = 1 Γ(3/2) and in the range of the exciton absorption—is shown in Fig. 2 where the difference in the position and halfwidth FWHM of the M band is clearly seen.</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The excitation below the exciton band gave rise to a defect M<SB>1</SB> subband with a maximum at 7.05 eV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The excitation above the Γ(3/2) exciton band bottom resulted in the appearance of two subbands with the predominance of a M<SB>2</SB> subband at 7.22 eV.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj7" novelty="New" advantage="None">In order to shed more light on the origin of the internal structure of the M band, we restored the excitation spectra of the M<SB>1</SB> and M<SB>2</SB> subbands.</annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The earlier data on the excitation spectra obtained by the “red–blue-side” separation method<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit31">31</REF> supported the assignment of the M<SB>2</SB> subband as originated from the M-STE in the regular lattice whereas the M<SB>1</SB> subband was assigned to the exciton of molecular configuration trapped in the defect site.</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, because of the strong overlapping of the two subbands the direct measurement of the separate excitation spectra of the M<SB>1</SB> and M<SB>2</SB> subbands is impossible.</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">To restore the excitation spectra we used the following procedure:<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF> a series of luminescence spectra were recorded with a successive increase of the excitation energy, then the luminescence spectra recorded were resolved into the M<SB>1</SB> and the M<SB>2</SB> components and the intensities of each subband were plotted as a function of the excitation energy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The resulting excitation spectra are shown in Fig. 3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The solid line represents the total yield of the luminescence in the M band as a function of the excitation energy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The procedure applied enabled us to estimate the low energy excitation thresholds <IT>E</IT><SB>1</SB> and <IT>E</IT><SB>2</SB> for the M<SB>1</SB> and M<SB>2</SB> subbands, respectively: <IT>E</IT><SB>1</SB> = 8.18 eV, <IT>E</IT><SB>2</SB> = 8.28 eV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The careful check of the spatial distribution of the centers emitting M<SB>1</SB> and M<SB>2</SB> subbands, performed with the electron beam of different energy, and hence, of different penetration depth, demonstrated the bulk origin of both centers.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results obtained provided solid evidence of the “defect” nature of the M<SB>1</SB> subband and the intrinsic nature of the M<SB>2</SB> subband—emission of the true M-STE center in the regular lattice.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Based on this assignment we measured the dose dependence of the M<SB>1</SB> and M<SB>2</SB> subbands to probe the defect creation upon excitation in the exciton band.</annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The primary monochromator was tuned to the energy of the <IT>n</IT> = 2 Γ(3/2) band in the absorption spectrum of solid Xe.</annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Due to the low absorption coefficient the exciting light penetrated deep inside the sample, and the M-STE dimers were efficiently formed in the bulk.</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj8" novelty="New" advantage="None">A sequence of spectra were measured upon exposure to the VUV light.</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj8" novelty="New" advantage="None">The internal structure and the intensity distribution were analyzed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The position and FWHM of the M<SB>1</SB> and M<SB>2</SB> subbands were obtained from the numerical fit of the band shape assuming a Gaussian shape of the subbands.</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The result of this treatment—the corresponding points of the curves—yields the dose dependence of the subband intensity shown in Fig. 4.</annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The intensity of the M<SB>2</SB> subband associated with the M-STE in the regular lattice remained constant during exposure to the VUV light.</annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">At the first stage of VUV irradiation (up to 100 min) we observed a pronounced enhancement of the M<SB>1</SB> subband intensity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that the exposure time is not corrected for the synchrotron radiation pulse duration, so it is in fact a real time of the measurements.</annotationART></s> <s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">During the next 100 min we observed a saturation of the dose dependence of the M<SB>1</SB> intensity followed by a slow decrease with long irradiation time.</annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The dose dependence of radiation-induced point defect (<IT>e.g.</IT> vacancies) concentration <IT>C</IT><SB>v</SB> is described by the following equation∂<IT>C</IT><SB>v</SB>/∂<IT>t</IT> = <IT>K</IT><SB>dc</SB> − <IT>K</IT><SB>r</SB> (<IT>C</IT><SB>i</SB><IT>C</IT><SB>v</SB>) − <IT>C</IT><SB>i</SB><SP>0</SP><IT>C</IT><SB>v</SB><SP>0</SP>) − <IT>K</IT><SB>t</SB> (<IT>C</IT><SB>v</SB> − <IT>C</IT><SB>v</SB><SP>0</SP>)Here <IT>K</IT><SB>dc</SB> is the coefficient that characterizes the rate of permanent defect creation <IT>via</IT> exciton self-trapping, whereas <IT>K</IT><SB>r</SB> and <IT>K</IT><SB>t</SB> are the coefficients of the vacancy-interstitial recombination and trapping by some kind of sinks, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">At low temperatures and small doses, the reactions of recombination and trapping are extremely slow, and we observe a linear increase of the M<SB>1</SB> subband intensity indicating the accumulation of defects in the sample.</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">With increasing the concentration of the radiation-induced Frenkel pairs (interstitials and vacancies) the contribution of the defect annihilation processes (second and third terms of the equation) increases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that at low temperatures the thermally activated diffusion of vacancies to sinks is negligible and only the radiation-induced defect motion comes to play.</annotationART></s> <s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">One can suggest that on long-term exposure there occurs an aggregation of defects.</annotationART></s> <s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The details of the defect transformation on long-term irradiation invite further investigation.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj9" novelty="New" advantage="None">Let us discuss some possible models of exciton-induced defect creation <IT>via</IT> self-trapping into molecular states—M-STE.</annotationART></s> <s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The self-trapping occurring during the lifetime of the excited state results in the formation of a molecular dimer aligned along the 〈110〉 crystallographic directions with an interatomic distance of 0.31 nm.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit35">35</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">This stage followed by the M-STE formation in the on-center position is shown in Fig. 5 (a and b).</annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The center formed resembles a “dumb-bell” configuration of the interstitial atom.</annotationART></s> <s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Its displacement along the 〈110〉 direction to an off-center configuration (position c in Fig. 5) cannot stabilize the center.</annotationART></s> <s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">It was shown<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit37">37</REF> that the split 〈100〉 “dumb-bell” form is the only stable form of the interstitial atom in the Xe lattice.</annotationART></s> <s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The separation between the “dumb-bell” atoms is found to be 0.86<IT>d</IT> (<IT>d</IT> is the distance between the nearest neighbours), which only slightly exceeds the interatomic distance between the atoms in the Xe<SB>2</SB>* dimer (0.31 nm).</annotationART></s> <s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Bearing this in mind, one can assume that the short-lived defect of the off-center configuration can be stabilized by the reorientation of the dimer axis to the 〈100〉 direction (<IT>d</IT> in Fig. 5).</annotationART></s> <s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Frank–Condon transition of this dimer to the ground state will correspond to the transition of the molecular center to the permanent defect level with almost no change in the interatomic distance.</annotationART></s> <s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The energy needed for the reorientation can be released in the lattice in the course of the vibronic relaxation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">As the theory shows,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit38">38</REF> in a system with a strong local vibration the energy release proceeds in a jump-like multiphonon process.</annotationART></s> <s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">It seems to be the case for the M-STE relaxation which offers the basis for the development of the “excited state” mechanism.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The model of defect creation by the “ground state” mechanism is not as straightforward as it may seem at first sight.</annotationART></s> <s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The matter is that during self-trapping Rg atoms are brought closer together displacing along the 〈110〉 direction, as shown in Fig. 5b.</annotationART></s> <s sid="143"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, there are no stable interstitials of the “dumb-bell” configuration aligned along the 〈110〉 crystallographic direction.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit37">37</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="144"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The recent theoretical studies<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit39 cit40">39,40</REF> showed that in the fcc lattice of rare-gas solids the weak coupling between close-packed atomic rows and the crystal matrix may give rise to an interstitial atom of a specific configuration—a smeared clump called a crowdion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="145"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The vacancy also becomes delocalized, forming a smeared sparsed region (anticrowdion).</annotationART></s> <s sid="146"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The computational results were presented for Ar and Kr cryoscrystals and it was mentioned that the formation of crowdions is also expected in the Xe lattice.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="147"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj10" novelty="New" advantage="None">We performed the experiment with detection of a thermally stimulated luminescence (TSL) spectrum of the samples irradiated by VUV photons.</annotationART></s> <s sid="148"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The recorded TSL spectrum is shown in Fig. 6.</annotationART></s> <s sid="149"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">In view of the low TSL intensity the spectrum was collected over the heating time.</annotationART></s> <s sid="150"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The recombination of STHs with electrons gives rise to the self-trapped excitons emitting the M<SB>2</SB> subband.</annotationART></s> <s sid="151"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">If the hole is trapped in a defect site one can expect the appearance of the M<SB>1</SB> subband in the TSL spectrum.</annotationART></s> <s sid="152"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The comparison with the luminescence spectrum excited by photons of 8.86 eV energy (in the band of intrinsic exciton absorption of solid Xe) shows that the TSL band consists of two components M<SB>1</SB> and M<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="153"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Because of low intensity, reliable decomposition of the M band in the TSL spectrum is impossible.</annotationART></s> <s sid="154"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the contribution of both subbands can be ascertained.</annotationART></s> <s sid="155"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">TSL of solid Xe at the photon energy 7.2 eV after irradiation by X-rays was observed in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit41">ref. 41</REF> but the M<SB>1</SB> and M<SB>2</SB> subbands in the TSL band were not discriminated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="156"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that the TSL from solid Xe grown at low temperature yielded a 7.6 eV band.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit42">42</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="157"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The recent study suggested this band to be originated from trimer Xe<SB>3</SB>*<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit43">43</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Summary</HEADER><P><s sid="158"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj11" novelty="New" advantage="None">The electronically induced lattice rearrangement of solid Xe was studied by the VUV spectroscopy methods under selective excitation with synchrotron radiation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="159"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="New" advantage="None">We used a combination of the luminescence analysis, excitation spectroscopy, and thermally stimulated luminescence.</annotationART></s> <s sid="160"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The existence of two subbands of molecular luminescence was verified—a defect related component and component originated from the exciton self-trapping in the regular lattice.</annotationART></s> <s sid="161"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Analysis of the intensity redistribution upon exposure to the VUV light in the range of the exciton absorption enabled us to gain clear evidence for the permanent lattice defect creation <IT>via</IT> exciton self-trapping into the molecular state.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
