<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b415563g" hasDoc="yes" version="1184" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Exact exchange and Wilson–Levy correlation: a pragmatic device for studying complex weakly-bonded systems</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">The Wilson–Levy (WL) correlation functional is used together with Hartree–Fock (HF) theory to evaluate interaction energies at intermediate separations (<IT>i.e.</IT> around equilibrium separation) for several weakly-bonded systems.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The HF+WL approach reproduces binding trends for all complexes studied: selected rare-gas dimers, isomers of the methane dimer, benzene dimer and naphthalene dimer, and base-pair stacking structures for pyrimidine, cytosine, uracil and guanine dimers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None">These HF+WL data are contrasted against results obtained from some popular functionals (including B3LYP and PBE), as well as two newly-developed functionals, X3LYP and xPBE.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The utility of HF+WL, with reference to exact-exchange (EXX) density-functional theory, is discussed in terms of a suggested EXXWL exchange–correlation functional.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="1.">Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The interaction energy between two weakly-interacting fragments comprises many distinct and well-understood (although perhaps not easy to calculate) contributions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Following Stone,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF> the interaction energy can be decomposed into first-order, second-order and higher-order contributions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Hartree–Fock (HF) theory adequately captures (at small and large separations) first-order contributions such as the electrostatic interaction and the exchange–repulsion interaction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="No">The performance of HF theory for second-order contributions is less comprehensive.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="No">Although HF theory can yield a reasonable estimate of the induction contribution, HF theory cannot recover the dispersion energy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Higher-order terms are recovered (with varying degrees of accuracy) <IT>via</IT> use of post-HF methods such as Møller–Plesset second-order perturbation theory, MP2, and coupled-cluster singles and doubles with triples corrections, CCSD(T).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Both induction and dispersion are present in the regime of large fragment separations (the ‘long-range’ form) where the charge distributions on each fragment do not overlap, and are also present in the small to intermediate separation regime (the ‘short-range’ form) where the charge distributions do overlap.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Where charge distributions overlap, second-order contributions are modified by general overlap effects as well as electron exchange, leading to damped induction, exchange-induction, damped dispersion and exchange–dispersion contributions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">These short-range terms should behave as a function of overlap between fragments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, in this article, the general phrase ‘dispersion energy’ does not solely refer to the London dispersion (with <IT>r</IT><SP>−6</SP> dependence) that characterises the long-range contribution, rather, it refers to the dispersion interaction at all separations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reader is directed to the body of work concerned with symmetry-adapted perturbation theory (SAPT), where such contributions to the interaction energy are rigorously defined (<IT>e.g.</IT>, the review article of Jeziorski <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">2</REF>)..</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Accurate calculation of these second-order contributions, at any separation, for large and/or complex weakly-interacting systems remains a challenging prospect in theoretical chemistry.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In the worst case, the use of post-HF methods such as MP2 or CCSD(T) can be limited at best to rather modest basis set sizes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="No">These methods may yield unreliable results for such small basis sets.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="No">For example, even with use of large basis sets, MP2 can substantially overestimate the attraction in weakly-bound aromatic systems.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">However, recent progress in the development of algorithms for the rapid evaluation of MP2 energies and gradients (<IT>e.g.</IT> see Saebø <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF>)., should in future enable practical geometry optimisations using larger basis sets.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Second-order contributions to the interaction energy arise from electronic correlation effects (beyond electron exchange alone).</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Density-functional theory (DFT) is often proposed as a means of obtaining the correlation contribution to the total electronic energy, in a way that is computationally economical.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="No">However, it is now well-known that no mainstream, practical correlation functional can recover the <IT>r</IT><SP>−6</SP> dependence of London dispersion at large fragment separations (see for example <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7 cit25">refs. 7 and 25</REF>, and references therein).</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="No">This fact will not be disputed here; lack of London dispersion remains a major limitation of all approaches that involve Kohn–Sham DFT in some way.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="No">However, many studies have amply demonstrated that application of DFT to weakly-bound systems can not yield globally reliable estimates of the interaction energy even at intermediate intermonomer separations<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6 cit7 cit8 cit9">5–9</REF> where there is overlap between fragments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Several groups have made progress in the development of ‘seamless DFT’ approaches that can describe dispersion contributions at all separations<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10 cit11 cit12">10–12</REF> (including in the overlapping regime).</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="No">However, all of these approaches are at present too computationally intensive to be applied to large and/or complex weakly-bonded systems.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the basis of Heitler–London calculations, Cybulski and Seversen<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF> correctly identified that the correlation functionals used in their study only showed binding when it was due to exchange effects from the correlation functional, such that the total intermolecular exchange was negative (for their decomposition scheme).</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, they noted that, as expected, this intermolecular exchange contribution vanishes faster with respect to separation than <IT>r</IT><SP>−6</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">This overlap effect has been observed (but not quantified) by others, <IT>e.g.</IT> see .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">ref. 7</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The decomposition analysis used by Cybulski and Seversen, while helpfully demonstrating the overlap effect of binding for some correlation functionals, does not explain <IT>why</IT> these correlation functionals yield negative contributions to the intermolecular exchange.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">While it is often the correlation functional which is identified as deficient in recovering second-order contributions in the overlapping regime, several studies have instead identified the exchange functional as problematic,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6 cit8 cit13 cit14 cit15 cit16">6,8,13–16</REF> especially under the conditions of low-density/high-density-gradient.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">An accurate description of exchange under such conditions is vital for describing weakly-bonded systems.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Empirical scaling of DFT exchange has also been examined by several groups,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14 cit16 cit17">14,16,17</REF> with a view to correcting this problem.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="No">However, the results of these studies do not show transferability of the scaling factor across different systems.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, the fact that mainstream DFT cannot recover short-range second-order contributions must be due, in part, to problems with the exchange functional.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Despite these well-known deficiencies of DFT, a number of schemes for empirically correcting DFT calculations by addition of damped dispersion (DFT+D) have been proposed.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6 cit18 cit19 cit20">6,18–20</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="Old" advantage="None">As an alternative to post-HF theories and also DFT+D, another route to gaining economical (and reasonable) estimates of the interaction energy for large weakly-bound systems is to use a Hartree–Fock (HF) plus dispersion approach (HF+D).</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">The use of HF implies that, for a given density, the exchange contribution will be exact (by definition), including under low-density/high-density-gradient conditions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">The HF+D approach was first introduced by Hepburn <IT>et</IT><IT>al.</IT>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF> has been successfully applied to small weakly-bound systems,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF> and recently Lim and coworkers have applied HF+D to small clusters of polyaromatic heterocycles to good effect.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23 cit24">23,24</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="Old" advantage="None">One issue to note with both HF+D and DFT+D is that these methods require good quality dispersion coefficients.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Also, the form of the damping function, including anisotropic damping, can be a very important factor in gaining good results from these DFT+D models.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">While some studies have reported progress in this area,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18 cit19">18,19</REF> further studies into damping are probably warranted.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both of these ‘+dispersion’ approaches may succeed for the long-range part of the dispersion interaction, but it is not entirely clear that the DFT+D approach is correct in the overlapping regime.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25">25</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The problem of calculating the short-range interaction energy can also be approached <IT>via</IT> the addition of a correlation contribution derived from DFT onto the total HF energy of the system, bearing in mind the deficiencies pointed out by Cybulski and Seversen.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">As in the HF+D approach, the exchange contribution should behave correctly at long range.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">This HF+DFT approach was shown by Pérez-Jordá <IT>et</IT><IT>al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26">26</REF>. to work very well for selected rare-gas dimers in the case where the Wilson–Levy correlation functional (WL)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27">27</REF> was used.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Some other correlation functionals also showed binding, but did not recover qualitatively correct equilibrium binding energies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Moreover, this study also showed that in all cases where binding was found, the interaction energy curve decayed to zero faster than <IT>r</IT><SP>−6</SP>, clearly not capturing any long-range dispersion contribution (as expected).</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, several correlation functionals did not yield any attractive contributions, notably the VWN<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28">28</REF> and Perdew–Wang<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29">29</REF> correlation functionals.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">This HF+DFT approach is not the same as Hartree–Fock Kohn–Sham (HFKS) theory, but Pérez-Jordá <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26">26</REF>. reported that the HF+DFT results for rare-gas dimers were almost identical to the HFKS results.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">In particular, these authors demonstrated that the Wilson–Levy correlation functional (WL)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27">27</REF> worked extremely well in partnership with HF theory, in reproducing the experimental well-depths of the rare-gas dimer systems studied “with remarkable agreement”.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Their data, shown in Fig. 1, emphatically reinforces their statement.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">This approach will herein be referred to as HF+WL.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The WL correlation functional is based on the Wigner correlation functional<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30">30</REF> (W38), contains gradient corrections, and includes four empirically-determined parameters.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The parameters were determined <IT>via</IT> comparison with the exact (calculated) correlation energy (in the traditional quantum chemistry definition) for several atoms (neutral and cationic), plus the experimental correlation energy of the helium atom.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hartree–Fock densities of these atoms were used in the parametrisation of this functional.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">As noted by Wilson and Levy,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27">27</REF> since the traditional quantum chemistry definition of correlation energy is not always equivalent to the DFT definition, the WL functional may not be successful if applied to systems where the HF density is substantially different to the true density of the system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the WL correlation functional was designed for use with HF densities, it may be an appropriate approximate correlation functional to use with exact exchange methods, at least for studying pure van der Waals interactions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the utility of this functional has principally been demonstrated only as a post-HF correction<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit31 cit32">8,31,32</REF> for atoms and molecules, not as a dynamic correlation contribution that is self-consistently evaluated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The performance of WL correlation for covalent bonds has not been as extensively tested.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Chermette <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit33">33</REF>. reported self-consistent KS-DFT optimisations of the CO and N<SB>2</SB>O molecules, using the B88 exchange functional<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit34">34</REF> with WL correlation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Their data indicate that, compared with other correlation functionals used with B88, WL underestimates covalent bond lengths.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The HF+WL method should essentially be regarded as an empirical correction to the HF interaction energy, and presumably has inherent deficiencies with the description of intermolecular exchange.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="New" advantage="None">It is the applicability of this approach as a pragmatic device that will be further explored in this work.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="New" advantage="None">Here, the HF+WL approach is applied to all homoatomic and heteroatomic rare-gas dimers RgKr {Rg = He, Ne, Ar, Kr}, the methane dimer, benzene dimer, naphthalene dimer and also DNA base-pair stacking interactions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="New" advantage="None">Some comments on the choice of example systems studied here are warranted.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is noted that, in general, any perturbative correction to the HF interaction energy should only hold under conditions such that the HF wavefunction will not substantially distort if (some) second-order effects are dynamically included.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, the method has been tested on systems where dynamic inclusion of such effects would not substantially distort the wavefunction, compared with the HF wavefunction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Systems exhibiting pure van der Waals interactions (dispersion and repulsion) are ideal in this case, and the systems chosen here reflect this.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="New" advantage="No">In general, all HF + dispersion methods are subject to this condition, which does limit the applicability of this type of approach.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, it appears possible that the HF+WL method can be extended such that all types of non-bonded system could be treated in future.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Specifically, it is conjectured that use of the WL correlation functional, applied self-consistently in conjunction with exact-exchange DFT (<IT>e.g.</IT> the optimised effective potential, OEP<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit35">35</REF>), denoted here as the EXXWL functional, should have a performance similar to the HF+WL approach.</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">The EXXWL functional would open up possibilities for qualitatively accurate calculations on complex systems not yet accessible by other methodologies, <IT>e.g.</IT> physisorption onto nanotubes, gas–surface interactions, <IT>etc</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj5" novelty="New" advantage="None">The example systems selected in this work examine aromatic ring interactions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Such interactions are ubiquitous in Nature, and should be described properly by any theory that claims to model ‘biological systems’.</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="New" advantage="No">Finally, it must be emphasised that, as demonstrated by Pérez-Jordá <IT>et al.</IT>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26">26</REF> the HF+WL method has no pretensions to capturing London dispersion (the long-range contribution).</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="New" advantage="None">However, this caveat does not necessarily exclude the HF+WL method yielding binding when there is overlap between fragments, crucially, around the equilibrium separation for many weakly-interacting systems.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Having accepted the caveats of HF+WL, the utility of this approach as a pragmatic device for locating low-energy structures of large van der Waals systems (some of which have low symmetry) in a simple and quick way will be demonstrated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">These HF+WL results will be compared with results obtained using several established mainstream functionals (<IT>e.g.</IT> B3LYP and PBE), as well as two newly-developed functionals, X3LYP<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit36">36</REF> and xPBE.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit37">37</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">It has been recently suggested that both of these functionals should adequately describe non-bonded interactions for systems involving the first ten elements in the periodic table<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit36 cit37">36,37</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.">Computational methods</HEADER><P><s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">All calculations in this work were done using GAUSSIAN.98<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit38">38</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The monomers were treated as rigid bodies throughout.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Unless otherwise stated, the monomer structures were fully optimised at the MP2/6-31G** level of theory.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">For a given arrangement of rigid monomers, the HF wavefunction was converged and the total electronic energy (<IT>E</IT><SB>HF</SB>) obtained, for both the complex, and also for each monomer in the complex.</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The monomer wavefunctions and energies were obtained in the full set of dimer basis functions, such that the interaction energies were corrected for basis-set superposition error (BSSE) <IT>via</IT> the counterpoise correction<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit39">39</REF> (CP).</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The correlation energy was then evaluated using the corresponding HF density.</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The integration was done over a pruned grid with 99 radial shells and 590 angular points per shell.</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The quadrature used here ensured that the correlation energy was converged to within 1–2 μ<IT>E</IT><SB>h</SB> per atom (depending on atom type).</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The WL correlation energy (<IT>E</IT><SB>corr</SB>) was then extracted from the calculation for both the complex and individual monomers (again using the CP correction).</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The interaction energy was calculated using the supermolecule method, in the following way:The performance of two newly-developed functionals, X3LYP<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit36">36</REF> and xPBE,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit37">37</REF> was also investigated here, in the case of the molecular dimers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both of these functionals were coded into GAUSSIAN98, and satisfactorily verified against the published data for He<SB>2</SB>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit36 cit37">36,37</REF> Ne<SB>2</SB><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit36 cit37">36,37</REF> and Ar<SB>2</SB><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit37">37</REF> systems.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj6" novelty="New" advantage="None">The basis set dependence of the HF+WL energies was examined.</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj6" novelty="New" advantage="None">This was done to confirm the dependence of the interaction energy on overlap, for short- to medium-range separations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj6" novelty="New" advantage="None">The interaction energy as calculated here by the supermolecule method is of course not variational, so we do not necessarily expect to see convergence of this energy from above.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj6" novelty="New" advantage="No">Furthermore, since the HF+WL method used here is an <IT>ad hoc</IT> post-Hartree–Fock correction (and not variationally obtained), this will cause further problems when seeking monotonically decreasing behaviour of interaction energies as a function of basis-set size.</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In all cases, a range of basis sets, chosen from 6-31G*, 6-31G*(0.25),<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit40">40</REF> 6-311G*, 6-31 + G* and the aug-cc-pV<IT>X</IT>Z<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit41 cit42 cit43">41–43</REF> {<IT>X</IT> = D, T, Q, 5} family were used.</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The HF+WL interaction energy was calculated as a function of separation in all cases, and the minimum interaction energy was reported in each case.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the methane dimer, three different relative orientations were examined, as shown in Fig. 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the benzene dimer, three geometries were considered: a T-shaped structure (<IT>C</IT><SB>2v</SB> symmetry), a slipped-parallel (SP) structure (<IT>C</IT><SB>2h</SB> symmetry) and an undisplaced parallel (F) structure (<IT>D</IT><SB>6h</SB> symmetry), also shown in Fig. 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the naphthalene dimer, four low-energy structures and one high-energy structure were examined: two crossed structures (<IT>D</IT><SB>2d</SB> and <IT>C</IT><SB>2</SB> symmetries) and two slipped-parallel structures (<IT>C</IT><SB>2h</SB> and <IT>C</IT><SB>i</SB> symmetries), and one undisplaced parallel structure (<IT>D</IT><SB>2h</SB>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The four low-energy structures are shown in Fig. 3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Optimised naphthalene dimer geometries were taken from previous work.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit44">44</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this case, the HF+WL interaction energies were calculated as a function of separation (along the vector that connects centre of mass points), while the relative orientations of each dimer structure were kept fixed.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Finally, for the base-pair stacking dimers, the geometries were taken from Hobza and Šponer.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit45">45</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">That is, antiparallel undisplaced structures were used for the pyrimidine and cytosine dimers, and the vertical displacement was optimised using HF+WL.</annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Compared with pyrimidine and cytosine, the procedure for creating the input structures for uracil and guanine was a little different.</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Following Hobza and Šponer, the uracil dimer geometry was optimised in this work at the MP2/6-31G** level, and agrees closely with the structural data of Hobza and Šponer.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit46">46</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Using this MP2 structure, the separation (along the vector connecting the centre of mass of each molecule) was optimised using HF+WL, while keeping the angle of the monomer normal vectors (normal to the ring plane) constant.</annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The guanine dimer structure was an undisplaced stacked geometry, where one monomer was rotated clockwise about its centre of mass (in the plane of the molecule).</annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The optimum twist angle was identified at the HF+WL/aug-cc-pVDZ level, for a fixed vertical separation of 3.4 Å.</annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The vertical separation (for the fixed optimum twist angle) was then optimised for this structure using HF+WL.</annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The geometries used for the base-pair calculations can be found in Fig. 4.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.">Results and discussion</HEADER><P><s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The calculated well-depths and minimum energy separations, obtained using the aug-cc-pV5Z basis, for Kr<SB>2</SB>, HeKr, NeKr and ArKr are presented in Table 1, along with reference values from Ogilvie and Wang,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit47 cit48">47,48</REF> and other DFT values from Patton and Pederson.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The interaction energies are also plotted in Fig. 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In agreement with the previous findings of Pérez-Jordá <IT>et al.</IT>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26">26</REF> the trend of the well depths presented here are in very good qualitative agreement with the experimental results, while not being quantitatively accurate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The minimum energy separation is consistently underestimated by not more than 0.5 <IT>a</IT><SB>0</SB>, as is also demonstrated in the results of Pérez-Jordá <IT>et al.</IT> The HF+WL approach has not captured the slight contraction in separation in going from KrHe to KrNe.</annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Examination of these data plus the data of Pérez-Jordá <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26">26</REF>. show that, with the exception of dimers containing helium, the HF+WL underestimates the interaction energy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The interaction energy for each system was also calculated for separations beyond the minimum-energy point.</annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">These calculations confirmed what has been reported previously by Pérez-Jordá <IT>et al.</IT>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26">26</REF> namely that the interaction energy decays to zero too rapidly compared with the <IT>r</IT><SP>−6</SP> decay observed with long-range London dispersion interactions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">These results re-emphasise that weak interactions for non-overlapping fragments cannot be captured by the HF+WL approach.</annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, these data also suggest that failure to recover long-range London dispersion does not preclude a DFT-based methodology from recovering binding at distances where fragments do overlap.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">As shown in Fig. 1, the qualitative agreement found using HF+WL clearly exceeds the performance of any other mainstream DFT approach (demonstrated, for example, in the results of Patton and Pederson.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF>)</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 1 also re-emphasises the point made by others that the PW91 and PBE functionals do not show great variation in energy between each rare-gas dimer system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The PW91 data fortuitously coincides with the HeKr and NeKr points, while the PBE data fortuitously coincides with the ArKr and Kr<SB>2</SB> points.</annotationART></s> <s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Neither can be said to describe rare-gas equilibrium interaction energies satisfactorily, while the HF+WL equilibrium interaction energies follow the trend of the Ogilvie and Wang data relatively closely.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The interaction energies of these rare-gas systems, calculated using HF+WL for a range of basis sets aug-cc-pV<IT>X</IT>Z {<IT>X</IT> = D, T, Q, 5} is shown in Fig. 5.</annotationART></s> <s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">For each basis the separation between atoms was optimised, but in most cases did not change appreciably for the different basis sets.</annotationART></s> <s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">It seems clear that the energy has converged by the aug-cc-pVTZ basis, and that the aug-cc-pVDZ basis still follows a reasonable qualitative trend (especially when compared with the PBE and PW91 data), although the trend for HeKr and NeKr is not captured.</annotationART></s> <s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The basis set dependence was also checked for the smaller 6-31G* basis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">For all systems but KrNe, the smaller basis set performed no worse than the aug-cc-pV5Z basis, in terms of capturing the correct trend.</annotationART></s> <s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the disagreement for HeNe is striking – the 6-31G* basis recovering an interaction energy of only −5.5 K. The optimum seperation was increased (to 7.0 <IT>a</IT><SB>0</SB>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">As will be confirmed with some of the other systems, the overlap obtained using the 6-31G* basis appears insufficient to ensure confident use of HF+WL here.</annotationART></s> <s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Clearly the HF+WL approach is not perfect here – but it is outperforming other DFT-based approaches.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj7" novelty="New" advantage="None">Three structures of the methane dimer were studied, as shown in Fig. 2; one <IT>D</IT><SB>3d</SB> structure and two <IT>D</IT><SB>3h</SB> structures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj7" novelty="New" advantage="None">The <IT>D</IT><SB>3d</SB> structure has been identified by Tsuzuki and coworkers<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit49">49</REF> as the global minimum structure, at least at the MP3/aug(df,pd)-6-311G** level of theory.</annotationART></s> <s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj7" novelty="New" advantage="None">The <IT>D</IT><SB>3d</SB> structure corresponds with isomer H, and the two <IT>D</IT><SB>3h</SB> structures as isomers A and G, in the nomenclature of Tsuzuki <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit49">49</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj7" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">Isomers A and G are other low-energy structures, and therefore these two geometries probe the interaction energy in regions of configuration space away from the global minimum.</annotationART></s> <s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Separations and interaction energies for these three structures, calculated using the HF+WL method, as well as the X3LYP and xPBE functionals, are shown in Table 2, along with the <IT>ab initio</IT> data of Tsuzuki <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit49">49</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The aug-cc-pVTZ basis was used here for HF+WL, X3LYP and xPBE.</annotationART></s> <s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">These data demonstrate that the HF+WL approach captures the binding trends for these three structures, for all basis sets considered, while clearly not displaying quantitative accuracy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="143"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Again, the HF+WL approach underestimates the minimum-energy separation, found to be 4.6, 3.5 and 3.4 Å for the A, G and H structures, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="144"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">For comparison, the MP3 separations from Tsuzuki <IT>et. al</IT>. are 4.8, 3.8 and 3.8 Å for the A, G and H structures, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="145"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast, the X3LYP and xPBE data seem less reliable here.</annotationART></s> <s sid="146"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although the xPBE data show binding for each structure, and also that the trend of the interaction energies seems correct (A &gt; G &gt; H), the binding is reduced compared with the MP3 results (except in the case of isomer A).</annotationART></s> <s sid="147"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The range of xPBE interaction energies is significantly compressedwith respect to the MP3 data.</annotationART></s> <s sid="148"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The X3LYP data show binding only for structure A. Out to a separation of 6 Å, the other two structures were not bound using the X3LYP functional.</annotationART></s> <s sid="149"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Also in contrast with the rare-gas systems, the isomers studied here showed little sensitivity to changes in basis set using the HF+WL approach.</annotationART></s> <s sid="150"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">For each basis set used (6-31G*, 6-31G*(0.25), aug-cc-pV<IT>X</IT>Z {<IT>X</IT> = D, T, Q}) the trend of interaction energies (A &gt; G &gt; H) was always followed.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="151"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The minimum energy separations and interaction energies for the three benzene dimer structures, calculated at the HF+WL/aug-cc-pVDZ level, are shown in Tables 3 and 4, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="152"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Again, the <IT>D</IT><SB>6h</SB> (F) structure provides a probe of the HF+WL method away from the two low-energy structures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="153"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">For comparison, the data of Tsuzuki <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit50">50</REF>. are shown.</annotationART></s> <s sid="154"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">These data were obtained using their extrapolation method where the interaction energy is calculated at the MP2 basis set limit plus a CCSD(T) correction evaluated with a large basis set.</annotationART></s> <s sid="155"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Again, it can be seen that the HF+WL separations are underestimated compared with the best estimate data.</annotationART></s> <s sid="156"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The interaction energies, although overestimated for the T and SP structures, still show a reasonable trend compared with the F structure, although the T and SP structures are not isoenergetic as suggested in the results of the <IT>ab initio</IT> calculations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="157"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The F structure is bound in the HF+WL model, but underestimates the attraction, again emphasising that the HF+WL method cannot compete with post-HF approaches.</annotationART></s> <s sid="158"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Also shown in Table 4 for comparison are results from full DFT calculations, as reported by Tsuzuki and Lüthi<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit51">51</REF> and also from current work, that confirm the unsuitability of these functionals as applied to weakly-bound systems.</annotationART></s> <s sid="159"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The HF+WL approach provides a reasonable estimate of the energetic and structural trends of this system (while not being quantitatively accurate), where full DFT can not.</annotationART></s> <s sid="160"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The similarity between the PBE and PW91 results is also noted.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="161"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">Table 4 shows the interaction energy of the T, F and SP structures calculated at the X3LYP/aug-cc-pVDZ and xPBE/aug-cc-pVDZ levels of theory, at the geometries taken from Tsuzuki <IT>et al.</IT>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit50">50</REF> revealing a similar performance of these two functionals compared with existing functionals.</annotationART></s> <s sid="162"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj8" novelty="New" advantage="None">The interaction energy as a function of centre-of-mass separation was also investigated for these two functionals.</annotationART></s> <s sid="163"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The F structure was unbound at all separations up to and including 6.0 Å at both the xPBE/aug-cc-pVDZ and X3LYP/aug-cc-pVDZ levels.</annotationART></s> <s sid="164"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">The T structure was bound at a separation of 5.7 Å at the xPBE/aug-cc-pVDZ level, with an optimum interaction energy of −0.48 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="165"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">Similarly, at the X3LYP/aug-cc-pVDZ level, the T structure was bound at an optimum distance of 5.6 Å with an interaction energy of −0.37 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="166"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj9" novelty="New" advantage="None">The SP structure was investigated in the neighbourhood of the structure of Tsuzuki <IT>et al.</IT>, such that the vertical and horizontal separations, as well as the distance along the vector connecting the two centre of mass points, was varied by displacements of ±0.2 Å.</annotationART></s> <s sid="167"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">None of these locally-perturbed structures showed binding at the xPBE/aug-cc-pVDZ level.</annotationART></s> <s sid="168"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">The performance was very similar at the X3LYP/aug-cc-pVDZ level.</annotationART></s> <s sid="169"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The only structure that yielded an interaction energy of less than +1 (but greater than zero) kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>, for either xPBE or X3LYP, was for the case when the distance along the vector connecting the two centre of mass points was extended by 0.2 Å.</annotationART></s> <s sid="170"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None">These results, as well as those summarised in Table 4, demonstrate that the recovery of binding for molecular complexes, even at separations where the fragments overlap, remains an elusive goal for mainstream DFT exchange–correlation functionals.</annotationART></s> <s sid="171"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The performance of all of the functionals examined here is poor in comparison with the HF+WL approach.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="172"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj10" novelty="New" advantage="None">The basis set dependence of the the HF+WL approach was also gauged for the benzene dimer structures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="173"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp10" novelty="None" advantage="None">At the minimum-energy separations found at the HF+WL/aug-cc-pVDZ level, the interaction energies were recalculated using the 6-31G* basis set.</annotationART></s> <s sid="174"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">While the T and SP structures remained bound (interaction energies of −2.83 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> and −1.85 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>, respectively), the F structure is unbound at this level of theory, at +0.78 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="175"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Exploration of the interaction energy of the F structure at a range of separations confirmed that this structure remained unbound.</annotationART></s> <s sid="176"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Increasing flexibility by using a triple split valence basis, in this case using 6-311G*, leads to binding of the F structure (−0.53 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="177"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">At the HF+WL/6-311G* level, the T and SP structures also remained with reasonable interaction energies (−3.16 and −2.84 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>, respectively).</annotationART></s> <s sid="178"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Similarly, diffuse functions were added to the 6-31G* basis, such that the 6-31+G* basis set was considered.</annotationART></s> <s sid="179"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">At this level, all structures are bound, with F, T and SP structures having interaction energies −0.20, −3.08 and −2.58 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="180"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None">These data suggest that a basis with at least split valence plus diffuse and polarization functions, or triple split valence plus polarization should be used to obtain qualitatively correct HF+WL interaction energies.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="181"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Finally, by way of comparison with other empirically-corrected methods, Wu <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF>. report a DFT + disp interaction energy for the SP structure (at the Tsuzuki <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit50">50</REF>. geometry) of −3.99 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="182"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Gonzalez and Lim<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF> report a HF + disp interaction energy of the T structure (at the geometry used by Tsuzuki <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit50">50</REF>). of −2.80 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>, albeit with a rather modest basis for the HF component.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="183"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj11" novelty="New" advantage="None">The naphthalene dimer presents a significant challenge in the calculation of competitive low-energy structures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="184"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Calculations at the MP2 level tend to overestimate the attraction in the naphthalene dimer, most significantly for the structures lowest in energy.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit52">52</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="185"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Application of DFT to this system is also particularly unsuitable: the high-energy structures have attractive electrostatic energy contributions and relatively small dispersion contributions, and the low-energy structures have electrostatic contributions that are less favourable, while having relatively large dispersion contributions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit44 cit52">44,52</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="186"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is opposed to the benzene dimer where the low-energy structures have favourable electrostatic interactions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="187"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Accordingly, with the exception of LDA, most functionals will incorrectly predict that the T structures (T<SB>1</SB> and T<SB>2</SB> as shown in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit44">ref. 44</REF>) are the lowest in energy (no isomers are bound using PW91 and B3LYP).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit53">53</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="188"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In other words, for the naphthalene dimer, fortuitous location of the low-energy structures, by virtue of attractive electrostatic interactions, is not possible, making this system an excellent test case for new functionals.</annotationART></s> <s sid="189"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Most published theoretical studies of the naphthalene dimer have made use of MP2 calculations.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit44 cit52 cit54 cit55 cit56">44,52,54–56</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="190"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Full CCSD(T) calculations with any reasonable basis set are currently out of reach, at least for the low symmetry structures.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="191"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Several studies have reported low-energy structures of the naphthalene dimer using MP2 calculations with a range of basis sets,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit44 cit52 cit54 cit55">44,52,54,55</REF> including correlation corrections to MP2 interaction energies, using CCSD(T) calculations.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit52">52</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="192"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">It appears that, at present, the lowest-energy structure corresponds to a crossed <IT>C</IT><SB>2</SB> geometry, with a slipped <IT>C</IT><SB>i</SB> structure also energetically competitive.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit44">44</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="193"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">This result has also been reported by Gonzalez and Lim, using a HF+D approach.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="194"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj12" novelty="New" advantage="None">Here, four low-energy structures (Fig. 3) and one high-energy structure are considered.</annotationART></s> <s sid="195"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The optimum interaction energies and centre-of-mass separations are summarised in Table 5, with the MP2 (CCSD(T)-corrected) data of Tsuzuki <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit52">52</REF>. presented for comparison, along with the HF+D data of Gonzalez and Lim.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="196"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp12" novelty="None" advantage="None">For each low-energy structure, the separations were varied with displacements of ±0.2 Å away (along the vector connecting the centre ofmass points) from the optimum separation (as was determined by MP2/6-31G* geometry optimizations.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit44">44</REF>)</annotationART></s> <s sid="197"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp12" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the high-energy <IT>D</IT><SB>2h</SB> structure, the optimum separation was taken from Tsuzuki <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit52">52</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="198"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp12" novelty="None" advantage="None">This separation was varied along the vector connecting the centre of mass points in the same way.</annotationART></s> <s sid="199"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is seen in Table 5 that the HF+WL separations all seem reasonable when compared with the <IT>ab initio</IT> data, although are consistently too short.</annotationART></s> <s sid="200"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">The trend in energetics for the <IT>D</IT><SB>2d</SB>, <IT>C</IT><SB>i</SB> and <IT>C</IT><SB>2h</SB> structures agrees with the best estimates, although there is not quantitative agreement.</annotationART></s> <s sid="201"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">In particular, the best estimates indicate that the <IT>D</IT><SB>2d</SB> and <IT>C</IT><SB>2h</SB> structures are almost isoenergetic, while the HF+WL data support a difference of over 0.5 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="202"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac20" novelty="None" advantage="None">Tsuzuki <IT>et al.</IT> did not examine the <IT>C</IT><SB>2</SB> structure, so we have made comparisons with the trend from the HF+D results of Gonzalez and Lim.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="203"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None">In agreement with their findings, and with previous MP2 optimisations,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit44">44</REF> the HF+WL approach also supports the <IT>C</IT><SB>2</SB> structure as the putative global minimum for the naphthalene dimer system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="204"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The absolute HF+WL interaction energy for the <IT>D</IT><SB>2h</SB> structure deviates significantly from the <IT>ab initio</IT> value, although it is bound, and exhibits the smallest interaction energy of the set, in accord with Tsuzuki <IT>et al.</IT> Again, these data emphasise that HF+WL cannot outperform high-quality post-HF calculations.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="205"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj13" novelty="New" advantage="None">The X3LYP and xPBE functionals were also tested for all five naphthalene dimer structures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="206"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">For both of these functionals, none of the five structures were bound, out to a centre-of-mass separation of 6.0 Å.</annotationART></s> <s sid="207"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the xPBE functional, at a 6.0 Å separation, interaction energies were 0.19, 0.12, 0.72, 0.06 and 0.23 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> for the <IT>D</IT><SB>2d</SB>, <IT>C</IT><SB>2</SB>, <IT>C</IT><SB>2h</SB>, <IT>C</IT><SB>i</SB> and <IT>D</IT><SB>2h</SB> structures, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="208"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" advantage="None">The X3LYP values showed a similar trend, with absolute interaction energies slightly higher in all cases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="209"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" advantage="None">This behaviour is similar to that noted for other popular functionals.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit53">53</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="210"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con15" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is clear that neither of these functionals can reliably yield binding for aromatic ring interactions at a qualitative level.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="211"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj14" novelty="New" advantage="None">The basis set dependence of the HF+WL approach was also tested for the naphthalene dimer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="212"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp13" novelty="None" advantage="None">At first the 6-31G* basis was used.</annotationART></s> <s sid="213"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None">This appeared to give satisfactory results for the four low-energy structures–yielding −4.77, −3.10, −4.70 and −3.93 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> for the <IT>C</IT><SB>2</SB>, <IT>D</IT><SB>2d</SB>, <IT>C</IT><SB>i</SB> and <IT>C</IT><SB>2h</SB> structures, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="214"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None">At this level of theory, the <IT>D</IT><SB>2h</SB> was not bound for any separation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="215"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None">This result confirms the behaviour of the HF+WL/6-31G* level as noted for the benzene dimer calculations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="216"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None">The <IT>D</IT><SB>2h</SB> was checked instead using both the 6-31+G* and 6-311G* basis sets, with both yielding binding, optimised at −1.07 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> and −1.80 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="217"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res29" novelty="None" advantage="None">The HF+WL/6-31+G* also yields reasonable results for the low-energy structures, giving interaction energies of −5.83, −4.14, −5.75 and −4.86 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> for the <IT>C</IT><SB>2</SB>, <IT>D</IT><SB>2d</SB>, <IT>C</IT><SB>i</SB> and <IT>C</IT><SB>2h</SB> structures respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="218"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con16" novelty="None" advantage="None">This confirms the necessity for using at least split-valence plus diffuse functions in the basis set when using HF+WL.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="219"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj15" novelty="New" advantage="None">The final test system comprises the base-stacking interaction for dimers of pyrimidine, cytosine, uracil and guanine.</annotationART></s> <s sid="220"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The stabilisation of stacked base-pairs is thought to arise from van der Waals interactions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit57">57</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="221"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The geometries of these systems are shown in Fig. 4.</annotationART></s> <s sid="222"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac21" novelty="None" advantage="None">These systems have been the subject of studies using MP2,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit45">45</REF> CCSD(T),<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit45">45</REF> empirically-corrected DFT<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16 cit18 cit58">16,18,58</REF> and HF+D calculations.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit58">58</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="223"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac21" novelty="None" advantage="None">The pyrimidine system has been best characterised, at the CCSD(T)/aug-cc-pVDZ(+f functions and bond functions) level of theory,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit45">45</REF> but only at one geometry (see Fig. 4) with the vertical separation fixed to 3.3 Å.</annotationART></s> <s sid="224"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac21" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the remaining systems (fixed at the geometries in Fig. 4) examined by Hobza and Šponer, uracil was characterised up to the MP2/aug-cc-pVTZ(+ bond functions) level, cytosine up to the MP2/aug-cc-pVTZ leveland guanine up to the MP2/aug-cc-pVDZ level.</annotationART></s> <s sid="225"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac21" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this by work of Hobza and Šponer,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit45">45</REF> the vertical separation of cytosine and guanine dimers were fixed at 3.3 Å and 3.4 Å, respectively, and the uracil dimer geometry came from geometry optimisation at the MP2/6-31G** level.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="226"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The minimum energy separations and interaction energies for these four systems, calculated at the HF+WL/aug-cc-pVDZ level, are reported in Table 6, as are <IT>ab initio</IT> data obtained by Hobza and Šponer.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit45">45</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="227"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac22" novelty="None" advantage="None">The <IT>ab initio</IT> data of Hobza and Šponer are the best estimates (obtained using an extrapolation procedure involving MP2 complete basis set data with CCSD(T) corrections) available at present.</annotationART></s> <s sid="228"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res30" novelty="None" advantage="None">The agreement with the best energetic estimates from Hobza and Šponer is good for all cases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="229"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res30" novelty="None" advantage="None">The trend in the interaction energies is reproduced, although the absolute values appear fortuitously close to the best estimates.</annotationART></s> <s sid="230"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is interesting to note that the lowest-energy separation for pyrimidine is larger than the separation estimated by Hobza and Šponer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="231"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res32" novelty="None" advantage="None">All other separations obtained using the HF+WL approach are, as expected, underestimated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="232"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj16" novelty="New" advantage="None">These systems were also investigated using the xPBE and X3LYP functionals, both with the aug-cc-pVDZ basis set.</annotationART></s> <s sid="233"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results are summarised in Table 6.</annotationART></s> <s sid="234"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res33" novelty="None" advantage="None">Every structure was bound for both functionals, although the attraction is decreased in comparison with the data of Hobza and Šponer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="235"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res34" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, the separation corresponding to the optimum interaction energy is increased relative to the results from Hobza and Šponer. xPBE manages to capture the trend of the interaction energies, although as already observed for the methane dimer, the range of interaction energies is considerably smaller than is seen in the <IT>ab initio</IT> results.</annotationART></s> <s sid="236"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res35" novelty="None" advantage="None">X3LYP is seen to perform similarly to xPBE for these systems.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="237"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj17" novelty="New" advantage="None">The basis set dependency was again explored by repeating these calculations at the HF+WL/6-31G* level.</annotationART></s> <s sid="238"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Again, the vertical separation between monomers was optimised to yield the optimum interaction energy in each case.</annotationART></s> <s sid="239"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res36" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results with the 6-31G* basis do not show much difference with the data obtained with the aug-cc-pVDZ basis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="240"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The interaction energies of pyrimidine, uracil, cytosine and guanine were −3.1, −11.3, −10.3 and −14.0 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="241"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs20" novelty="None" advantage="None">The corresponding optimised separations at the HF+WL/6-31G* level were 3.4, 2.97, 3.1 and 3.0 Å, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="242"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res37" novelty="None" advantage="None">This behaviour in stark contrast with the behaviour noted for the <IT>D</IT><SB>2h</SB> isomer of the naphthalene dimer, and the F structure of the benzene dimer, both of which were unbound at the HF+WL/6-31G* level.</annotationART></s> <s sid="243"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con17" novelty="None" advantage="None">It must be re-emphasised that, as a general rule, it appears that HF+WL calculations must be used with at least split-valence plus diffuse functions in order to capture qualitative behaviour.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="244"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con17" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is clear from all of the test cases examined that the HF+WL approach is capable of recovering qualitative trends in interaction energies for pure van der Waals (dispersion and repulsion) systems, albeit with shorter equilibrium distances (most of the time).</annotationART></s> <s sid="245"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Relative orientations seemed to be captured well for the HF+WL approach.</annotationART></s> <s sid="246"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con17" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, no claim is made to suggest that the HF+WL approach can describe a pure van der Waals system with quantitative accuracy, and therefore is not competitive with post-Hartree–Fock methodologies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="247"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con17" novelty="None" advantage="None">To quantify the conditions under which this approach appears to be of value it is noted that, for example, in the case of the rare gas dimers, the HF+WL approach yields reasonable results for systems with overlaps no smaller than around 10<SP>−5</SP> (with the exception of the helium dimer).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="248"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">A HF+WL-type of approach may be extremely useful for optimising geometries of low-symmetry structures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="249"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac23" novelty="None" advantage="None">Low-symmetry structures can be very time-consuming to optimise at any post-HF level (with a sufficiently large basis set), although advances are being made in this area (<IT>e.g.</IT> see .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">ref. 4</REF>)</annotationART></s> <s sid="250"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results of HF+WL optimisations would at least indicate which of the structures should be considered for further refinement by more expensive post-HF methods.</annotationART></s> <s sid="251"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con18" novelty="None" advantage="None">For example, the location of the <IT>C</IT><SB>2</SB> structure of the naphthalene dimer was missed by several MP2-based geometry optimisation studies, presumably because of the low symmetry and the computational demands this creates.</annotationART></s> <s sid="252"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Another example is the geometry optimisation of small molecules adsorbed onto periodic substrates.</annotationART></s> <s sid="253"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac24" novelty="None" advantage="None">Periodic EXX calculations are now possible <IT>via</IT> some mainstream plane-wave codes, making EXXWL presumably more efficient than currently available periodic MP2 implementations (as found in GAUSSIAN03).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="254"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con19" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is also noted that the HF+WL approach appeared to work reliably only when a basis set featuring at least split-valence plus diffuse functions was used.</annotationART></s> <s sid="255"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The HF+WL/6-31G* level was demonstrated to be insufficient in several instances.</annotationART></s> <s sid="256"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, these conclusions only hold at separations where the charge distribution on each fragment overlaps.</annotationART></s> <s sid="257"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The HF+WL approach cannot be successfully applied in the large separation regime.</annotationART></s> <s sid="258"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con20" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is also clear that the current group of exchange–correlation functionals, B3LYP, PBE, X3LYP and xPBE, cannot be reliably used even for qualitative work.</annotationART></s> <s sid="259"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con20" novelty="None" advantage="None">For these functionals, of those structures that showed any binding at all, the binding was substantially underestimated compared with best estimates from <IT>ab initio</IT> calculations.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="260"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac25" novelty="None" advantage="None">Two clear limitations of these current calculations are acknowledged.</annotationART></s> <s sid="261"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con21" novelty="None" advantage="None">The first is that for all the systems studied here, the monomers were treated as rigid body fragments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="262"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con21" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the intramolecular degrees of freedom could in principle be optimised using the HF+WL approach.</annotationART></s> <s sid="263"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con22" novelty="None" advantage="None">The second limitation is on the type of system that can be studied with this method (the same restrictions apply to HF+D methods), and is a consequence of how the correlation contribution forms a perturbative correction to the total Hartree–Fock energy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="264"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con22" novelty="None" advantage="None">This limitation could be lifted if the WL correlation could be included dynamically, within Kohn–Sham DFT, <IT>via</IT> the implementation of exact-exchange methods (denoted here as the proposed EXXWL functional).</annotationART></s> <s sid="265"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac26" novelty="None" advantage="None">Methods based on exact exchange, such as the optimised effective potential (OEP),<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit35">35</REF> the KLI approximation,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit59">59</REF> and more recently, the localised HF approach<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit60">60</REF> and the direct optimisation method,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit61">61</REF> will also ensure that the intermolecular exchange behaves as HF exchange.</annotationART></s> <s sid="266"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con23" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fully self-consistent EXXWL functional would allow treatment of systems where a general HF+D approach currently fails (such as the NaAr complex, molecular physisorption on metal surfaces, <IT>etc</IT>)., where the HF wavefunction cannot distort if dynamic correlation effects are not accounted for.</annotationART></s> <s sid="267"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac27" novelty="None" advantage="None">Work is currently underway to enable calculations with the EXXWL functional in future.</annotationART></s> <s sid="268"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac27" novelty="None" advantage="None">Compared with the HF+WL approach, a much wider range of systems could be treated with the EXXWL functional.</annotationART></s> <s sid="269"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac28" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, promising developments of inclusion of ‘left–right’ correlation with exact exchange within the KS-DFT framework<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit62">62</REF> suggest that an approach that combines non-dynamical correlation with the EXXWL functional may in future permit reasonable modelling of bond-breaking in weakly-bonded systems.</annotationART></s> <s sid="270"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac28" novelty="None" advantage="None">Such an EXXWL functional is not intended to act as a replacement for more accurate post-HF methods, but rather as a device for optimising the structure and energetics of weakly-bonded systems that are not amenable even to MP2 optimisations.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="271"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con24" novelty="None" advantage="None">Compelling reasons for why the WL functional works so well in the cases studied here remain unclear.</annotationART></s> <s sid="272"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con24" novelty="None" advantage="None">Of course, there is no way that the WL correlation functional can provide a realistic description of London dispersion interactions at long range.</annotationART></s> <s sid="273"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="New" advantage="None">WL was parametrised from high-quality quantum chemical data for a small number of atoms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="274"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">It also, by design, should work well with Hartree–Fock densities.</annotationART></s> <s sid="275"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac29" novelty="None" advantage="None">Wilson and Levy point out that, due to the way in which the functional was parametrised, it may not perform well for systems where the Hartree–Fock density differs substantially from the true density.</annotationART></s> <s sid="276"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac29" novelty="None" advantage="None">Because of the constraints imposed by the HF+D-like approach used here, the systems chosen for study should have HF densities that are reasonably close to the true density.</annotationART></s> <s sid="277"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac29" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, an investigation of systems where there is less similarity between HF and real densities is, at present, desirable.</annotationART></s> <s sid="278"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac29" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, these systems should only be studied within a fully self-consistent implementation of the EXXWL functional.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="279"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con25" novelty="None" advantage="None">The WL correlation potential has been examined, and appears to have unremarkable properties in comparison with other correlation potentials.</annotationART></s> <s sid="280"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con25" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is similar to other correlation potentials, <IT>e.g.</IT> the Perdew(86)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit63">63</REF> correlation functional, in the sense that the potential decays to the asymptotic limit exponentially.</annotationART></s> <s sid="281"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con25" novelty="None" advantage="None">This behaviour is reasonable in the sense that the correlation potential should decay faster than the exchange potential (in the case of the HF potential, the asymptotic decay goes like −1/<IT>r</IT>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="282"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac30" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, it has been remarked by others<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit64">64</REF> that perhaps a more realistic asymptotic behaviour of the correlation potential would be −<IT>α</IT>/<IT>r</IT><SP>4</SP>, where <IT>α</IT> is the polarizability.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="283"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The WL correlation functional is based on the local Wigner correlation functional<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30">30</REF> (W38).</annotationART></s> <s sid="284"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The LYP correlation functional,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit65">65</REF> due to its basis on the Colle–Salvetti formula, is also based on the form of the W38 functional.</annotationART></s> <s sid="285"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The LYP functional comprises a (local) W38 component multiplied by another functional that contains gradient correction terms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="286"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="Old" advantage="None">This is in common with many exchange functionals that analogously comprise the Dirac (local) exchange, multiplied by another functional that contains gradient correction terms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="287"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">Functionals of a form such as this lend themselves easily to an analysis in the low-density/high-density-gradient regime, since one can construct an ‘enhancement factor’ (the function that is multiplied by the local component of the functional).</annotationART></s> <s sid="288"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="Old" advantage="No">Unfortunately, the WL functional is not multiplicatively separable in this sense from the W38 functional.</annotationART></s> <s sid="289"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="Old" advantage="No">Since it is difficult to disentangle the W38 functional from the WL functional, the WL functional is therefore not amenable to an analogous analysis of the ‘enhancement factor’.</annotationART></s> <s sid="290"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac31" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is worth mentioning that even W38 (without gradient corrections) in partnership with Becke88<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit34">34</REF> exchange (the B-W functional)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit66">66</REF> has been shown to perform comparably with BLYP, although the reasons for this also remain unclear.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="291"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac32" novelty="None" advantage="None">Finally, it is plausible that the WL functional yields unphysical attractive contributions for some of the short-ranged contributions to the interaction energy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="292"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac33" novelty="None" advantage="None">A decomposition scheme based on Heitler–London type calculations, as reported by Cybulski and Seversen,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF> may be helpful in this instance.</annotationART></s> <s sid="293"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con26" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fact that the HF+WL almost always underestimates monomer separations seems consistent with this idea.</annotationART></s> <s sid="294"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con26" novelty="None" advantage="None">Even if the origins of this unphysical behaviour can be revealed, further work is required to understand why these (potentially) unphysical terms combine such that very good interaction energies are ultimately recovered, albeit fortuitously.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="295"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con26" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, while admittedly not having a satisfying and physically rigorous theoretical justification, the HF+WL approach (or in future, the EXXWL functional) may become a useful pragmatic device for optimising the geometries of large and/or complicated van der Waals complexes that are currently beyond the reach of optimisation by more sophisticated <IT>ab initio</IT> methods.</annotationART></s> <s sid="296"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con26" novelty="None" advantage="None">Other functionals, including those that are claimed to describe weak interactions such as xPBE and X3LYP, while also not capable of recovering London dispersion, cannot reliably perform the role of a pragmatic device, even when monomer charge distributions overlap.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.">Conclusions</HEADER><P><s sid="297"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj18" novelty="New" advantage="None">The Wilson–Levy (WL) correlation functional was used as a post-Hartree–Fock (HF) perturbative correction in the evaluation of the interaction energy for a range of weakly-bound dimers, in the regime of small to intermediate fragment separations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="298"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con27" novelty="None" advantage="None">It was found that this HF+WL approach works well in a pragmatic and qualitative sense for the energetics of closed-shell van der Waals systems, but without a satisfying physical justification, and without quantitative accuracy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="299"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res38" novelty="None" advantage="None">Two newly-developed exchange–correlation functionals, designed for applications to biological systems (X3LYP and xPBE), were also investigated and found to perform not as well as the HF+WL approach.</annotationART></s> <s sid="300"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con28" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results of this work suggest an apparently promising device in the form of the EXXWL functional, for determining the energetic trends of molecules physisorbed on surfaces, nanotubes and other periodic structures.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
