<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b416924g" hasDoc="yes" version="1184" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Observation and rovibrational analysis of the intermolecular HCl libration band <IT>ν</IT>16 of HCN–HCl, DCN–HCl and H<SP>13</SP>CN–HCl<XREF TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" /></annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">The high-resolution far-infrared absorption spectrum of the intermolecular HCl libration band <IT>ν</IT>16 (<IT>ν</IT><SB>B</SB>) of the gaseous molecular complex H<SP>12</SP>CN–HCl and the two isotopically substituted species H<SP>13</SP>CN–HCl and D<SP>12</SP>CN–HCl is recorded by means of static gas-phase Fourier transform far-infrared spectroscopy at 205 K using an electron storage ring source.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rotational structure of the <IT>ν</IT>16 band has the typical appearance of a perpendicular type band of a linear polyatomic molecule.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The structure is analyzed using a standard semi-rigid linear molecule model including <IT>l</IT>-type doubling to yield the band origin <IT>ν</IT><SB>0</SB>, together with values for the upper state rotational constant <IT>B</IT>′, the upper state quartic centrifugal distortion constant <IT>D</IT>′<SB><IT>J</IT></SB> and the value for the <IT>l</IT>-type doubling constant <IT>q</IT><SB>6</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The values for the ground-state spectroscopic constants <IT>B</IT>″ and <IT>D</IT>″<SB><IT>J</IT></SB> for D<SP>12</SP>CN–H<SP>35</SP>Cl and H<SP>13</SP>CN–H<SP>35</SP>Cl are determined for the first time by ground state combination difference analyses.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">A number of <IT>ν</IT>16 + <IT>ν</IT>17 − <IT>ν</IT>17 and <IT>ν</IT>16 + 2<IT>ν</IT><SB>7</SB><SP>2</SP> − 2<IT>ν</IT><SB>7</SB><SP>2</SP> hot bands are observed in the spectra and the sum of the anharmonicity constants <IT>X</IT><SB>6,7</SB> + <IT>g</IT><SB>6,7</SB> is estimated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The observed decrease of the rotational constant <IT>B</IT> together with the simultaneous increase of the quartic centrifugal distortion constant <IT>D</IT><SB><IT>J</IT></SB> upon excitation of the HCl libration mode indicate that the hydrogen bond in the molecular complex is significantly destabilized upon intermolecular vibrational excitation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The calculated harmonic force constants for the intermolecular hydrogen bond stretching vibration <IT>ν</IT><SB><IT>σ</IT></SB> for the ground state and the excited HCl libration state indicate that the excitation of the HCl libration mode destabilizes the intermolecular interaction between HCN and HCl by almost 20%.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The hydrogen bond is elongated by 0.030 Å upon excitation of the <IT>ν</IT>16 mode.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="1.">Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The high-resolution infrared absorption spectrum of a bimolecular complex provides detailed information about the forces acting between the two molecular species defined by intermolecular potential energy surface (IPES), as well as how the intramolecular force fields within the subunits are modified by the incorporation into the bimolecular entity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The accurate characterization of the IPES for a molecular complex requires the observation and analysis of a wide variety of gas phase spectra of fundamental bands, overtone bands, hot bands, combination bands, not only for the parent species but also for a sufficient number of isotopomers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The low-wavenumber intermolecular vibrational degrees of freedom depend directly on the properties of the IPES and are therefore of special importance.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Infrared absorption spectra of hydrogen-bonded molecular complexes have been a subject of a long range of studies in the literature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, only a few numbers of these studies have dealt with the important intermolecular part of the vibrational spectrum for such molecular complexes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reason appears to be that there exist few suitable spectroscopic radiation sources in the far-infrared spectral region where the floppy intermolecular vibrations of molecular complexes are normally observed.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Measurements of rotationally resolved absorption spectra of intermolecular vibrations of gaseous molecular complexes require a spectral resolution close to the Doppler limit in the far-infrared spectral region.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the steep fall-off of energy with decreasing frequency for conventional black body radiators means that far-infrared spectroscopy generally is energy-limited at normal source temperatures in the sense that the resolution which can be attained is ultimately limited by the intensity of the source.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Far-infrared synchrotron radiation from an electron storage ring provides a far more brilliant source than conventional black body radiators, if the noise problems connected with electron beam oscillations can be solved.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">A high-brightness source of far-infrared synchrotron radiation is therefore suitable for measurements in which high spectral resolution and high sensitivity is needed simultaneously.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">This was demonstrated in our earlier publication on the intermolecular HCl libration band <IT>ν</IT><SB>4</SB><SP>1</SP>of the linear hydrogen-bonded heterodimer OC–H<SP>35</SP>Cl.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2">1,2</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">In the present work we investigate the high-resolution far-infrared absorption spectrum of the gaseous hydrogen-bonded heterodimer of HCN and HCl.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast to the wealth of spectroscopic information available for the closely related prototype dimer HCN–HF (see <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">ref. 3</REF> and references therein) and to a lesser extent for (HCN)<SB>2</SB> (see <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">ref. 4</REF>, and references therein) the spectroscopic information about the molecular complex HCN–HCl reported in the literature is rather limited.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The first observation of the isolated molecular complex between HCN and HCl in the gas phase was reported by Legon <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF>. who used Fourier transform microwave (MW) spectroscopy conducted in a Fabry–Perot cavity with a pulsed nozzle molecular source.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None">In this study, accurate ground-state spectroscopic constants were determined for the parent isotopic molecular complex and three additional isotopomers containing D, <SP>15</SP>N and <SP>37</SP>Cl.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Interpretation of the spectroscopic constants led to the conclusion that the most stable configuration of the molecular complex of HCN and HCl is collinear or near collinear at equilibrium, establishing the presence of a hydrogen bond to the N atom of the HCN molecule.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The vibrationally averaged distance between the centers of mass of the two monomers was determined to be 3.9380 Å.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Bender <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF>. observed and assigned the intramolecular C–H stretching vibration band <IT>ν</IT><SB>1</SB> of HCN–H<SP>35</SP>Cl using a static gas long-path absorption cell at 199 K interfaced with a tunable single-frequency color-center laser spectrometer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Bender <IT>et al</IT>. also managed to make tentative assignments of the three hot bands <IT>ν</IT><SB>1</SB> + <IT>ν</IT>17 − <IT>ν</IT>17, <IT>ν</IT><SB>1</SB> + 2<IT>ν</IT>27 − 2<IT>ν</IT>27 and <IT>ν</IT><SB>1</SB> + 3<IT>ν</IT>37 − 3<IT>ν</IT>37 where <IT>ν</IT>17 is the doubly degenerate low-wavenumber intermolecular bending vibration (libration of HCN).</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The assignment of the <IT>ν</IT><SB>1</SB> band was later slightly modified and extended by Block and Miller.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The observed small red shift of 2.5 cm<SP>−1</SP> for the band origin of <IT>ν</IT><SB>1</SB> of HCN–H<SP>35</SP>Cl relative to the C–H stretching vibration band of monomer HCN indicates that the hydrogen bond is rather unaffected by excitation of the <IT>ν</IT><SB>1</SB> mode.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In a recent study<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF> the present authors reported the observation and rovibrational analysis of the intramolecular H–Cl stretching vibration band <IT>ν</IT><SB>2</SB> of HCN–H<SP>35</SP>Cl.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">A red shift of 107 cm<SP>−1</SP> of the <IT>ν</IT><SB>2</SB> band of HCN–H<SP>35</SP>Cl relative to the H–Cl stretching vibration band for monomeric H<SP>35</SP>Cl together with a positive value of Δ<IT>B</IT> upon vibrational excitation of <IT>ν</IT><SB>2</SB> showed that the hydrogen bond strengthens upon intramolecular vibrational excitation of the <IT>ν</IT><SB>2</SB> mode.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The intermolecular hydrogen bond vibrations of the HCN–HCl complex have not been observed directly.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Bender <IT>et al</IT>. estimated the band origin of the intermolecular HCN libration band <IT>ν</IT>17 to be 41(3) cm<SP>−1</SP> from the value of the <IT>l</IT>-type doubling constant.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The same authors estimate the harmonic frequency for the intermolecular hydrogen bond stretching vibration <IT>ν</IT><SB>4</SB> (<IT>ν</IT><SB><IT>σ</IT></SB>) to be 100(5) cm<SP>−1</SP> from the ground-state spectroscopic constants using the modified pseudo diatomic (MPD) approximation developed by Millen.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The harmonic frequency for the intermolecular HCl libration band <IT>ν</IT>16 (<IT>ν</IT><SB>B</SB>) is computed to be 311 cm<SP>−1</SP> in the <IT>ab initio</IT> study by Araújo <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="New" advantage="None">The present study reports the direct observation and rovibrational analysis of the intermolecular HCl libration band of HCN–HCl, DCN–HCl and H<SP>13</SP>CN–HCl by means of static gas-phase Fourier transform far-infrared spectroscopy and a far-infrared synchrotron radiation source.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.">Experimental</HEADER><P><s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The present experiments are carried out at the infrared beam-line at MAX-Lab at Lund University.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">A temperature controlled 200-L static absorption cell made of stainless steel is interfaced with a Bruker IFS 120 HR Fourier transform spectrometer (FTS).</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The absorption cell has a White type multipass mirror system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The base length of the absorption cell is 2.85 m and the optics provide a total optical path length of <IT>ca.</IT> 91.2 m.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The absorption cell is equipped with two sets of 3.2 mm CsI windows.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The cell temperature is measured in the middle and at both ends of the inner cell with standard Pt100 resistance thermometers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">A computer emulated PID temperature controller regulates the current supplied to the three different resistive heaters welded to the outside of the inner cell and maintains the cell temperature of 205 ± 0.25 K during the experiment.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This temperature is close to the condensation point of HCN at the pressure used for the experiment.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">HCN and DCN are prepared by dropwise addition of diluted H<SB>2</SB>SO and D<SB>2</SB>SO<SB>4</SB> (99.8 atom% diluted in 99.3 atom% D<SB>2</SB>O) onto KCN <IT>in vacuo</IT> and condensation of the gaseous product.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The hydrogen cyanide samples are dried by vacuum distillation through a column containing the P<SB>2</SB>O<SB>5</SB> drying agent.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Impurities of CO<SB>2</SB> and (CN)<SB>2</SB> are then removed from the samples by fractional distillation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The partial pressures of HCN and natural isotopic HCl in the absorption cell are 2 Torr and 5 Torr, respectively.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The radiation source is synchrotron radiation from the electron storage ring MAX-I at MAX-lab.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11 cit12">11,12</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">MAX-I is a 550 MeV electron storage ring with a 250 mA maximum ring current and a mean lifetime of 4 h.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The transfer optics are described elsewhere.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The CsI exit window from the electron storage ring is mounted at Brewster’s angle to the horizontally polarized radiation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The plane of polarization is then converted to vertical, since far-infrared beam splitters are more effective with this polarization.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The electron storage ring is a high-brightness source of broadband infrared radiation, covering the full far-infrared spectral region.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Synchrotron radiation is very close to a point source and is very suitable for high-resolution infrared spectroscopy.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11 cit12 cit13 cit14 cit15 cit16 cit17 cit18 cit19 cit20">11–20</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The radiation output from the electron storage ring relative to the radiation output from a conventional globar source is characterized in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11 cit12">refs. 11 and 12</REF>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The interferometer is equipped with a 6 μm multilayer beam splitter which works well over the entire spectral range 50−600 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The detector is a liquid He cooled Si-bolometer operating at 1.7 K (Infrared Laboratories, Inc)..</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The detector element is small, and allows us to use high scanning speeds.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The high scanning speeds make the bolometer less sensitive to motions of the electron beam.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">A cold band pass optical filter (0–370 cm<SP>−1</SP>) is mounted in the bolometer in order to reduce the photonic noise level and detector nonlinearity effects in the final spectra.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The combination of optical filters at the bolometer, the 6 μm multilayer beam splitter and the CsI cell and exit windows gives a band pass in the region 190–370 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The FTS instrument resolution (RES) is defined as RES = 0.9/(MOPD), where MOPD is the maximum optical path difference in the interferometer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Sample interferograms are recorded with a resolution of 0.005 cm<SP>−1</SP> (MOPD = 180 cm).</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The recorded sample interferograms are transformed using Mertz phase correction and boxcar apodization.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">A total scan time for each spectrum of <IT>ca.</IT> 10 h is achieved.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Throughout the measurements the FTS is evacuated by a vacuum pump reducing absorption by atmospheric gasses in the optical path inside the FTS.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Background interferograms of the evacuated absorption cell are recorded with a resolution of 0.08 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">These are transformed and interpolated onto a wavenumber grid matching that of the sample spectra using a zero-filling factor of 16.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">This background resolution is appropriate in order to cancel out the most dominant interference fringes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The resulting signal-to-noise ratio in the final absorbance spectra is about 20 : 1 for the most intense observed transitions.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The absolute wavenumber scale of the absorption spectrum is calibrated against published rotational lines of H<SB>2</SB>O<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF> observed in the spectrum.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The H<SB>2</SB>O lines appear in our spectra due to residual water vapor in the evacuated interferometer tank.</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The accuracy of these water line positions is estimated to be 0.0002 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Line positions from the absorbance spectra are generated using the Microcal Origin 7.0 software package (Microcal software, Inc)..</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The precision of the line positions is estimated to be ten times better than the spectral resolution.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.">Results and analysis</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3a.">HCN–H<SP>35</SP>Cl and HCN–H<SP>37</SP>Cl</HEADER><P><s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The high-resolution far-infrared absorption spectrum of the mixture of natural isotopic HCl and HCN shows extensive rotational structures which are assigned to the intermolecular HCl libration band <IT>ν</IT>16 of the HCN–H<SP>35</SP>Cl and HCN–H<SP>37</SP>Cl heterodimers and hot band progressions for the parent isotopomer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The appearance of the main band is typical for a linear molecule perpendicular type band (Σ–Π) with a rather large negative value for Δ<IT>B</IT>, as may be expected for the HCl libration motion of the HCN–HCl complex.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This observation together with the fact that the HCN–HCl system has high symmetry in the equilibrium configuration suggest that a standard semi-rigid linear molecule model is suitable for the present spectral analysis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The central Q-branch of the band is located at 331.4 cm<SP>−1</SP> and degrades widely at lower wavenumbers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Q-branch is accompanied by weaker P- and R-branches; the R-branch forms a band head near 335.4 cm<SP>−1</SP> while the P-branch shows increasing <IT>J</IT>-spacing at lower wavenumbers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Q-branch and the P-branch are assigned to <IT>J</IT> = 65 and 53, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the R-branch the band head appears for <IT>J</IT> = 55, 56.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">This branch is therefore assigned up to <IT>J</IT> = 46.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 1 shows part of the <IT>J</IT>-assignment of the Q-branch and Fig. 2 shows part of the <IT>J</IT>-assignment and the observed band head for the R-branch.</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The total number of rovibrational transitions assigned to the <IT>ν</IT>16 band of HCN–H<SP>35</SP>Cl is listed in Table S1 which is available as ESI.<SUP TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" /></annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">A number of additional weak absorption lines is observed in the Q-branch region for HCN–H<SP>35</SP>Cl.</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fifteen of these weak lines are picked out and assigned to Q-branch transitions with <IT>J</IT> ∈ [27;50] for HCN–H<SP>37</SP>Cl by use of computer-assisted Loomis–Wood diagrams.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is not possible to identify any P- and R-branch lines for the <SP>37</SP>Cl isotopomer and the Q-branch <IT>J</IT>-assignment cannot be verified by ground state combination differences (GSCDs).</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The assigned Q-transitions in the <IT>ν</IT>16 band of HCN–H<SP>37</SP>Cl are listed in Table S2 as ESI.<SUP TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" /></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to determine the values of the upper state spectroscopic constants <IT>B</IT>′ and <IT>D</IT>′<SB><IT>J</IT></SB> (<IT>v</IT><SB>6</SB> = l) for HCN–H<SP>35</SP>Cl the standard semi-rigid linear molecule model based on the following rovibrational energy expressions for the vibrational ground state, <IT>E</IT>″, and excited vibrational state, <IT>E</IT>′, is used:<IT>E</IT>″ = <IT>B</IT>″<IT>J</IT>(<IT>J</IT> + 1) − <IT>D</IT>″<IT><SB>J</SB>J</IT><SP>2</SP>(<IT>J</IT> + 1)<SP>2</SP><IT>E</IT>′ = <IT>ν</IT><SB>0</SB> + <IT>B</IT>′<IT>J</IT>(<IT>J</IT> + 1) − <IT>D</IT>′<IT><SB>J</SB>J</IT><SP>2</SP>(<IT>J</IT> + 1)<SP>2</SP> ± (1/2)<IT>q</IT><SB>6</SB><IT>J</IT>(<IT>J</IT> + 1)In the fit the ground-state constants <IT>B</IT>″and <IT>D</IT>″<SB><IT>J</IT></SB> are constrained to the MW values for HCN–H<SP>35</SP>Cl reported in .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">ref. 5</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">It appears that the effective Δ<IT>B</IT> value obtained from the Q-branch fit is larger than the Δ<IT>B</IT> value from the P, R-branch fit.</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">This indicates the presence of <IT>l</IT>-type doubling<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF> which is accounted for in eqn. (2).</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The plus sign is used for the analysis of the Q-branch; the minus sign is used for the analysis of the P,R-branch system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Including the <IT>l</IT>-type doubling constant <IT>q</IT> in the model the P, Q, and R-branch transitions are analyzed simultaneously.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">A least-squares fit of a total number of 95 rovibrational transitions determines the values of <IT>ν</IT><SB>0</SB>, Δ<IT>B</IT>, Δ<IT>D</IT><SB><IT>J</IT></SB> and <IT>q</IT><SB>6</SB> listed in Table 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The <IT>J</IT>-assignment of the Q-branch and the determination of the spectroscopic constants <IT>ν</IT><SB>0</SB>, Δ<IT>B</IT> and Δ<IT>D</IT><SB><IT>J</IT></SB> for the HCN–H<SP>37</SP>Cl isotopomer are based on a fit of the 15 observed transitions to the conventional diatomic molecule expression given in eqn. (3):<IT>Q</IT>(<IT>J</IT>) = <IT>ν</IT><SB>0</SB> + Δ<IT>BJ</IT>(<IT>J</IT> + 1) − Δ<IT>D</IT><SB><IT>J</IT></SB><IT>J</IT><SP>2</SP>(<IT>J</IT> + 1)<SP>2</SP>Since the polynomial fit is based solely on observed Q-branch transitions the determined value of Δ<IT>B</IT> is affected by <IT>l</IT>-type doubling.</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The actual value is therefore an effective rotational constant Δ<IT>B</IT> ± 0.5<IT>q</IT><SB>6</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="New" advantage="None">The <IT>J</IT>-assignment leading to the fit with minimum standard deviation is chosen.</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The resulting spectroscopic constants are listed in Table 1.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the analysis of the <IT>ν</IT><SB>1</SB> band for HCN–HCl by Bender <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF>. the hot band progressions <IT>ν</IT><SB>1</SB> + <IT>ν</IT>17 − <IT>ν</IT>17, <IT>ν</IT><SB>1</SB> + 2<IT>ν</IT>27 − 2<IT>ν</IT>27 and <IT>ν</IT><SB>1</SB> + 3<IT>ν</IT>37 − 3<IT>ν</IT>37 from the low-wavenumber hydrogen-bond bending vibration <IT>ν</IT>17 were observed.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">A similar hot band pattern consisting of rovibrational structures centered at <IT>ca.</IT> 325, 320 and 315 cm<SP>−1</SP> is observed in the present spectrum.</annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">These features seem to consist of Q-branch lines only.</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is not possible to assign corresponding P- and R-branch lines which makes it difficult to establish the definitive <IT>J</IT>-assignments of the Q-branch lines.</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">From a tentative <IT>J</IT>-assignment of the 325 cm<SP>−1</SP> feature, which is assigned to the <IT>ν</IT>16 + <IT>ν</IT>17 − <IT>ν</IT>17 hot band, the band origin is estimated to be 325.690(5) cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The following sum of anharmonicity constants is estimated based on the band origin of the main band located at 331.400 cm<SP>−1</SP>:<IT>X</IT><SB>6,7</SB> + <IT>g</IT><SB>6,7</SB> = −5.710(5) cm<SP>−1</SP>The spectral feature observed at <IT>ca.</IT> 320 cm<SP>−1</SP> is assigned to the hot band <IT>ν</IT>16 + 2<IT>ν</IT>27 − 2<IT>ν</IT>27 and the band origin is estimated to be 320.155(10) cm<SP>−1</SP> from a tentative <IT>J</IT>-assignment of the Q-branch.</annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The following sum of anharmonicity constants is estimated assuming as in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">ref. 6</REF> that this hot band involves the <IT>l</IT> = 2 component:<IT>X</IT><SB>6,7</SB> + <IT>g</IT><SB>6,7</SB> = −5.622(5) cm<SP>−1</SP>which is in reasonable agreement with the result for <IT>ν</IT>16 + <IT>ν</IT>17 − <IT>ν</IT>17.</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">We predict the band origin of the <IT>ν</IT>16 + 3<IT>ν</IT>37 − 3<IT>ν</IT>37 (<IT>l</IT> = 3) hot band at 314.4 cm<SP>−1</SP> from the average value of <IT>X</IT><SB>6,7</SB> + <IT>g</IT><SB>6,7</SB> of −5.67 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is difficult to locate the beginning of the Q-branch due to the weak intensity of this hot band.</annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, an estimate of the band origin of 314.60(15) cm<SP>−1</SP> seems reasonable, and this is taken as a further confirmation that our assignment of the hot band progressions is consistent.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3b.">DCN–H<SP>35</SP>Cl and DCN–H<SP>37</SP>Cl</HEADER><P><s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The far-infrared absorption spectrum of the mixture of DCN and natural isotopic HCl shows rotational resolved structures which are almost identical to the structures observed for the HCN/HCl mixture and are assigned to the <IT>ν</IT>16 band of DCN–H<SP>35</SP>Cl and DCN–H<SP>37</SP>Cl and weak hot band progressions of DCN–H<SP>35</SP>Cl.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The central Q-branch of the band for DCN–H<SP>35</SP>Cl is located at 331.7 cm<SP>−1</SP> and the R-branch forms a band head near 335.62 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 3 shows part of the <IT>J</IT>-assignment of the Q-branch.</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Q-branch and the P-branch are assigned to <IT>J</IT> = 71 and 61, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the R-branch the band head appears for <IT>J</IT> = 58, 59.</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">This branch is assigned up to <IT>J</IT> = 51.</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">The total number of rovibrational transitions assigned to the band for DCN–H<SP>35</SP>Cl is listed in Table S3, provided as ESI.<SUP TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" /></annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">An additional number of weak absorption lines is observed in the Q-branch region for DCN–H<SP>35</SP>Cl.</annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">A series of 31 weak lines is picked out and assigned to the Q-branch with <IT>J</IT> ∈ [12;70] for the DCN–H<SP>37</SP>Cl isotopomer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">The assigned transitions for DCN–H<SP>37</SP>Cl are listed in Table S4, provided as ESI.<SUP TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" /></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The present P- and R-branch assignments allow us to perform a ground-state combination difference (GSCD) analysis for DCN–H<SP>35</SP>Cl.</annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" advantage="None">A total number of 26 GSCDs is formed with <IT>J</IT> values in the range of 11 to 49 and the resulting values for the ground-state constants <IT>B</IT>″ and <IT>D</IT>″<SB><IT>J</IT></SB> of DCN–H<SP>35</SP>Cl are listed in Table 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">A total number of 132 assigned P-, Q- and R-branch transitions are subsequently analyzed simultaneously using the standard semi-rigid linear molecule model based on eqns. (1) and (2) to obtain values of the band origin <IT>ν</IT><SB>0</SB> and the upper state rotational constant <IT>B</IT>′, the upper state quartic centrifugal distortion constant <IT>D</IT>′<SB><IT>J</IT></SB> and the <IT>l</IT>-type doubling constant <IT>q</IT><SB>6</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this fit, the ground-state spectroscopic constants are constrained to the values obtained from the GSCD analysis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The resulting values of <IT>ν</IT><SB>0</SB>, Δ<IT>B</IT> and Δ<IT>D</IT><SB><IT>J</IT></SB> and <IT>q</IT><SB>6</SB> are listed in Table 1.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The assignment and rovibrational analysis of the 31 observed Q-branch lines in the band for DCN–H<SP>37</SP>Cl are based on the conventional diatomic molecule expression given in eqn. (3).</annotationART></s> <s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None">The <IT>J</IT>-assignment leading to the fit with minimum standard deviation is chosen and the resulting spectroscopic constants are listed in Table 1.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" advantage="None">A hot band pattern with rotational resolved features at <IT>ca.</IT> 325 and 320 cm<SP>−1</SP> is observed in the absorption spectrum.</annotationART></s> <s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None">These features are assigned to the <IT>ν</IT>16 + <IT>ν</IT>17 − <IT>ν</IT>17 and <IT>ν</IT>16 + 2<IT>ν</IT>27 − 2<IT>ν</IT>27 hot bands for DCN–H<SP>35</SP>Cl and are assumed to consist of Q-branch lines.</annotationART></s> <s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None">Tentative <IT>J</IT>-assignments of these Q-branches yield the band origins of 326.50(10) cm<SP>−1</SP> and 321.60(20) cm<SP>−1</SP>, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res29" novelty="None" advantage="None">The observed shifts of 5.20(10) and 10.10(20) cm<SP>−1</SP> relative to the main band give the following average value for the sum of anharmonicity constants:<IT>X</IT><SB>6,7</SB> + <IT>g</IT><SB>6,7</SB> = − 5.12(14)</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3c.">H<SP>13</SP>CN–H<SP>35</SP>Cl and H<SP>13</SP>CN–H<SP>37</SP>Cl</HEADER><P><s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The central Q-branch of the <IT>ν</IT>16 band of H<SP>13</SP>CN–H<SP>35</SP>Cl is located at 331.49 cm<SP>−1</SP> and the R-branch forms a band head near 335.45 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res30" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Q-branch and the P-branch are assigned to <IT>J</IT> = 72 and 56, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the R-branch the band head appears for <IT>J</IT> = 56, 57.</annotationART></s> <s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" advantage="None">This branch is assigned up to <IT>J</IT> = 39.</annotationART></s> <s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res32" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rovibrational transitions assigned to the band for H<SP>13</SP>CN–H <SP>35</SP>Cl are listed in Table S5, provided as ESI.<SUP TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" /></annotationART></s> <s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res33" novelty="None" advantage="None">A series of 27 weak lines is picked out and assigned to the Q-branch with <IT>J</IT> ∈ [19;70] for the <IT>ν</IT>16 band of H<SP>13</SP>CN–H<SP>37</SP>Cl.</annotationART></s> <s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res34" novelty="None" advantage="None">The assigned transitions for H<SP>13</SP>CN–H<SP>37</SP>Cl are listed in Table S6 as ESI.<SUP TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" /></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res35" novelty="None" advantage="None">A GSCD analysis for H<SP>13</SP>CN–H<SP>35</SP>Cl based on 16 GSCDs with <IT>J</IT> in the range 6 to 39 determines the values for the ground-state constants <IT>B</IT>″ and <IT>D</IT>″<SB><IT>J</IT></SB> listed in Table 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">An upper state analysis of 119 assigned P-, Q- and R-branch transitions is subsequently carried out with the ground-state spectroscopic constants constrained to the values obtained from the GSCD analysis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res36" novelty="None" advantage="None">The values of the spectroscopic constants for H<SP>13</SP>CN–H<SP>35</SP>Cl are listed in Table 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="143"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The assignment and rovibrational analysis of the 27 observed Q-branch lines in the <IT>ν</IT>16 band of H<SP>13</SP>CN–H<SP>37</SP>Cl is based on the conventional diatomic molecule expression given in eqn. (3).</annotationART></s> <s sid="144"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res37" novelty="None" advantage="None">The <IT>J</IT>-assignment leading to the fit with minimum standard deviation is chosen and the resulting spectroscopic constants are listed in Table 1.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="145"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res38" novelty="None" advantage="None">A single Q-branch structure is observed in the spectrum around 326 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="146"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res38" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Q-branch is assigned to <IT>ν</IT>16 + <IT>ν</IT>17 − <IT>ν</IT>17 hot band for H<SP>13</SP>CN–H<SP>35</SP>Cl and the sum of anharmonicity constants <IT>X</IT><SB>6,7</SB> + <IT>g</IT><SB>6,7</SB> is estimated to be −5.42(14) cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.">Discussion</HEADER><P><s sid="147"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The appearance of the rotational structure of the HCl libration band <IT>ν</IT>16 and, in particular, the presence of <IT>l</IT>-type doubling observed in the far-infrared absorption spectra confirms the collinearity of the atoms in the molecular complex HCN–HCl.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="148"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The observed decrease of the rotational constant <IT>B</IT> together with the simultaneous increase of the quartic centrifugal distortion constant <IT>D</IT><SB><IT>J</IT></SB> upon excitation of the HCl libration mode indicate that the hydrogen bond in the molecular complex is significantly destabilized upon intermolecular vibrational excitation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="149"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In terms of electrostatics the observed destabilization may be understood from the angular dependence of the dominant dipole–dipole interaction energy between HCN and HCl.</annotationART></s> <s sid="150"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The dipole–dipole interaction between HCN and HCl can be described by a simple potential energy function:where <IT>μ</IT><SB>HCN</SB> and <IT>μ</IT><SB>HCl</SB> are the electric dipole moments of HCN and HCl, respectively, <IT>θ</IT><SB>HCl</SB> and <IT>θ</IT><SB>HCN</SB> are the libration angles (the angles between the two monomeric species and the line between the centers of mass), (<IT>ϕ</IT><SB>1</SB> − <IT>ϕ</IT><SB>2</SB>) is the dihedral angle and <IT>r</IT> is the center of mass separation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="151"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res39" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the harmonic oscillator approximation based on the HCl libration band origin and the rotational constant for HCl the classical HCl bending amplitude <IT>θ</IT><SB>HCl</SB> increases from 14.4° in the ground state to 20.3° upon excitation of the HCl libration mode for H<SP>12</SP>CN–H<SP>35</SP>Cl.</annotationART></s> <s sid="152"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The electric dipole moment of HCl is tilted away from the intermolecular symmetry axis in the molecular complex as the HCl subunit carries out the librational motion and the dipole–dipole interaction becomes more unfavorable owing to the enhanced non-linearity of the configuration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="153"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">In an attempt to quantify this destabilizing effect we use the relations between the determined centrifugal distortion parameters and the parameters of the analytical Morse potential function derived by Larsen <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="154"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this work the values of the Dunham parameters <IT>B</IT>, <IT>D</IT><SB><IT>J</IT></SB> and <IT>H</IT><SB><IT>J</IT></SB> were related to the Morse potential parameters <IT>r</IT>, <IT>a</IT> and <IT>D</IT><SB>e</SB> and used to characterize the intermolecular potential energy surface for the stretching of the hydrogen bond in the linear OC–H<SP>35</SP>Cl complex.</annotationART></s> <s sid="155"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The center of mass separation <IT>r</IT> between HCN and HCl is related to the rotational constant according to:where <IT>B</IT> is the rotational constant of the molecular complex, <IT>I</IT><SB>HCN</SB> and <IT>I</IT><SB>HCl</SB> are the moments of inertia for the HCN and HCl subunits and <IT>μ</IT> is the reduced mass of the molecular complex.</annotationART></s> <s sid="156"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The values for the moments of inertia of the subunits are taken from .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24 cit25 cit26">refs. 24–26</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="157"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The harmonic frequency <IT>ω</IT><SB>4</SB> for the intermolecular stretching vibration of the hydrogen bond is related to the rotational constant and quartic centrifugal distortion constant <IT>D</IT><SB><IT>J</IT></SB> by eqn. (6) assuming that the dominant contribution to the centrifugal distortion of the center of mass distance comes from the hydrogen bond stretching vibration:</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="158"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res40" novelty="None" advantage="None">In Table 2 the estimated center of mass distance and harmonic frequency for the hydrogen bond stretching vibration are listed for the ground state and the excited HCl libration state for H<SP>12</SP>CN–H<SP>35</SP>Cl, D<SP>12</SP>CN–H<SP>35</SP>Cl and H<SP>13</SP>CN–H<SP>35</SP>Cl.</annotationART></s> <s sid="159"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res41" novelty="None" advantage="None">The corresponding harmonic force constants <IT>k</IT><SB>4</SB> which are correlated directly to the dissociation energies of the molecular complexes are also listed in Table 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="160"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res42" novelty="None" advantage="None">It appears that the hydrogen bond elongates by 0.030 Å upon excitation of the HCl libration mode for all three complexes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="161"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res43" novelty="None" advantage="None">The harmonic frequency for the hydrogen bond stretching vibration for H<SP>12</SP>CN–H<SP>35</SP>Cl decreases from <IT>ca.</IT> 100(5) to 90(5) cm<SP>−1</SP> upon excitation of <IT>ν</IT>16 and the corresponding harmonic force constant thereby decreases by 19%.</annotationART></s> <s sid="162"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res43" novelty="None" advantage="None">These values are the same as those obtained using Millen’s modified pseudodiatomic approximation.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="163"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The estimated force constants suggest that the excitation of the HCl libration mode destabilizes the intermolecular interaction between HCN and HCl by almost 20%.</annotationART></s> <s sid="164"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">This very pronounced destabilizing effect due to excitation of the high-wavenumber intermolecular bending mode <IT>ν</IT><SB>B</SB> of the molecular complex has also been observed for other hydrogen bonded systems like HCN–HF,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27">27</REF> OC–HCl<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF> and (H<SB>2</SB>O)<SB>3</SB>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28">28</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="165"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the strong HCN–HF dimer the hydrogen bond weakens by <IT>ca.</IT> 20% upon excitation of the HF libration mode and for the weaker OC–HCl dimer the hydrogen bond is destabilized by almost 30% upon excitation of the HCl libration mode.</annotationART></s> <s sid="166"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore Keutsch <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28">28</REF>. showed that the lifetime of the doubly hydrogen bonded water trimer decreases by three orders of magnitude upon single excitation of the intermolecular out-of-plane libration mode.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="167"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Unfortunately, the Morse model described in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">ref. 1</REF> cannot give values for the dissociation energy <IT>D</IT><SB>e</SB> of the molecular complex without values for the sextic centrifugal distortion constant <IT>H</IT><SB><IT>J</IT></SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="168"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In an attempt to quantify the relative dissociation energy from the determined values for the ground-state spectroscopic constants Legon <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF>. used the Lennard-Jones 6/12 potential function.</annotationART></s> <s sid="169"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="No">This potential energy function may not provide an entirely satisfactory description of the radial behavour of the intermolecular hydrogen bonding interaction but has the clear advantage that it allows the dissociation energy of the molecular complex to be estimated from the values of <IT>B</IT> and <IT>D</IT><SB><IT>J</IT></SB> alone.</annotationART></s> <s sid="170"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Legon <IT>et al</IT>. estimate the dissociation energy for HCN–HCl to be 1199 cm<SP>−1</SP> in the simple pseudodiatomic approximation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="171"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Standard <IT>ab initio</IT> molecular orbital theory<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29">29</REF> calculations are carried out using the program package GAUSSIAN 98<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30">30</REF> in order to validate the empirical value for the dissociation energy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="172"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Geometry optimization procedures are performed for HCN, HCl and HCN–HCl using CCSD(T)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit31">31</REF> methodology in combination with correlation consistent polarized valence double-, triple- and quadruple zeta basis sets including polarization and diffuse functions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit32">32</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="173"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Single-point energy calculations on selected geometries are performed in order to calculate BSSE corrections being assessed using the counterpoise (CP) correction, as suggested by Boys and Bernadi.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit33">33</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="174"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res44" novelty="None" advantage="None">The calculated dissociation energies for the HCN–HCl dimer corrected for the BSSE are listed in Table 3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="175"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to estimate the basis set limit we use the results of Dunning.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit34">34</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="176"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this work, the BSSE corrected values of <IT>D</IT><SB>e</SB> for (H<SB>2</SB>O)<SB>2</SB> and (HF)<SB>2</SB> were calculated using the CCSD(T) level of theory in combination with the aug-cc-pV<IT>n</IT>Z basis sets, <IT>n</IT> = 1–4.</annotationART></s> <s sid="177"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The conclusion of this work was that the basis set convergence errors for (H<SB>2</SB>O)<SB>2</SB> and (HF)<SB>2</SB> for a specific basis set are very similar.</annotationART></s> <s sid="178"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">For (H<SB>2</SB>O)<SB>2</SB>, the CCSD(T)/aug-cc-pVTZ level of theory yields 94% of the value for the basis set limit.</annotationART></s> <s sid="179"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res45" novelty="None" advantage="None">Assuming this to be true also for the HCN–HCl dimer we predict a dissociation energy <IT>D</IT><SB>e</SB> of −1530 cm<SP>−1</SP> in the complete basis set limit.</annotationART></s> <s sid="180"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res46" novelty="None" advantage="None">The computed value for the center of mass distance at equilibrium is 3.910 Å at the CCSD(T)/aug-cc-pVTZ level of theory which is close to the empirical value.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="181"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs20" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is interesting to note that the band origins for the HCl librations of H<SP>13</SP>CN–H<SP>35</SP>Cl and DCN–H<SP>35</SP>Cl are slightly blueshifted relative to the band origin for the HCl libration of HCN–H<SP>35</SP>Cl.</annotationART></s> <s sid="182"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the harmonic oscillator approximation we expect that the HCl libration frequencies are lower for the heavier isotopomers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="183"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod11" novelty="None" advantage="None">We consider the following potential energy function for the two libration modes given in eqn. (9):where <IT>θ</IT><SB>HCl</SB> and <IT>θ</IT><SB>HCN</SB> are the libration angles and <IT>φ</IT><SB>1</SB> − <IT>φ</IT><SB>2</SB> is the dihedral angle.</annotationART></s> <s sid="184"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod11" novelty="None" advantage="None">We estimate the importance of the third term in the potential energy function involving the mixed harmonic force constant <IT>k</IT><SB>67</SB> assuming that the HCN libration and the coupling between the libration modes are dominated by the dipole–dipole interaction (<IT>k</IT><SB>67</SB> = 1/2<IT>k</IT><SB>7</SB>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="185"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The values of the force constant <IT>k</IT><SB>7</SB> are estimated from Bender <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="186"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod11" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this way we estimate how much the HCl libration frequencies are blueshifted due to the coupling with the HCN libration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="187"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The estimated differences in these shifts upon isotopic substitution are much smaller than the observed blueshifts and it seems that the fourth term in the potential energy function involving the anharmonic force constant <IT>k</IT><SB>6677</SB> is more important for the couplings.</annotationART></s> <s sid="188"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod12" novelty="None" advantage="None">If we assume that this anharmonic term also determines the shifts of the observed <IT>ν</IT>16 + <IT>ν</IT>17 − <IT>ν</IT>17 hot bands, we can estimate the HCl libration shifts expected from the <IT>k</IT><SB>6677</SB> term alone.</annotationART></s> <s sid="189"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res47" novelty="None" advantage="None">We obtain 0.539 and 0.073 cm<SP>−1</SP> for the frequency shifts upon isotopic substitution of D and <SP>13</SP>C, respectively, compared to the observed values of 0.302 86(33) and 0.088 46(33) cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="5.">Conclusions</HEADER><P><s sid="190"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj5" novelty="New" advantage="None">In the present study, we report the direct observation and rovibrational analysis of the intermolecular HCl libration bands <IT>ν</IT>16 for gaseous H<SP>12</SP>CN–H<SP>35</SP>Cl, H<SP>13</SP>CN–HCl and D<SP>12</SP>CN–H<SP>35</SP>Cl by means of static gas-phase Fourier transform far-infrared spectroscopy at 205 K using an infrared synchrotron radiation source.</annotationART></s> <s sid="191"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res48" novelty="None" advantage="None">A limited number of Q-branch lines are observed and assigned for the <IT>ν</IT>16 bands of the corresponding <SP>37</SP>Cl species in natural abundance.</annotationART></s> <s sid="192"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res49" novelty="None" advantage="None">A number of <IT>ν</IT>16 + <IT>ν</IT>17 − <IT>ν</IT>17 and <IT>ν</IT>16 + 2<IT>ν</IT>27 − 2<IT>ν</IT>27 hot bands are observed in the spectra and sums of the anharmonicity constants <IT>X</IT><SB>6,7</SB> + <IT>g</IT><SB>6,7</SB> are estimated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="193"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The relative HCl libration band origins seem to be determined from the anharmonic coupling to the HCN libration modes.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="194"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The observed decrease of the rotational constants <IT>B</IT> together with the simultaneous increase of the quartic centrifugal distortion constants <IT>D</IT><SB><IT>J</IT></SB> upon excitation of the HCl libration modes indicate that the hydrogen bond in the molecular complexes is significantly destabilized upon excitation of the intermolecular HCl libration modes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="195"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The estimated force constants for the intermolecular hydrogen bond stretching vibration suggest that the excitation of the HCl libration mode destabilizes the intermolecular interaction between HCN and HCl by almost 20%.</annotationART></s> <s sid="196"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res50" novelty="None" advantage="None">The hydrogen bond elongates by 0.030 Å upon excitation of the <IT>ν</IT>16 mode for all three complexes.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
