<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b504178c" hasDoc="yes" version="1184" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">The role of the radical-complex mechanism in the ozone recombination/dissociation reaction</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">The data bases for low-pressure rate coefficients of the dissociation of O<SB>3</SB> and the reverse recombination of O with O<SB>2</SB> in the bath gases M = He, Ar, N<SB>2</SB>, CO<SB>2</SB> and SF<SB>6</SB> are carefully analyzed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">At very high temperatures, the rate constants have to correspond solely to the energy transfer (ET) mechanism.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">On condition that this holds for Ar and N<SB>2</SB> near 800 K, average energies transferred per collision of −〈Δ<IT>E</IT>〉/<IT>hc</IT> = 18 and 25 cm<SP>−1</SP> are derived, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None">Assuming an only weak temperature dependence of 〈Δ<IT>E</IT>〉 as known in similar systems, rate coefficients for the ET-mechanism are extrapolated to lower temperatures and compared with the experiments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The difference between measured and extrapolated rate coefficients is attributed to the radical complex (RC) mechanism.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The derived rate coefficients for the RC-mechanism are rationalized in terms of equilibrium constants for equilibria of van der Waals complexes of O (or O<SB>2</SB>) with the bath gases and with rate coefficients for oxygen abstraction from these complexes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The latter are of similar magnitude as rate coefficients for oxygen isotope exchange which provides support for the present interpretation of the reaction in terms of a superposition of RC- and ET-mechanisms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">We obtained rate coefficients for the ET-mechanism of <IT>k</IT>ETrec,0/[Ar] = 2.3 × 10<SP>−34</SP> (<IT>T</IT>/300)<SP>−1.5</SP> and <IT>k</IT>ETrec,0/[N<SB>2</SB>] = 3.5 × 10<SP>−34</SP> (<IT>T</IT>/300)<SP>−1.5</SP> cm<SP>6</SP> molecule<SP>−2</SP> s<SP>−1</SP> and rate coefficients for the RC-mechanism of <IT>k</IT>RCrec,0/[Ar] = 1.7 × 10<SP>−34</SP> (<IT>T</IT>/300)<SP>−3.2</SP> and <IT>k</IT>RCrec,0/[N<SB>2</SB>] = 2.5 × 10<SP>−34</SP> (<IT>T</IT>/300)<SP>−3.3</SP> cm<SP>6</SP> molecule<SP>−2</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The data bases for M = He, CO<SB>2</SB> and SF<SB>6</SB> are less complete and only approximate separations of RC- and ET-mechanism were possible.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="New" advantage="None">The consequences of the present analysis for an analysis of isotope effects in ozone recombination are emphasized.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="1">Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The thermal recombination reactionO + O<SB>2</SB> + M → O<SB>3</SB> + Mand the reverse thermal dissociation of ozoneO<SB>3</SB> + M → O + O<SB>2</SB> + Mhave been studied extensively in experiments covering the temperature range 80–3000 K, the pressure range 10<SP>−4</SP>–10<SP>3</SP> bar, and a large number of bath gases M. Experiments up to 1973 have been summarized in .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">ref. 1</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Later recombination experiments were discussed in CODATA/IUPAC evaluations like <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2 cit3 cit4">refs. 2–4</REF> or in NASA evaluations like .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">ref. 5</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">There have been only few later dissociation studies such as summarized in the present work.</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Combining recombination and dissociation studies by the help of the equilibrium constant,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF> a large body of data exist for the recombination/dissociation reaction (1) and (−1) which wait for a quantitative analysis.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Applying standard unimolecular rate theory to the data available in 1979, the treatment given in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7 cit8 cit9">refs. 7–9</REF> did not reveal anything unusual, except the conclusion that collisional energy transfer was fairly inefficient.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The picture changed when recombination experiments were extended down to 80 K in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10 cit11">refs. 10 and 11</REF> and up to pressures of 10<SP>3</SP> bar in .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">ref. 11</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The pressure dependence did not show the falloff behaviour of a typical unimolecular reaction and the temperature dependence below 300 K was much stronger than expected for a unimolecular reaction governed by the energy transfer (ET) mechanism, <IT>i.e.</IT> a mechanism following the schemeA + B → AB*AB* → A + BAB* → AB + MThe situation in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">ref. 11</REF> was rationalized by suggesting that the reaction at low temperatures was dominated by the radical-complex (RC) or Chaperon mechanism, <IT>i.e.</IT> a mechanism following the schemeA + M → AMAM → A + MAM + B → AB + Mand that only at high temperatures the ET-mechanism took over.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rates for the two mechanisms were estimated at least semiquantitatively, providing a rational interpretation of the experimental observations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The transition between the RC- and the ET-mechanism was suggested to happen near 200 K for M = He and near 400 K for M = Ar and N<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since 1990 attention has shifted away from the absolute rates for reactions (1) and (−1) towards an interpretation of unusual isotope effects in the recombination reaction (1) such as they are of great interest for atmospheric chemistry, see <IT>e.g</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12 cit13 cit14">refs. 12–14</REF>..</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Theoretical attempts to explain the observed isotope effects have been numerous, see <IT>e.g</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15 cit16 cit17 cit18">refs. 15–18</REF>.; however, mostly the ET-mechanism was employed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ET-mechanism in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">ref. 17</REF> was also used to reproduce absolute values of the recombination rate coefficients between 130–300 K. However, much larger collision efficiencies for energy transfer had to be employed than suggested in .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">ref. 11</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Looking only at the limited temperature range considered in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">ref. 17</REF> does not appear sufficient to solve the problem.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In any case, one cannot expect to explain the isotope effects without understanding the whole body of available dissociation/recombination data.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The question of an adequate interpretation of isotope effects and rate data for reactions (1) and (−1), therefore, to the present authors remains open.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both isotope effects and ozone recombination rates are of large importance for atmospheric chemistry.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">They are interconnected and have to be analyzed together.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Other theoretical studies of the recombination reaction in terms of the energy transfer mechanism<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19">19</REF> apparently were too simplified to explain the experimental rates.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">A single theoretical attempt to explain the recombination rates in terms of the RC-mechanism<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF> missed the experimental rates by one order of magnitude.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reason why we come back 15 years after <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">ref. 11</REF> to an interpretation of ozone dissociation/recombination rates is twofold.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our knowledge on the ozone potential energy surface has been improved very much (see .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21 cit22 cit23">refs. 21–23</REF>)</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, we have collected experience with the analysis of the radical-complex mechanism in other reaction systems, see <IT>e.g</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">ref. 24</REF>..</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, theoretical work with the new <IT>ab initio</IT> potential on oxygen isotope exchange in the reaction O + O<SB>2</SB> → O<SB>2</SB> + O,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">25</REF> on collisional energy transfer of highly vibrationally excited ozone<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26">26</REF> as well as on the RC-mechanism in ozone recombination<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27">27</REF> seems to fall in line with our analysis from .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">ref. 11</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">It, therefore, appears advisable to reanalyze more carefully the available data base of dissociation/recombination rate coefficients on the basis of our improved knowledge of molecular parameters.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj5" novelty="New" advantage="None">At this stage, we focus attention on the low-pressure range only because that range is difficult enough to understand.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Our strategy is as follows: we first consider measurements at the highest available temperatures and assume that here the reaction is dominated by the ET-mechanism.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Employing state-of-the art unimolecular rate theory to these data, we derive the average energy 〈Δ<IT>E</IT>〉 transferred per collision.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">This quantity then is the only parameter from the ET-mechanism which needs to be fitted empirically because theoretical determinations are not yet sufficiently reliable for cases like O<SB>3</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In agreement with other experimental systems governed by the ET-mechanism, we assume that 〈Δ<IT>E</IT>〉 has only a weak temperature dependence.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This allows one to extrapolate the rate coefficients for the ET-mechanism towards lower temperatures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">A comparison with the experimental rate coefficients at lower temperatures then leads to the RC-contribution of the rate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="New" advantage="None">The derived rate coefficients for the RC-mechanism finally are analyzed in terms of O–M and O<SB>2</SB>–M radical-complex equilibrium constants and rate coefficients for the reactions OM + O<SB>2</SB> → O<SB>3</SB> + M or O<SB>2</SB>M + O → O<SB>3</SB> + M. These results are compared with analogous quantities of other RC-systems like those investigated in .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">ref. 24</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj6" novelty="New" advantage="None">The consequences of our analysis for an understanding of the pressure dependence and of isotope effects finally are indicated.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2">Modelling of the ET-mechanism</HEADER><P><s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ET-mechanism of reaction (1) can be characterized symbolically by the steps O + O<SB>2</SB> → O<SB>3</SB>*O<SB>3</SB>* → O + O<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB>* + M → O<SB>3</SB> + M.For dissociation, there is the additional stepO<SB>3</SB> + M → O<SB>3</SB>* + Mwhile step (2) is absent.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj7" novelty="New" advantage="None">In the present work we only consider the low-pressure range of the reaction (termolecular for recombination, bimolecular for dissociation).</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this case, the limiting low-pressure rate coefficients (pseudo-second-order for recombination and pseudo-first-order for dissociation) are written symbolically as<IT>k</IT><SB>rec,0</SB> = <IT>k</IT><SB>3</SB>[M](<IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB>/<IT>k</IT><SB>−2</SB>)and<IT>k</IT><SB>diss,0</SB> = <IT>k</IT><SB>−3</SB>[M] = <IT>k</IT><SB>3</SB>[M]([O<SB>3</SB>*]/[O<SB>3</SB>])<SB>eq</SB>while the equilibrium constant is given by<IT>K</IT><SB>eq</SB> = <IT>k</IT><SB>rec,0</SB>/<IT>k</IT><SB>diss,0</SB> = <IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB><IT>k</IT><SB>3</SB>/<IT>k</IT><SB>−2</SB><IT>k</IT><SB>−3</SB>.By analytically solving the steady-state master equation of the dissociation<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28">28</REF> and the recombination<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29">29</REF> reaction, eqn. (5) takes the formwith the overall collision frequency <IT>Z</IT> for energy transfer, the collision efficiency <IT>β</IT><SB>c</SB>, the threshold energy <IT>E</IT><SB>0</SB>(<IT>J</IT>) as a function of angular momentum (quantum number <IT>J</IT>) and the equilibrium population <IT>f</IT>(<IT>E</IT>,<IT>J</IT>) as a function of <IT>J</IT> and the energy <IT>E</IT>. The sum and the integral ∑∫ in eqn. (7) correspond to ([O<SB>3</SB>*]/ [O<SB>3</SB>])<SB>eq</SB> in eqn. (5).</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The solution of the master equation allows one to relate <IT>β</IT><SB>c</SB> with the average energy 〈Δ<IT>E</IT>〉 transferred per collision, for which <IT>β</IT><SB>c</SB>/(1 − <IT>β</IT><SB>c</SB><SP>1/2</SP>) ≈ −〈Δ<IT>E</IT>〉/<IT>F</IT><SB><IT>E</IT></SB><IT>kT</IT>was derived in .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28">ref. 28</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the sake of transparency, the sum and the integral ∑∫ were expressed in factorized form by<IT>k</IT><SB>diss,0</SB> = <IT>Z</IT>[M]<IT>β</IT><SB>c</SB>(<IT>ρ</IT><SB>vib,<IT>h</IT></SB>(<IT>E</IT><SB>0</SB>)<IT>kT</IT>/<IT>Q</IT><SB>vib</SB>)<IT>F</IT><SB><IT>E</IT></SB><IT>F</IT><SB>anh</SB><IT>F</IT><SB>rot</SB> exp(−<IT>E</IT><SB>0</SB>/<IT>kT</IT>) in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit9">refs. 8 and 9</REF>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this expression one has the harmonic vibrational density of states <IT>ρ</IT><SB>vib,<IT>h</IT></SB>(<IT>E</IT><SB>0</SB>) and the vibrational partition function <IT>Q</IT><SB>vib</SB>, while the factors <IT>F</IT><SB><IT>E</IT></SB>, <IT>F</IT><SB>anh</SB> and <IT>F</IT><SB>rot</SB> account for the energy dependence of <IT>ρ</IT><SB>vib,<IT>h</IT></SB>(<IT>E</IT>), for vibrational anharmonicity, and for rotational effects including the influence of <IT>E</IT><SB>0</SB>(<IT>J</IT>), respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">With the equilibrium constant<IT>K</IT><SB>eq</SB> = <IT>Q</IT>(O<SB>3</SB>)/[<IT>Q</IT>(O)<IT>Q</IT>(O<SB>2</SB>) exp(−<IT>E</IT><SB>0</SB>/<IT>kT</IT>)],eqn.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">(9) leads to where the partition functions <IT>Q</IT> contain translational, rotational, vibrational and electronic contributions.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The various factors in eqns. (10) and (11) in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit9 cit11">refs. 8, 9 and 11</REF> have been calculated on the basis of the then available knowledge of the molecular parameters.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">By comparison with the experiments finally <IT>β</IT><SB>c</SB> and, through eqn. (8), 〈Δ<IT>E</IT>〉 were fitted.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None"><IT>E.g.</IT>, −〈Δ<IT>E</IT>〉/<IT>hc</IT> = (20 ± 10) cm<SP>−1</SP> in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">ref. 11</REF> were derived for M = He, Ar and N<SB>2</SB> near 800 K. These values were found to be in fair agreement with the results from classical trajectory calculations of <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30 cit31">refs. 30 and 31</REF>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The analysis from <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">ref. 17</REF> gave much larger values, being around 200 cm<SP>−1</SP> for deactivating collisions which would correspond<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF> to about −〈Δ<IT>E</IT>〉/<IT>hc</IT> ≈ 100 cm<SP>−1</SP> at 300 K. The present analysis disputes such interpretation.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">Because the characterization of the ET-contribution to <IT>k</IT><SB>rec,0</SB> is a central element of our interpretation, we repeat the calculation of the factors in eqns. (10) and (11) on the basis of the improved molecular parameters available today.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The calculation of the various factors is elaborated in the Appendix.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The resulting rate coefficients even over the large temperature range 80–3000 K can be well approximated by a <IT>k</IT><SB>rec,0</SB> ∝ <IT>T</IT><SP>−<IT>n</IT></SP> dependence with a temperature independent exponent <IT>n</IT>. 〈Δ<IT>E</IT>〉 is fitted by the experimental values at 800 K and then used without further change.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The assumption of a nearly temperature independent 〈Δ<IT>E</IT>〉 appears justified, if one looks at related dissociation/recombination reactions being evaluated by the same procedure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None"><IT>E.g.</IT>, the well studied recombination H + O<SB>2</SB> + M → HO<SB>2</SB> + M in the bath gases M = Ar and N<SB>2</SB> in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit32">ref. 32</REF> over the temperature range 220–1500 K was analyzed in the same way as the present treatment; values of −〈Δ<IT>E</IT>〉/<IT>hc</IT> = 21 (<IT>T</IT>/300)<SP>+0.1</SP> cm<SP>−1</SP> for M = Ar and of 60 (<IT>T</IT>/300)<SP>−0.2</SP> cm<SP>−1</SP> for M = N<SB>2</SB> were derived.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Likewise, the evaluation of the reaction H + CH<SB>3</SB> + M → CH<SB>4</SB> + M over the temperature range 1000–5000 K with M = Ar<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit33">33</REF> led to −〈Δ<IT>E</IT>〉/<IT>hc</IT> = 50 (<IT>T</IT>/300)<SP>0±0.3</SP> cm<SP>−1</SP> while, for M = He,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit34">34</REF> −〈Δ<IT>E</IT>〉/<IT>hc</IT> ≈ 20 (<IT>T</IT>/300)<SP>1±0.5</SP> cm<SP>−1</SP> was found over the range 300–1000 K. A look at other reaction systems in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit33">ref. 33</REF> confirms that 〈Δ<IT>E</IT>〉 in the present type of analysis either is practically temperature independent or at most has a small positive temperature coefficient up to about <IT>T</IT><SP>1</SP> for M = He.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">It appears important to emphasize that 〈Δ<IT>E</IT>〉 is not expected to have a large negative temperature coefficient, see below.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj8" novelty="New" advantage="None">In this work we analyze experimental data for reactions (1) and (−1) in the bath gases M = He, Ar, N<SB>2</SB>, CO<SB>2</SB> and SF<SB>6</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the discussed way we fit 〈Δ<IT>E</IT>〉 to the experimental results near 800 K, assuming that <IT>k</IT><SB>rec,0</SB> here is dominated by the ET-mechanism.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the next section the individual cases are considered in more detail.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The analysis of the data is based on <IT>k</IT><SB>rec,0</SB>/[M] = (12, 5.1, 8.0, 36, 61) × 10<SP>−35</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP> at 800 K, see below, which leads to the values −〈Δ<IT>E</IT>〉/<IT>hc</IT> = (18, 18, 25, 150, 280) cm<SP>−1</SP> at 300 K for the bath gases M = He, Ar, N<SB>2</SB>, CO<SB>2</SB> and SF<SB>6</SB>, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The values of 〈Δ<IT>E</IT>〉 are assumed to be nearly temperature independent, except for M = He where 〈Δ<IT>E</IT>〉 ∝ <IT>T</IT><SP>0.5</SP> follows from the data, see below.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="New" advantage="None">The corresponding temperature-dependent values of the rate coefficients from the ET-mechanism in Table 1 are compared with the strong collision rate coefficients <IT>k</IT><SB>rec,0</SB><SP>ET,SC</SP>/[M], <IT>i.e.</IT> the calculated values from eqn. (11) with <IT>β</IT><SB>c</SB> from eqn. (8).</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3">Experimental determination of the contribution from the RC-mechanism</HEADER><P><s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="New" advantage="None">In the following the experimental results are compared with the rate coefficients from the ET-mechanism such as determined in section 2 and fitted to experimental data near 800 K. Because this comparison provides the empirical justification for our conclusions on the RC-mechanism, particular care had to be taken to obtain the best available experimental data base.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="New" advantage="None">We, therefore, have gone back to the individual experimental studies and, in part, re-evaluated the data with improved knowledge<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2 cit3 cit4 cit5">1–5</REF> on the rates of reference reactions.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="New" advantage="None">The most complete data base is available for M = Ar where the experiments from <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7 cit10 cit11 cit35 cit36 cit37 cit38 cit39 cit40 cit41 cit42 cit43 cit44 cit45 cit46 cit47 cit48">refs. 7, 10, 11, 35–48</REF> cover the temperature range 80–3000 K which is probably the largest range which would be accessible experimentally.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="New" advantage="None">(The experiments from <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit43">ref. 43</REF> in the range 1100–3000 K become increasingly scattered at temperatures above 1500 K and in shock waves using more than 1% O<SB>3</SB> in Ar.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="New" advantage="None">We, therefore, discard experimental data above 1500 K and using higher ozone concentrations; these data were included in .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">ref. 11</REF>)</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 1 shows the data.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">One notices a large negative temperature coefficient.</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">One also observes a slight change of the temperature coefficient from low to high temperatures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The experimental <IT>k</IT><SB>rec,0</SB> markedly differs from the ET-calculations which we denote by <IT>k</IT>ETrec,0, see Table 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">We attribute this behaviour to the contribution of the RC-mechanism to <IT>k</IT><SB>rec,0</SB> which we determine from<IT>k</IT>RCrec,0 = <IT>k</IT><SB>rec,0</SB> − <IT>k</IT>ETrec,0For M = Ar, in this way we obtain<IT>k</IT>RCrec,0/[Ar] = 1.7 × 10<SP>−34</SP> (<IT>T</IT>/300)<SP>−3.2</SP> cm<SP>6</SP> molecule<SP>−2</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>while<IT>k</IT>ETrec,0/[Ar] = 2.3 × 10<SP>−34</SP> (<IT>T</IT>/300)<SP>−1.5</SP> cm<SP>6</SP> molecule<SP>−2</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>.The interpretation of the experimental rate coefficients <IT>k</IT><SB>rec,0</SB> by the ET-mechanism, in terms of eqns. (8) and (11) alone, would require a markedly negative temperature coefficient of 〈Δ<IT>E</IT>〉.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to reproduce the measured <IT>k</IT><SB>rec,0</SB> one would have to use −〈Δ<IT>E</IT>〉/<IT>hc</IT> ≈ 50 (<IT>T</IT>/300)<SP>−1</SP> cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Such temperature coefficient of 〈Δ<IT>E</IT>〉 would be far from that found for related reactions being analyzed in the same way.</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is also at variance with the general trends of temperature dependence from directly measured or trajectory calculated 〈Δ<IT>E</IT>〉 at related conditions in various systems.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit49">49</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, the interpretation of the low temperature data by the ET-mechanism alone can practically be ruled out.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="New" advantage="None">The data base for M = N<SB>2</SB> is similarly complete as for M = Ar.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 2 summarizes data from <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7 cit11 cit12 cit35 cit37 cit38 cit40 cit41 cit45 cit47 cit50 cit51 cit52">refs. 7, 11, 12, 35, 37, 38, 40, 41, 45, 47, 50–52</REF>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this case we obtain<IT>k</IT>RCrec,0/[N<SB>2</SB>] = 2.5 × 10<SP>−34</SP> (<IT>T</IT>/300)<SP>−3.3</SP> cm<SP>6</SP> molecule<SP>−2</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>and<IT>k</IT>ETrec,0/[N<SB>2</SB>] = 3.5 × 10<SP>−34</SP> (<IT>T</IT>/300)<SP>−1.5</SP> cm<SP>6</SP> molecule<SP>−2</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>.The results look similar as for M = Ar.</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, both <IT>k</IT>ETrec,0 and <IT>k</IT>RCrec,0 are about a factor of 1.5 larger than for M = Ar.</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">An interpretation by the ET-mechanism alone would require −〈Δ<IT>E</IT>〉/<IT>hc</IT> ≈ 70 (<IT>T</IT>/300)<SP>−1</SP> cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The value of 70 cm<SP>−1</SP> would not be much different from the value of 100 cm<SP>−1</SP> (which corresponds to down step sizes near 200 cm<SP>−1</SP> at 300 K) which was used in .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">ref. 17</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, as for M = Ar, the temperature coefficient of 〈Δ<IT>E</IT>〉 would be very unusual and different from related reactions analyzed in the same way, as well as from the typical trends in direct determinations of 〈Δ<IT>E</IT>〉 at chemically significant energies.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The picture for M = He looks slightly different.</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 3 summarizes experimental results from <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7 cit11 cit37 cit38 cit39 cit41 cit47 cit53">refs. 7, 11, 37–39, 41, 47 and 53</REF>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The representation shows a curvature which appears to be outside the experimental error.</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In part, this may be attributed to the positive temperature coefficients of 〈Δ<IT>E</IT>〉 ∝ <IT>T</IT><SP>+0.5</SP> used in our analysis which would lead to<IT>k</IT>ETrec,0/[He] = 3.4 × 10<SP>−34</SP> (<IT>T</IT>/300)<SP>−1.05</SP> cm<SP>6</SP> molecule<SP>−2</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>.However, the data base is too limited at the low and high temperature ends to be sure of the curvature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">If eqn. (17) would be adequate, one would have<IT>k</IT>RCrec,0/[He] = 7 × 10<SP>−33</SP> cm<SP>6</SP> molecule<SP>−2</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>at 100 K and an only negligible contribution from the RC-mechanism at 300 K. If one would assume 〈Δ<IT>E</IT>〉 ∝ <IT>T</IT><SP>0</SP>, a smaller value for <IT>k</IT>RCrec,0 would be derived.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The data base is even less complete for M = CO<SB>2</SB> and SF<SB>6</SB>, see Fig. 4 which compares the data from <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7 cit36 cit37 cit39 cit42 cit54 cit55">refs. 7, 36, 37, 39, 42, 54 and 55</REF> for M = CO<SB>2</SB> and from <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7 cit37 cit42">refs. 7, 37 and 42</REF> for M = SF<SB>6</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Like for M = He, it would be difficult to separate the contributions from the ET- and RC-mechanisms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, if the data near 800 K are attributed to the ET-mechanism, one has<IT>k</IT>ETrec,0/[CO<SB>2</SB>] = 1.4 × 10<SP>−33</SP> (<IT>T</IT>/300)<SP>−1.34</SP> cm<SP>6</SP> molecule<SP>−2</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>and<IT>k</IT>ETrec,0/[SF<SB>6</SB>] = 2.1 × 10<SP>−33</SP> (<IT>T</IT>/300)<SP>−1.26</SP> cm<SP>6</SP> molecule<SP>−2</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>.Through eqn. (12) then<IT>k</IT>RCrec,0/[CO<SB>2</SB>] ≈ 1 × 10<SP>−33</SP> cm<SP>6</SP> molecule<SP>−2</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>für <IT>T</IT> = 200 K and<IT>k</IT>RCrec,0/[SF<SB>6</SB>] ≈ 1 × 10<SP>−33</SP> cm<SP>6</SP> molecule<SP>−2</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>for <IT>T</IT> = 300 K would be estimated; however, these data would be fairly uncertain.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">It should be emphasized that the data base for M = He, CO<SB>2</SB> and SF<SB>6</SB> is too small to arrive at a satisfactory separation of the ET- and RC-contributions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="New" advantage="None">However, the data for M = Ar and N<SB>2</SB> appear sufficient for the separation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">An interpretation of the data by the ET-mechanism alone would only be possible with quite unrealistic temperature dependences of 〈Δ<IT>E</IT>〉 such as they have not been found before in this type of analysis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition the derived absolute values of 〈Δ<IT>E</IT>〉 would be much larger than have been obtained from classical trajectory calculations of energy transfer of excited ozone, or directly measured in other systems at related conditions.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4">Interpretation of the radical complex contribution to the reaction rate</HEADER><P><s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Having empirically determined the contributions <IT>k</IT>RCrec,0 of the RC-mechanism to the overall rate coefficients <IT>k</IT><SB>rec,0</SB> = <IT>k</IT>ETrec,0 + <IT>k</IT>RCrec,0 in the previous section, in the following we try to rationalize the obtained data.</annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The RC-mechanism symbolically is described by the van der Waals-type equilibriaO + M ⇄ OMO<SB>2</SB> + M ⇄ O<SB>2</SB>Mwith the equilibrium constants <IT>K</IT><SB>23</SB> = ([OM]/[O][M])<SB>eq</SB> and <IT>K</IT><SB>24</SB> = ([O<SB>2</SB>M]/[O<SB>2</SB>][M])<SB>eq</SB> and the reactionsOM + O<SB>2</SB> → O<SB>3</SB> + MO<SB>2</SB>M + O → O<SB>3</SB> + M.In the low-pressure range considered here, reactions of the typeOM + O<SB>2</SB>M → O<SB>3</SB> + 2 Mare neglected.</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Assuming that the pre-equilibria (23) and (24) are established, <IT>k</IT>RCrec,0 follows as<IT>k</IT>RCrec,0/[M] = <IT>k</IT><SB>25</SB><IT>K</IT><SB>23</SB> + <IT>k</IT><SB>26</SB><IT>K</IT><SB>24</SB>.The equilibrium constants <IT>K</IT><SB>23</SB> and <IT>K</IT><SB>24</SB> are estimated by a modification of the Bunker-Davidson relationship<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit56">56</REF> such as given by Schwarzer and Teubner.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit57">57</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">As the latter authors pointed out, Bunker and Davidson omitted metastable states of the complexes with energies larger than the dissociation energy but smaller than the centrifugal barriers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Including these states increases the equilibrium constants up to a factor of 2 at higher temperatures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Following this method, the equilibrium constants from Table 2 were obtained on the basis of the following Lennard-Jones parameters: <IT>σ</IT><SB>LJ</SB> = 3.2, 3.5, 3.4, 3.7 and 4.3 Å and <IT>ε</IT><SB>LJ</SB>/<IT>k</IT> = 27, 93, 107, 121 and 126 K for O–He, –Ar, –N<SB>2</SB>, –CO<SB>2</SB> and –SF<SB>6</SB> complexes, respectively; <IT>σ</IT><SB>LJ</SB> = 3.4, 3.6, 3.7 and 4.3 Å and <IT>ε</IT><SB>LJ</SB>/<IT>k</IT> = 29, 130, 126, 142 and 148 K for O<SB>2</SB>–He, –Ar, –N<SB>2</SB>, –CO<SB>2</SB> and –SF<SB>6</SB> complexes, respectively, which were taken from .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit58 cit59 cit60">refs. 58–60</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Assuming <IT>k</IT><SB>25</SB> ≈ <IT>k</IT><SB>26</SB>, the experiments for M = Ar and N<SB>2</SB> through eqns. (13), (15) and (28) lead to<IT>k</IT><SB>25</SB> ≈ <IT>k</IT><SB>26</SB> ≈ 1.2 × 1 0<SP>−12</SP> (<IT>T</IT>/300)<SP>−1.4</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>for M = Ar and<IT>k</IT><SB>25</SB> ≈ <IT>k</IT><SB>26</SB> ≈ 1.1 × 10<SP>−12</SP> (<IT>T</IT>/300)<SP>−1.7</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>for M = N<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Following the analysis given, these two values appear now to be established with reasonable certainty.</annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is much less the case for the results with M = He, CO<SB>2</SB> and SF<SB>6</SB>, see eqns. (18), (21) and (22).</annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Employing the tentative values for the latter bath gases we would obtain <IT>k</IT><SB>25</SB> ≈ <IT>k</IT><SB>26</SB> ≈ 8 × 10<SP>−11</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP> at 100 K for M = He, 3.8 × 10<SP>−12</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP> at 300 K for M = CO<SB>2</SB> and 2.2 × 10<SP>−12</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP> at 300 K for M = SF<SB>6</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">While the latter data, within the uncertainties of our approach appear not unrealistic, clearly the He data are problematic.</annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">It appears too difficult to establish <IT>k</IT>RCrec,0 from few low temperature points only, see Fig. 3, and on the basis of an uncertain temperature dependence of 〈Δ<IT>E</IT>〉.</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">We, therefore, cannot provide a meaningful separation of the He results into ET- and RC-contributions.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj9" novelty="New" advantage="None">In the following we discuss whether the results from eqns. (29) and (30) for M = Ar and N<SB>2</SB> can be understood in terms of related quantities.</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">We consider reaction (25) with M = Ar as an example.</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the one hand this process may be part of a set of competing processes likeOAr + O<SB>2</SB> → O<SB>3</SB> + ArOAr + O<SB>2</SB> → O + O<SB>2</SB>ArOAr + O<SB>2</SB> → O + O<SB>2</SB> + Ar.On the other hand, it is related to oxygen isotope exchange processesO<SP>a</SP> + O<SP>b</SP>O<SP>c</SP> → O<SP>a</SP>O<SP>b</SP> + O<SP>c</SP>for which<IT>k</IT><SB>32</SB> ≈ (2–3) × 10<SP>−12</SP> (<IT>T</IT>/300)<SP>−1</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>was determined experimentally and analyzed theoretically in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25 cit61 cit62">refs. 25, 61 and 62</REF>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">At this stage we note the similarity of the values from eqns. (29), (30) and (35).</annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The slightly different temperature coefficients may attributed to the fact that reaction (33) will become more important than reaction (31) with increasing temperatures and that reaction (34) is closer to reaction (32) than to reaction (31).</annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">It also appears not improbable that reaction (31) at room temperature is slower than reaction (34).</annotationART></s> <s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None">In any case, the similarity of eqns. (29) and (30) with eqn. (35) in our view presents strong evidence for the validity of the present interpretation.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="5">Conclusions</HEADER><P><s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj10" novelty="New" advantage="None">We have reconsidered the experimental data base for ozone recombination and dissociation in the low-pressure limiting range.</annotationART></s> <s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Assuming that the energy transfer mechanism dominates the reaction at temperatures near 800 K and that the corresponding rate coefficients can safely be extrapolated to lower temperatures, we interpret the differences between measured rate coefficients at lower temperatures and the extrapolations from the ET-mechanism as being due to a contribution from the radical complex mechanism.</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The derived rate coefficients from the RC-mechanism can well be interpreted in terms of equilibrium constants of O- and O<SB>2</SB>-van der Waals complexes and rate coefficients for oxygen abstraction from these complexes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The latter values are very close to rate coefficients for oxygen isotope exchange.</annotationART></s> <s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None">This observation strongly supports the present interpretation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None">A final proof will come from a detailed theoretical modelling of processes of the type of OAr + O<SB>2</SB> → O<SB>3</SB> + Ar.</annotationART></s> <s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Such modelling is underway<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27">27</REF> and the preliminary results apparently confirm the present empirically determined values from eqns. (29) and (30).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The present conclusions have also consequences for the interpretation of the isotope effects in ozone recombination which together with the recombination rate is of great importance for atmospheric chemistry.</annotationART></s> <s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">While the ET- and RC-contributions (<IT>k</IT>ETrec,0 and <IT>k</IT>RCrec,0, respectively) to the low-pressure rate coefficients <IT>k</IT><SB>rec,0</SB> are of similar magnitude at 300 K with decreasing temperature <IT>k</IT>RCrec,0 starts to dominate over <IT>k</IT>ETrec,0.</annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Explanations for the experimentally observed isotope effects, therefore, have to be searched both in the ET- and in the RC-mechanism.</annotationART></s> <s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The latter to our knowledge has not yet been done.</annotationART></s> <s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con15" novelty="None" advantage="None">For this reason, we think that the explanation of the isotope effects in ozone recombination still remains an open problem.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Appendix</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Molecular parameters for the low-pressure rate coefficients in the ET-mechanism, eqns. (7)–(11)</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>Lennard-Jones collision parameters</HEADER><P><s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None"><IT>σ</IT><SB>LJ</SB>/Å = 3.98 (O<SB>3</SB>), 2.551 (He), 3.542 (Ar), 3.798 (N<SB>2</SB>), 3.941 (CO<SB>2</SB>), 5.128 (SF<SB>6</SB>); (<IT>ε</IT><SB>LJ</SB>/<IT>k</IT>)/K = 161.2 (O<SB>3</SB>), 10.22 (He), 93.3 (Ar), 71.4 (N<SB>2</SB>), 195.2 (CO<SB>2</SB>), 222.1 (SF<SB>6</SB>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fitted average energies transferred per collision 〈Δ<IT>E</IT>〉, see section 2.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>Bond energy</HEADER><P><s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Δ<IT>H</IT><SB>0</SB><SP>o</SP> = <IT>E</IT><SB>0</SB>(<IT>J</IT> = 0) = <IT>hc</IT> 8475.5 cm<SP>−1</SP><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit5 cit6">4–6</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>Rotational constants</HEADER><P><s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod12" novelty="None" advantage="None">O<SB>3</SB>: 3.553 81, 0.445 30, 0.394 77 cm<SP>−1</SP>; O<SB>2</SB>: 1.437 66 cm<SP>−1</SP><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>Electronic states</HEADER><P><s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod13" novelty="None" advantage="None">O<SB>3</SB>: <IT>g</IT> = 1; O<SB>2</SB>: <IT>g</IT> = 3; O: 0 (<IT>g</IT> = 5), 158.265 (<IT>g</IT> = 3), 226.977 (<IT>g</IT> = 1) cm<SP>−1</SP><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>Fundamental frequencies</HEADER><P><s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod14" novelty="None" advantage="None">O<SB>3</SB>: 1103, 701, 1042 cm<SP>−1</SP>;<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit63">63</REF> O<SB>2</SB>: 1556 cm<SP>−1</SP><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>Anharmonic vibrational densities of states</HEADER><P><s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Spectroscopic constants for O<SB>3</SB>: <IT>ω</IT><SB>1</SB> = 1134.3, <IT>ω</IT><SB>2</SB> = 713.5, <IT>ω</IT><SB>3</SB> = 1097.4, <IT>x</IT><SB>11</SB> = −6.89, <IT>x</IT><SB>22</SB> = −1.28, <IT>x</IT><SB>33</SB> = −10.94, <IT>x</IT><SB>12</SB> = −8.25, <IT>x</IT><SB>13</SB> = −36.83, <IT>x</IT><SB>23</SB> = −17.62;<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit64">64</REF> anharmonic numbers of vibrational states <IT>W</IT>(<IT>E</IT>) are determined with the spectroscopic constants (<IT>W</IT><SB><IT>a</IT></SB>(<IT>E</IT>)) or with the empirical anharmonicity model from <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit65">ref. 65</REF> (<IT>W</IT><SB><IT>b</IT></SB>(<IT>E</IT>)), the harmonized frequencies 1201.99, 724.28, 1058.98 cm<SP>−1</SP> and local bond energies 9114.4, 42044 cm<SP>−1</SP> reproduce the fundamental frequencies, see .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit65">ref. 65</REF>)</annotationART></s> <s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod15" novelty="None" advantage="None">They are compared with the accurate values (<IT>W</IT><SB><IT>c</IT></SB>(<IT>E</IT>)) from an <IT>ab initio</IT> potential.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="143"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Table 3 shows the results (<IT>E</IT> = energy above the vibrational ground state of O<SB>3</SB>).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="144"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Because of the sparsity of levels, densities of states <IT>ρ</IT><SB>vib</SB>(<IT>E</IT>) = d<IT>W</IT>(<IT>E</IT>)/d<IT>E</IT> have to be smoothed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="145"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Whitten–Rabinovitch expression<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit63">63</REF> gives <IT>ρ</IT><SB>vib,<IT>h</IT></SB>(<IT>E</IT><SB>0</SB>) = 0.061/cm<SP>−1</SP> employing fundamental frequencies and the Whitten-Rabinovitch parameter <IT>a</IT>(<IT>E</IT><SB>0</SB>) = 0.984.</annotationART></s> <s sid="146"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod15" novelty="None" advantage="None">One obtains d<IT>W</IT><SB><IT>a</IT></SB>(<IT>E</IT>)/d<IT>E</IT> ≈ 0.065/cm<SP>−1</SP>, d<IT>W</IT><SB><IT>b</IT></SB>(<IT>E</IT>)/d<IT>E</IT> ≈ 0.082/cm<SP>−1</SP> and d<IT>W</IT><SB><IT>c</IT></SB>(<IT>E</IT>)/d<IT>E</IT> ≈ 0.07/cm<SP>−1</SP> at <IT>E</IT> = <IT>E</IT><SB>0</SB>, see .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">ref. 21</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="147"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Using the Whitten–Rabinovitch value, such as calculated with the anharmonic fundamental frequencies, for <IT>ρ</IT><SB>vib,<IT>h</IT></SB>(<IT>E</IT><SB>0</SB>) = 0.061/cm<SP>−1</SP>, with <IT>ρ</IT><SB>vib</SB>(<IT>E</IT><SB>0</SB>) ≈ 0.082/cm<SP>−1</SP> one has <IT>F</IT><SB>anh</SB> ≈ 1.34 which is used here; an overestimate of <IT>F</IT><SB>anh</SB> of about 15% appears possible, but would be compensated by lowering <IT>β</IT><SB>c</SB> and 〈Δ<IT>E</IT>〉 correspondingly.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>Centrifugal barriers <IT>E</IT><SB>0</SB>(<IT>J</IT>) and rotational factors <IT>F</IT><SB>rot</SB>(<IT>T</IT>)</HEADER><P><s sid="148"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Centrifugal barriers are calculated with a fit to the <IT>ab initio</IT> potential from <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25">ref. 25</REF> (Fig. 1) as represented by <IT>V</IT>(<IT>r</IT>) = <IT>E</IT><SB>0</SB> + <IT>D</IT><SB>1</SB>{exp[−2<IT>β</IT><SB>1</SB>(<IT>r</IT> − <IT>r</IT><SB>e</SB><SB>1</SB>)] – 2exp[−<IT>β</IT><SB>1</SB>(<IT>r</IT> − <IT>r</IT><SB>e</SB><SB>1</SB>)]} – <IT>D</IT><SB>2</SB>{exp[−2<IT>β</IT><SB>2</SB>(<IT>r</IT> − <IT>r</IT><SB>e2</SB>)] – 2exp[−<IT>β</IT><SB>2</SB>(<IT>r</IT> − <IT>r</IT><SB>e</SB><SB>2</SB>)]} with the center-of-mass O–O<SB>2</SB> distance <IT>r</IT>, <IT>D</IT><SB>1</SB>/<IT>hc</IT> = 409.4 cm<SP>−1</SP>, <IT>D</IT><SB>2</SB>/<IT>hc</IT> = 230.4 cm<SP>−1</SP>, <IT>r</IT><SB>e1</SB> = 2.704 Å, <IT>r</IT><SB>e2</SB> = 2.637 Å, <IT>β</IT><SB>1</SB> = 1.987 Å<SP>−1</SP>, <IT>β</IT><SB>2</SB> = 2.932 Å<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="149"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Because of the presence of a potential reef 114 cm<SP>−1</SP> below the dissociation limit<SP>25</SP> at c.o.m. distance <IT>r</IT> ≈ 2.4 Å, there is centrifugal barrier switching at <IT>J</IT> ≈ 28.</annotationART></s> <s sid="150"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod16" novelty="None" advantage="None">For <IT>J</IT> ≤ 28, one obtains <IT>E</IT><SB>0</SB>(<IT>J</IT>) – <IT>E</IT><SB>0</SB>(<IT>J =</IT> 0) ≈ <IT>hc</IT> 9.0 × 10<SP>−3</SP> [<IT>J</IT>(<IT>J</IT> + 1<IT>)</IT>]<SP>1.21</SP> cm<SP>−1</SP>; for <IT>J</IT> &gt; 28, one has <IT>E</IT><SB>0</SB>(<IT>J</IT>) – <IT>E</IT><SB>0</SB>(<IT>J</IT> ≈ 0) ≈ <IT>hc</IT> 1.3 × 10<SP>−1</SP> [<IT>J</IT>(<IT>J</IT> + 1)]<SP>1.36</SP> cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="151"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod16" novelty="None" advantage="None"><IT>F</IT><SB>rot</SB>(<IT>T</IT>) was calculated with the accurate <IT>E</IT><SB>0</SB>(<IT>J</IT>) using the method of <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">ref. 9</REF> and leading to <IT>F</IT><SB>rot</SB>(<IT>T</IT>) = 26.2, 15.4, 11.7, 9.7, 7.4, 6.0, 5.0, 3.5 in comparison to <IT>F</IT><SB>rot,max</SB>(<IT>T</IT>) (see <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">ref. 9</REF>) = 292, 103, 56, 37, 20, 13, 9.2, 5.0 for <IT>T</IT>/K = 100, 200, 300, 400, 600, 800, 1000, 1500.</annotationART></s> <s sid="152"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod16" novelty="None" advantage="None"><IT>F</IT><SB>rot</SB>(<IT>T</IT>) can well be approximated by <IT>F</IT><SB>rot</SB> ≈ 11.7 (<IT>T</IT>/300)<SP>−0.71</SP>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
