<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b508281a" hasDoc="yes" version="1184" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Role of water molecules in the KcsA protein channel by molecular dynamics calculations</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Molecular dynamics simulations supported by electrostatic calculations have been conducted on the KcsA channel to determine the role of water molecules in the pore.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">Starting from the X-ray structure of the KcsA channel in its closed state at 2.0 Å resolution, the opening of the pore towards a conformation built on the basis of EPR results is studied.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">We show that water molecules act as a structural element for the K<SP>+</SP> ions inside the filter and the hydrophobic cavity of the channel.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the filter, water tends to enhance the depth of the wells occupied by the K<SP>+</SP> ions, while in the cavity there is a strong correlation between the water molecules and the cavity ion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">As a consequence, the protein remains very stable in the presence of three K<SP>+</SP> ions in the selectivity filter and one in the cavity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The analysis of the dynamics of water molecules in the cavity reveals preferred orientations of the dipoles along the pore axis, and a correlated behavior between this dipole orientation and the displacement of the K<SP>+</SP> ion during the gating process.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="1.">Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The equilibrium and dynamical properties of a solvent in confined geometry can be very different from those in the bulk.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2 cit3">1–3</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is particularly important in the case of confined environments present in proteins, such as the interior of deep crevices, pockets or other poorly accessible regions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Prominent examples include the substrate binding sites of enzymes<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF> and the narrow pores of membrane channels.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Simulation studies of a number of channel models with cylindrical shapes have suggested that the average dynamical properties of water molecules in a protein pore differ substantially from those in bulk water, exhibiting in particular decreased translational and rotational mobility.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3 cit4 cit5 cit6 cit7">3,5–7</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Molecular dynamics (MD) has been used to simulate the behavior of water molecules located between two planar hydrophobic surfaces<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF> or within cylindrical and spherical cavities.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9 cit10">9,10</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">These studies have shown that water confined in such molecular sized volumes displays a greater degree of order than in bulk, with the formation of distinct layers of molecules parallel to the surfaces.</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This confinement changes the dielectric constant of the solvent which, in turn, influences the effective electrostatic field within the liquid.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The situation becomes more complicated when we consider ionic channels since, in addition to the influence of the confinement due to the specific geometry of the polypeptide chains,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF> much larger variations of the dielectric constant are obtained due to the solvation of ions, like K<SP>+</SP>, present in the channel.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12 cit13 cit14">12–14</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">There are few experimental measurements of the solvent dielectric constant within a protein pore.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Let us cite for instance experimental studies of a water pool confined in reverse micelles and biological pores, which have revealed a substantial decrease of polarization<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15 cit16">15,16</REF> and a dramatic slowing of the rate of relaxation of water molecules.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17 cit18 cit19">17–19</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The behavior of water molecules bound within a cyclodextrine cycle has also been found to be very different from that in bulk water.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20 cit21">20,21</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Due to these specific properties relating dielectric behavior and confinement, water is becoming more and more understood as a structuring element in proteins, and <IT>ab initio</IT> calculations have been used to prove this feature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Frey and Cleland <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22 cit23">22,23</REF> have reviewed the evidence supporting the idea that short and strong hydrogen bonds could provide at least five orders of magnitude in rate acceleration of enzymatic catalysis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Green<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF> has proposed that a partially charged H<SB>5</SB>O<SB>2</SB> group could strongly block a voltage-gated channel by preventing motions of transmembrane helices.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this paper we refer to a pH-gated K<SP>+</SP> channel from <IT>Streptomyces lividans</IT>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25 cit26 cit27 cit28">25–28</REF> the KcsA channel.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The past few years have witnessed the determination of the structure of several species of ion channels by X-ray diffraction<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29 cit30">29,30</REF> and by cryoelectron microscopy.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit31 cit32">31,32</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In particular, there has been substantial advances in the structural determination of potassium channels.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Combined with a large number of numerical studies,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit33 cit34 cit35 cit36 cit37 cit38 cit39 cit40 cit41 cit42 cit43">33–43</REF> these structures provide an opportunity to relate atomic resolution structures (3.2 and 2.0 Å resolution for KcsA) to their various physiological functions (selectivity, gating, permeation, <IT>etc</IT>)..<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit44 cit45 cit46">44–46</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In previous studies, we have built a model for the open and closed structures of KcsA based on the 2.0 Å resolution structure.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit47 cit48 cit49">47–49</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have conducted MD simulations based on the idea that this channel could support several K<SP>+</SP> ions in its pore.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Based on simplified arguments, four K<SP>+</SP> ions were assumed to occupy the pore, being alternately separated by water molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Their locations were chosen to be consistent with the sites determined experimentally.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27">27</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">This so-called KWKWK…K sequence was proved to be stable over nanosecond time scales in either the closed or open state of the channel.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit47 cit48">47,48</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this paper, we try to explain this choice in a more quantitative way by investigating the structural role of the protein and water on the K<SP>+</SP> ions properties.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The specific dynamical behavior of water molecules in the hydrophobic cavity found in KcsA has been described for the closed conformation of the pore.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3 cit6 cit50">3,6,50</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa3" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have conducted similar studies and tried to elucidate the correlation between the motions of the K<SP>+</SP> ions located in the cavity with the orientation of the water molecule in the closed and open structures.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.">Theory and methods</HEADER><P><s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The complexity of ion channels is such that information extracted from computational models can greatly contribute to the refinement of our understanding of their physiological properties in the cell and <IT>de facto</IT> to better apprehend ion channel diseases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">MD simulations on protein with explicit solvents and membranes and Brownian dynamics<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit33 cit34 cit35 cit36 cit37 cit38 cit39 cit40 cit41 cit42 cit43">33–43</REF> based on a simplified description of the pore have been used to study ion permeation at the microscopic level.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="No">Nonetheless all these models, at any level, contain more or less severe approximations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="No">In particular, it is well known that electrostatics plays a dominant role for the protein structure and function including transmembrane architectures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="No">Macroscopic continuum electrostatic models, in which the solvent is described as a structureless dielectric medium, are particularly useful to reveal the dominant energetic factors related to ion permeation, but they occult the specific role of individual water molecules in confined zones.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa4" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is what we want to stress by using KcsA, which is a nice example as it exhibits different types of water pockets.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this section, we briefly describe our KcsA models for the open and closed states and the MD protocols we used.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Details can be found elsewhere.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit47 cit48 cit49">47–49</REF></annotationART></s></P><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.1.">Model construction from experiments</HEADER><P><s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="New" advantage="None">We have built open and closed state models of the KcsA channel on the basis of experimental results.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The closed conformation of KcsA, as revealed by X-ray experiments at 100 K, is a tetramer formed by four outer helices M<SB>1</SB>, pore helices P and inner helices M<SB>2</SB> (Fig. 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Three main regions appear in this protein.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The narrowest part of the pore, formed by the backbone carbonyl oxygens of the amino acid sequence TVGYG (Thr75–Val76–Gly77–Tyr78–Gly79), acts as a selectivity filter (F) for the K<SP>+</SP> ions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">It extends over about 12 Å with a mean radius of 1.4 Å.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">At the membrane center, the size of the pore increases to form a 5 Å radius hydrophobic cavity (C).</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The gate (G), which is a thin hydrophobic region formed by the inner M<SB>2</SB> helix bundle, closes the channel with a zone of small radius (about 1.6 Å) on the intracellular side.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Very little is known about the open state of KcsA and the relationship between the structure and gating mechanism.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Homology modeling with MthK and KvAP,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit51 cit52 cit53">51–53</REF> which are nicely representative of the open state of the KcsA pore conformation, could have been used as a starting basic structure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Also, direct experiments on KcsA using site-directed labeling and EPR spectroscopy allowed the visualization of the structural rearrangements of the intracellular M<SB>2</SB> helices in the process from closed to open state.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit54 cit55 cit56">54–56</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The crystallized structure of KcsA (1JQ2), averaged over 50 protein configurations was improved by additional energy minimization using molecular mechanics to obtain the 1JQ1 structure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Three main experimental conformations (homology based structures, 1JQ2 and 1JQ1) could thus be considered as starting structures in an optimization process to reach a stable open state for KcsA.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although none of these structures are totally resolved, 1JQ1 has been chosen as being the most representative.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Moreover, the positions of several <IT>C</IT><SB>α</SB> atoms of M<SB>2</SB> helices occurring in the gate region are known in a precise way (Leu86 to Gln119 for the first monomer and their analogues in the other three monomers).</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have thus built a model of the open structure combining the <IT>C</IT><SB>α</SB> known skeleton positions of the open structure derived from EPR experiments and the well-defined closed structure modeled on the basis of X-ray data.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit49">49</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The diameter of the narrowest part of the gate in the permeation path was estimated to be about 5 Å.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Nevertheless, there is currently a controversy with respect to this value which seems, on the view of Brownian dynamics results,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit57">57</REF> too small to allow for fast K<SP>+</SP> diffusion motions comparable to experimental observations.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.2.">Hydration of the different confined zones</HEADER><P><s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The lipid bilayer of the cellular membrane (hydrophobic area) is mimicked by an octane box.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit36 cit47">36,47</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Of course octane molecules are not amphiphilic and cannot reproduce all the properties of a real membrane aligned phospholipids bilayer (<IT>e.g.</IT> different viscosity, stability, interactions with the protein) but both have nearly the same density and exhibit the same hydrophobic character.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The extracellular and intracellular sides of the octane box are formed by slabs of water molecules of 22 Å thickness.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have already stressed that we must distinguish the behavior of the water molecules belonging to the intra- and extracellular areas from that of the molecules which hydrate the cavity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore we fixed the density of bulk water in the extra- and intracellular sides to 1, while the density of water molecules in the cavity was determined by evaluating the Connolly surface.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit58">58</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">As a consequence a bulk water molecule, which occupies on average a volume of 30 Å<SP>3</SP> at 300 K, has its mobility appreciably reduced in the cavity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is correlated to a strong increase in water density (≥1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The cavity could thus contain between 30 and 40 water molecules.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit35 cit47">35,47</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fluctuations of this number initially optimized in the closed state of KcsA were studied during the gating of the channel, in consistency with the conditions required for the hydration properties of potassium ion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Indeed MD studies using the 3.2 Å resolution structure have shown<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13 cit42">13,42</REF> that the K<SP>+</SP> ion retrieves its complete solvation shell (8 water molecules) when the cavity is filled by at least 30 water molecules.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">As already mentioned, the pore axis at the filter level contains both K<SP>+</SP> ions and water molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Among the seven ionic sites observed in the 2.0 Å resolution structure<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27">27</REF> (2 extracellular sites S<SB>ext</SB> and S<SB>0</SB> and 5 sites S<SB>1</SB> to S<SB>cav</SB>) inside the channel, we deal with sites S<SB>0</SB> to S<SB>cav</SB> because S<SB>ext</SB> only appears at high K<SP>+</SP> concentration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Inside the filter, the filling sequence alternates, with two K<SP>+</SP> ions being separated by a water molecule in order to increase the solvation of the K<SP>+</SP> ions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit35 cit59">35,59</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although this quasi-linear sequence remains intuitive, its existence could be better understood by considering a steric effect (the K<SP>+</SP> radius and the average radius of a water molecule are close, equal to 1.33 and 1.41 Å, respectively) and the strong repulsive interaction occurring between nearest neighbor K<SP>+</SP> ions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the basis of such qualitative arguments, our sequence KWKWK…K was composed of 2 water molecules (named W<SB>1</SB> and W<SB>3</SB>) in the S<SB>1</SB> and S<SB>3</SB> sites and 4 potassium ions (1 extracellular, K<SB>0</SB>, 2 ions inside the filter, K<SB>2</SB> and K<SB>4</SB>, and 1 in the cavity, K<SB>cav</SB>, otherwise filled by water molecules) at the S<SB>0</SB>, S<SB>2</SB>, S<SB>4</SB> and S<SB>cav</SB> crystallographic sites, respectively.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.3.">MD protocols and calculated properties</HEADER><P><s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The simulations were performed with the AMBER suite of programs using the AMBER6 force field.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit60">60</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The open and closed conformations were relaxed over at least 1 ns so that local minima could be ruled out.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit47 cit48 cit49">47–49</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The water molecules were described by the parameters of the TIP3P model.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit61">61</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Time steps of 1 fs were required to describe all external movements, including the water rotations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the closed state, we have first proceeded with the solvent (water + octane) dynamics at 300 K in order to optimize the environment of the protein, the latter being frozen in its crystallized structure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In a second step, MD of the protein has been performed by increasing progressively the temperature up to 300 K during ≈200 ps.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This simulation was continued in the (NVT) and (NPT) ensembles during 3.4 additional ns in order to follow the approach proposed by Bernèche <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit35">35</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">This time was shown to be sufficient to reach equilibrium for the protein built on the basis of the 3.2 Å resolution structure.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13 cit42">13,42</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The temperature was maintained to a constant value using Berendsen’s thermal coupling<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit62">62</REF> at 1 fs relaxation time.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Targeted MD was conducted during about 3 ns to find an open state structure of the protein.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit48 cit49">48,49</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Starting from the experimental structure 1JQ1 discussed previously, containing the KWKWK…K sequence, we progressively increased a constraint applied to each <IT>C</IT><SB>α</SB> atom, for reaching the open conformation.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit48">48</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">This conformation was finally relaxed by releasing the constraint partially, then totally.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">This approach displays two main advantages over previous simulations already devoted to the gating of the KcsA channel:<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit39 cit41">39,41</REF> (i) the refined structure of the protein contains 24 additional aminoacids at the intracellular side of the membrane, which are pointed out here as dominant for the gating mechanism; (ii) the gating mechanism is monitored step by step as a function of the constraint in an all-atom description of the pore.</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">As shown in Fig. 1, the filter is not affected by the opening process, whereas the M<SB>2</SB> helices participate strongly in it.</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">During the relaxation, the filter remains stable while M<SB>1</SB> and M<SB>2</SB> helices tend to move slightly toward closing, indicating that the pore is still significantly opened after 1.5 ns (remember that the experimental gating occurs on a millisecond time scale).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The energy profiles have been obtained by calculating the potential energy of a positive (+1e) probe charge mimicking the K<SP>+</SP> ion displaced adiabatically along the central (<IT>z</IT>) axis of the pore.</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Lennard-Jones interactions between the protein atoms, water molecules and potassium ions have also been added.</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Energy minimization at a given <IT>z</IT> position was made along the other directions perpendicular to the channel axis in order to follow the most favorable energetic pathway.</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The components of the dipole moment generated by the set of water molecules in the cavity were determined by following the orientation of all of these water molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The projection <B><IT>μ</IT></B><SB><IT>z</IT></SB> of the dipole moment of each water molecule onto the <IT>z</IT> axis could then be calculated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that for an ideal TIP3P water molecule, the dipole moment is equal to 2.35 D.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Quantum calculations have been performed on a model of the selectivity filter containing 304 atoms.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit63">63</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">We truncated the KcsA structure at the level of the four Tyr78 residues, where the peptide bond with Gly79 was cut and ended with a hydrogen (–CHO), while near the cavity below the four Thr74, –NH of the amide bond was completed in NH<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The portion of the sequence considered was thus (Thr74–Thr75–Val76–Gly77–Tyr78)<SB>4</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The atomic positions were issued from MD relaxed structures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">No further energy minimization was done, in order to be strictly consistent with the MD results as for the geometries.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">No lipidic or water environment constitutive of the MD construct was considered.</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">We used GAUSSIAN03 suite of programs<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit64">64</REF> to evaluate the electrostatic potential.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Partial charges were fitted to reproduce the electrostatic potential surface using 6-31G(d) Hartree–Fock wave functions, with constraint of total charge conservation and following the Merz–Kollman–Singh scheme.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit65 cit66">65,66</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Determining partial charges is in general a difficult task.</annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, Merz–Kollman–Singh population analysis was proved to be efficient in determining such charges since it takes into account several molecular properties<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit66">66</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.">Results and discussion</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.1.">Motions of the KWKWK…K sequence</HEADER><P><s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 2 shows the trajectories of the centers of mass of the K<SP>+</SP> ions and of the water molecules in the KWKWK…K sequence observed in the relaxed closed (Fig. 2a) and open (Fig. 2b) structures during 3.6 and 1.6 ns of the MD production run, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Four main features can be extracted from these trajectories.</annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">First, the species located in the filter are strongly bound to the protein since they do not move significantly.</annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Indeed, in the closed state, the motions of W<SB>1</SB>, K<SB>2</SB>, W<SB>3</SB> and K<SB>4</SB> are contained on average in spheres of diameters ranging between 2.7 and 4 Å.</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">This behavior has been corroborated in our previous studies<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit47">47</REF> by the calculation of the root mean square displacements (rmsd).</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">These display very low values, from 0.5 Å in NVT conditions to 1.3 Å in NPT conditions, indicating very confined positions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Second, it should be noted that the spheres belonging to the trajectories of two adjacent species overlap.</annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">This does not mean that repulsive interactions always occur but rather shows that the atoms move in the filter in a concerted manner.</annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Indeed, a close examination of the time dependent correlation functions of their instantaneous positions already confirmed these concerted motions within the KWKWK…K file.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit47">47</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The third main feature concerns the K<SB>cav</SB> ion, which undergoes much larger motions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the closed state, its trajectory extends over 9.8 Å along the pore axis and 7.2 Å in the perpendicular directions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the open state, similar trends are obtained with the respective values 11.8 Å along the pore axis and 9.1 Å in the other directions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fourth, and perhaps most notable, the average location of the K<SB>cav</SB> ion changes between the two structures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">While in the closed state, this K<SP>+</SP> ion remains on average close to the cavity site, <IT>i.e.</IT> located at the upper part of the cavity as determined experimentally, but it shifts down toward the intracellular side of the cavity in the open configuration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The difference between the center of gravity of the K<SB>cav</SB> trajectories in the two situations (closed and open) is equal to about 5.4 Å.</annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Finally, let us mention that the large dispersion in the K<SB>0</SB> and W<SB>1</SB> locations observed at the outer mouth of the open structure when compared to the closed state may indicate an escape of these species from the pore.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.2.">Water as a structuring element</HEADER><P><s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None">In this section, we analyze the structuring role of water in the filter and the cavity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 3 shows the potential energy created by the protein alone in the open and closed conformations calculated along the <IT>z</IT> axis by minimization of the displacement of a K<SP>+</SP> ion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the filter does not exhibit strong deformation upon gating, this energy is nearly the same in the two conformations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The curves display a deep well in the filter, with a structured shape at the well bottom, indicating the presence of sites.</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the cavity and gate regions, no stable site is found for the two conformations, the main difference being obtained for the height of the barrier at the gate, which decreases by about 2 eV in the open state.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 4 exhibits the potential energy created by the filter at various <IT>z</IT> positions of a single K<SP>+</SP> ion for the closed conformation of the protein.</annotationART></s> <s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The energy has been calculated for the protein alone with three different methods to test their accuracy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The first curve (black dots) corresponds to the potential energy extracted directly from <IT>ab initio</IT> calculations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The second (dark grey line, blue in the html) is calculated on the basis of the Merz–Kollman charges derived from this <IT>ab initio</IT> potential while the last (light grey line, red in the html) is derived directly from the AMBER force field parameters (see Fig. 3).</annotationART></s> <s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 4 reveals that all the three methods display the same behavior, namely a deep structured well at the center of the filter.</annotationART></s> <s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Similar depths and shapes for the wells obtained from the three methods reinforce the fact that the semi-empirical force fields used in MD simulations are reasonable enough to describe the protein environment from the point of view of the potential energy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="New" advantage="None">We will therefore discuss our results on the basis of the AMBER force field, since <IT>ab initio</IT> calculations are in practice too time consuming for systems containing more than 300 atoms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although the secondary minima are more or less pronounced according to the method, this comparison clearly demonstrates that the well depth is mostly due to the electrostatic interactions between the ion and the 8 carbonyl groups coming from Val55 and Gly56 in their neighboring environment.</annotationART></s> <s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Indeed, the position of the minima correspond exactly in the three cases to the sites S<SB>0</SB>, S<SB>2</SB> and S<SB>4</SB> determined by MD.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">However it would be premature to claim at this stage that the protein field determines fully the sites and one fundamental aspect is to precisely define the influence of water.</annotationART></s> <s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 5 exhibits the potential energy (calculated with the AMBER force field) when two water molecules W<SB>1</SB> and W<SB>3</SB> are included in the filter at their preferred sites S<SB>1</SB> and S<SB>3</SB>, and in addition when the cavity is hydrated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Comparison of the curves including or not the presence of water in the filter and cavity reveals its structuring role.</annotationART></s> <s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Indeed the previous locations are clearly reinforced by the presence of the two water molecules in S<SB>1</SB> and S<SB>3</SB> since the energy experienced by the ions in sites S<SB>2</SB> and S<SB>4</SB> decreases by at least 0.5 eV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Even more indicative is the reinforcement of site S<SB>0</SB> as well as the occurrence of a new site corresponding exactly to the S<SB>cav</SB> position.</annotationART></s> <s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The presence of S<SB>0</SB> is enhanced by the W<SB>1</SB> water molecule.</annotationART></s> <s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The occurrence of S<SB>cav</SB> would be due to an organization of the water molecules and to the influence on the protein environment itself, both inducing the corresponding well.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">As a short conclusion to this section, one can say that the water molecules in these confined positions (filter and cavity) undoubtedly play a dominant structuring role for the K<SP>+</SP> crossing the channel.</annotationART></s> <s sid="143"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">They act first by enhancing the structure of the stable filter sites for the potassium ions, already partially outlined by the field of the protein alone, and second by revealing the cavity and S<SB>0</SB> sites.</annotationART></s> <s sid="144"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">It should also be noted that the sites S<SB>1</SB> and S<SB>3</SB> were found stable in the closed state of the pore, on the time scale of our simulation, only if one K additional site is present in the cavity<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit42">42</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.3.">Water as a dynamical element in the cavity</HEADER><P><s sid="145"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">In Fig. 6, the time evolution of the components of the total dipole moment of the water molecules located in the cavity, defined as the geometrical sum of all individual H<SB>2</SB>O dipoles, is shown for the closed and open states.</annotationART></s> <s sid="146"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">A positive sign for <B><IT>μ</IT></B><SB><IT>z</IT></SB> means that the dipole is oriented along the pore axis towards the extracellular side.</annotationART></s> <s sid="147"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">This quite noisy evolution is due to several factors: the atom fluctuations in the protein, the K<SB>cav</SB> motions and the thermal fluctuations in the orientational motions of light water molecules at 300 K. However, we can note that the dipoles projected along the directions perpendicular to the pore axis get close to zero on average while the component along the <IT>z</IT> axis reaches finite values.</annotationART></s> <s sid="148"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">A relatively stable mean value of −10 D is obtained for the closed conformation while a +11 D value is reached in the open state with, however, much larger fluctuations and thus relatively large standard deviations from the average value.</annotationART></s> <s sid="149"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">As a consequence, we expect for the open situation a large fluctuating electric field promoted by the water dipoles in the cavity.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="150"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to interpret these features, different hypotheses can be drawn.</annotationART></s> <s sid="151"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None">These finite values can be due to the dynamics of confined waters which cannot rotate freely in this hydrophobic pocket.</annotationART></s> <s sid="152"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None">This could also be due to the electric field created by the protein which would tend to orient the dipoles along a given direction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="153"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Finally, the field induced by the K<SB>cav</SB> ion may also play an important role.</annotationART></s> <s sid="154"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj5" novelty="New" advantage="None">Furthermore, we studied the electric field induced by the protein alone along the pore axis (not shown).</annotationART></s> <s sid="155"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj5" novelty="New" advantage="None">This quantity can be viewed as the gradient of the potential energy discussed previously (Fig. 3).</annotationART></s> <s sid="156"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Similar behaviors are obtained for the closed and open conformations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="157"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, a large difference occurs at the gate region where a global inversion of the electric field can be observed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="158"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Indeed for the closed structure, mainly positive values of the field indicate that K<SP>+</SP> ions will be pushed toward the cavity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="159"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the contrary, K<SP>+</SP> ions will be pushed toward the intracellular side in the open state since the electric field exhibits mostly negative values.</annotationART></s> <s sid="160"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None">This feature corroborates the fact that two positions of K<SB>cav</SB> are observed in the MD simulations, namely in the upper (closed state) or lower (open state) part of the cavity (Fig. 2), which is certainly also linked to the different mean orientations of the water molecule dipoles in the cavity.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="161"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj6" novelty="New" advantage="None">A closer examination of the dynamical behavior of the water molecules leads to another interesting feature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="162"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 7 characterizes the dependence of the <IT>z</IT> component of the total dipole of water molecules in the cavity <IT>vs</IT>. the K<SB>cav</SB> motions along the <IT>z</IT> axis of the cavity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="163"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">This component <B><IT>μ</IT></B><SB><IT>z</IT></SB> clearly follows the behavior of K<SB>cav</SB>, being relatively stable when K<SB>cav</SB> does not move and, on the contrary, changing its value with the ion motion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="164"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None">As a consequence, the orientational motions of the water molecules are more or less characterized by the ion dynamics.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit42">42</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="165"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Similar conclusions apply to the open channel with, however, larger fluctuations for K<SP>+</SP> displacement and water dipole component values.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="166"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa5" novelty="None" advantage="None">To demonstrate such a correlation between the water dipole and the K<SB>cav</SB> motions along the <IT>z</IT> axis, we have drawn (bottom of Fig. 7) the behavior of <B><IT>μ</IT></B><SB><IT>z</IT></SB><IT>vs</IT>. the position <IT>z</IT> of the ion center of mass in the cavity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="167"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">We see three sets of points for the closed and open conformations which describe relatively well the coupled behavior <B><IT>μ</IT></B><SB><IT>z</IT></SB><IT>vs</IT>. <IT>z</IT> (K<SP>+</SP> position).</annotationART></s> <s sid="168"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the closed state, the ion K<SB>cav</SB> is mainly located at the upper side of the cavity around 41.5 ± 1 Å, and the corresponding dipole due to water molecules in the cavity takes values which range between 0 and −20 D, with a mean value around −10 D, as already given.</annotationART></s> <s sid="169"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The center of the cavity, around 38 ± 1 Å, is much less occupied by the K<SP>+</SP> ion and corresponds to a dipole ranging between −10 and +10 D with a vanishing mean value.</annotationART></s> <s sid="170"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The third region at the lower side of the cavity (35 ± 1 Å) is still less explored by the ion and it leads to a positive dipole whose value fluctuates significantly.</annotationART></s> <s sid="171"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the open state, we recover the three regions, but with an occupation for the K<SP>+</SP> ion which is totally reversed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="172"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Indeed, the ion remains mainly located at the bottom of the cavity (≈31–34 Å) and the water dipole is clearly positive.</annotationART></s> <s sid="173"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The other two regions correspond either to a K<SP>+</SP> location close to the center of the cavity (around 37–38 Å) or to the gate region (around 29 Å), with positive values for the water dipole, respectively small (around 0 D) and large (20–25 D), respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="174"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The distribution of points describing <B><IT>μ</IT></B><SB><IT>z</IT></SB> (<IT>z</IT>(K<SP>+</SP>)) displays a relatively large standard deviation, with regard to the straight lines (Fig. 7).</annotationART></s> <s sid="175"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">These lines would correspond to vanishing fluctuations in the correlation between <B><IT>μ</IT></B><SB><IT>z</IT></SB> and <IT>z</IT>(K<SP>+</SP>).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="176"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 8 shows snapshots of the pore in the closed and open states.</annotationART></s> <s sid="177"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">We can see an illustrative example of what we described before.</annotationART></s> <s sid="178"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The two K<SP>+</SP> ions in the filter are similarly located in the two states while the K<SB>cav</SB> ion occupies drastically different positions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="179"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">A striking feature is the location of the water molecules in the cavity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="180"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the first situation (closed state), they are all located below the ion, and thus hydrate it only partially.</annotationART></s> <s sid="181"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">This means that preferential binding occurs with the innermost part of the filter, with the resulting water dipole component <B><IT>μ</IT></B><SB><IT>z</IT></SB> taking a strongly negative value (−19 D).</annotationART></s> <s sid="182"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the contrary, in the second situation (open state), the water molecules are more equally distributed around the ion, due to the pore opening, and the corresponding dipole value becomes strongly positive (+33 D)(<IT>i.e.</IT> toward the extracellular side).</annotationART></s> <s sid="183"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the open state, some water molecules are also located in the gate part, suggesting entry or exit from the cavity, while no similar behavior is observed in the closed state.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="184"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to study the influence of the gating mechanism, which initiates relatively large motions of the K<SP>+</SP> ion in the cavity, on the behavior of the water molecules motions, we have calculated (Fig. 9) the variation of the number of H<SB>2</SB>O molecules present in the cavity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="185"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Here, we have to define the limits of the cavity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="186"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">We considered that the upper side of the cavity corresponds to Thr74 while the lower side ends at the Ala108 residue.</annotationART></s> <s sid="187"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the closed state, this number is nearly constant and equal to about 31 (not shown).</annotationART></s> <s sid="188"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The relaxation process which follows the constrained opening induces some perturbations at the beginning of the simulation run, resulting in a large fluctuation of the number from 22 to 30.</annotationART></s> <s sid="189"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">These perturbations disappear after 0.5 ns of simulation to display a constant number of water molecules (around 32 H<SB>2</SB>O) in the cavity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="190"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">At about 1 ns, we see that the K<SB>cav</SB> ion, which was located close to the gate, has moved up toward the top of the cavity (Fig. 7b), and this leads to an increase in the number of H<SB>2</SB>O molecules (38 instead of 32).</annotationART></s> <s sid="191"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None">This value then fluctuates between 32 and 38, depending on the position of K<SB>cav</SB> in the cavity.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="192"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Some examples of the behavior of the center of mass of some water molecules <IT>vs</IT>. simulation time in the open state are illustrated in Fig. 10.</annotationART></s> <s sid="193"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The first example concerns a water molecule which remains inside the cavity during the simulation time.</annotationART></s> <s sid="194"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the second example, the molecule initially located in the gate region enters the cavity after 0.4 ns and remains confined inside.</annotationART></s> <s sid="195"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The third example corresponds to a molecule which exits the cavity after an initial ≈0.4 ns stay at its lower limit toward the intracellular medium.</annotationART></s> <s sid="196"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs20" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the last example, the water molecule inside the cavity leaves.</annotationART></s> <s sid="197"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">A striking behavior can be observed for all the water molecules which migrate in or outside the cavity: there is a transit residence time varying between 0.2 and 0.4 ns, <IT>i.e.</IT> a plateau for <IT>z vs</IT>. time when entering or exiting the cavity, near its lower limit.</annotationART></s> <s sid="198"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">Let us mention that in the open relaxed state, among the 40 water molecules located in the filter + cavity + reservoir (on each side of KcsA), only 28 are conserved over the 1.5 ns simulation time, while 12 water molecules have been replaced by others initially located in the intracellular region.</annotationART></s> <s sid="199"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None">This remark shows the great mobility of water in the open pore.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="200"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj7" novelty="New" advantage="None">Finally, it is also interesting to correlate the motions of the water molecules inside the cavity with those of K<SB>cav</SB> ion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="201"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj7" novelty="New" advantage="None">The distance between the centers of mass of the two species has been studied for most of the water molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="202"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs21" novelty="None" advantage="None">In Fig. 11 we illustrate the behavior of this distance with time for one water molecule.</annotationART></s> <s sid="203"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs21" novelty="None" advantage="None">The minimum distance <IT>D</IT><SB>OK</SB> ≈ 2.8 Å corresponds to the radius of the first sphere of solvation for the K<SB>cav</SB> ion (mean distance between the centers of mass of K<SP>+</SP> and oxygen atoms).</annotationART></s> <s sid="204"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">We see that the water molecule spends a rather long time in this sphere, but it can also rapidly move far away from the ion, to distances that can reach 8–12 Å.</annotationART></s> <s sid="205"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">Such values for this mutual distance correspond to opposite locations in the cavity for the two species K<SP>+</SP> and H<SB>2</SB>O.</annotationART></s> <s sid="206"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con15" novelty="None" advantage="None">This feature is reproduced for most of the other water molecules in the cavity (not shown), indicating that solvation is a very dynamical process, <IT>i.e.</IT> there are permanent exchanges of water molecules in the solvation spheres.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.">Conclusion</HEADER><P><s sid="207"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con16" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have shown that MD simulations complemented by arguments based on an electrostatic description of the protein can help to deepen our understanding of the role played by water molecules confined in the filter and the cavity of a KcsA pore.</annotationART></s> <s sid="208"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con17" novelty="None" advantage="None">With regard to the formation of the K<SP>+</SP> ion sites and the dynamics of the ions, interesting features have also been obtained by comparing the behavior of water in the closed and open conformations of the pore.</annotationART></s> <s sid="209"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con17" novelty="None" advantage="None">First, we demonstrated that water in the filter reinforces the potential wells’ signature of the K<SP>+</SP> sites in the sequence KWKWK…K.</annotationART></s> <s sid="210"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Second, we observed that the water dipole orientations in the cavity are strongly correlated with the motions of the K<SB>cav</SB> ion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="211"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con19" novelty="None" advantage="None">This correlation nevertheless does not prevent water molecules from entering or exiting the cavity when the protein conformation changes (through opening or relaxation of the M<SB>2</SB> helices at the gate), and water diffusion proceeds by always keeping an optimal shell of oxygen atoms around the K<SP>+</SP> ions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="212"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con20" novelty="None" advantage="None">A yet deeper insight to describe in a more explicit way the interactions between water, protein and K<SP>+</SP> ions could be provided (i) by the use of <IT>ab initio</IT> calculations and (ii) by considering the water diffusion over much longer times, which would require other numerical methods than MD, and would also allow the study of the variation of the number of water molecules in the cavity during the closing process.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
