<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b508092d" hasDoc="yes" version="1184" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">The low energy tautomers and conformers of the dipeptides HisGly and GlyHis and of their sodium ion complexes in the gas phase<XREF TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" /></annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">The low-lying conformers of the dipeptides HisGly and GlyHis, and of their sodium cation complexes, have been studied with a combination of Monte Carlo search with the Amber force field and local geometry optimization at the <IT>ab initio</IT> HF/6-31G(d) level, completed with MP2(full)/6-311+G(2d,2p) energetics at the HF/6-31G(d) geometries.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">For each dipeptide, both the N<SP>δ</SP>–H and N<SP>ε</SP>–H tautomers of the imidazole side chain of His were considered.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">For each of the four isomeric dipeptides, 20–30 conformers were fully characterized at the <IT>ab initio</IT> level.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">All low energy structures are found to involve H-bonding at the N<SB>δ</SB> position of imidazole, either as a N–H donor or a N acceptor, depending upon the tautomer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In three out of the four species, the most stable conformer involves a C-terminus carboxylic acid in its less favorable <IT>trans</IT> conformation, in order to maximize intramolecular H bonding.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">It turns out that the lowest energy tautomer of HisGly is N<SP>ε</SP>–H, while that of GlyHis is N<SP>δ</SP>–H.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This result argues in favor of the diversity of His tautomeric states in peptides and proteins.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">The sodium cation complexes of both GlyHis and HisGly have been studied as well, again considering both tautomers in each case.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In three out of the four species, the most stable structure involves chelation of sodium by the two carbonyl oxygens and the imidazole ring.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the contrary, the sodium complex of the N<SP>δ</SP>–H tautomer of HisGly favors chelation to the peptidic carbonyl oxygen, the imidazole ring and the amino terminus.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the N<SP>ε</SP>–H tautomers of both peptides, the most favorable binding site of imidazole is the N<SB>δ</SB> nitrogen, while in the N<SP>δ</SP>–H tautomers, it is the π cloud which provides side chain interaction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">As a result, both GlyHisNa<SP>+</SP> and HisGlyNa<SP>+</SP> favor the N<SP>ε</SP>–H tautomer of His, in contrast to what was found for the free peptides.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Among all naturally occurring α-amino acids in living systems, histidine (His) occupies a special position.</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The side chain of His, methylene-imidazole, bears two nitrogen atoms with variable protonation states.</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Their p<IT>K</IT>’s are such that imidazole may easily exchange protons with its surroundings in the biologically significant range of pH, effectively supporting many chemical reactions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Because of this versatility, histidine has been found to be involved in <IT>ca</IT>. 50% of the active sites of all enzymes, in a recent analysis of the enzyme structural database.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Lewis basicity of His also makes it a common ligand in the first metal coordination sphere of metallo-proteins.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is even considered that coordinated His may exist in its fully deprotonated form, at least as a transient species.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">2</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, the protonation state of His in peptides and proteins is a matter of great interest.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the pH range 6.3–9.0 in aqueous solution at room temperature, isolated His exists as a zwitterion with a non-protonated side chain imidazole.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this and higher pH range, the imidazole is in either of two tautomeric forms, N<SP>δ</SP>–H and N<SP>ε</SP>–H.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Scheme 1 shows the two N<SP>δ</SP>–H and N<SP>ε</SP>–H tautomers in the non-zwitterionic form.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Protonation of either form at the imino nitrogen leads to an imidazolium ion from which proton release may occur from either of the two nitrogens, leading to each of the two tautomers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In His-containing peptides and proteins, it is therefore expected that the occurrence of the two tautomers is strongly influenced by the presence of H bond donors and acceptors in the surroundings, and by the chemical reactions which occur.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Determining the tautomer populations in proteins usually relies on NMR measurements.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="No">One-dimensional measurements on various nuclei suffer from various drawbacks, although <SP>15</SP>N spectra have been shown to yield unambiguous information on His tautomers in <SP>15</SP>N-enriched proteins, and in isolated His at various pH and temperatures, in several solvents.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">More recently, several techniques have been devised to identify the protonation state and tautomeric forms of His, including N–C <IT>J</IT> couplings<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit4">1,4</REF> and 2D <SP>1</SP>H/<SP>13</SP>C<SB>δ</SB> correlations.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">It remains the case, however, that the protonation and tautomeric states of most His residues in most crystallographic structures in protein databases are not unequivocally assigned.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In such cases, hydrogen locations are assigned, either in the structure determination and refinement procedure, or in post-structural analysis, using tools whose reliability is not known in general.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="No">A recent computational and statistical study<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF> has indeed issued a warning signal about the significance of proton positions in His residues in protein databases, whenever specific NMR data is not available.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">This study, based on local energy minimization of His side chain torsions using the Amber force field, showed that proton assignments appear to be no better than random.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus it is currently difficult to extract from structural databases whether there is a strong preference for one of the tautomers of His in proteins, even with the restriction to the interior of proteins, where the solvent is not expected to have a strong influence.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">One result of the computational study is that there appears to be no general preference for one tautomer over the other.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to understand in details the factors determining the relative stabilities of His tautomers, it is therefore of interest to study model systems.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The situation is simple in isolated His, for which <SP>15</SP>N NMR, as well as other techniques, have established that the N<SP>ε</SP>–H tautomer is largely dominant.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">This dominance has been discussed in terms of the intramolecular hydrogen bond which may establish between the N<SB>δ</SB> and one or two of the N–H bond(s) of the ammonium group (note that in the following, we use the notation N<SB>δ</SB> and N<SB>ε</SB>, with δ and ε as subscripts, for the imidazole nitrogen atom at the δ and ε position, respectively, so that N<SB>δ</SB>–H and N<SB>ε</SB>–H denote the nitrogen–hydrogen bonds at these positions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the other hand, N<SP>δ</SP>–H and N<SP>ε</SP>–H, with δ and ε as superscripts, are used to describe the tautomers with the N–H bond at the δ and ε position, respectively).</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The same type of argument was found to explain the structure of the dipeptide HisGly, for which several crystal structures have been determined.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the crystals of both the chloride<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7a">7<IT>a</IT></REF> and dichloride<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7b">7<IT>b</IT></REF> salts of HisGly (with one and two chloride ions, and singly and doubly protonated HisGly, respectively), there appears to be a strong hydrogen bond between the ammonium group and the imine N<SB>δ</SB> of imidazole.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The crystal structure of the hemihydrate of HisGly has also been obtained,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7c">7<IT>c</IT></REF> in which the His side chain is not protonated; the structural parameters are consistent with the existence of a zwitterion, involving a N-terminus ammonium and a C-terminus carboxylate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Rather surprisingly, it was found that the crystal structure contains two peptide molecules per asymmetric crystal unit, in the two different tautomeric forms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">One is the expected N<SP>ε</SP>–H tautomer while the second is the N<SP>δ</SP>–H tautomer, involving H-bonding between N<SB>δ</SB>–H and the C terminal carboxylate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus it appears that HisGly is a simple model in which the coexistence and possible competition between the two tautomers of His already exist.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None">For this reason, we have explored the conformational landscape of HisGly.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to delineate in detail the interactions which influence the relative stabilities of the tautomers, we have also studied its dipeptide isomer GlyHis, for which there is no structural information available, to the best of our knowledge.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="New" advantage="None">Clearly such simple models lack the side chain–side chain interactions in which His imidazoles are often involved in proteins.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">Yet local interactions within small dipeptides are found to have a significant influence on the relative stabilities of the tautomers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="New" advantage="None">We have also studied the sodium cation complexes of HisGly and GlyHis, since in a recent study of the Na<SP>+</SP> complexes of a series of small peptides, we found that there exists a significant sequence effect on the binding affinities of HisGly and GlyHis to Na<SP>+</SP>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Sodium is known to bind peptides mostly through their oxygen atoms, however, in GlyHis and HisGly, it is expected that the imidazole side chain can provide an additional binding site, in a way which will depend significantly upon the tautomer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the present context, it is interesting to see if cation attachment may be a way to differentiate tautomers.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The detailed understanding of the conformation landscape of small biomolecules is a challenging task, both because there is generally a large to very large number of low-lying energy minima, and because energy barriers connecting these minima are often small, leading to several conformers being populated at room temperature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Various experimental methods are capable of yielding some structural data on such molecules, yet it remains very difficult to identify the lowest energy conformers with certainty, and to obtain an overview of the potential energy surface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="New" advantage="None">Quantum chemistry is an efficient alternative to experimental methods to explore the conformations of flexible molecules of relatively small size, as it provides relative energies of conformers with good accuracy, and enables a thorough exploration of the potential energy surface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">There has been ample work on the conformations of Gly in the 1990’s,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF> and other amino acids have also been studied, including alanine,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF> serine, cysteine,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF> valine,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF> proline,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF> glutamic acid<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF> and arginine.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Several oligopeptides have also been studied.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Herein we use <IT>ab initio</IT> computations to establish the structures of the low energy conformations of the dipeptides GlyHis and HisGly in each of their possible tautomeric forms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Analogous work has also been carried out for the sodium cation complexes of the four isomers.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Computational methods</HEADER><P><s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="New" advantage="None">The number of weakly hindered rotors (seven covalent single bonds between non-hydrogen atoms) is large enough in GlyHis and HisGly that constructing structures based on chemical intuition solely is not appropriate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="New" advantage="None">Thus we resorted to a non local exploration of the potential energy surface, as a preliminary step prior to local geometry optimization with the <IT>ab initio</IT> methods mentioned below.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Monte Carlo sampling was carried out with the Metropolis criterion at 300 K, in which random values were generated for the torsion angles around all single bonds between non-hydrogen atoms except the peptide bond.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to keep this procedure computationally tractable, the Amber 94 force field was used for energy calculations, with RESP atomic charges.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">At least two independent searches were performed for each case.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">A limit of 1000 random tries or 500 geometry optimizations was set for each search.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The first search was started from a β-strand like extended structure, while the second was started from the lowest energy structure found in the first, ensuring that the two would be largely different.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Random sampling was systematically followed by local geometry optimization at the same level.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">However the Amber calculations lead to an energy ordering of conformers which deviates significantly from that obtained with accurate <IT>ab initio</IT> calculations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to locate all of the low lying structures, a large sample was selected from the Amber results and subjected to geometry re-optimization at the <IT>ab initio</IT> level, typically between 20 and 30 in each case (each tautomeric form of GlyHis and HisGly).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In one case, the N<SP>ε</SP>–H tautomer of HisGly, we first searched the potential energy surface without a Monte Carlo search, but rather with a combination of scanning the relevant torsion angles and selecting structures on the basis of maximizing hydrogen bond interaction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Then we carried out an MC search starting from one of the low energy structures previously found.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This led structures of ranks 5, 10 and 1 at the optimized Amber level to insert into those previously obtained, and become structures of ranks 2, 6 and 18, respectively, after <IT>ab initio</IT> re-optimization and final energy calculations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="New" advantage="None">Yet this procedure is too lengthy to be used in general, therefore we resorted to initial MC searches for all three other cases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In all cases, the lowest 15 structures at the <IT>ab initio</IT> level arose from structures in the lower half of the Amber set, which contained from 30 to 40 unique structures, depending upon the case.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="New" advantage="None">The experience gained from the N<SP>ε</SP>–H tautomer of HisGly led us to inspect all of the low energy structures finally obtained at the <IT>ab initio</IT> level, and change some torsions when it appeared that a related structure might be of lower energy based on the criterion of enhancement of the hydrogen bond network.</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">We believe it is this combination of random and hydrogen bonding searches that may lead to an efficient determination of most, if not all, of the low energy conformers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Yet the present work does not aim at providing an exhaustive description of these very complex potential energy surfaces.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="New" advantage="None"><IT>Ab initio</IT> calculations were carried out at levels which represent a compromise between accuracy and tractability for consideration of a significant number of structures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Geometries were optimized at the HF/6-31G(d) level, vibrational analyses were carried out at the same level to determine zero-point vibrational energies, thermal corrections to total energies, and entropies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Final energetics were determined at the MP2(full)/6-311+G(2d,2p) level using the HF/6-31G(d) geometries, a level of computation which has been previously shown to yield accurate energetics.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">All results mentioned below are computed at this MP2(full)/6-311+G(2d,2p)//HF/6-31G(d) level except otherwise noted.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Relative energies computed at the HF and MP2 levels were usually found to be in satisfactory agreement with each other (differing by less than 10 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>, and often by less than 5 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">It turned out, however, that in some cases the differences were as large as 10–25 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">A careful inspection showed that such large differences occur when the conformers being compared have the C-terminal carboxylic acid in different conformations (<IT>cis</IT><IT>vs</IT>. <IT>trans</IT>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Test calculations on acetic acid itself indicate that the <IT>cis</IT>-<IT>trans</IT> relative energy is 7 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> lower at the MP2(full)/6-311+G(2d,2p)//HF/6-31G(d) level, compared to the HF/6-31G(d) result.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Moreover, low energy structures always bear a <IT>trans</IT> carboxylic acid that is H-bond donating, and this H bond is not very accurately described at the HF level.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the energy differences between the best structures of the two tautomers turned out to be very small for both dipeptides, additional calculations were carried out.</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The geometries of the most stable conformers were optimized at the MP2/6-31G(d) level, and final energetics were recomputed at the MP2/6-311+G(2d,2p)//MP2/6-31G(d) and MP2/aug-cc-pVTZ(−f)//MP2/6-31G(d) levels.</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the latter “(−f)” indicates that the most diffuse f functions on C, N and O, and the most diffuse d functions on H have been dropped from the regular aug-cc-pVTZ set As described in the text, these more accurate levels lead to relative energies in reasonable agreement with the MP2(full)/6-311+G(2d,2p)//HF/6-31G(d) values.</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In particular, there was no change on the energetic ordering.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Monte Carlo calculations were carried out with HyperChem 6.0,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19">19</REF> while the Gaussian03 package was used for <IT>ab initio</IT> calculations<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Results and discussion</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Conformer descriptors</HEADER><P><s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Several different ways are conceivable for the description of conformers, for each of the tautomers of HisGly and GlyHis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is due to the presence of seven weakly hindered rotors in each species: the C<SB>α</SB>–C(O) and C<SB>α</SB>–N of the main chain of each residue, the C<SB>α</SB>–C<SB>β</SB> and C<SB>β</SB>–C<SB>ring</SB> of the His side chain, and the C–OH bond of the C-terminus acid.</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Describing each of the conformers by the value of the torsion angle around each of these bonds would be rather tedious, although it would carry all of the information.</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have chosen to define families using a hierarchy of structural criteria (descriptors), of which several are non local.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The first descriptor is the existence of a hydrogen bond between an atom of the main chain and the N<SB>δ</SB> or N<SB>δ</SB>–H of the imidazole ring.</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">All of the low energy conformers determined in this work bear such a hydrogen bond; for instance for the N<SP>ε</SP>–H tautomer of GlyHis, the lowest lying conformer found without a hydrogen bond at N<SB>δ</SB> is higher in energy than the most stable by 18 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">We denote the cyclic motif formed by such H bonds as “C<SB><IT>n</IT></SB>”, meaning that the H bond generates a <IT>n</IT>-membered cycle.</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The various types of C<SB><IT>n</IT></SB> structures, C<SB>6</SB>–C<SB>10</SB>, are depicted schematically in Scheme 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The arrows in Scheme 2 are oriented from the hydrogen bond donor to the acceptor.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">For instance in the N<SP>δ</SP>–H tautomers of HisGly and GlyHis, the N<SB>δ</SB>–H bond can be a H-donor towards the carbonyl oxygen of His, generating a C<SB>7</SB> motif.</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">C<SB>7</SB> motifs also exist for the N<SP>ε</SP>–H tautomers, in which the N<SB>δ</SB> atom is a H-bond acceptor from an N–H bond of Gly in HisGly or the C-terminus OH bond in GlyHis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the other hand, in none of the conformers is the N<SB>ε</SB> or N<SB>ε</SB>–H oriented in such a way as to engage in a H bond of any C<SB><IT>n</IT></SB> type, because the dipeptide chain is too short.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The second conformation descriptor is the conformation of the C<SB><IT>n</IT></SB> ring.</annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The types of ring conformations encountered in low energy structures are presented in more detail in Fig. 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">C<SB>6</SB> rings connect the N<SB>δ</SB> position to the main chain nitrogen of His, which is the peptidic nitrogen in GlyHis and the N terminus in HisGly.</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In both N<SP>ε</SP>–H tautomers, there are two possible conformations, chair and half-chair (see Fig. 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that the half-chair may be inverted, leading to a different energy since steric repulsions with the rest of the molecule are different.</annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the N<SP>δ</SP>–H tautomer of HisGly, a chair conformation is formed by H bonding from the N<SB>δ</SB>–H to the amino terminus.</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">For GlyHis, the H bond would point to the peptidic nitrogen, but the rigidity of the peptide linkage precludes formation of the C<SB>6</SB> ring in this case.</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Other C<SB><IT>n</IT></SB> rings may be formed in several isomers, but the C<SB>7</SB> is the only one which occurs in all.</annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The various C<SB>7</SB> possibilities have been introduced above.</annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">We find two conformations for the C<SB>7</SB>, half-chair-like and boat-like.</annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hydrogen bonding is favored when the N–H⋯OC segment is nearly planar in both types of conformation, since it allows the N–H bond to point approximately towards an oxygen lone pair, and the two bond dipoles to be oriented favourably for electrostatic stabilization.</annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">This restricts significantly the flexibility of the C<SB>7</SB> motif.</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">As shown in Fig. 1, formation of a C<SB>8</SB> ring is possible only for the N<SP>δ</SP>–H tautomer of GlyHis, connecting the N<SB>δ</SB>–H bond to the carbonyl oxygen of Gly.</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">We found two conformations for this C<SB>8</SB> which may be loosely defined as half-chair-like and boat-like.</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">As for C<SB>8</SB>, a C<SB>9</SB> ring is compatible with one isomer only; in this case it is the N<SP>ε</SP>–H tautomer of GlyHis, in which the H bond connects N<SB>δ</SB> to one of the N–H bonds of the amino terminus.</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The C<SB>9</SB> ring is associated in some cases with a C<SB>6</SB> ring, when the main chain is oriented in a way which also permits interaction of N<SB>δ</SB> with the peptidic N–H bond.</annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Finally, C<SB>10</SB> rings exist in both tautomers of HisGly.</annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the N<SP>δ</SP>–H tautomer it is due to a H bond between the N<SB>δ</SB>–H bond and the oxygens at the C terminus, while in the N<SP>ε</SP>–H tautomer, the H bond is between the C terminus O–H bond of the <IT>trans</IT> conformation of carboxylic acid and N<SB>δ</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In both cases, we find two conformers, which are deduced from each other by a 180° rotation around the C<SB>α</SB>–N bond of Gly (see Fig. 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">This leads to opposite orientations of the OC−N–H peptidic group with respect to the mean plane of the C<SB>10</SB> cycle.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The third descriptor is the relative orientations of the peptidic OC–N–H plane with respect to that of the C terminal carboxylic acid.</annotationART></s> <s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">There are two rough relative orientations: either coplanar, defining a fragment of a β sheet, or perpendicular.</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Finally, the fourth descriptor is the relative position of imidazole and of the peptidic plane.</annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">“Open” conformers correspond to extended structures, in which the Gly residue and imidazole are distant, <IT>i.e.</IT> they cannot interact <IT>via</IT> H bonding.</annotationART></s> <s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">“Closed” conformers are such that such H bonds can be established, between the N<SB>δ</SB> position of His and an atom of either the peptidic bond or of the C terminus.</annotationART></s> <s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Altogether, each existing combination of these four descriptors defines a “family”.</annotationART></s> <s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have noted these families with capital roman numbers, in the stability order.</annotationART></s> <s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">For instance for the N<SP>δ</SP>–H tautomer of GlyHis, the lowest energy conformer belongs to family “I”, which corresponds to the existence of a C<SB>7</SB> ring, in a boat-like conformation, in a “closed” relative orientation of Gly and imidazole, and a perpendicular relative orientation of the peptidic and carboxylic planes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Within each family, there remain conformational differences.</annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">These are specified by the orientation of the terminal NH<SB>2</SB> and COOH groups.</annotationART></s> <s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The various possibilities encountered in low energy structures are gathered in Fig. 2, together with the numbering used hereafter.</annotationART></s> <s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">For instance in conformations “1” the NH<SB>2</SB> terminus is a H bond acceptor towards the peptidic N–H, while in “2” it is a H bond donor towards the peptidic oxygen, <IT>etc</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In conformations “a” the carboxylic C terminus is in its <IT>trans</IT> conformation and it is a H bond donor towards the peptidic oxygen, while in “b” it is <IT>cis</IT>, and a H bond acceptor from the peptidic N–H.</annotationART></s> <s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">There is some redundancy between these notations and the specification of the C<SB><IT>n</IT></SB> rings, since, <IT>e.g.</IT>, conformations 5 are C<SB>9</SB> rings (see Fig. 2).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">For all isomers, the most stable conformer of each family is depicted in Fig. 3–6.</annotationART></s> <s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to illustrate the conformational flexibility offered by the NH<SB>2</SB> and COOH termini, the six most stable conformations of the most stable family of the N<SP>δ</SP>–H tautomer of GlyHis are shown in Fig. 7.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Low energy conformers of the N<SP>δ</SP>–H tautomer of GlyHis</HEADER><P><s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The relative energies of all conformers, grouped in five families according to the descriptors defined above, are gathered in the left part of Table 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The structures of the most stable conformers for each of the first five families are shown in Fig. 3, while a series of conformers of family I are shown in Fig. 7.</annotationART></s> <s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The best structure overall is I-1-ad, which bears a C<SB>7</SB> ring with a H bond from the N<SB>δ</SB>–H to the His carbonyl oxygen.</annotationART></s> <s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to maximize H bonding, the carboxyl group is <IT>trans</IT>, enabling H bond donation from its O–H bond to the peptidic oxygen (which happens to be a C<SB>7</SB> ring of another type, not used herein for structure specification).</annotationART></s> <s sid="143"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The so-defined orientation of the peptide linkage is such that its N–H bond may interact with the π cloud of imidazole.</annotationART></s> <s sid="144"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">At the same time, the NH<SB>2</SB> terminus is oriented in such a way as to be a H bond acceptor from the peptidic N–H.</annotationART></s> <s sid="145"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">This structure is particularly stable since all heteroatoms are engaged in H bonding, except for the N<SB>ε</SB> (for which it is structurally impossible).</annotationART></s> <s sid="146"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The second most stable conformer is I-2-ad (see Fig. 7), 10 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> less stable than I-1-ad.</annotationART></s> <s sid="147"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The only difference between I-1-ad and I-2-ad is the orientation of the CH<SB>2</SB>NH<SB>2</SB> at the N-terminus.</annotationART></s> <s sid="148"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">In I-1-ad, the amino terminus is a H bond acceptor from the peptidic N–H, while in I-2-ad it is a double H bond donor to the peptidic oxygen.</annotationART></s> <s sid="149"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">In all cases studied herein, we find the same energy ordering between these two orientations of the N terminus.</annotationART></s> <s sid="150"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The next conformer of the same family (the fourth most stable overall) is I-3-ad, which differs from I-2-ad by the orientation of the amino terminus, which interacts with the peptidic oxygen <IT>via</IT> a single N–H bond rather than both.</annotationART></s> <s sid="151"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fact that this single N–H bond is better oriented towards the peptidic oxygen than either of the N–H bonds in I-2-ad does not compensate completely for the loss of one interaction, leading to a destabilization of 3 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> (<IT>i.e.</IT> 13 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> less stable than I-1-ad).</annotationART></s> <s sid="152"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Other conformers of the same family have the carboxyl group in the <IT>cis</IT> conformation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="153"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although it is intrinsically more stable than the <IT>trans</IT> (by 22 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> in acetic acid), it does not allow simultaneous H bonding to the oxygen carbonyl on the one hand, and from the O–H bond on the other.</annotationART></s> <s sid="154"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The most stable of such conformers is I-1-d, which differs from I-1-ad only by the orientation of the OH group.</annotationART></s> <s sid="155"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">It lies 17 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> higher in energy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="156"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Other conformers add to this another less favourable interaction relative to I-1-ad, such as the orientation of the amino terminus, or the hydroxyl oxygen instead of the more basic carbonyl oxygen as a H bond acceptor (see Fig. 7), and are more than 20 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> less stable than I-1-ad.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="157"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj5" novelty="New" advantage="None">We now turn to the lowest energy conformers of other families.</annotationART></s> <s sid="158"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The most stable structure in family II, II-1-b, shown in Fig. 3, bears a C<SB>8</SB> ring.</annotationART></s> <s sid="159"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Here it is the peptide carbonyl oxygen, rather than that of the carboxyl terminus, which interacts with the N<SB>δ</SB>–H bond of imidazole.</annotationART></s> <s sid="160"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The peptide linkage is oriented in such a way as to allow H bond donation from the peptidic N–H to both the amino terminus and the carbonyl oxygen of the C terminus.</annotationART></s> <s sid="161"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is 12 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> less stable than I-1-ad.</annotationART></s> <s sid="162"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">The most stable structure in family III, III-1-b, has a C<SB>8</SB> ring analogous to that in family II, however, in a boat-like conformation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="163"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">The peptide linkage has the same orientation as II-1-b, and thus forms the same H bonds involving the amidic hydrogen.</annotationART></s> <s sid="164"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">The most stable structure in family IV, IV-1-bd, has a C<SB>7</SB> ring involving the C-terminus carbonyl oxygen as in family I, however, the ring has a half-chair-like conformation, while it is boat-like in family I. The two families also differ by the relative orientations of the peptidic and C-terminus planes (third descriptor above), perpendicular for family I and parallel for family IV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="165"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">This parallel orientation is common with family II, and it allows again the peptidic N–H bond to interact with both termini.</annotationART></s> <s sid="166"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">This leaves the peptidic carbonyl oxygen without a H bond, so that this structure is less stable than I-1-ad by 14 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="167"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">Family V has a C<SB>7</SB> ring of the same type as that of family I, but they differ by their conformation: half-chair-like in I, and boat-like in V. With a cis carboxyl group leaving the OH bond without H bonding, the most structure of family V, V-1-d, lies 16 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> above I-1-a.</annotationART></s> <s sid="168"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Some additional, generally less stable, conformers of this species may be found in Table 1.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Low energy conformers of the N<SP>ε</SP>–H tautomer of GlyHis</HEADER><P><s sid="169"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The relative energies of all conformers are gathered in the right part of Table 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="170"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The most stable conformers for each of the first seven families are shown in Fig. 4.</annotationART></s> <s sid="171"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">As for the most stable conformer of the N<SP>δ</SP>–H tautomer, the most stable structure (I-1-jb) involves a boat-like C<SB>7</SB> ring, which is closed in this case by a O–H⋯N bond from the C terminus to the imidazole N<SB>δ</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="172"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">For this to occur, the carboxyl group is in its <IT>trans</IT> conformation, another feature that is common to both tautomers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="173"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">The main chain has parallel peptide and carboxyl groups, and has glycine and imidazole in an open arrangement.</annotationART></s> <s sid="174"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">This allows the peptidic N–H to interact with both the C-terminus carbonyl oxygen and with the amino terminus.</annotationART></s> <s sid="175"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the other hand, the open structure precludes any interaction of the peptide carbonyl, which may explain why this conformer is less stable than the best N<SP>δ</SP>–H conformer (see Table 1; at the MP2/6-311+G(2d,2p)//MP2/6-31G* level, this difference is 6.5 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="176"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">The second most stable conformer (I-2-jb, not shown) resembles the first, the only difference being that the amino terminus is a H bond donor towards the peptidic carbonyl, rather than an acceptor from the peptidic N–H.</annotationART></s> <s sid="177"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus the lower portion of the conformational spaces of the N<SP>δ</SP>–H and N<SP>ε</SP>–H tautomers are fairly similar.</annotationART></s> <s sid="178"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The third most stable structure is also the first of family II (II-1,5-b, see Fig. 4).</annotationART></s> <s sid="179"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">It has a C<SB>9</SB> ring connecting the amino terminus to the imidazole N<SB>δ</SB>, and in addition, the relative orientations of the peptide linkage and of the carboxyl group, and of the main chain and the imidazole, enable the formation of a C<SB>6</SB> ring between N<SB>δ</SB> and the peptidic N–H.</annotationART></s> <s sid="180"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None">This structure is 7 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> higher in energy than I-1,5-jb.</annotationART></s> <s sid="181"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" advantage="None">A structure analogous to that of II-1,5-b, with a C<SB>9</SB> ring and planar main chain, is found with IV-1,5-b (the seventh most stable conformer in Table 2).</annotationART></s> <s sid="182"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" advantage="None">However the C<SB>9</SB> conformation is different, precluding the formation of a C<SB>6</SB> ring.</annotationART></s> <s sid="183"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs19" novelty="None" advantage="None">This conformer is only 3 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> less stable than II-1,5-b.</annotationART></s> <s sid="184"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is likely that the loss of a H bond is partly compensated by a smaller strain, permitting better relative orientations of the amino terminus and the peptidic N–H for H bonding.</annotationART></s> <s sid="185"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs20" novelty="None" advantage="None">A slightly more stable structure is the best conformer of family III, III-1-f.</annotationART></s> <s sid="186"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None">Its favourable features are a C<SB>6</SB> ring and a H bond from the peptidic N–H to the amino terminus.</annotationART></s> <s sid="187"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, none of its carboxyl oxygens can engage into H bonds, which is why this structure is 8 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> higher in energy than I-1-jb.</annotationART></s> <s sid="188"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs21" novelty="None" advantage="None">Another structure shown in Fig. 4 is V-1-b, which has a stable, planar main chain skeleton, but which lacks a H bond to the imidazole N<SB>δ</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="189"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs21" novelty="None" advantage="None">This leads to a high energy, 18 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> higher above I-1-jb.</annotationART></s> <s sid="190"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs22" novelty="None" advantage="None">Other structures in Fig. 4, the most stable of families VI and VII, are of even higher energies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="191"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs23" novelty="None" advantage="None">There are also conformers of intermediate energies, in the 12–20 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> range above I-1-jb, which are not described in detail here, but for which the specification of descriptors in Table 2 should be reasonably explicit.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Low energy conformers of the N<SP>δ</SP>–H tautomer of HisGly</HEADER><P><s sid="192"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs24" novelty="None" advantage="None">The relative energies of all conformers found are gathered in the left part of Table 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="193"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs25" novelty="None" advantage="None">The structures of the most stable conformers for each of the eight families identified are shown in Fig. 5.</annotationART></s> <s sid="194"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None">The best conformer, I-1-h, has a boat-like C<SB>7</SB> ring which involves the peptidic carbonyl, as compared to the carboxyl carbonyl in GlyHis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="195"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res29" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, the perpendicular orientations of the peptidic linkage and the carboxyl terminus enable the latter to interact with the N<SB>δ</SB>–H of imidazole, forming a C<SB>10</SB> ring.</annotationART></s> <s sid="196"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res30" novelty="None" advantage="None">The favourable orientation of the amino terminus towards the peptidic N–H, already described previously, also permits some interaction of one of its N–H bonds with the π cloud of imidazole.</annotationART></s> <s sid="197"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs26" novelty="None" advantage="None">As seen in Table 2, this is the most stable conformer, however, it is slightly less stable than the best conformer of the N<SP>ε</SP>–H tautomer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="198"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" advantage="None">The most stable conformer of family II, II-1-b (see Fig. 5), differs from I-1-h by the orientation of the Gly backbone, with the terminal carbonyl interacting with the peptidic N–H rather than with N<SB>δ</SB>–H.</annotationART></s> <s sid="199"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is a weaker interaction, essentially a dipole–dipole interaction of the CO and N–H bonds with antiparallel dipoles, rather than a H bond.</annotationART></s> <s sid="200"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs27" novelty="None" advantage="None">As a consequence, it is less stable than I-1-h by 5 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="201"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs28" novelty="None" advantage="None">The next two conformers (not shown) are higher congeners of family I, differing from I-1-h only by the orientation of the COOH group.</annotationART></s> <s sid="202"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs28" novelty="None" advantage="None">They are less stable than I-1-h by 6–8 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="203"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs29" novelty="None" advantage="None">The next most stable structure is the first of family III (III-4-h, see Fig. 5).</annotationART></s> <s sid="204"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res32" novelty="None" advantage="None">It has a C<SB>10</SB> ring as does I-1-h, but with a different conformation (of type a for III-4-h), in which the C<SB>7</SB> ring no longer exists.</annotationART></s> <s sid="205"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res32" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although the amino terminus –N–H peptidic bond interaction is maintained, together with that of one amino N–H with the π cloud of imidazole, the lack of the C<SB>7</SB> ring leads to a destabilization of 12 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="206"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res33" novelty="None" advantage="None">Structure IV-1-h, the next higher conformer, presents a b-type C<SB>10</SB> ring, no C<SB>7</SB> ring, and has no amino N–H-imidazole stabilization.</annotationART></s> <s sid="207"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs30" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is about 1 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> less stable than III-4-h.</annotationART></s> <s sid="208"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs31" novelty="None" advantage="None">Several conformers belonging to the III, IV and I families follow with increasing energies, and the first members of families V-VIII (shown in Fig. 5) are all at least 20 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> less stable than I-1-h.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Low energy conformers of the N<SP>ε</SP>–H tautomer of HisGly</HEADER><P><s sid="209"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs32" novelty="None" advantage="None">The relative energies of all conformers found are gathered in the right part of Table 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="210"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs33" novelty="None" advantage="None">The structures of the most stable conformers for each of the seven families identified are shown in Fig. 6.</annotationART></s> <s sid="211"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs34" novelty="None" advantage="None">The best structure, I-1-a, involves a C<SB>6</SB> ring in a half-chair conformation (as do the next two most stable, I-1-f and I-1-b).</annotationART></s> <s sid="212"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res34" novelty="None" advantage="None">The amino terminus is both a H bond donor, to N<SB>δ</SB>, and an acceptor, from the peptidic N–H.</annotationART></s> <s sid="213"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res34" novelty="None" advantage="None">As discussed above, the latter interaction is common in low energy structures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="214"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res34" novelty="None" advantage="None">The carboxyl terminus adopts a <IT>trans</IT> conformation to act as a H bond donor to the peptidic carbonyl.</annotationART></s> <s sid="215"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs35" novelty="None" advantage="None">Its other typical, <IT>cis</IT> conformation, is adopted in I-1-f, which is 7 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> less stable.</annotationART></s> <s sid="216"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res35" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus here again, the most stable structure involves a <IT>trans</IT> carboxylic acid.</annotationART></s> <s sid="217"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs36" novelty="None" advantage="None">The first member of family II, II-1-i, is the fourth most stable overall.</annotationART></s> <s sid="218"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res36" novelty="None" advantage="None">Its ring is a C<SB>10</SB>, and it is now the carboxyl terminus in its <IT>trans</IT> conformation which behaves as a H bond donor towards the N<SB>δ</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="219"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res36" novelty="None" advantage="None">Again the amino terminus can accept H bonding from the peptidic N–H, however, both carbonyl oxygen are left without significant interaction, leading to an energy 10 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> higher than that of I-1-a.</annotationART></s> <s sid="220"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res36" novelty="None" advantage="None">While the C<SB>7</SB> ring was clearly the most favorable for the three previous isomers, in this case the only possibility to form a C<SB>7</SB> is to bind the peptidic N–H bond to the N<SB>δ</SB>, which is incompatible with H bond donation of the peptidic N–H to the amino terminus.</annotationART></s> <s sid="221"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs37" novelty="None" advantage="None">Not only is the C<SB>7</SB> not the best ring in this case, but the most stable conformer bearing a C<SB>7</SB>, III-2-b, is found to lie 15 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> higher than I-1-a.</annotationART></s> <s sid="222"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs38" novelty="None" advantage="None">The first member of family IV, IV-3-b, has a conformation very close to that of III-2-b.</annotationART></s> <s sid="223"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs38" novelty="None" advantage="None">They differ only by the C<SB>7</SB> conformation (half-chair-like in IV-3-b).</annotationART></s> <s sid="224"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs39" novelty="None" advantage="None">Another C<SB>7</SB> occurs in family V, V-2-a, with the same C<SB>7</SB> conformation as in IV-3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="225"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res37" novelty="None" advantage="None">The difference consists in the perpendicular orientation of the acid function with respect to the peptidic plane (third descriptor).</annotationART></s> <s sid="226"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res37" novelty="None" advantage="None">This orientation allows the carboxyl group in <IT>trans</IT> conformation to make a H bond to the peptidic carbonyl, instead of being <IT>cis</IT> and bind electrostatically with the peptidic N–H (as in IV-3-b).</annotationART></s> <s sid="227"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs40" novelty="None" advantage="None">As a balance of these changes, the energies of these three conformers III-2-b, IV-3-b and V-2-a are very close and differ only by 3 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Zwitterions</HEADER><P><s sid="228"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Amino acids are known to have zwitterionic structures in aqueous solution in the biologically significant range of pH (<IT>ca</IT>. 6–9).</annotationART></s> <s sid="229"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the gas phase, the positive and negative charges cannot be as efficiently stabilized as they are in solution, and the zwitterions are expected to be much less stable.</annotationART></s> <s sid="230"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">In fact, all available evidences point to structures without formal charges in the gas phase.</annotationART></s> <s sid="231"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus we expect that for dipeptides such as HisGly and GlyHis, zwitterions are not the most stable isomers either.</annotationART></s> <s sid="232"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj6" novelty="New" advantage="None">Yet it was deemed necessary to check this issue computationally.</annotationART></s> <s sid="233"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The number of stable conformers for the zwitterions of the tautomers of HisGly and GlyHis is expected to be significantly smaller than for the “neutral” structures described above.</annotationART></s> <s sid="234"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res38" novelty="None" advantage="None">Preliminary calculations indeed showed that many structures lead to collapse to non-zwitterions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="235"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res39" novelty="None" advantage="None">As expected, the most favorable structures involve direct interaction between one of the carboxylate oxygens and one of the ammonium N–H bonds.</annotationART></s> <s sid="236"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">For such motifs to be stable against proton transfer from the ammonium to the carboxylate, at least one of the charges must be stabilized by a second hydrogen bond, for instance O<SP>−</SP> by the imidazole N<SB>δ</SB>–H, or N<SP>+</SP>–H by the imidazole N<SB>δ</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="237"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res40" novelty="None" advantage="None">In all cases, the zwitterions were found to be much less stable than many conformers without formal charges.</annotationART></s> <s sid="238"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs41" novelty="None" advantage="None">The smallest difference found between the best zwitterion and the best “neutral” conformer is for the N<SP>ε</SP>–H tautomer of HisGly, where it is 89 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="239"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res41" novelty="None" advantage="None">This zwitterion happens to have a structure that is fairly similar to that reported for the crystal structure of the hemihydrate of HisGly.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7<IT>c</IT></REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="240"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since all zwitterions are so high in energy, they are not described further here for the sake of brevity.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>General trends</HEADER><P><s sid="241"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res42" novelty="None" advantage="None">All of the low energy structures determined in this work (in a range of <IT>ca</IT>. 20 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>) bear a C<SB><IT>n</IT></SB> ring.</annotationART></s> <s sid="242"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res42" novelty="None" advantage="None">Moreover, this ring is a C<SB>7</SB> in the most stable conformers of three out of the four isomers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="243"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs42" novelty="None" advantage="None">In these three cases, the ring conformation is boat-like.</annotationART></s> <s sid="244"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res43" novelty="None" advantage="None">Clearly whenever the skeleton is compatible with such a motif, it is highly favorable.</annotationART></s> <s sid="245"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res44" novelty="None" advantage="None">A feature that is common to all four lowest energy conformers, is the N-terminus conformation, in which the amino group is a H bond acceptor from the peptidic N–H bond.</annotationART></s> <s sid="246"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res45" novelty="None" advantage="None">Finally, in three out of the four cases, maximizing the strength of hydrogen bonding leads to a <IT>trans</IT> carboxyl group being present in the most stable conformer, even though it is intrinsically much less stable than the <IT>cis</IT> conformer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="247"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res46" novelty="None" advantage="None">As expected, though, the specificities of the various isomers are such that not all of the descriptors can take similar values for all most stable conformers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="248"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The relative orientations of the peptide linkage and the carboxyl group, the relative orientations of the Gly skeleton and the imidazole ring, and the <IT>cis</IT> or <IT>trans</IT> conformation of the carboxyl group, lead to structures that are significantly different, in order to optimize the network of hydrogen bonds.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="249"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Comparison of the energies of the most stable conformers, for the N<SP>δ</SP>–H and N<SP>ε</SP>–H tautomers, indicate that the most favorable tautomer of GlyHis is the N<SP>δ</SP>–H, while that for HisGly is the N<SP>ε</SP>–H.</annotationART></s> <s sid="250"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs43" novelty="None" advantage="None">The energy differences are 4 and 1 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> for GlyHis and HisGly, respectively, at the MP2/6-311+G(2d,2p)//HF/6-31G* level, including ZPE correction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="251"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Such values are too small to draw a safe conclusion regarding the lowest energy tautomers, therefore they were recomputed with more accurate geometries and final energetics.</annotationART></s> <s sid="252"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs44" novelty="None" advantage="None">At the MP2/6-311+G(2d,2p)//MP2/6-31G* level, the energy differences between the tautomers are found to be slightly increased, to 5 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> for both GlyHis and HisGly.</annotationART></s> <s sid="253"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs45" novelty="None" advantage="None">At the MP2/aug-cc-pVTZ(-f)//MP2/6-31G* level, they increase again, and amount to 7 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> for GlyHis and 8 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> for HisGly.</annotationART></s> <s sid="254"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None">These results leave little doubt that the most stable tautomer is N<SP>δ</SP>–H for GlyHis and N<SP>ε</SP>–H for HisGly.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Sodium complexes</HEADER><P><s sid="255"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The low energy conformation spaces for the sodium complexes of the four isomers are expected to be significantly restricted as compared to those of the free peptides, since previous studies<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF> have shown that multidentate binding of Na<SP>+</SP> is a strong stability factor in its complexes with amino acids and oligopeptides.</annotationART></s> <s sid="256"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">For GlyGly, it was shown that the most stable structures involve ion interaction with both carbonyl oxygens, differing by the interaction, or lack thereof, with the amino terminus.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="257"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In GlyHis and HisGly, our results above suggest that for the N<SP>ε</SP>–H tautomers, the imidazole N<SP>δ</SP> nitrogen may be an additional chelation site.</annotationART></s> <s sid="258"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">It may also be anticipated that interaction of sodium with part or all of the imidazole π electrons will introduce an alternative binding capability, open to both types of tautomers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="259"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Because the number of low-energy structures is much less for sodium complexes than for free peptides, we do not introduce descriptors, and mostly describe the structures in terms of the sodium chelation sites and intramolecular H binding they involve.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Low energy structures of the N<SP>δ</SP>–H tautomer of GlyHisNa<SP>+</SP></HEADER><P><s sid="260"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res47" novelty="None" advantage="None">The principles summarized above are illustrated by the relative energies of the most stable structures (see Table 3 and Fig. 8): the most favorable chelation of sodium is to both carbonyl oxygens and the imidazole ring.</annotationART></s> <s sid="261"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res47" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since strong binding to N<SB>ε</SB> is sterically impossible, the ion interacts with the π cloud of imidazole.</annotationART></s> <s sid="262"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res48" novelty="None" advantage="None">In both I and II, Na<SP>+</SP> is bound to both carbonyl oxygens, and sits above the plane of imidazole, with closer interaction with one of the CN bonds.</annotationART></s> <s sid="263"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res48" novelty="None" advantage="None">The two structures differ by the orientation of the NH<SB>2</SB> terminus: it interacts with the peptidic N–H in I, while it is a H-bond acceptor from the imidazole N<SB>δ</SB>–H in II.</annotationART></s> <s sid="264"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs46" novelty="None" advantage="None">The distances from sodium to its chelation partners are almost the same in both cases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="265"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs47" novelty="None" advantage="None">I is more stable than II by 12 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="266"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs48" novelty="None" advantage="None">A third structure of the same type, III, differs from I by the terminal acid which is <IT>cis</IT> in I and <IT>trans</IT> in III, with the O–H bond pointing towards the peptidic nitrogen.</annotationART></s> <s sid="267"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res49" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the latter is not a particularly strong H bond acceptor, III is less stable than I by 20 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="268"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs49" novelty="None" advantage="None">A fourth structure, V, is also bound to sodium <IT>via</IT> the same sites as I, II and III.</annotationART></s> <s sid="269"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res50" novelty="None" advantage="None">It now has the NH<SB>2</SB> terminus interacting with the peptidic CO.</annotationART></s> <s sid="270"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res51" novelty="None" advantage="None">As seen above for the conformations of the free peptides, this is less favorable for NH<SB>2</SB> than interacting with the peptidic N–H.</annotationART></s> <s sid="271"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res52" novelty="None" advantage="None">V is less stable than I by 28 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>, and is essentially degenerate with structure IV, in which the peptidic CO is H-bound to the N<SB>δ</SB>–H of imidazole rather than to sodium as in the previous cases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="272"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs50" novelty="None" advantage="None">The remaining, less stable structures of this isomer (V, VI and VII) all have sodium bound to the two carbonyl oxygens only.</annotationART></s> <s sid="273"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res53" novelty="None" advantage="None">In all cases, the peptidic N–H bond interacts with both the NH<SB>2</SB> terminus and imidazole in varying orientations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="274"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs51" novelty="None" advantage="None">These three structures have similar energies, 30–40 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> higher than that of I.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Low energy structures of the N<SP>ε</SP>–H tautomer of GlyHisNa<SP>+</SP></HEADER><P><s sid="275"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs52" novelty="None" advantage="None">Here as for the N<SP>δ</SP>–H tautomer above, the most stable structures involve chelation to both carbonyl oxygen (see Table 3 and Fig. 9).</annotationART></s> <s sid="276"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res54" novelty="None" advantage="None">However the most favorable binding mode of Na<SP>+</SP> to imidazole is no longer to the π cloud, but rather to the N<SB>δ</SB> nitrogen.</annotationART></s> <s sid="277"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res54" novelty="None" advantage="None">This tridentate binding is found in I, II, IV and VI.</annotationART></s> <s sid="278"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res54" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the lowest three of these structures, the NH<SB>2</SB> terminus is in its most favorable conformation, interacting with the peptidic N–H.</annotationART></s> <s sid="279"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs53" novelty="None" advantage="None">I and II differ by the side chain conformation of His.</annotationART></s> <s sid="280"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs53" novelty="None" advantage="None">In I it is such that imidazole is closer to the C terminus, while it is closer to the main chain and peptidic carbonyl in II.</annotationART></s> <s sid="281"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res55" novelty="None" advantage="None">I and II are isoenergetic.</annotationART></s> <s sid="282"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res56" novelty="None" advantage="None">II and IV share a similar main chain conformation, however, in IV the C terminus acid is in its less favorable <IT>trans</IT> conformation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="283"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res56" novelty="None" advantage="None">This enables interaction of the acid O–H with the peptidic nitrogen, albeit not strongly enough to compensate for the acid destabilization.</annotationART></s> <s sid="284"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs54" novelty="None" advantage="None">A better compromise is obtained in III, where Na<SP>+</SP> interacts with the carbonyl oxygens and the N terminus nitrogen.</annotationART></s> <s sid="285"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs54" novelty="None" advantage="None">Here the acid is <IT>trans</IT> as in IV, with the O–H now pointing towards the N<SB>δ</SB> of imidazole.</annotationART></s> <s sid="286"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res57" novelty="None" advantage="None">This leads to favorable H binding with a O–H⋯N bond angle of 164°.</annotationART></s> <s sid="287"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs54" novelty="None" advantage="None">Yet this structure is less stable than I by 14 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="288"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs55" novelty="None" advantage="None">Another type of intramolecular H bond is found in V and VII, in which it is the peptidic N–H which binds to the N<SB>δ</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="289"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res58" novelty="None" advantage="None">These two structures have very similar backbones, with both carbonyls bound to Na<SP>+</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="290"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res58" novelty="None" advantage="None">They mostly differ by the conformation of the N terminus, and it is the interaction of NH<SB>2</SB> with Na<SP>+</SP> (in V) rather than with the peptidic N–H (in VII) which is the most favourable.</annotationART></s> <s sid="291"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res59" novelty="None" advantage="None">Finally, VI differs from II by the NH<SB>2</SB> conformation, and as seen several times before, H donation to the peptidic CO is less favourable than H acceptance from the peptidic N–H, by 25 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> in this case.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Low energy structures of the N<SP>δ</SP>–H tautomer of HisGlyNa<SP>+</SP></HEADER><P><s sid="292"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs56" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results are summarized in Table 4 and Fig. 10.</annotationART></s> <s sid="293"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res60" novelty="None" advantage="None">As for the N<SP>δ</SP>–H tautomer of GlyHisNa<SP>+</SP>, interaction of the ion with the N<SB>ε</SB> of imidazole is not possible, therefore Na<SP>+</SP> interacts with the π cloud.</annotationART></s> <s sid="294"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res60" novelty="None" advantage="None">However in this case, a significant difference may be seen: the most stable structure does not involve Na<SP>+</SP> chelation to both carbonyls, but rather to the peptidic carbonyl and the NH<SB>2</SB> terminus, and sits on top of the ring.</annotationART></s> <s sid="295"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res60" novelty="None" advantage="None">This arrangement allows for efficient H bond donation from the N<SB>δ</SB>–H to the C terminal carbonyl oxygen, with a relatively short H⋯O distance of 2.03 Å.</annotationART></s> <s sid="296"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs57" novelty="None" advantage="None">More importantly, the N–H⋯O and H⋯OC angles are 160 and 143°, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="297"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res61" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reason why the N<SP>δ</SP>–H tautomer of HisGlyNa<SP>+</SP> is unique is that this H bond involves a C<SB>10</SB> cycle (see Scheme 2) with enough flexibility to allow for nearly optimum N–H⋯OC orientation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="298"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res62" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast, in the GlyHisNa<SP>+</SP> N<SP>δ</SP>–H tautomer, there is only a C<SB>7</SB> or C<SB>8</SB> possible between the N<SB>δ</SB>–H and the terminal or peptidic CO, respectively (see, <IT>e.g.</IT>, isomers IV of GlyHisNa<SP>+</SP> in Fig. 8 with N–H⋯O and H⋯OC angles of 145 and 129°).</annotationART></s> <s sid="299"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res63" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the N<SP>δ</SP>–H tautomers of GlyHisNa<SP>+</SP> and HisGlyNa<SP>+</SP>, the N<SB>ε</SB>–H bond cannot form any significant interaction; the N<SB>δ</SB>–H bond can indeed engage into H bonds (see, <IT>e.g.</IT>, isomers III of GlyHisNa<SP>+</SP> in Fig. 9), but this can only occur at the expense of imidazole no longer being a sodium ligand.</annotationART></s> <s sid="300"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res64" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore it is only in N<SP>δ</SP>–H HisGlyNa<SP>+</SP> that such imidazole N–H bonding can compensate for the loss of a carbonyl ligand to Na<SP>+</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="301"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res65" novelty="None" advantage="None">All other structures have Na<SP>+</SP> bound to the two carbonyl oxygens and to the π cloud of imidazole.</annotationART></s> <s sid="302"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res65" novelty="None" advantage="None">They differ by two main characteristics: (i) the conformation of the side chain of His is such that imidazole is closer either to the C terminus (as in II and IV) or to the peptidic chain (as in III and V), and (ii) the orientation of the amino terminus.</annotationART></s> <s sid="303"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res65" novelty="None" advantage="None">The latter is a H bond acceptor from the imidazole N<SB>δ</SB>–H in II and III, from the C<SB>ε</SB>–H in IV and provides a fourth chelation site to Na<SP>+</SP> in V. These four structures span an energy range of less than 20 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>, while II is 6 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> less stable than I.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Low energy structures of the N<SP>ε</SP>–H tautomer of HisGlyNa<SP>+</SP></HEADER><P><s sid="304"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs58" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results are summarized in Table 4 and Fig. 11.</annotationART></s> <s sid="305"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res66" novelty="None" advantage="None">As with the N<SP>ε</SP>–H tautomer of GlyHisNa<SP>+</SP>, strong interaction of the ion with the N<SB>δ</SB> of imidazole is possible, so that the most favorable chelation of sodium is to both carbonyl oxygens and the N<SB>δ</SB> in I. Yet the next two structures in stability order, II and III, have Na<SP>+</SP> bound to N<SB>δ</SB>, the peptidic oxygen and the amino terminus, differing only by the conformation of the C terminus.</annotationART></s> <s sid="306"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res66" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both are very close in energy, 22 and 24 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> higher than I. Structures IV and VI have the same tridentate chelation as I, however, now the conformation of His side chain is such that imidazole is closer to the peptidic chain, rather than to the C terminus as in I. As a consequence, the amino terminus is a H bond donor to the peptidic oxygen in IV and VI, rather than being an acceptor from the peptidic N–H as in I. These differences lead to IV and VI being less stable than I by 26 and 32 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="307"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs59" novelty="None" advantage="None">Finally, Na<SP>+</SP> is only bound to two sites in V and VII.</annotationART></s> <s sid="308"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res67" novelty="None" advantage="None">V is more stable than VII by 8 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>, because its two ligands are the two carbonyl oxygens.</annotationART></s> <s sid="309"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res67" novelty="None" advantage="None">As seen for other cases previously, it has a <IT>trans</IT> acid which allows for hydrogen bonding, to the N<SB>δ</SB> in this case.</annotationART></s> <s sid="310"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res67" novelty="None" advantage="None">Yet with only two chelation sites to Na<SP>+</SP>, it is less stable than structure I by 31 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Conclusion</HEADER><P><s sid="311"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None">A comprehensive study of the low energy structures of both tautomers of GlyHis and HisGly, and their sodium complexes has been described.</annotationART></s> <s sid="312"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res68" novelty="None" advantage="None">Compared to what has been described previously in the literature for GlyGly, the side chain of His provides additional binding capability.</annotationART></s> <s sid="313"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res68" novelty="None" advantage="None">While the N<SB>ε</SB> position is too remote for interaction, the N<SB>δ</SB> can engage in H bonding either as an acceptor or as a donor, depending upon the tautomer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="314"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res68" novelty="None" advantage="None">This capability has a strong influence on all low energy structures of the four peptides.</annotationART></s> <s sid="315"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res69" novelty="None" advantage="None">Maximizing the H-bonding also leads to the C-terminal carboxylic acid being in its <IT>trans</IT> conformation in three out of the four cases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="316"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Overall, the most stable tautomer of gaseous GlyHis is found to be the N<SP>δ</SP>–H, while that of HisGly is the N<SP>ε</SP>–H, however, the energy differences are small in both cases, less than 10 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> at all computational levels used.</annotationART></s> <s sid="317"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Because of these small differences, the picture might be significantly changed in the condensed phase, especially in a protic solvent where intra- and inter-molecular hydrogen bonds might be in competition.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="318"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res70" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the sodium complexes, the N<SB>δ</SB> position of the imidazole side chain of His again has a strong influence on stability.</annotationART></s> <s sid="319"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the N<SP>ε</SP>–H tautomers, N<SP>δ</SP> is an efficient sodium chelator or H bond acceptor, while in the N<SP>δ</SP>–H, it may act as an acceptor, with Na<SP>+</SP> interacting with the π cloud of imidazole.</annotationART></s> <s sid="320"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The stronger ion–molecule interactions in the N<SP>ε</SP>–H tautomers lead them to be the most stable in GlyHisNa<SP>+</SP> and HisGlyNa<SP>+</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="321"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con15" novelty="None" advantage="None">These results illustrate the role of environment (here, sequence effects and ion chelation) on the relative energies of His tautomers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="322"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con15" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is highly probable that environment effects in proteins are even stronger.</annotationART></s> <s sid="323"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Tautomeric forms of His in X-ray diffraction structures should therefore be assigned with caution.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
