<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b508229c" hasDoc="yes" version="1184" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Vibrational relaxation dynamics of I<SP>35</SP>Cl(<IT>B</IT>, <IT>v</IT>′) induced by low-temperature collisions with He atoms</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Using laser-induced fluorescence and two-laser, pump–probe spectroscopy, collision-induced vibrational relaxation is observed to compete with the dissociation of electronically excited ICl in a helium carrier gas expansion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">By thoroughly characterizing the expansion properties, we observe that collisions of ICl(<IT>B</IT>, <IT>v</IT>′ = 3) molecules with He atoms in the expansion induce vibrational relaxation of the initially prepared dihalogen down to rotor states in the next lower ICl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 2) level on timescales that compete with the rate for non-adiabatic transfer from the <IT>B</IT> state to the <IT>Z</IT>1 state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The resulting ICl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 2,<IT>j</IT>′) product rotational distribution, along with the analogous ICl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 1,<IT>j</IT>′) distribution formed by collisional relaxation of molecules in the long-lived ICl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 2) level are compared to ICl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 2,<IT>j</IT>′) products formed by vibrational predissociation of He⋯ICl complexes prepared in different intermolecular vibrational levels within the He + ICl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 3) potential.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">No evidence is observed for resonance-enhanced collisional cross sections, even at the low temperatures achieved, <IT>T</IT> &lt; 1.0 K.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="I.">Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">A fundamental goal of reaction dynamicists is to develop an understanding of a bimolecular encounter on the state-to-state level.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">While this is particularly true for reactive systems, insights into the dynamics and mechanisms guiding energy transfer in non-reactive partners are also desirable.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">With this goal in mind, groups have undertaken investigations into the collision dynamics of several systems, some of which include rare-gas atoms with halogen molecules, especially helium atoms with molecular iodine, I<SB>2</SB>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2 cit3 cit4 cit5 cit6 cit7 cit8 cit9 cit10 cit11 cit12">1–12</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">These rare gas–dihalogen systems have the advantage of being both experimentally and theoretically feasible.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13 cit14">13,14</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Experimentally, the dynamics are simplified within a supersonic expansion in which low temperatures, and consequently small initial-state distributions, are easily attainable.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Also, the halogens have a low-lying electronic state, the <IT>B</IT><SP>3</SP>Π<SB>0+</SB> state, with multiple vibrational levels that can be easily accessed.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The He + I<SB>2</SB> system has received extra attention in these studies because of the significant absorption cross section of I<SB>2</SB> in the visible wavelength region, and because it was noted near the advent of supersonic beam methods that there is a large cross section for collisions of He atoms to induce vibrational relaxation of I<SB>2</SB>(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since then, a debate has ensued over the role that orbiting resonances, or weakly-bound collision complexes, have in the collisional relaxation of I<SB>2</SB>(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′).</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">An initial report suggested that orbiting resonances were the primary contributor to the large vibrational relaxation cross sections observed.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Subsequent papers have suggested, however, that resonances need not be invoked to explain the large cross sections.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit9 cit10 cit12">8–10,12</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">These papers do acknowledge, however, that even though resonances are not required to explain the results, they could still be contributing to the observed behavior.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Because of this, the debate is still considered by some to be open.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">A special subset of the experiments examining the collisional-relaxation dynamics of halogen molecules with rare gas atoms involves dissociation of rare gas–dihalogen van der Waals complexes, Rg⋯XY.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The dissociation of these complexes is often thought of as a half-collision event because it mimics the second half of a collision that occurs at a specified intermolecular geometry.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, while numerous papers have been published on the dissociation dynamics of Rg⋯XY van der Waals complexes both by experimentalists and theoreticians,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14 cit15">14,15</REF> surprisingly little effort has been spent connecting the half-collision and full-collision regimes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Presumably, this is because until recently the dynamics of Rg⋯XY complexes were only observed from one geometry, that of the T-shaped intermolecular orientation.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13 cit14">13,14</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Recent work by our group, however, has shown that different conformers of Rg⋯XY complexes can be stabilized within a supersonic expansion.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16 cit17 cit18 cit19">16–19</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, these conformers have different Franck–Condon windows, enabling access to different excited-state intermolecular vibrational levels.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">A recent publication on He⋯ICl has shown that excitation to these different intermolecular vibrational levels gives rise to different vibrational predissociation dynamics due in large part to the region of the intermolecular potential that is populated.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The experiments that are described in this manuscript were undertaken to identify the relaxation dynamics induced by collisions of a He carrier gas with ICl excited in the <IT>B</IT>–<IT>X</IT> spectral region within a supersonic expansion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">The larger rotor constant of ICl in comparison to that of I<SB>2</SB> permits rotational populations to be accurately determined.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">A combination of laser-induced fluorescence (LIF) and two-color, pump–probe experiments are performed in conjunction with a systematic interrogation of the spectra recorded using different expansion conditions to shed light on these energy transfer processes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="New" advantage="None">The full-collision data can be analyzed to determine whether evidence exists for resonance-enhanced cross sections for collisions of ICl with He at low temperatures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">Also, the dynamics of the full-collision events are conveniently compared to those of the half-collision dynamics that were recently reported for vibrational predissociation of He⋯ICl van der Waals complexes from varying energy regions within the He + ICl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 3) intermolecular potential energy surface (PES)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="II.">Experimental</HEADER><P><s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">These experiments were performed in a similar manner as reported previously.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16 cit17 cit18 cit21">16–18,21</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ICl was seeded in a carrier gas by passing the gas over a vessel of solid ICl maintained at 274 K. A pure helium carrier gas was used unless otherwise noted.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ICl/carrier gas mixture was pulsed through an orifice with a diameter, <IT>d</IT>, of 890(30) μm at 10 Hz into a vacuum chamber maintained at pressures &lt;2.7 × 10<SP>−5</SP> bar during an experiment using a roots blower mechanical pumping system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The pulsed valve and the supply lines, except for the sample reservoir, were kept at room temperature, <IT>ca</IT>. 294 K. The collision frequencies and densities in the expansion region were varied by utilizing different carrier-gas backing pressures within the range of 3.8 to 28.6 bar.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Regions with different local temperatures within the expansion, as well as varying densities and collision frequencies, were sampled by adjusting the downstream distance at which the laser axis intersected the supersonic expansion; most of these experiments were performed at downstream distances, <IT>x</IT>, ranging from 5.0 to 25.0 mm, or <IT>xd</IT><SP>−1</SP> = 5.6 to 28.1.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">A commercial dye laser, pumped by the 532 nm output of a 10 Hz, Nd:YAG laser, was used in LIF spectroscopy experiments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The laser pulse energies for most of the scans performed in the ICl <IT>B</IT>–<IT>X</IT>, 2–0 and 3–0 region (560 to 567 nm) were <IT>ca</IT>. 20 mJ after the beam was spatially filtered to a diameter of 3 mm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The frequency resolution of the dye laser was measured to be 0.06–0.07 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fluorescence was detected by imaging the interaction region of the laser with the expansion onto a photomultiplier tube (PMT) <IT>via</IT> a mirror and telescope assembly.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fluorescence was filtered spatially using a 16.5 mm × 2.8 mm mask, with the long axis positioned parallel to the expansion, so that only fluorescence from the center, coldest region of the expansion was detected by the PMT.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The current signal from the PMT was amplified, integrated and averaged with a boxcar-gated integrator, and recorded as a function of laser wavelength.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rotational contour of the I<SP>35</SP>Cl <IT>B</IT>–<IT>X</IT>, 2–0 LIF band was fit using known spectroscopic constants<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22 cit23">22,23</REF> in order to determine the Boltzmann rotational temperature representative of the I<SP>35</SP>Cl(<IT>X</IT>,<IT>v</IT>″ = 0) ground state level, <IT>T</IT><SB>rot</SB>, in each set of experiments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is critical since <IT>T</IT><SB>rot</SB> is dependent on the precise expansion conditions utilized, specifically the downstream distance that the laser crosses the expansion<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF> and, to a lesser extent, the backing pressure of the carrier gas.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, the mechanical opening of the solenoid pulsed valve varied slightly on a day-to-day basis and, as a result, the pulsed valve widths and the temporal delay between the opening of pulsed valve and the firing of the laser were optimized for each set of experiments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Slight deviations in the I<SP>35</SP>Cl(<IT>X</IT>,<IT>v</IT>″ = 0) rotational temperatures were found with these timing changes even when all other conditions were kept constant.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">For two-color, pump–probe experiments, the laser system described above was used as the pump laser, and a second commercial Nd:YAG (355 nm) pumped dye laser was used as the probe laser.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The bandwidth was 0.06 cm<SP>−1</SP>, and neutral density filters were used to lower the laser pulse energies so that saturation effects were minimized; we found that pulse energies as low as 30 μJ were needed to avoid saturating individual rotational lines in the strong ICl <IT>E</IT>–<IT>B</IT>, <IT>v</IT><SP>†</SP>–<IT>v</IT>′ product spectra.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">A dichroic mirror was used to co-propagate the pump and probe laser beams through the expansion region.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The temporal delay between the pump and probe lasers was typically 15 to 20 ns with a pulse-to-pulse timing jitter of ±1 ns.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">A UG-1 filter was used to block laser scatter from both the pump and probe lasers and to minimize the detection of intense ICl <IT>B</IT> → <IT>X</IT> emission induced by the pump laser.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="III.">Results and discussion</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="a.">Laser-induced fluorescence spectra of ICl in He</HEADER><P><s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">High-resolution LIF spectra of ICl entrained in a He supersonic expansion were recorded in the ICl <IT>B</IT>–<IT>X</IT>, 2–0 and 3–0 spectral regions, Fig. 1a and b, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">These spectra were recorded using a He-backing pressure of 14.8 bar, at <IT>xd</IT><SP>−1</SP> = 11.9, and with the same laser pulse energies and PMT settings so that the relative intensities of the spectral features observed in both spectra can be compared.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The spectrum recorded in the ICl <IT>B</IT>–<IT>X</IT>, 2–0 region was reported previously in Fig. 1 of <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">ref. 20</REF> but is plotted again in Fig. 1a for clarity of the discussion in these studies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This spectrum is dominated by the I<SP>37</SP>Cl and I<SP>35</SP>Cl monomer bands near 17 659 and 17 664 cm<SP>−1</SP>, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">To higher energy than the monomer bands are spectroscopic features attributed to transitions of He⋯I<SP>35,37</SP>Cl complexes with T-shaped and linear equilibrium orientations in the ground state to different intermolecular vibrational levels in the excited state.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16 cit18 cit24">16,18,24</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The intensities of the He⋯ICl features are <IT>ca</IT>. 100 times weaker than the ICl monomer bands.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">(Note the ×100 magnification of the fluorescence intensity scale for transition energies &gt;17 665 cm<SP>−1</SP>).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The LIF spectrum recorded in the ICl <IT>B</IT>–<IT>X</IT>, 3–0 region, Fig. 1b, was also published previously, Fig. 2 of <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25">ref. 25</REF>, and is dominated by features attributed to transitions of the T-shaped and linear He⋯I<SP>35,37</SP>Cl(<IT>X</IT>,<IT>v</IT>″ = 0) complexes.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16 cit18 cit24">16,18,24</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The weak features near 17 821 and 17 828 cm<SP>−1</SP> correspond to transitions of the I<SP>37,35</SP>Cl(<IT>X</IT>,<IT>v</IT>″ = 0) monomers to the short-lived I<SP>37,35</SP>Cl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 3,<IT>j</IT>′) rotational states.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26 cit27">26,27</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Based upon previous experimental investigations, the low ICl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 3,<IT>j</IT>′) rotor states accessed in these transitions have lifetimes on the order of 0.5 ns due to the presence of a nearby repulsive curve, the <IT>Z</IT> 1 state.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27 cit28 cit29 cit30">27–30</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, because our integration gate is delayed 150 ns after the laser, I<SP>35,37</SP>Cl <IT>B</IT> → <IT>X</IT>, 3 → <IT>v</IT>″ fluorescence is not detected.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Previously reported pump–probe experiments indicate that the I<SP>35,37</SP>Cl <IT>B</IT>–<IT>X</IT>, 3–0 LIF features are observed as a result of a mechanism that populates rotational states of the long-lived I<SP>35,37</SP>Cl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 2) vibrational level following the preparation of rotor states in the short-lived I<SP>35,37</SP>Cl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 3) level.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25">25</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rotational structure within the I<SP>35,37</SP>Cl <IT>B</IT>–<IT>X</IT>, 3–0 LIF features is accurately simulated using published ground and excited-state rotational constants and term values.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22 cit23">22,23</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">These features, therefore, cannot be attributed to transitions originating from bound He⋯I<SP>35,37</SP>Cl(<IT>X</IT>,<IT>v</IT>″ = 0) intermolecular vibrational levels or from weakly interacting He + I<SP>35,37</SP>Cl(<IT>X</IT>,<IT>v</IT>″ = 0) collision complexes that would have different rotational contours than those observed.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to best characterize the dynamics and mechanism of the collision processes occurring in the expansion, special attention was focused on characterizing the local environment within the supersonic expansion and on tracking the experimental observables as a function of the expansion conditions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">These measurements are used to estimate the physical parameters associated with the collisions of He atoms with ICl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 3,<IT>j</IT>′) molecules that compete with the non-adiabatic dissociation dynamics of the excited-state molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Finally, a comparison of the full-collision measurements with half-collision dynamics of He⋯ICl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 3) complexes will be made.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="b.">Characterization of the supersonic expansion</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="1.">Local temperature within the expansion</HEADER><P><s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Extensive experimental and theoretical investigations have been undertaken to characterize the properties of atoms and molecules within isentropic supersonic expansions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit31 cit32 cit33 cit34 cit35">31–35</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The thermodynamics for a perfect gas require the temperature <IT>T</IT>, pressure <IT>P</IT>, and density <IT>ρ</IT>, within the expansion region to be related by<IT>T</IT>/<IT>T</IT><SB>0</SB> = (<IT>P</IT>/<IT>P</IT><SB>0</SB>)<SP>(<IT>γ</IT>−1)/<IT>γ</IT></SP> = (<IT>ρ</IT>/<IT>ρ</IT><SB>0</SB>)<SP><IT>γ</IT>−1</SP>,where <IT>T</IT><SB>0</SB>, <IT>P</IT><SB>0</SB>, and <IT>ρ</IT><SB>0</SB> represent the temperature, pressure, and density of the reservoir gas behind the nozzle, and <IT>γ</IT> is the heat capacity ratio, <IT>C</IT><SB><IT>p</IT></SB>/<IT>C</IT><SB><IT>v</IT></SB>, or 5/3 for a monatomic gas.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit36">36</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">These quantities can be related to the Mach number, <IT>M</IT>, and consequently the distance downstream in nozzle diameters, <IT>xd</IT><SP>−1</SP>, by<IT>T</IT>/<IT>T</IT><SB>0</SB> = [1 + <IT>M</IT><SP>2</SP> (<IT>γ</IT> – 1)/2]<SP>−1</SP>, where <IT>M</IT> = <IT>A</IT> (<IT>xd</IT><SP>−1</SP>) <SP><IT>γ</IT>−1</SP>,where <IT>A</IT> is a constant, 3.26 for a monatomic gas expansion.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit36">36</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Eqn (2) is only valid for the region within an expansion where the two-body collision frequency is sufficient for continued cooling.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Previous experiments performed in our laboratory<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF> indicate that collisions of He atoms with ICl(<IT>X</IT>,<IT>v</IT>″ = 0) molecules and He⋯ICl(<IT>X</IT>,<IT>v</IT>″ = 0) complexes occur at downstream distances of at least <IT>xd</IT><SP>−1</SP> = 69, and thus eqns (1) and (2) would be expected to hold for regions in the expansion up to this distance.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The local temperatures associated with each <IT>xd</IT><SP>−1</SP> at which LIF spectra were recorded are calculated using eqn (2).</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">These temperatures, <IT>T</IT><SB>calc</SB>, are shown in Fig. 2 as open squares, as are the I<SP>35</SP>Cl(<IT>X</IT>,<IT>v</IT>″ = 0) Boltzmann rotational temperatures <IT>T</IT><SB>rot</SB>, that were experimentally determined by fitting the rotational contour of the I<SP>35</SP>Cl <IT>B</IT>–<IT>X</IT>, 2–0 LIF band, black squares.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">There is poor agreement between the values of <IT>T</IT><SB>calc</SB> and <IT>T</IT><SB>rot</SB>, especially at low <IT>xd</IT><SP>−1</SP>, as <IT>T</IT><SB>calc</SB> is more than a factor of two greater than <IT>T</IT><SB>rot</SB> up to <IT>xd</IT><SP>−1</SP> = 14.0.</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">A fit of the experimental data indicates that the functional form of eqn (2) is appropriate only with a larger value for the constant <IT>A</IT>, 5.28(5), black line in Fig. 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Similar behavior has been reported for a He/I<SB>2</SB> expansion using a slit nozzle.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">As noted previously,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit33">33</REF> the reason for the discrepancy may be that for He expansions the terminal Mach number reached is much larger than that predicted using classical equations.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The intermolecular translational energy that arises from the different terminal velocities of the seeded molecules and the carrier-gas atoms in an expansion gives rise to another temperature value, <IT>T</IT><SB>slip</SB>, that is not necessarily represented by either <IT>T</IT><SB>calc</SB> or <IT>T</IT><SB>rot</SB>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit31 cit37 cit38 cit39 cit40">8,31,37–40</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The difference in the velocities along the expansion direction results from the different masses of the species and is referred to as a velocity slip, with the heavier species travelling more slowly than the lighter species.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ICl molecules in a He expansion are thus predicted to be travelling slower than the lighter He atoms, and collisions between the two species will occur with a temperature of <IT>T</IT><SB>slip</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, each species in the expansion will have a different velocity distribution, which can be characterized by a translational temperature, <IT>T</IT><SB>trans</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The distribution of the lighter species is broader than that of the heavier species, which will also contribute to the slip between the light and heavy species in the expansion.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to estimate a value for the velocity slip between the ICl molecules and the He atoms in the expansion as well as the velocity distribution of the ICl molecules, we have directly measured the time-of-flight of excited-state ICl* molecules that is needed to travel a fixed distance along the expansion using a pump–probe experimental scheme.</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The pump laser was fixed at the wavelength of the I<SP>35</SP>Cl <IT>B</IT>–<IT>X</IT>, 2–0 bandhead, at 17 664 cm<SP>−1</SP>, and the probe laser was fixed on the I<SP>35</SP>Cl <IT>E</IT>–<IT>B</IT>, 11–2 bandhead, 23 066 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The laser beams were spatially filtered down to <IT>ca</IT>. 1 mm diameters, and a 0.5 m focal length lens was inserted after the iris to focus the lasers to diameters of <IT>ca</IT>. 320 and <IT>ca</IT>. 180 μm for the pump and probe lasers, respectively, in the expansion region.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The probe laser was aligned so that it crossed the expansion 3.5(1) mm downstream from the pump laser.</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The intensity of the I<SP>35</SP>Cl <IT>E</IT> → <IT>X</IT>, 11 → <IT>v</IT>″ fluorescence induced by the probe laser was then monitored as a function of the temporal delay between the pump and probe lasers.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The maximum probe signal was observed at a temporal delay of 2.00 μs with the pump laser crossing the expansion 9.9 mm downstream from the pulsed valve orifice, <IT>xd</IT><SP>−1</SP> = 11.1, when using a backing pressure of 14.8 bar.</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">This time delay corresponds to an I<SP>35</SP>Cl velocity of <IT>ca</IT>. 1750(50) m s<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The measurement was repeated with the pump laser set at 21.7 mm downstream, <IT>xd</IT><SP>−1</SP> = 24.4, and with backing pressures of 7.9 and 14.8 bar, and the same velocity was obtained in all measurements.</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Within the experimental error, this value is the same as both the terminal velocity of pure He in a supersonic expansion, 1760 m s<SP>−1</SP>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit38">38</REF> and the mass weighted terminal velocity of 360 ppm ICl in a He expansion, 1747 m s<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Consequently, we can only deduce an upper limit for the velocity slip between the I<SP>35</SP>Cl molecules and the He atoms of 60 m s<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">This velocity would correspond to <IT>T</IT><SB>slip</SB> &lt; 0.6 K, suggesting that <IT>T</IT><SB>slip</SB> may be either within or below the range of <IT>T</IT><SB>rot</SB>, 0.19 to 3.0 K. Consequently, we do include <IT>T</IT><SB>slip</SB> in some of the analyses described below to investigate what contribution the velocity slip may have on the observed dynamics.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa6" novelty="None" advantage="None">We also attempted to estimate the velocity distribution of the ICl molecules in the expansion by recording the temporal breadth of the pump–probe delay signals recorded as described above and with the pump laser at <IT>xd</IT><SP>−1</SP> = 11.1 and 24.4, and with backing pressures of 7.9 and 14.8 bar.</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The temporal breadth of the pump–probe signals in all the measurements was approximately the same, <IT>ca</IT>. 0.22 μs, and appears to be limited by the diameters of the focused lasers in the expansion region.</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, we do not include effects from the velocity distribution in the analyses below.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.">Local densities within the expansion</HEADER><P><s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since <IT>T</IT><SB>rot</SB> is the most reliable measurement of the expansion temperature for our current apparatus, and <IT>T</IT><SB>rot</SB> is known to be an upper limit for the equilibrium temperature, <IT>T</IT><SB>eq</SB>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit40">40</REF><IT>T</IT><SB>rot</SB> is used in eqn (1) to approximate the total density (He atoms and ICl molecules) <IT>ρ</IT> at each distance in the expansion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">As will be shown below, the general trend observed of decreasing I<SP>35</SP>Cl density as a function of <IT>xd</IT><SP>−1</SP> is reproduced using <IT>T</IT><SB>rot</SB> in eqn (1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">This provides some validity for using <IT>T</IT><SB>rot</SB> as the local temperature in eqn (1), despite the fact that eqn (2) does not quantitatively reproduce our temperature measurements.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The calculated total densities range from 3.8 × 10<SP>17</SP> cm<SP>−3</SP> at <IT>xd</IT><SP>−1</SP> = 5.8 down to 0.6 × 10<SP>17</SP> cm<SP>−3</SP> at <IT>xd</IT><SP>−1</SP> = 14.0.</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The densities of the ground state I<SP>35</SP>Cl(<IT>X</IT>,<IT>v</IT>″ = 0) molecules <IT>ρ</IT><SB>I35Cl</SB> are then estimated by multiplying <IT>ρ</IT> by the partial pressure of ICl in a He carrier gas, <IT>ca</IT>. 360 ppm at 14.8 bar and 274 K,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit41">41</REF> and by the isotopic abundance of the I<SP>35</SP>Cl isotope, 0..7577<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit42">42</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The resultant estimates of <IT>ρ</IT><SB>I35Cl</SB> vary from 1.0 × 10<SP>14</SP> cm<SP>−3</SP> at <IT>xd</IT><SP>−1</SP> = 5.8 down to 1.6 × 10<SP>13</SP> cm<SP>−3</SP> at <IT>xd</IT><SP>−1</SP> = 14.0, as shown in Fig. 3 as open squares.</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the I<SP>35</SP>Cl(<IT>X</IT>,<IT>v</IT>″ = 0) densities are orders of magnitude less than the total density in the expansion, the He-carrier gas density at each downstream distance is approximately <IT>ρ</IT>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.">Local ICl–He collision frequency</HEADER><P><s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Several models and methods have been implemented in calculations of the collision frequencies of molecules with carrier gas atoms within supersonic expansions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The simplistic equation for collisions between hard spheres<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit43">43</REF> is most often implemented to estimate order-of-magnitude collision frequencies of a molecule A with carrier gas atoms B:<IT>Z</IT><SB>HS</SB> = π<IT>d</IT>2AB (8<IT>kT</IT><SB>AB</SB>/π<IT>μ</IT><SB>AB</SB>)<SP>1/2</SP><IT>ρ</IT><SB>B</SB>The collision diameter <IT>d</IT><SB>AB</SB> is taken to be the average of the diameters of A and B, <IT>d</IT><SB>AB</SB> = ½(<IT>d</IT><SB>A</SB> + <IT>d</IT><SB>B</SB>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The relative temperature between A and B is <IT>T</IT><SB>AB</SB>, the local density of B within the expansion is <IT>ρ</IT><SB>B</SB>, the reduced mass of the collision pair is <IT>μ</IT><SB>AB</SB>, and <IT>k</IT> is Bolzmann’s constant.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The different values of the temperatures within the expansion, <IT>T</IT><SB>calc</SB>, <IT>T</IT><SB>rot</SB>, and <IT>T</IT><SB>slip</SB>, indicate the complexity of fully characterizing the properties of an expansion comprised of multiple species.</annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Rather than attempting to incorporate each of the temperatures in estimating <IT>Z</IT><SB>HS</SB>, we have chosen to use <IT>T</IT><SB>tot</SB> = <IT>T</IT><SB>rot</SB> + <IT>T</IT><SB>slip</SB> for <IT>T</IT><SB>AB</SB> and <IT>ρ</IT> for <IT>ρ</IT><SB>B</SB> in eqn (3) to provide an upper limit for <IT>Z</IT><SB>HS</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">We also assume <IT>d</IT><SB>He(ICl)</SB> = 3.7 Å, based on approximations of atomic He and molecular ICl diameters.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit43">43</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Calculations of the He + ICl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 2) PES<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit44">44</REF> indicate that this approximation may be a slight overestimate for <IT>d</IT><SB>He(ICl)</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Examining a slice through the T-shaped orientation reveals a hard-sphere radius of 3.34 Å.</annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, considering that collisions will occur at multiple orientations, including the linear orientation, which has a longer hard-sphere radius than the T-shaped orientation,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF> we believe that <IT>d</IT><SB>He(ICl)</SB> = 3.7 Å is a reasonable estimate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Using this value, we calculate hard-sphere collision frequencies ranging from 2.2 × 10<SP>7</SP> collisions s<SP>−1</SP> at <IT>xd</IT><SP>−1</SP> = 5.8 down to 2.7 × 10<SP>6</SP> collisions s<SP>−1</SP> at <IT>xd</IT><SP>−1</SP> = 14.0.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Previous studies have shown, however, that for the low temperatures prevalent in a free-jet expansion a hard-sphere model is not appropriate.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit39 cit45 cit46 cit47">8,39,45–47</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Because of the low temperatures, a potential incorporating an attractive term gives much more reasonable estimates of collision frequencies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">One such model that has worked well is the Lennard-Jones 6–12 potential.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit39 cit45 cit46 cit47">8,39,45–47</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">The Lennard-Jones 6–12 model is especially convenient because the collision frequency, <IT>Z</IT><SB>LJ</SB>, can be related to the hard sphere collision frequency, <IT>Z</IT><SB>HS</SB>, using published <IT><IT><IT>Ω</IT></IT></IT><SP>(2,2)*</SP> collision integrals: <IT>Z</IT><SB>LJ</SB> = <IT><IT><IT>Ω</IT></IT></IT><SP>(2,2)*</SP><IT>Z</IT><SB>HS</SB>The collision integrals have been tabulated as a function of the reduced temperature, <IT>T</IT>*, where<IT>T</IT>* = <IT>kT</IT>/<IT>ε</IT>and <IT>ε</IT> corresponds to the well depth of the potential.</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The values of the collision integrals in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit48">ref. 48</REF> only extend to <IT>T</IT>* = 0.3; however, lower values of <IT>T</IT>* have been reported by Knight and co-workers.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit39">39</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa7" novelty="None" advantage="None">We use here a fit of Knight’s reported values to determine the <IT>Ω</IT><SP>(2,2)*</SP> values that correspond to our experimentally determined values for <IT>T</IT><SB>tot</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">We take the Lennard-Jones well depth, <IT>ε</IT>, to be equal to that of the calculated He + ICl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 3) PES, 32 cm<SP>−1</SP> in the T-shaped orientation;<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF> the potential will be more shallow at other collision geometries.</annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The estimated values of <IT>Z</IT><SB>LJ</SB> decrease almost an order of magnitude from <IT>ca</IT>. 9.7 × 10<SP>7</SP> collisions s<SP>−1</SP> down to <IT>ca</IT>. 1.5 × 10<SP>7</SP> collisions s<SP>−1</SP> with increasing distances in the range investigated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The assumption that <IT>T</IT><SB>tot</SB> = <IT>T</IT><SB>AB</SB> will be qualitatively justified in the following section.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="c.">Collisional relaxation of ICl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 3) to ICl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 2)</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="1.">Propensities for ICl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 3)–He collisions</HEADER><P><s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Using the aforementioned equations for density and collision frequency, eqns (1), (3), and (4), as well as the characterization of the temperature of the expansion, we can model the downstream-distance and backing-pressure dependences of the intensities of the I<SP>35</SP>Cl <IT>B</IT>–<IT>X</IT>, 2–0 and 3–0 features in an attempt to gain insight into the collision dynamics that give rise to the observed signals.</annotationART></s> <s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="New" advantage="None">The LIF spectra recorded in the ICl <IT>B</IT>–<IT>X</IT>, 2–0 and 3–0 regions at several distances downstream are used to characterize the dependence of the I<SP>35</SP>Cl <IT>B</IT>–<IT>X</IT>, 3–0 band intensity on carrier gas density and I<SP>35</SP>Cl–He collision frequency.</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The integrated intensities of the I<SP>35</SP>Cl <IT>B</IT>–<IT>X</IT>, 2–0 and 3–0 bands recorded using a backing pressure of 14.8 bar and at four different distances downstream are shown in Fig. 3 as black squares and circles, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The error bars were estimated using the signal-to-noise levels of the LIF features.</annotationART></s> <s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="New" advantage="None">Weighted fits of the data to power dependencies were made to provide a guide for the experimental trends of the intensities, shown as solid lines.</annotationART></s> <s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="New" advantage="None">The data points and the fits were normalized by dividing each data point by the value of the fit at <IT>xd</IT><SP>−1</SP> = 5.8.</annotationART></s> <s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The intensities of the I<SP>35</SP>Cl <IT>B</IT>–<IT>X</IT>, 2–0 and 3–0 bands decay monotonically with increasing distance with the 3–0 band decaying more rapidly than the 2–0 band.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">The intensities of the I<SP>35</SP>Cl <IT>B</IT>–<IT>X</IT>, 2–0 band are found to be proportional to the density of the ground-state I<SP>35</SP>Cl(<IT>X</IT>,<IT>v</IT>″ = 0) molecules at each distance, <IT>ρ</IT><SB>I35Cl</SB>, calculated as described in Section III. b.</annotationART></s> <s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">2, and, as a result, we use the intensity of the I<SP>35</SP>Cl <IT>B</IT>–<IT>X</IT>, 2–0 band to monitor changes in the I<SP>35</SP>Cl(<IT>X</IT>,<IT>v</IT>″ = 0) ground-state density.</annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that some collisional relaxation of ICl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 2) to ICl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 1) does occur, but this represents only <IT>ca</IT>. 1% of the ICl molecules excited.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Any ICl signals that arise from collisions of the ICl molecules with He atoms should be proportional to the product of the I<SP>35</SP>Cl–He collision frequency and the I<SP>35</SP>Cl density, <IT>Z</IT><SB>LJ</SB>*<IT>ρ</IT><SB>I35Cl</SB>, at each downstream distance.</annotationART></s> <s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">These products are fit to a power dependence, lower dashed curve in Fig. 3, and normalized using the value of the fit at the shortest <IT>xd</IT><SP>−1</SP>, open circles.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Strong agreement between the integrated intensity of the I<SP>35</SP>Cl <IT>B</IT>–<IT>X</IT>, 3–0 band, filled circles, and <IT>Z</IT><SB>LJ</SB>*<IT>ρ</IT><SB>I35Cl</SB>, open circles, is observed in Fig. 3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The agreement of <IT>Z</IT><SB>HS</SB>*<IT>ρ</IT><SB>I35Cl</SB> with the I<SP>35</SP>Cl <IT>B</IT>–<IT>X</IT>, 3–0 band is reasonable but not quite as good as the agreement with <IT>Z</IT><SB>LJ</SB>*<IT>ρ</IT><SB>I35Cl</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">This indicates that the Lennard-Jones potential is a slightly better model for calculating collision frequencies than the simplistic hard-sphere potential.</annotationART></s> <s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, the effectiveness of both of these potentials in modeling collision frequencies eliminates the necessity of invoking a resonance enhancement to the collision cross section.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">The data in Fig. 3 also indicates that following the preparation of the short-lived rotational states within the I<SP>35</SP>Cl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 3) level, some of these excited-state molecules undergo collisions with He atoms in the expansion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">The collisions vibrationally relax a fraction, <IT>f</IT><SB>3–2</SB>, of the predissociative I<SP>35</SP>Cl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 3) states down to the long-lived I<SP>35</SP>Cl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 2) rotor states, which in turn fluoresce.</annotationART></s> <s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="New" advantage="None">Recall that since we have monitored the intensity of the fluorescence signal using a boxcar integration gate positioned 150 ns after the excitation laser pulse, we detect fluorescence from only those excited-state molecules that undergo collisions and not from a vast majority of the prepared molecules that non-adiabatically dissociate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="New" advantage="None">It is also important to emphasize that the rotational structure indicates that bare I<SP>35</SP>Cl molecules are being promoted to rotational states within the I<SP>35</SP>Cl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 3) level, not He⋯I<SP>35</SP>Cl complexes that would form I<SP>35</SP>Cl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 2) products <IT>via</IT> vibrational predissociation of metastable He⋯I<SP>35</SP>Cl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 3) intermolecular vibrational levels.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="143"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rates and cross sections for the collision-induced, vibrational energy relaxation of I<SP>35</SP>Cl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 3) rotor states down to I<SP>35</SP>Cl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 2) states, <IT>k</IT><SB>3–2</SB> and <IT>σ</IT><SB>3–2</SB>, can be estimated using the <IT>f</IT><SB>3–2</SB> values measured at varying downstream distances.</annotationART></s> <s sid="144"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fraction of the predissociative I<SP>35</SP>Cl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 3) excited-state molecules that re-stabilize in rotational states of the I<SP>35</SP>Cl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 2) level, <IT>f</IT><SB>3–2</SB>, is estimated using the LIF spectra, Fig. 1, and published Franck–Condon factors; the I<SP>35</SP>Cl <IT>B</IT>–<IT>X</IT>, 3–0 Franck–Condon factors are three times greater than those of the 2–0 band.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit49">49</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="145"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">The integrated intensity of the 2–0 band is 30.4 on this intensity scale, and we would expect the 3–0 band to have an integrated intensity of 91.2 on the same scale if the <IT>v</IT>′ = 3 rotational states were not predissociative.</annotationART></s> <s sid="146"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the fluorescence following excitation of the 3–0 band is from the I<SP>35</SP>Cl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 2) level, we can directly compare the value of 91.2 to the integrated intensity of the 3–0 band, 0.12, and we find that <IT>f</IT><SB>3–2</SB> ≈ 1.3 × 10<SP>−3</SP> at <IT>xd</IT><SP>−1</SP> = 11.2 and with a He-backing pressure of 14.8 bar.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="147"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rates, <IT>k</IT><SB>3–2</SB>, can be approximated using the <IT>f</IT><SB>3–2</SB> values at each distance and the I<SP>35</SP>Cl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 3) excited-state lifetime.</annotationART></s> <s sid="148"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">We assume that the contribution of the spontaneous emission of ICl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 3) is negligible.</annotationART></s> <s sid="149"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="New" advantage="None">In order to calculate <IT>k</IT><SB>3–2</SB>, we use <IT>f</IT><SB>3–2</SB> to determine the relative yields of the I<SP>35</SP>Cl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 2) and I <SP>2</SP>P<SB>3/2</SB> + Cl <SP>2</SP>P<SB>3/2</SB> products that result from collisional relaxation and non-adiabatic dissociation, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="150"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">We then assume a lifetime of 0.5 ns for non-adiabatic dissociation onto the ICl(<IT>Z</IT> 1) state, <IT>τ</IT><SB>NA</SB>, corresponding to the lifetimes of I<SP>35</SP>Cl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 3) states with little rotational excitation.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26 cit27">26,27</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="151"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None">The values of <IT>f</IT><SB>3–2</SB> and <IT>τ</IT><SB>NA</SB> are then used to determine <IT>k</IT><SB>3–2</SB>:<IT>k</IT><SB>3–2</SB> = <IT>f</IT><SB>3–2</SB>/((1 − <IT>f</IT><SB>3–2</SB>)<IT>τ</IT><SB>NA</SB>)The estimates of <IT>k</IT><SB>3–2</SB> at each <IT>xd</IT><SP>−1</SP> drop an order of magnitude, from <IT>ca</IT>. 10<SP>7</SP> s<SP>−1</SP> down to <IT>ca</IT>. 10<SP>6</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>, with increasing downstream distance over the range investigated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="152"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The cross sections for vibrational relaxation induced by collisions with He atoms along the expansion, <IT>σ</IT><SB>3–2</SB>, are then found using<IT>σ</IT><SB>3–2</SB> = <IT>k</IT><SB>3–2</SB>(<IT>μ</IT><SB>AB</SB>π/8<IT>kT</IT><SB>AB</SB>)<SP>1/2</SP>/<IT>ρ</IT><SB>B</SB>,<SP>43</SP>where <IT>T</IT><SB>AB</SB> is represented by either <IT>T</IT><SB>rot</SB> or <IT>T</IT><SB>tot</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="153"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The values of <IT>σ</IT><SB>3–2</SB> are in the range of 20–50 Å<SP>2</SP> under these conditions and are comparable to the hard-sphere scattering cross section of 43 Å<SP>2</SP> obtained using <IT>d</IT><SB>He(ICl)</SB> = 3.7 Å.</annotationART></s> <s sid="154"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None">The values of <IT>σ</IT><SB>3–2</SB> as well as <IT>f</IT><SB>3–2</SB>, and <IT>k</IT><SB>3–2</SB> at each <IT>xd</IT><SP>−1</SP> are listed in Table 1.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="155"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">While several approximations and assumptions were made in extracting these cross sections, the large values are suggestive of the significant probability for vibrational relaxation of ICl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 3) rotor states induced by collisions with He atoms in the supersonic expansion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="156"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our estimates of the vibrational relaxation cross sections of ICl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 3), 20–50 Å<SP>2</SP>, are in accord with the reported cross sections for vibrational relaxation of I<SB>2</SB>(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′) molecules in a He expansion, which are found to be in the range of 15 to 700 Å<SP>2</SP> with a dependence on the initially prepared vibrational level, <IT>v</IT>′.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6">5,6</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="157"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The collision-induced vibrational relaxation of ICl* molecules should be proportional to the product of the He-atom carrier gas density and the ICl*–He collision frequency, as mentioned above.</annotationART></s> <s sid="158"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">We have also monitored the dependence of the intensities of the I<SP>35</SP>Cl <IT>B</IT>–<IT>X</IT>, 2–0 and 3–0 LIF bands as a function of He-backing pressure; LIF spectra in each vibronic region were recorded at <IT>xd</IT><SP>−1</SP> = 10.7 nozzle diameters using various He-backing pressures between 11.4 and 28.6 bar.</annotationART></s> <s sid="159"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res29" novelty="None" advantage="None">The values of <IT>T</IT><SB>rot</SB> were found to change only slightly with increasing backing pressure throughout this pressure range, varying from 1.36(3) to 1.49(3) K. The I<SP>35</SP>Cl–He collision frequency, which should be approximately proportional to the I<SP>35</SP>Cl*–He collision frequency, was calculated using eqns (1), (3), and (4) and assuming <IT>T</IT><SB>AB</SB> is equal to either <IT>T</IT><SB>rot</SB> or <IT>T</IT><SB>tot</SB> at each pressure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="160"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res30" novelty="None" advantage="None">The collision frequency increased linearly with backing pressure, as expected.</annotationART></s> <s sid="161"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The intensity of the I<SP>35</SP>Cl <IT>B</IT>–<IT>X</IT>, 3–0 band also increases with He-backing pressure and tracks roughly with the collision frequency of ICl molecules with He atoms in the expansion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="162"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None">This similar dependence on the backing pressures supports the conclusion that the I<SP>35</SP>Cl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 2) molecules that are detected following preparation of I<SP>35</SP>Cl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 3) rotor states are a consequence of collision-induced vibrational relaxation.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.">ICl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′) product-state distributions</HEADER><P><s sid="163"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Having observed that the I<SP>35</SP>Cl <IT>B</IT>–<IT>X</IT>, 3–0 band is detected as a result of collision-induced vibrational relaxation with He atoms in the expansion, we sought to characterize the full-collision dynamical process by examining the I<SP>35</SP>Cl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 2,<IT>j</IT>′) rotational product-state distribution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="164"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa9" novelty="None" advantage="None">This distribution could then be compared to the recently published He⋯ICl half-collision data<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF> in an effort to understand the relationships, if any, between the two processes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="165"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="New" advantage="None">In order to do this, high-resolution pump–probe spectra were recorded by probing the Δ<IT>v</IT> = −1 channel that results from collisions between molecules initially prepared in the long-lived I<SP>35</SP>Cl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 2) and short-lived I<SP>35</SP>Cl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 3) levels and He atoms in the expansion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="166"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The spectra were taken using a He-backing pressure of 14.8 bar, and at a downstream distance of <IT>xd</IT><SP>−1</SP> = 11.2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="167"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Under these conditions an I<SP>35</SP>Cl(<IT>X</IT>,<IT>v</IT>″ = 0) rotational temperature of <IT>ca</IT>. 1.5 K was measured.</annotationART></s> <s sid="168"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rotationally resolved spectrum of the I<SP>35</SP>Cl <IT>E</IT>–<IT>B</IT>, 10–2 band recorded with the pump laser fixed on the I<SP>35</SP>Cl <IT>B</IT>–<IT>X</IT>, 3–0 bandhead, which corresponds to excitation of the <IT>j</IT>′ = 1–3 rotor levels, is shown in Fig. 4a.</annotationART></s> <s sid="169"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The spectrum of the I<SP>35</SP>Cl <IT>E</IT>–<IT>B</IT>, 9–1 band recorded with the pump laser fixed on the I<SP>35</SP>Cl <IT>B</IT>–<IT>X</IT>, 2–0 bandhead, which also corresponds to excitation of the <IT>j</IT>′ = 1–3 rotor levels, is plotted in Fig. 4b for comparison.</annotationART></s> <s sid="170"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rotational quantum number of the I<SP>35</SP>Cl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′) state associated with several of the <IT>P</IT>-lines are shown to emphasize the degree of rotational excitation in the product channels.</annotationART></s> <s sid="171"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that the <IT>P</IT>-rotor lines are overlapped by weaker <IT>R</IT>-lines originating from states with higher rotational excitation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="172"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The highest observed rotor lines are the <IT>P</IT>(21) and the <IT>P</IT>(23) lines in the 10–2 and 9–1 spectra, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="173"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None">We believe that these spectra are of the nascent product-state distributions since pump–probe spectra were recorded at two extreme distances downstream, 5 mm and 20 mm, and therefore in regions with different collision frequencies, and no significant changes in the rotational distributions were observed.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="174"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="New" advantage="None">The rotational-state distributions of the Δ<IT>v</IT> = −1 vibrational relaxation channels were determined using a linear least-squares fitting algorithm, known spectroscopic constants,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22 cit50">22,50</REF> and the appropriate rotational linestrength factors<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit51">51</REF> to fit the rotational contours.</annotationART></s> <s sid="175"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The distributions obtained from the I<SP>35</SP>Cl <IT>E</IT>–<IT>B</IT>, 10–2 and 9–1 bands, Fig. 4a and b, are plotted as a function of I<SP>35</SP>Cl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′) internal rotational energy in Fig. 5a as black circles and open squares, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="176"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rotational-state distributions are bimodal with an overall maximum at <IT>j</IT>′ = 6 and another maximum at <IT>j</IT>′ = 12 in both of the Δ<IT>v</IT> = −1 channels.</annotationART></s> <s sid="177"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Minima were observed at <IT>j</IT>′ = 8 and 10 for the I<SP>35</SP>Cl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 2) and I<SP>35</SP>Cl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 1) products, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="178"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" advantage="None">The mean rotational energy found in each of these product levels is 9.5 and 10.9 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="179"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the energy difference between the I<SP>35</SP>Cl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 3,<IT>j</IT>′ = 0) and I<SP>35</SP>Cl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 2,<IT>j</IT>′ = 0) states and the I<SP>35</SP>Cl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 2,<IT>j</IT>′ = 0) and I<SP>35</SP>Cl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 1,<IT>j</IT>′ = 0) states is 163.4 and 182.7 cm<SP>−1</SP>, respectively,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF> we can estimate the fraction of the available energy that is found in rotational excitation of the products.</annotationART></s> <s sid="180"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The amount of energy found in the I<SP>35</SP>Cl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 2) and I<SP>35</SP>Cl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 1), Δ<IT>v</IT> = −1 vibrational relaxation channels represents <IT>ca</IT>. 6% of the total available energy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="181"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, most of the available energy is converted into kinetic energy of the ICl* and He collision partners.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.">Propensities for collisions of ICl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 3) with other gases</HEADER><P><s sid="182"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None">We have recorded LIF spectra of ICl entrained in a number of different carrier gases to qualitatively check for the effect of the collision partner on the vibrational relaxation of ICl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 3).</annotationART></s> <s sid="183"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Recall that the intensity of the I<SP>35</SP>Cl <IT>B</IT>–<IT>X</IT>, 3–0 band is <IT>ca</IT>. 10<SP>3</SP> times weaker than the 2–0 band when using a He-carrier gas with a backing pressure of 14.8 bar and at <IT>xd</IT><SP>−1</SP> = 10.7.</annotationART></s> <s sid="184"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast, the intensity of the 3–0 band is significantly smaller, <IT>ca</IT>. 10<SP>6</SP> times weaker, than the 2–0 when using a 90% Ne in He carrier gas at the same backing pressure and distance.</annotationART></s> <s sid="185"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None">When using a 100% Ar carrier gas, no ICl <IT>B</IT>–<IT>X</IT>, 3–0 LIF signals were observed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="186"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None">It should be noted, though, that the intensity of the I<SP>35</SP>Cl <IT>B</IT>–<IT>X</IT>, 2–0 LIF feature is weaker when using an Ar-carrier gas and, consequently, the signal-to-noise levels are worse than those of the ICl in He or Ne/He spectra.</annotationART></s> <s sid="187"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="New" advantage="None">Finally, LIF spectra were also recorded using a pure hydrogen expansion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="188"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The intensities of the ICl <IT>B</IT>–<IT>X</IT>, 3–0 features in these ICl/H<SB>2</SB> spectra are about twice those measured in the helium expansion.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="189"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The different efficiencies for vibrational relaxation with the He, Ne, Ar, and H<SB>2</SB> collision partners do not appear to be a result of the corresponding attractive intermolecular potential wells in the excited state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="190"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The intermolecular potential energy surfaces for He + ICl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 3), Ne + ICl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 3), and <IT>ortho</IT>-H<SB>2</SB> + ICl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 3) have all been shown to have minima in the T-shaped orientation with binding energies of 16.2(7),<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit52">52</REF> 65(5),<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit53">53</REF> and 69.5(3)–76.3(3) cm<SP>−1</SP>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit54">54</REF> respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="191"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res32" novelty="None" advantage="None">Of these three collision partners, Ne is observed to have the smallest probability for inducing vibrational relaxation even though the excited-state binding energy of I<SP>35</SP>Cl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 3) with Ne is significantly larger than that with He and comparable to that with H<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="192"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res33" novelty="None" advantage="None">The lighter H<SB>2</SB> partner, in contrast, is the most efficient vibrational relaxation partner.</annotationART></s> <s sid="193"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con15" novelty="None" advantage="None">This might lead one to believe that it is the mass mismatch, and thus the velocity slip, between the ICl molecule and the collision partner that gives rise to the different probabilities for collisional relaxation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="194"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con15" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, using the aforementioned binding energies of the He⋯ICl, Ne⋯ICl, and H<SB>2</SB>⋯ICl complexes to estimate their well depth, as well as our velocity-slip experiments to determine <IT>T</IT><SB>tot</SB>, we find that the velocity slip is not nearly large enough to account for the different values of <IT>Z</IT><SB>LJ</SB> that would be required to justify the observed vibrational-relaxation efficiencies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="195"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con15" novelty="None" advantage="None">For instance, in order to be in accord with our observed efficiencies, the <IT>Z</IT><SB>LJ</SB> for the Ne expansion would have to be three orders of magnitude less than <IT>Z</IT><SB>LJ</SB> for the He expansion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="196"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res34" novelty="None" advantage="None">Using our observed upper limit for the slip temperature for the He calculations and assuming no slip for the Ne calculations, the worst case scenario, we find that there is a factor of 2.5 more collisions in the Ne expansion than in the He expansion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="197"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con16" novelty="None" advantage="None">This indicates that some other phenomenon must be giving rise to the observed trends.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="198"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, we propose an alternative possibility.</annotationART></s> <s sid="199"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">In our group’s work on the Ne⋯ICl complex,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit53">53</REF> we noted that the signals observed in the ICl <IT>B</IT>–<IT>X</IT>, 2–0 region were larger than the signals observed in the 3–0 region.</annotationART></s> <s sid="200"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">This was attributed to the competition between electronic predissociation and vibrational predissociation that is present in the 3–0 region due to the presence of the nearby repulsive ICl(<IT>Z</IT> 1) electronic state.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26">26</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="201"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Because of the strong possibility that Ne⋯ICl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 3) van der Waals complexes undergo electronic predissociation, we find it plausible that collisions between Ne atoms and ICl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 3) excited-state molecules can induce non-adiabatic dissociation of ICl <IT>via</IT> the repulsive <IT>Z</IT>1 state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="202"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con17" novelty="None" advantage="None">This mechanism would compete with vibrational relaxation and thereby reduce the observed yields for the collisional-relaxation products.</annotationART></s> <s sid="203"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, because of the relatively large mass and polarizability of Ne compared to H<SB>2</SB> or He, collision-induced non-adiabatic dissociation should be much more prevalent with a Ne carrier gas than with H<SB>2</SB> or He.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="d.">Comparison of full-collision and half-collision dynamics</HEADER><P><s sid="204"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj5" novelty="New" advantage="None">It is interesting to compare the results of the full-collision dynamics with those of the recently reported half-collision, vibrational predissociation dynamics of He⋯I<SP>35</SP>Cl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 3) van der Waals complexes prepared with varying amounts of intermolecular vibrational excitation.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="205"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Collision-induced vibrational relaxation results in a bimodal I<SP>35</SP>Cl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ − 1) rotational state distribution with maxima at <IT>j</IT>′ = 6 and 12 and a minimum at <IT>j</IT>′ = 8 or 10, Fig. 5a.</annotationART></s> <s sid="206"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs20" novelty="None" advantage="None">Bimodal distributions are also evident in the vibrational predissociation measurements of He⋯ICl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 3) when preparing the complex in the lowest, <IT>n</IT>′ = 0, and second excited, <IT>n</IT>′ = 2, intermolecular vibrational levels.</annotationART></s> <s sid="207"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs21" novelty="None" advantage="None">When more highly excited intermolecular vibrational levels are prepared, however, the bimodal structure blurs out.</annotationART></s> <s sid="208"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ICl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 2) rotational product-state distributions that result from vibrational predissociation for these two extreme cases was reported previously, Fig. 5 of <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">ref. 20</REF>, and is plotted here in Fig. 5b.</annotationART></s> <s sid="209"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ICl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 2) rotational populations that result following the preparation of complexes in the metastable He⋯ICl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 3,<IT>n</IT>′ = 0,<IT>J</IT>′ = 0) and He⋯ICl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 3, <IT>n</IT>′ = 4, <IT>J</IT>′ = 1) states are shown as black diamonds and open triangles, respectively.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="210"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs22" novelty="None" advantage="None">While both of these vibrational predissociation product-state distributions bear some resemblance to those of the collision-induced product-state distribution, Fig. 5a, the distribution formed from the vibrational predissociation of the <IT>n</IT>′ = 0, <IT>J</IT>′ = 0 level is quantitatively more similar.</annotationART></s> <s sid="211"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs22" novelty="None" advantage="None">Qualitatively, the bimodal structure for this channel is reproduced almost identically, with maxima at <IT>j</IT>′ = 5 and 13 and a minimum at <IT>j</IT>′ = 10.</annotationART></s> <s sid="212"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs23" novelty="None" advantage="None">The main difference is that in the collisional-relaxation data the two maxima have comparable populations, while vibrational predissociation from the <IT>n</IT>′ = 0, <IT>J</IT>′ = 0 level has the first maxima with significantly more population.</annotationART></s> <s sid="213"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs24" novelty="None" advantage="None">Vibrational predissociation from the <IT>n</IT>′ = 4,<IT>J</IT>′ = 1 level is better in this respect, but lacks a definitive bimodal distribution as well as non-negligible population at <IT>E</IT><SB>rot</SB> &gt; 20 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="214"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res35" novelty="None" advantage="None">Quantitatively, a comparison of the residuals between the collisional-relaxation product-state distribution and the half-collision <IT>n</IT>′ = 0, <IT>J</IT>′ = 0 distribution is <IT>ca</IT>. 35% less than for the comparison with the <IT>n</IT>′ = 4, <IT>J</IT>′ = 1 distribution.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="215"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res36" novelty="None" advantage="None">Somewhat surprisingly, then, collision-induced vibrational relaxation mimics vibrational predissociation from lower intermolecular vibrational levels that tend to more localized in the T-shaped region, <IT>n</IT>′ = 0 or 2, more closely than vibrational predissociation from more highly excited intermolecular vibrational levels with states that are delocalized in the angular coordinate, such as the <IT>n</IT>′ = 4 level.</annotationART></s> <s sid="216"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con18" novelty="None" advantage="None">A possible explanation for this behavior may be that in colliding with the ICl molecule at the low temperatures achieved in the expansion, the He atom is steered by the He + ICl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 3) potential where it tends to find the region of the minimum of the multi-dimensional PES, which is also where the lowest bound intermolecular vibrational level is localized.</annotationART></s> <s sid="217"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hence, similar rotational product-state distributions are observed.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="IV.">Conclusions</HEADER><P><s sid="218"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj6" novelty="New" advantage="None">Pathways that compete with the non-adiabatic dissociation of electronically excited ICl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 3) in a He-carrier gas expansion are investigated using LIF and two-laser, pump–probe spectroscopy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="219"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res37" novelty="None" advantage="None">We find that collisions between ICl molecules and He atoms occur over extended distances along the expansion direction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="220"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res38" novelty="None" advantage="None">The collision frequency between molecules prepared in the short-lived I<SP>35</SP>Cl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 3) level and the He atoms is high enough that vibrational relaxation down to rotational states in the next lower I<SP>35</SP>Cl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 2) level can occur with measurable yields.</annotationART></s> <s sid="221"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con19" novelty="None" advantage="None">At the same time, the vibrational relaxation can be modeled using a Lennard-Jones 6–12 collision-frequency model, arguing that there is no need to invoke a resonance-enhancement to the collisional cross section.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="222"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con20" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rotational-state distributions of the low-energy, collision-induced vibrational relaxation and of the vibrational predissociation from low-lying He⋯ICl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′) intermolecular vibrational levels are seen to match quite well as opposed to the agreement with the distributions from the vibrational predissociation of levels that have more intermolecular vibrational excitation and are delocalized in the angular coordinate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="223"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con21" novelty="None" advantage="None">This suggests that at low temperatures, the He atoms are steered toward the minimum of the He + ICl(<IT>B</IT>,<IT>v</IT>′ = 3) intermolecular potential before scattering off the repulsive wall.</annotationART></s> <s sid="224"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con22" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ability to accurately measure the ICl vibrational and rotational product-state distributions suggests that this system would be well-suited for complimentary theoretical investigations of intermolecular energy transfer.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
