<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b510884e" hasDoc="yes" version="1184" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Regular Liesegang patterns and precipitation waves in an open system</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">We investigate the regular and moving Liesegang pattern formation phenomena in an open system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">First, simulations have been performed at fixed coupling between the reactive medium and the reservoir, later this control parameter was varied during the simulations resulting in various phenomena.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">We predicted and monitored for the first time various—dynamically changing—precipitation structures and a spatial hysteresis phenomenon, which is beyond the scope of the Turing instability.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The dynamics of the reaction is well detectable using specific quantities: the total amount of precipitate and its center of gravity.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="1.">Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Detailed investigations of homogeneous chemical systems showed that phenomena like bistability, complex and chaotic oscillations may exist only in open chemical systems, far from thermodynamic equilibrium.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2 cit3">1,2,3</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The appropriate experiments are carried out using a <IT>continuously stirred tank reactor</IT> (CSTR).</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In 1952, Turing predicted that the diffusion of species may destabilize a homogeneous chemical system producing stationary patterns in a spontaneous way.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit5">4,5</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The pioneering work of De Kepper and his coworkers provided for the first time an experimental evidence for the formation of Turing patterns.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Up to the last decade, a wide range of spatial or spatiotemporal reaction–diffusion patterns (such as complex Turing patterns, phase waves, autocatalytic chemical fronts, <IT>etc</IT>). have been designed and investigated also in open systems. <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7 cit8">7,8</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Formation of the precipitation patterns in the wake of diffusion driven chemical fronts has been extensively studied from the end of the 1800’s.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9 cit10">9,10</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is the first chemically designed and controlled spatiotemporal pattern formation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although the generation of such patterns (called Liesegang patterns) is quite easy, the research on this topic still has a great relevance.</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In the typical experimental setup, one chemical reagent is uniformly distributed in a gelled medium (called inner electrolyte, <IT>B</IT>), while the other one (called outer electrolyte, <IT>A</IT>) diffuses from outside.</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The initial concentration of <IT>A</IT> is chosen to be much larger than that of <IT>B</IT>. This condition ensures the higher diffusion flux of the outer electrolyte into the gel.</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The coupling of the diffusion and the precipitation reaction between the two chemical components produces a non-soluble precipitate (<IT>AB</IT>) in the reaction front.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The distribution of the precipitate is usually non-uniform behind this front.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Appearing precipitation zones (Liesegang bands or rings, depending on the geometry of the experimental setup)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11 cit12 cit13 cit14 cit15 cit16 cit17 cit18 cit19">11–19</REF> have several empirical regularities (time, <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20 cit21">20,21</REF> spacing,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF> and width law<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23 cit24 cit25">23–25</REF>), in which some well-measurable quantities are connected with each other.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">These are <IT>X</IT><SB><IT>n</IT></SB>, the position of the <IT>n</IT>th band, measured from the junction point of the electrolytes, <IT>t</IT><SB><IT>n</IT></SB> the appearance time, and <IT>w</IT><SB><IT>n</IT></SB>, the width of the <IT>n</IT>th band, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Matalon–Packter law describes the dependence of the spacing coefficient (<IT>P</IT> = <IT>X</IT><SB><IT>n</IT>+1</SB>/<IT>X</IT><SB><IT>n</IT></SB>) on the initial concentration of the inner and outer electrolytes.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26 cit27 cit28">26–28</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Recently, a new and more general law has been proposed, which also includes advective dynamics in the reactive medium.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29">29</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">For this, two new quantities are introduced: <IT>p</IT><SB>tot</SB>, the total amount of precipitate and <IT>X</IT><SB><IT>c</IT></SB>, the position of the center of gravity of precipitation system measured from the junction point of the electrolytes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Besides the theoretical derivation, experimental and numerical evidences confirmed the new law, which states that <IT>p</IT><SB>tot</SB> is linearly proportional to <IT>X</IT><SB><IT>c</IT></SB>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29">29</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">From the beginning of the last decade, more and more complex precipitation pattern formation scenarios have been studied and discussed.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30 cit31 cit34 cit35 cit36">30,31,34–36</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Several authors reported that the precipitation process followed by complex formation of precipitate may produce moving Liesegang patterns (“moving” bands)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit34 cit35 cit36">34–36</REF> or moving precipitation pulse (precipitation waves).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12 cit30 cit31 cit32 cit33">12,30–33</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In several papers, deterministic chaotic time oscillation of the total number of bands,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit35 cit37">35,37</REF> effect of an electric field on pattern structure,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12 cit38">12,38</REF> and crossover from the precipitation waves to moving Liesegang patterns<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit39">39</REF> have been investigated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">These are the recent trends in the study of the precipitation pattern formation phenomena.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Das <IT>et al</IT>. presented the Liesegang pattern formation in 2D using a gel-ring reactor, in which the two electrolyte solutions were fed from reservoirs<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF>: The outer electrolyte was fed continuously from the center, while the inner one from a gel ring outside the reaction medium.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Several years ago Bhattacharya <IT>et al</IT>. proposed a model, which included a single autocatalytic reaction step followed by nucleation and growth.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit40">40</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Based on the fact that a cubic autocatalytic step coupling with CSTR may give rise to Turing patterns,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit41">41</REF> they demonstrated formation of spatially periodic precipitation patterns.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit40">40</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">In classical experimental setup, the diffusion front of the outer (invading) electrolyte depletes the inner electrolyte from the reactive medium due to the precipitation reaction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The aim of this paper is to provide for the first time a systematic investigation of the regular and moving Liesegang pattern formation in an <IT>open system</IT>, where a continuous feeding of the inner electrolyte is allowed.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.">Model</HEADER><P><s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">To illustrate our idea, we have chosen the simplest precipitation mechanism (1 : 1 type, <IT>AB</IT>), giving rise to precipitation patterns, according to the reaction<IT>A</IT>(aq) + <IT>B</IT>(aq) → <IT>AB</IT>(s),where <IT>A</IT> and <IT>B</IT> yield the outer and inner electrolytes, respectively, while <IT>AB</IT> is the precipitation product.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, the precipitate reacts with the excess of the outer electrolyte, producing a soluble complex<IT>AB</IT>(s) + <IT>A</IT>(aq) → <IT>A</IT><SB>2</SB><IT>B</IT>(aq).For simplicity, we supposed that the formed complex <IT>A</IT><SB>2</SB><IT>B</IT> is stable, so the reverse step was neglected.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Due to the irreversible step the stable complex does not affect dynamically the pattern formation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, it was supposed that neither the complex nor the precipitate diffuses.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">A sketch of our system appears in Fig. 1 where for a clear visual interpretation we provide a 2-D description.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In fact, the thickness of the reactive medium is negligible and therefore, the reaction is described using only horizontal coordinates.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The dimensionless governing equations for the reactive medium, coupled with a well-mixed reservoir for the inner electrolyte (open system) in 1-D arewith <IT>τ</IT> and <IT>x</IT> being the time and length coordinates, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Here <IT>a</IT>, <IT>b</IT>, <IT>c</IT>, and <IT>p</IT> denote the concentrations (or even density for solid phase) of the outer and inner electrolyte, the complex, and the precipitate, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None"><IT>D</IT><SB><IT>a</IT></SB> and <IT>D</IT><SB><IT>b</IT></SB> are the diffusion coefficients of the corresponding species, while <IT>b</IT><SB>0</SB> is the concentration of the inner electrolyte in the reservoir (CSTR).</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None"><IT>k</IT> is the reaction rate constant for the complex formation (eqn (2)).</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None"><IT>κ</IT> is related to the coupling between the reactive medium and CSTR, which maintains a continuous mass flux of the inner electrolyte.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None"><IT>κ</IT> is the inverse of the residence time of species in the reactor, which can be accurately controlled by the flow rate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The function Δ(<IT>ab</IT>, <IT>K</IT>, <IT>L</IT>) (will be specified later on) describes the precipitate formation based on Ostwald’s supersaturation theory.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Despite its simplicity and generality this concept provides a perspicuous mechanism in many cases, where the precipitation process plays a partial role.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None">The efficiency of the above mentioned precipitation mechanism was tested by simulating the effect of an electric field,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit42 cit43">42,43</REF> stochastic precipitation pattern formation,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit44">44</REF> and also moving Liesegang bands and precipitation waves.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit37">37</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The term <IT>kpa</IT> in eqns (3), (5) and (6) represents the complex formation rate, whereas <IT>κ</IT>(<IT>b</IT><SB>0</SB> − <IT>b</IT>) in eqn (4) describes the coupling between the reactive medium and the reservoir.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">However, it should be noted that the immobilization of the complex is not a necessary condition for the moving pattern formation.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">To describe the precipitation formation presented by the simple mechanism (1) we choose the model proposed by Büki <IT>et al</IT>.,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit45 cit46">45,46</REF> which is based on the Ostwald’s ion-product supersaturation theory.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit47">47</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The precipitation reaction term Δ(<IT>ab</IT>,<IT>K</IT>,<IT>L</IT>) is defined as follows: where <IT>k</IT><SB>0</SB> is the rate constant of the precipitation reaction (1), <IT>K</IT> is the nucleation product, <IT>L</IT> is the solubility product, and <IT>Θ</IT> is the Heaviside step function.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The coefficient <IT>S</IT><SB><IT>p</IT></SB> is related to the extent of the supersaturation of the system and influences the intensity of the reaction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Formally, <IT>S</IT><SB><IT>p</IT></SB> is calculated using the equation (<IT>a</IT> − <IT>S</IT><SB><IT>p</IT></SB>) (<IT>b</IT> − <IT>S</IT><SB><IT>p</IT></SB>) = <IT>L</IT>. As far as <IT>ab</IT> ≤ <IT>L</IT> we do not need to define it, since the precipitation reaction term in (7) is zero, anyway.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit45 cit46">45,46</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The precipitation reaction continues at a certain point <IT>x</IT> until the concentration <IT>p</IT> in <IT>x</IT> has reached a threshold <IT>p</IT><SB>max</SB>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Numerical simulations were performed using a “method of lines” technique.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Discretization of eqns (3)–(6) was carried out on a 1-D equidistant grid applying a second-order finite difference scheme.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this procedure, at any fixed time the functions <IT>a</IT>,<IT>b</IT>,<IT>c</IT> and <IT>p</IT> in (3)–(6) are substituted with vectors [<IT>a</IT>(<IT>τ</IT>, <IT>x</IT><SB>1</SB>), <IT>a</IT>(<IT>τ</IT>, <IT>x</IT><SB>2</SB>),…,<IT>a</IT>(<IT>τ</IT>, <IT>x</IT><SB><IT>n</IT></SB>)] and similarly for <IT>b</IT>, <IT>c</IT> and <IT>p</IT>, respectively, where <IT>x</IT><SB>1,</SB><IT>x</IT><SB>2,…,</SB><IT>x</IT><SB><IT>n</IT></SB> are the grid points.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The spatial differential operator turns to be a matrix of dimension <IT>n</IT> × <IT>n</IT> and with this, (3)–(6) can be approximated by a system of ordinary differential equations (of size <IT>n</IT>) with respect to time.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">This has been solved using a second-order Runge–Kutta method with the following initial conditions:<IT>a</IT>(0,<IT>x</IT>) = <IT>a</IT><SB>0</SB><IT>Θ</IT>(−<IT>x</IT>), <IT>b</IT>(0,<IT>x</IT>) = <IT>b</IT><SB>0</SB><IT>Θ</IT>(<IT>x</IT>), <IT>p</IT>(0,<IT>x</IT>) = <IT>c</IT>(0,<IT>x</IT>) =0.The boundary condition is no flux type both for the inner and the outer electrolyte at the end of the reactive medium.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is Dirichlet type <IT>a</IT>(<IT>t</IT>,0) = <IT>a</IT><SB>0</SB> for the outer electrolyte at the junction point of the electrolytes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although both <IT>κ</IT> and <IT>b</IT><SB>0</SB> could be used as control parameters of the system, <IT>b</IT><SB>0</SB> was fixed in the simulations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">This concentration has been chosen to coincide that of the initial concentration of <IT>B</IT> in the reactive medium.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The presented model allows to describe the crossover from Liesegang patterns to precipitation waves using only one parameter: in case of <IT>k</IT> = 0 regular Liesegang pattern formation, and for <IT>k</IT> ≠ 0 moving patterns are expected.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In all simulations, we used the parameter set <IT>D</IT><SB><IT>a</IT></SB> = <IT>D</IT><SB><IT>b</IT></SB> = 1.0, <IT>K</IT> = 0.15, <IT>L</IT> =0.1, <IT>k</IT><SB>0</SB> = 1.0, and <IT>p</IT><SB>max</SB> = 50.0.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The grid spacing was Δ<IT>x</IT> = 1.0, and the numerical simulations were performed with the time step Δ<IT>τ</IT> = 0.01.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.">Results and discussion</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.1.">Regular and moving precipitation patterns at fixed coupling</HEADER><P><s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="New" advantage="None">First, the dependence of pattern structure on the coupling coefficient (<IT>κ</IT>) has been investigated in the case of regular Liesegang patterns (<IT>k</IT> = 0), and precipitation wave (<IT>k</IT> = 10<SP>−3</SP>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="New" advantage="None">Obviously, if <IT>κ</IT> = 0 (there is no coupling between the reactive medium and reservoir), then regular Liesegang pattern and precipitation wave evolve, and the final pattern will depend on the particular parameter set.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="New" advantage="None">If <IT>κ</IT> ≫ 0, a single precipitation zone develops, starting from the junction point of the electrolytes instead of the (regular or moving) Liesegang patterns, due to the high flux of the inner electrolyte from the reservoir.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="New" advantage="None">This extremely high coupling reduces and slightly modifies the purely diffusive profile of the invading (outer) electrolyte <IT>A</IT>. This intensive coupling ensures that the product of the local concentrations is kept above the nucleation product (<IT>K</IT>), therefore, the precipitate is formed continuously.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 2a,b shows the final pattern structure for fixed values of <IT>κ</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Results of the numerical experiments are in good agreement with the above explanation.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of the precipitation waves, increasing <IT>κ</IT> results in a thicker precipitation zone, the final position of which is getting more and more close to the junction point.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Increasing <IT>κ</IT> promotes the precipitation reaction, thus reduced concentration of the outer electrolyte puts back the complex formation.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast to the case of precipitation waves, we predict regular Liesegang patterns for small values of <IT>κ</IT>, and a single precipitation zone for relatively high values of the control parameter.</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The <IT>time law</IT> for the regular Liesegang patterns (even for 1-D or planar ones) states that the position of each band is linearly proportional to the square root of its formation time.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is a consequence of the diffusive dynamics of the invading electrolyte.</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">In several cases, modification of the dynamics (including the presence of external electric field, advection field, curvature effect) results in some deviations compared to the time law.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 3a presents the evolution of the pattern for various values of <IT>κ</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Relatively high coupling hampers the depletion of <IT>B</IT>, therefore, the more intensive precipitate formation reduces the concentration of <IT>A</IT> in the reactive medium, which leads to the slower evolution of the pattern.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Similarly, the center of gravity of the precipitation system (<IT>X</IT><SB>c</SB>) exhibits slower motion in time as depicted in Fig. 3b.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The total amount of the precipitate <IT>p</IT><SB>tot</SB> and the center of gravity of the precipitation system <IT>X</IT><SB>c</SB> are defined as follows:where <IT>L</IT> is the length of the 1-D reactive medium.</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">At the same time, the enhanced reaction rate increases the total amount of precipitate (<IT>p</IT><SB>tot</SB>), the evolution of which has been plotted in Fig. 3c.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that increasing the coupling coefficient affects more significantly <IT>p</IT><SB>tot</SB> than <IT>X</IT><SB>c</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this way increasing <IT>κ</IT>, dependence of <IT>p</IT><SB>tot</SB> on <IT>X</IT><SB>c</SB> exhibits an accelerating growing rate (Fig. 3d).</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the regular 1-D case, in all of the subfigures of Fig. 3 one can observe a linear dependence.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Moreover, this linear dependence in Fig. 3d is also valid in the case of an additional advective flux in the system<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29">29</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.2.">Moving precipitation patterns using time dependent coupling</HEADER><P><s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="New" advantage="None">Up to this time, the control parameter (<IT>κ</IT>) was fixed at certain values during the numerical experiments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj5" novelty="New" advantage="None">Now we will focus on the behavior of the system with the coupling rate between the reactive medium and reservoir being varied on a continuous scale: various time dependences of <IT>κ</IT> have been applied.</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Accordingly, variation of the total amount of the precipitate (<IT>p</IT><SB>tot</SB>) and the center of gravity of the precipitation system (<IT>X</IT><SB>c</SB>) is depicted in Fig. 4 as a function of log <IT>κ</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The change of log <IT>κ</IT> was linear on [<IT>nT</IT>, (<IT>n</IT> + 1)<IT>T</IT>] with integer values of <IT>n</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">We give the exact time dependence of log <IT>κ</IT> as follows:which allows to illustrate clearly its effect on the distribution of the precipitate, where <IT>T</IT> is the time period of one cycle.</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="New" advantage="None">All simulations were started at <IT>κ</IT> = 10<SP>−9</SP>, which corresponds to a very weak coupling.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="New" advantage="None">Increasing <IT>κ</IT> results in an increased amount of the precipitate due to the enhanced mass-flux of the inner electrolyte from the reservoir into the reactive medium.</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The maximum of <IT>p</IT><SB>tot</SB> is attained at the maximal rate of the coupling (<IT>κ</IT> = 1 in the simulations).</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Similarly, <IT>p</IT><SB>tot</SB> is decreasing when the coupling coefficient <IT>κ</IT> is decreased (Fig. 4a).</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">One can observe a slightly different behavior of the center of gravity with varying <IT>κ</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The position <IT>X</IT><SB>c</SB> is an increasing function of <IT>κ</IT> up to a certain coupling coefficient, afterwards, <IT>X</IT><SB>c</SB> is decreasing (Fig. 4b).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Decreasing <IT>κ</IT> from the maximum to its minimum value, <IT>X</IT><SB>c</SB> monotonically increases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">At the first stage, when the coupling is weak, a precipitation wave travels in the reactive medium.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of higher coupling, the precipitate formation behind the pattern will dominate compared to the precipitate dissolution by complex formation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">At the same time, the precipitate formation is stopped in front of the pattern, because the coupling and precipitation reaction behind it reduces the concentration of the invading electrolyte.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, <IT>X</IT><SB>c</SB> is shifted backward, however, the total amount of precipitate increases continuously.</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The complex formation of the precipitate has a more significant role behind the pattern, when the coupling rate is decreased.</annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The same applies to <IT>p</IT><SB>tot</SB>, while <IT>X</IT><SB>c</SB> increases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">At weak coupling, the precipitation process continues in front of the precipitation wave and the wave evolves further.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The most interesting scenario observed during the simulations is the <IT>hysteresis</IT> of the pattern.</annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Accordingly, one can observe the hysteresis of the quantities <IT>p</IT><SB>tot</SB> and <IT>X</IT><SB>c</SB> related to the pattern.</annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The time oscillation of <IT>p</IT><SB>tot</SB> is a trivial consequence of the variation of <IT>κ</IT> in time, but the hysteresis is a unique feature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that similar hysteresis curves (with different maxima) belong to different time dependent functions of <IT>κ</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hysteresis occurs due to the interaction of the reaction rate (for the precipitation and complex formation), diffusion of the electrolytes, and the coupling rate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">When increasing <IT>κ</IT>, the dominant process is the precipitate formation behind the pattern due to the high coupling, which reduces the diffusion of the invading electrolyte.</annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">When decreasing <IT>κ</IT>, the precipitate formation process diminishes behind the pattern, and the evolution of the pattern will be driven by complex formation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">This process may be accompanied with the precipitate formation in front of the pattern, if the diffusion profiles of the outer electrolyte are regenerated.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="New" advantage="None">In the simulations, we varied <IT>κ</IT> periodically over some periods (Fig. 5).</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">We observed that the values of <IT>p</IT><SB>tot</SB> corresponding to the maximal and minimal values of <IT>κ</IT> have been increased, compared to those of the first period.</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">An interesting feature (using a given parameter set) of the observed system is that after the first loop, a periodic change of <IT>κ</IT> results in the periodic change of total amount of the precipitate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Analyzing the evolution of <IT>X</IT><SB>c</SB> while varying the time dependent <IT>κ</IT> in the same way, a similar behavior of the center of gravity has been found.</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 6 presents the evolution of the precipitation wave over four periods.</annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Position of the front and back section of the wave and the center of gravity exhibit a forced time oscillation according to the change of <IT>κ</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Time dependence of the back section of the wave has different dynamics whenever the variation of log <IT>κ</IT> (in time) was linear, while decreasing or increasing this control parameter.</annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that the thickness of the precipitation zone is related to the total amount of the precipitate, therefore both of them exhibit the same behavior.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.">Conclusion</HEADER><P><s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj6" novelty="New" advantage="None">In this study, we have investigated the regular and moving precipitation pattern formation in an open system using a CSTR for the coupling of the inner electrolyte between the reactive medium and reservoir.</annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj7" novelty="New" advantage="None">Evolution of patterns in both cases, and the distortion of the existing laws (time and “universal” laws) due to the coupling coefficient have been investigated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The coupling of the inner electrolyte between the CSTR and the reactive medium has a great impact on the pattern structure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Variation of the coupling coefficient (<IT>κ</IT>) during the individual simulations resulted in a unique behavior for the moving precipitation wave phenomenon: the pattern structure and the corresponding characterizing quantities, the total amount of the precipitate (<IT>p</IT><SB>tot</SB>) and the center of gravity (<IT>X</IT><SB>c</SB>) have hysteresis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">This new result is a unique observation on this research field.</annotationART></s> <s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Compared to the Turing patterns which are stationary ones, the above investigated moving precipitation wave phenomenon in an open system represents dynamic patterns.</annotationART></s> <s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The spatial hysteresis of the Turing patterns has been known for more than one decade.</annotationART></s> <s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The novel result of our study is that we observed the hysteresis phenomenon in a precipitation system, which qualitatively differs from activator–inhibitor or cubic autocatalytic systems, where Turing patterns have been reported.</annotationART></s> <s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The coming step in our study is to design the experimental setup to validate our new predictions.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
