<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b511334b" hasDoc="yes" version="1184" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Electrochemical multi-tagging of cysteinyl peptides during microspray mass spectrometry: numerical simulation of consecutive reactions in a microchannel<XREF TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" /></annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">On-line electrogeneration of mass tags in a microspray emitter is used to quantify the number of cysteine groups in a given peptide.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="New" advantage="None">A finite-element simulation of the multi-step process yields the relative distribution and concentration of tags, untagged and tagged species in the microchannel before the spray event.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The work focuses on the tagging of cysteine moieties in peptides or proteins by electrogenerated quinone mass probes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">The main chemical parameters determining the kinetics of the labelling are assessed and discussed considering the microfluidic aspects of the process.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">The control of the tagging extent allows the simultaneous MS analysis of both the unmodified and modified peptide(s).</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The number of cysteine groups corresponds to the number of characteristic mass shifts observed from the unmodified peptide.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The present theoretical work establishes the range of optimum conditions for the determination of the number of cysteine groups in peptides containing up to five cysteine groups.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In proteomics, the identities of most proteins represented in sequence databases can be determined by correlating mass spectrometric data with databases.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">To narrow down possible matching candidates, specific searching constraints are needed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The mass mapping or fingerprinting of peptides derived from proteolytic digestion of a protein provides the basic constraint.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2 cit3 cit4 cit5 cit6 cit7">2–7</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="No">However, a sufficient coverage of the protein (<IT>i.e.</IT> the determination of a sufficient number of proteolytic peptides from a particular protein) is required to unambiguously identify a protein.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Tandem mass spectrometric (MS/MS) analysis of peptides in mixtures is the most common and restrictive constraint used in addition to mass mapping.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit9">8,9</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In most cases a collision-induced dissociation (CID) spectrum from a single peptide through electrospray (ESI) MS/MS is then sufficient to conclusively identify a protein.</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In this technique, peptides ions are sequentially selected for MS/MS from a mixture.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10 cit11">10,11</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="No">However, in the case of a complex mixture, the generation of CID spectra for all of the components fails because of time limitations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Automated analysis is thus routinely programmed to give priority to peptides having the highest ion current.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="No">Therefore, when the mixture is complex, many detected ions with low intensities are not fragmented, thus reducing the dynamic range of the method.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Procedures capable of enhancing the identification procedure are of great value.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The accuracy in the mass determinations is a way of constraining the database search.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12 cit13">12,13</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The molecular weight of the protein, the isoelectric point of the protein or tryptic peptides,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF>and the presence of rare amino acids such as cysteine, methionine, or tryptophan in the peptide sequence provide powerful information to enhance the matching.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Counting the cysteine groups in a peptide using the isotopic signature of a specific tag for thiol<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12 cit15">12,15</REF> or the differential analysis of unlabelled and labelled cysteinyl samples<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF> can be used to significantly improve protein identification by database searching.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Recently, the electrochemically induced tagging of peptides by probes electrogenerated at the microband electrode of a microspray emitter<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF> have enabled the on-line counting of cysteine units in peptides<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF> to improve the processes of identification of model proteins.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19">19</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The tagging reaction happens in the microspray emitter which behaves as an electrolytic-flow cell reactor and is quasi-instantaneous.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">As a post-column treatment, the technique would provide powerful information on cysteine content, notably for low intensity peptides that would not be selected for MS/MS.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Here, the cysteine content determination relies on the control of the extent of the reaction to ensure that a minimum amount of the unmodified peptide together with a minimum amount of the fully tagged peptide is produced.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The number of cysteine units is determined by mass spectrometry as the number of mass shift(s) from the unmodified peptide.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Because the starting peptide should not be totally converted to guarantee the success of the analysis, understanding the kinetics of the flow reaction is relevant to control the process and to generalize the technique.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">To numerically simulate the on-line electrochemical tagging of peptides, multi-stage chemical reactions should be considered in a fluid flow.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20 cit21">20,21</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="New" advantage="None">Validated by comparison to previous works,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22 cit23">22,23</REF> a finite-element convection–diffusion reaction model for an electrochemical (EC) mechanism<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF> has been further developed for the consecutive tagging by markers electrogenerated at the bottom of a microchannel (2 cm in length).</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Some numerical simulations are carried out for the addition of one to up to five tags (multi-step consecutive reactions) to determine the major chemical and kinetic parameters involved in the microfluidic process.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The present theoretical work establishes the range of optimal conditions to achieve the counting of cysteine units in peptides, in order to apply the counting/identification technique to complex protein mixtures.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Results and discussion</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="1.">Microspray characteristics</HEADER><P><s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The MS experimental set-up comprised the emitter shown in Fig. 1, which behaves as an electrolytic-flow cell reactor.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The analyte is mixed with the electro-active probe prior to pressure-driven infusion through a capillary tube to the microspray emitter.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The probes studied are 1,4-hydroquinone and methoxycarbonyl-1,4-hydroquinone (HQ in general).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The overall tagging process can proceed <IT>via</IT> an electrochemical–chemical–electrochemical (ECE) mechanism (Fig. 2) where:</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">(i) The first electrochemical reaction is the oxidation of HQ in 1,4-benzoquinone or methoxycarbonyl-1,4-benzoquinone (BQ in general).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">(ii) The chemical reaction is the 1,4-Michael addition of the thiol functional group of the cysteine of a protein or peptide (P) on the BQ ring that yields the products (PQ<SB><IT>i</IT></SB>), where <IT>i</IT> represents the number of cysteine groups being tagged.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">(iii) The final electrochemical reaction involves the oxidation of the adduct, but under the present flow conditions this second electrochemical oxidation has no time to occur.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">It implies that only one thiol addition on the BQ core can happen.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, a simple EC mechanism will be considered in the present study.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.">Numerical model</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.1.">Model</HEADER><P><s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The present model is developed for species containing up to five cysteine groups.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">It addresses the convection–diffusion reaction of the eight species <IT>i</IT> considered here (HQ, BQ, P, PQ<SB>1–5</SB> for the hydroquinone, the benzoquinone, the protein or peptide, and the five possible successive degrees of the tagged protein or peptide, respectively).</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This transient model (eqn (1)) is applied in a steady state regime to a 2D cross section of the geometry (see section 2.2 and Fig. 1):where <IT>c</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB> is the concentration of the species <IT>i</IT>, <IT>D</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB> its diffusion coefficient, <B><IT>v</IT></B> is the fluid velocity vector and <IT>R</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB> is the rate of generation or consumption of <IT>i</IT> (Fig. 2).</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ∇ symbol is used to simplify the notation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the Appendix, the global forms of these local equations are described for each species, using the Galerkin formulation (finite-element method).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The tagging conditions and numerical parameters are given in Table 1 and in the computational section (Flux-Expert® software).</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.2.">Assumptions</HEADER><P><s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">(i) The electrochemical oxidation of HQ is assumed to be limited by the diffusion (fast electrode reaction) and HQ is assumed to be only species oxidised at the electrode.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">(ii) The solution is assumed to be sufficiently dilute and isothermal so that the viscosity and the density of the fluid can be considered to be unmodified by concentration or temperature variations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The diffusion coefficients of the species are also treated as uniform in the entire study domain.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">(iii) The channel walls are considered to be smooth and the eventual migration effects due to the applied potential are neglected.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">(iv) The width <IT>d</IT> of the channel is assumed to be much larger than its height 2<IT>h</IT> so that the velocity gradient in the third dimension can be neglected (2D Cartesian assumption to overcome numerical limitations).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">(v) The fluid is assumed to be Newtonian and its velocity is described according to a Poiseuille profile (laminar flow conditions, <IT>Re</IT> = 0.035).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">(vi) The reactivity of cysteine is taken to be equal at every site of the biomolecule (equal to that of the cysteine amino acid) and any other parasite reactions are neglected.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">(vii) The numerical simulations of the tagging reaction are considered only in the channel, thereby neglecting the reactions in the Taylor cone or in the ESI plume.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Previous experimental MS mono-tagging of the synthetic peptide AIKCTK carried out with microchannel emitters of variable channel length have clearly shown that the channel contribution is predominant for a channel length of 2 cm with the present flow rate.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25">25</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">(viii) The flow rate of the fluid is a fixed parameter.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The simulations correspond to a flow rate of 250 nL min<SP>−1</SP> (<IT>i.e.</IT> a mean flow velocity <B><IT>v̄</IT></B> = 4 × 10<SP>−3</SP> m s<SP>−1</SP> before scaling).</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.">Kinetics of multi-tagging</HEADER><P><s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The parameters playing a key role in the tagging final efficiency are investigated using the finite-element model (see Computational methods).</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The multi-tagging process in a laminar flow is evaluated in terms of tagging extent <IT>TE</IT> (= (Σ<SB><IT>n</IT></SB> [PQ<SB><IT>n</IT></SB>])/[P]<SB>0</SB> = ([P]<SB>0</SB> – [P])/[P]<SB>0</SB>, <IT>i.e.</IT> the consumption of the protein or peptide P).</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The addition rate constants are assumed to be equal to those corresponding to the addition of l-cysteine on 1,4-benzoquinone and methoxycarbonyl-1,4-benzoquinone (210 and 5000 M<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>, respectively, in methanol–water–acetic acid 50 : 49 : 1).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26 cit27">26,27</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">For simplification, the diffusion coefficient of all the quinone probes is taken to be equal to 3.5 × 10<SP>−10</SP> m<SP>2</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>, which in fact corresponds to the diffusion coefficient of methoxycarbonyl-1,4-hydroquinone in methanol–water–acetic acid 50 : 49 : .1<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28">28</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The mean diffusion coefficient of the target biomolecule P was chosen to be 1 × 10<SP>−10</SP> m<SP>2</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29">29</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">As the target biomolecule concentration is uniform at the inlet, its diffusion coefficient does not affect the final adduct amount (the diffusion coefficient of BQ plays an important role as the BQ generated at the electrode diffuses from the bottom of the channel and along the flow).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The initial species concentrations are taken in accordance to previous experimental works that showed valuable analyses of proteins and peptides (Table 1).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19 cit26">19,26</REF></annotationART></s></P><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>Mono-tagging</HEADER><P><s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Simulations were first run for a species containing a single thiol group.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In Fig. 3, a comparison of species distributions along the channel in its central portion (<IT>y</IT> = <IT>h</IT>) is proposed for the two probes considered for a single-cysteine target.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The formation of adduct PQ<SB>1</SB> becomes efficient with methoxycarbonyl-1,4-hydroquinone (<IT>k</IT> = 5000 M<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>), inducing subsequent consumption of both the biomolecule and the electrogenerated BQ.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>Multi-tagging</HEADER><P><s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The same kinetic comparison was made for a biomolecule with five cysteine units (each cysteine site is considered to have the same labelling rate constant).</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">For <IT>k</IT> = 210 M<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP> (Fig. 4a), the first adduct PQ<SB>1</SB> is the only species produced in a reasonable amount.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The production is higher than in the case of a single-cysteine target (15.3 μM instead of 5.0 μM at the outlet of the channel) since here it possesses five cysteine groups.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In fact, the probability for the probe to react with a cysteine in a target possessing five cysteine groups is five-fold higher than the probability to react with cysteine in a single-cysteine target.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The first step of the consecutive tagging reactions presents an apparent rate constant <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB> = 5<IT>k</IT> since the rate law is here formulated as a function of the biomolecule concentration [P] (Fig. 2).</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, the reaction rate is multiplied as shown below.Part of the first adduct PQ<SB>1</SB> reacts with BQ to give the successive adducts, the production of which is limited to PQ<SB>2</SB> for the present <IT>k</IT> value.</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">For <IT>k</IT> = 5000 M<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP> (Fig. 4b), almost all of the BQ generated at the electrode is consumed at the end of the channel.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The production of all adducts is enhanced, apart from the first, whose concentration decreased beyond a distance of 5 mm from the electrode (<IT>i.e.</IT> 1.25 s of reaction) to feed the following additions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The second adduct PQ<SB>2</SB> is the most favoured species at the end of the channel (15 μM).</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fifth adduct PQ<SB>5</SB> is also observable in small amounts.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Simulations with a rate constant of <IT>k</IT> = 20 000 M<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP> were performed as shown in Fig. 4c.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reaction is quite fast and the thermodynamic equilibrium is reached in about 2.5 s (<IT>i.e.</IT> 1 cm from the electrode).</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The electrogenerated BQ, which is correlated to the HQ initial concentration, is in deficit with respect to cysteine units.</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">It implies that the species P, PQ<SB>1</SB>, PQ<SB>2</SB>, PQ<SB>3</SB>, PQ<SB>4</SB> and PQ<SB>5</SB> remain unchanged for <IT>x</IT> &gt; 1 cm (no more BQ to react).</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This result is not only the effect of the addition rate constant but also a consequence of the multi-tagging that amplifies this tendency.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 5 reports the influence of the HQ initial concentration on the <IT>TE</IT> (= (Σ<SB><IT>n</IT></SB> [PQ<SB><IT>n</IT></SB>])/[P]<SB>0</SB> = ([P]<SB>0</SB> – [P])/[P]<SB>0</SB>) of a species containing five cysteine units.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">When the BQ is in excess ([HQ]<SB>0</SB> ≥ 6 mM), a total conversion of P is obtained for <IT>k</IT> values above 2500 M<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the other hand, for initial HQ concentrations of 1 and 2.5 mM, the electrochemically-produced BQ is in deficit with respect to the cysteine moieties and, for high <IT>k</IT> values, BQ is found to be totally consumed before the end of the channel when the protein is still present (see Fig. 4c).</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The high kinetics limits the consumption of P because the following steps consume BQ rapidly.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Optimization of the multi-tagging of peptides</HEADER><P><s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The initial concentration of HQ plays a key role in the final tagging degree since it controls the production of the BQ markers (in the present assumption of diffusion control of the current).</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In Fig. 6a and b, the evolution of the species at the end of the channel is given according to [HQ]<SB>0</SB> for biomolecules containing three and five cysteine groups, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">As expected, the higher the [HQ]<SB>0</SB>, the higher the consumption of P and the production of the completely tagged species (<IT>i.e.</IT> PQ<SB>3</SB> and PQ<SB>5</SB> for peptides containing three and five cysteine groups, respectively).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="New" advantage="None">In the previous section, a target with five cysteine groups was used for emphasizing kinetics and a better understanding of the multi-stage process.</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="New" advantage="None">A peptide with three cysteine groups serves as a reference since such peptides are more probable in proteomic analysis.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">To enable the MS cysteine counting in peptides in future experiments, we have decided to impose the following criteria for the simulation: both the proportion of P (= 100 × [P]/[P]<SB>0</SB>) and of the completely tagged species PQ<SB><IT>n</IT></SB> (= 100 × [PQ<SB><IT>n</IT></SB>]/[P]<SB>0</SB>) should be above 10% in order to be detectable by MS.</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">In Fig. 6, the corresponding working domains mark these conditions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">For a three cysteine peptide (Fig. 6a) the two conditions are compatible (1.755 mM &lt; [HQ]<SB>0</SB> &lt; 2.275 mM), but the two working domains do not intersect for a five cysteine peptide (Fig. 6b).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The initial concentration of HQ drives the tagging rate and thereby the proportion of the species at the end of the channel.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">When the [HQ]<SB>0</SB> is too high, there is not enough P left and when it is too low, there is not enough PQ<SB><IT>n</IT></SB> produced.</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">As shown in Fig. 7, tagging reaction times <IT>t</IT> in the channel could thus be chosen to make the two conditions expressed above compatible.</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The 10% working conditions are represented in Fig. 7a for the three cysteine peptide.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The domain shows that high concentrations of HQ imply working over small times to ensure that P is not totally consumed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Nevertheless, a wide range of concentrations is then compatible with these short times: 0.6 s of reaction time allows working between 10 and 20 mM of HQ.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">When working with a longer reaction time, the concentration possibilities are narrower but the analysis can be done at many times (for instance, the analysis is possible from 2 to more than 5 s for an initial concentration of 2 mM).</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In other words, when the apparent kinetics become slower, the fixed conditions are satisfied for wider time ranges (the scale is widespread due to the second order kinetic law).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the five-stage tagging (Fig. 7b), the conditions are almost never compatible except at high concentrations, and for very restrictive time ranges (for [HQ]<SB>0</SB> = 25 mM, the reaction time must be fixed at 0.3 s).</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">When the criteria level is reduced to 5%, a much wider working domain appears for the five-stage reaction (Fig. 7c).</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The technique appears applicable to peptides containing five or less cysteine groups since the co-existence of P and PQ<SB><IT>n</IT></SB> is no more likely when more cysteine groups are present as BQ is stocked in the intermediate species.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">For successful cysteine counting, the initial concentration of P is also a key feature to consider, all the more so as [P]<SB>0</SB> is not really controlled by the manipulator.</annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Indeed, in proteomic analysis, the amounts of tryptic peptides derive from the protein concentrations, which are quite variable from one to another in a complex mixture.</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the simulated data of Fig. 8, for a given reaction time <IT>t</IT> = 5 s (<IT>i.e. L</IT><SB>ch</SB> = 2 cm), concentration [P]<SB>0</SB> varies from 0.1 to 75 μM.</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The initial concentrations [HQ]<SB>0</SB> that provide 10% of P and PQ<SB>3</SB> according to each initial concentration [P]<SB>0</SB> are reported.</annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Between the two curves, the hatched domain indicates that both conditions are satisfied.</annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reference point (◆) shows that [HQ]<SB>0</SB> = 2.5 mM, which was used in the previous section, provides good analysis of three-cysteine peptides from 55 to 100 μM.</annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Defining the ratio Δ[HQ]<SB>0</SB>/[HQ]<SB>0</SB> for the 10% working domain, 0.51 and 0.31 are obtained for [P]<SB>0</SB> = 0.l and 75 μM, respectively, showing that the working interval slightly decreases with the concentration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The nature of the curve proves that the ratio [HQ]<SB>0</SB>/[P]<SB>0</SB> can not be used as a term to predict the tagging extent in general.</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is further confirmed by several numerical studies at different concentrations while keeping the ratio [HQ]<SB>0</SB>/[P]<SB>0</SB> constant (see supplementary information Fig. S1<SUP TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" />).</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Computational methods</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Numerical technique</HEADER><P><s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The finite-element formulation was generated on the numerical software Flux-Expert® (Astek Rhône-Alpes, Grenoble, France), in a 2-D Cartesian form.</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">It was operated on a Dell PC, 2 Gb RAM (Red Hat Linux).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The mesh size adopted for the channel was <IT>δ</IT> = 5 μm and it was reduced (<IT>i.e.</IT> to 0.4 μm) at the electrode extremities in order to take into account the edge effects.</annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The resulting mesh Péclet number <IT>P</IT><SB>S</SB> = <B><IT>v̄</IT></B><IT>δ</IT>/<IT>D</IT> was found to be 50 and 14 for the P and the BQ respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The error induced by a 7 μm channel mesh (compared to a 4 μm channel) was checked and found to be 0.01 and 0.05% for BQ and P respectively at the end of the channel (see Fig. S2 in the ESI<SUP TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" />).</annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">It confirms the mesh Péclet number limit of 100 determined in the literature.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30">30</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The total mesh number is 30 000, leading to 240 000 degrees of freedom for the eight unknowns in the five-tagging case.</annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The conservation of species flux (BQ and P) was verified.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Scaling</HEADER><P><s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Because of the 2 cm channel experimental length, scaling was necessary to have an acceptable mesh Péclet number while keeping a meshing grid and matrix size that could be numerically treated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Then, a 0.5 cm long geometry was used but the channel height (2<IT>h</IT>) and the electrode length were kept the same (the electrode length remains quasi-negligible compared to channel length, <IT>i.e.</IT> the ratio is 1 : 50 instead of 1 : 200 for the experimental conditions).</annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The flow rate was divided by four to ensure the same residence time in the channel and the same transversal diffusion time.</annotationART></s> <s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The incoming HQ concentration was adapted to have the same flux ratio between the incoming protein or peptide P and the BQ generated at the electrode.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">With the Levich equation,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit31 cit32">31,32</REF> one can express a proportionality relationship between the flux rate of produced BQ at the electrode <IT>N</IT><SB>BQ</SB> and the flow rate <IT>F</IT><SB><IT>V</IT></SB> = <B><IT>v̄</IT></B>2<IT>hd</IT> (where <B><IT>v̄</IT></B> is the mean flow velocity, 2<IT>h</IT> and <IT>d</IT> are the height and width of the channel)<IT>N</IT><SB>BQ</SB> ∝ [HQ]<SB>0</SB><IT>F</IT><SB><IT>V</IT></SB><SP>1/3</SP>From Relation 1, if the flow rate is divided by four, the flux of BQ is divided by 4<SP>1/3</SP> = 1.6.</annotationART></s> <s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">It has been checked by simulation that the ratio of flux of BQ at the electrode for the normal case (<B><IT>v̄</IT></B> = 4 × 10<SP>−3</SP> m s<SP>−1</SP>) over the scaling by 4 (<B><IT>v̄</IT></B> = 1 × 10<SP>−3</SP> m s<SP>−1</SP>) is 1.589 (≈1.6).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Moreover, the flux of the protein <IT>N</IT><SB>P</SB> coming into the channel is given by<IT>N</IT><SB>P</SB> = [P]<SB>0</SB><IT>F</IT><SB><IT>V</IT></SB>Whatever the flow rate scaling, the ratio of these fluxes must be conservedTo conserve the ratio <IT>N</IT><SB>BQ</SB>/<IT>N</IT><SB>P</SB> if the flow rate is multiplied by 4, the initial concentration [HQ]<SB>0</SB> must be multiplied by 4<SP>2/3</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The mean concentration [BQ] remains unchanged by this operation asThe scaling was fully validated by the numerical comparisons of the concentration of BQ and PQ<SB>3</SB> along the channel for a scaling by 2 (channel length of 10 mm) and 4 (channel length of 5 mm), which appear in Figs. S3 and S4 in the ESI.<SUP TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" /></annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Numerical simulation studies were pursued with a scaling of 4.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Conclusions</HEADER><P><s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The influence of the tagging rate constant as well as the impact of the probe and target concentrations have been simulated for a single and a five-step tagging reaction in a microchannel.</annotationART></s> <s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">The finite-element model has shown how strongly the tagging efficiency derives from the number of consecutive tagging reactions (<IT>i.e.</IT> the number of cysteine moieties in the protein or peptide determining the apparent kinetics of each consecutive reaction).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="New" advantage="None">The non-suppression of the unmodified molecule signal is essential to guarantee the success of the on-line MS counting of cysteine moieties.</annotationART></s> <s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the other hand, the residence time and the probe concentration should be sufficient to achieve all the tagging degrees.</annotationART></s> <s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Numerical simulations have been used to determine the optimal conditions for this.</annotationART></s> <s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">It has been shown that the cysteine counting is possible for up to five units.</annotationART></s> <s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None">When the molecule possesses more cysteine residues, the co-existence of both the untagged and fully tagged molecule is no more likely whatever the residence time.</annotationART></s> <s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None">To overcome this, the introduction of a recognition signal could be added to the tag.</annotationART></s> <s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Some mass tags presenting characteristic isotopic patterns could thus be employed.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
