<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b211806h" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Intermittent dynamics and hyper-aging in dense colloidal gels<XREF TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" /></annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">We investigate the slow dynamics of strongly aggregated particle gels by diffusing wave spectroscopy (DWS) using a charge coupled device (CCD) camera as a multispeckle detector.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The evolution of the slow dynamics after the gel-point is followed using two different techniques, the multispeckle method and a novel correlation scheme, time resolved correlation (TRC), which allows us to obtain time resolved information on the dynamics of the gel.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">We find that the intensity autocorrelation function measured by multispeckle DWS exhibits an ultraslow relaxation, whose characteristic time strongly depends on the age of the gel.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">An analysis of the TRC data reveals that the slow dynamics is intermittent.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">We propose that the intermittency is due to rare disruptions or formations of bonds affecting the elastic backbone of the network, which lead to sudden long range rearrangements of the particle position and thus to a sudden change of the speckle pattern.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Slow dynamics and aging phenomena are characteristics shared by many disordered, metastable solids.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">As a system is quenched into a jammed state<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF> the constituent of the system becomes kinetically trapped, precluding further exploration of phase space.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Because of the non-equilibrium nature of this state, however, most systems tend to evolve after the quench, where this evolution sensitively depends on the quench depth and on the history of the sample.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although there has been considerable theoretical effort devoted to understanding the essential physics of aging in spin and structural glasses,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2 cit3 cit4 cit5">2–5</REF> as well as in soft glassy materials,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6 cit7">6,7</REF> the rather general phenomena of slow dynamics in jammed systems is still poorly understood.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Experiments exploring the detailed dynamics of the constituent of a system are sparse;<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit9 cit10 cit11 cit12">8–12</REF> however, they are essential to gain insight in the origin of slow relaxation processes.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Experimental</HEADER><P><s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Colloidal gels are obtained by salt-induced aggregation of polystyrene (PS) particles of radius <IT>a</IT> = 85 nm, suspended in a buoyancy-matching mixture of H<SB>2</SB>O and D<SB>2</SB>O at a volume fraction <IT>ϕ</IT> = 0.045.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In order to obtain homogeneous destabilization the ions are produced <IT>in situ</IT><IT>via</IT> an enzymatic reaction.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">We set the final ionic strength to 310 mM, which is 3 times higher than the critical ionic strength required to fully screen the surface charge of the PS-particles.</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The critical ionic strength is reached after ∼200 s and the gel-point after ∼400 s, indicating a gradual change of the aggregation conditions from reaction limited to diffusion limited cluster aggregation.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The dynamics of particle gels are probed by diffusion wave spectroscopy (DWS).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The measurements are performed in transmission with a setup similar to that described by Viasnoff <IT>et al.</IT>:<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF> a combination of the two-cell technique<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16 cit17">16,17</REF> and the multispeckle method<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF> is used to measure the intensity correlation function <IT>g</IT><SB>2</SB>(<IT>τ</IT>) for time delays spanning 13 decades, 10<SP>−8</SP> &lt; <IT>τ</IT> &lt; 10<SP>5</SP> s.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Results and discussion</HEADER><P><s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The typical time evolution of the correlation function of an aging gel is shown in Fig. 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">With the onset of gelation,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF> which we define as the sample age <IT>t</IT><SB>w</SB> = 0, the appearance of a second decay in the intensity correlation function is observed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This decay quickly develops as the sample ages and can be approximated by an exponential decay, as denoted by the solid lines in Fig. 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The corresponding relaxation time, <IT>τ</IT><SB>exp</SB>, is shown in the inset of Fig 1 as a function of the sample age, <IT>t</IT><SB>w</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">For <IT>t</IT><SB>w</SB> &lt; 5 × 10<SP>5</SP> s the dependence of the final relaxation is well described by a power law of <IT>τ</IT><SB>exp</SB> ∼ <IT>t</IT><SB>w</SB><SP><IT>μ</IT></SP>, where we find <IT>μ</IT> = 1.37 ± 0.02.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Similar aging behavior has been observed for other jammed materials, although the exponent is usually <IT>μ</IT> ≤ .1<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19 cit20 cit21">19–21</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The aging exponent being larger than one indicates that the relaxation time would eventually exceed the sample age and thus, become undetectable.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Instead we find that the final relaxation time eventually decreases again, which seems to indicate the complete collapse of the gel.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="New" advantage="None">To gain insight in this intriguing aging behavior we develop a new scheme, which we term time resolved correlation (TRC).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="New" advantage="None">We use the CCD camera to take pictures of the speckle field scattered by the sample at regular time intervals.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="New" advantage="None">The degree of correlation, <IT>c</IT><SB>I</SB>(<IT>t</IT><SB>w</SB>,<IT>τ</IT>), between two images spaced by a lag time <IT>τ</IT> is then calculated as a function of <IT>t</IT><SB>w</SB>, where we define <IT>t</IT><SB>w</SB> as the sample age at which the first image was taken.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="New" advantage="None">The degree of correlation is calculated according to:where <IT>I<SB>p</SB></IT>(<IT>t</IT><SB>w</SB>) is the intensity measured at age <IT>t</IT><SB>w</SB> for the <IT>p</IT>th CCD pixel and &lt;...&gt;<IT><SB>p</SB></IT> denotes the average over pixels.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="New" advantage="None">Note that in the traditional correlation scheme, <IT>g</IT><SB>2</SB>(<IT>τ</IT>) − 1 has a form similar to that of <IT>c</IT><SB>I</SB>(<IT>t</IT><SB>w</SB>,<IT>τ</IT>), except that the intensity fluctuations are measured for a single speckle (<IT>p</IT> = 1) and the pixel averaging is replaced by an extensive time average.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The age dependence of <IT>c</IT><SB>I</SB>(<IT>t</IT><SB>w</SB>,<IT>τ</IT>) is shown in Fig. 2 for different lag times.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">As a general trend, <IT>c</IT><SB>I</SB>(<IT>t</IT><SB>w</SB>,<IT>τ</IT>) grows with <IT>t</IT><SB>w</SB> at all lag-times before it catastrophically decreases at <IT>t</IT><SB>w</SB> ≥ 5 × 10<SP>5</SP> s.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="New" advantage="None">The way the data is plotted may at first appear unusual, since we normally plot the degree of correlation as a function of lag time instead of <IT>t</IT><SB>w</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="New" advantage="None">Indeed, the lag time dependence of <IT>c</IT><SB>I</SB>(<IT>t</IT><SB>w</SB>,<IT>τ</IT>) at a given <IT>t</IT><SB>w</SB> can be obtained from a vertical cut through the data, which in principle enables us to generate a two point correlation function <IT>g</IT><SB>2</SB>(<IT>τ</IT>,<IT>t</IT><SB>w</SB>) − 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Corresponding to the increase of the relaxation time shown in Fig. 1, we find in Fig. 2 that <IT>c</IT><SB>I</SB>(<IT>t</IT><SB>w</SB>,<IT>τ</IT>) becomes larger than zero for increasingly large delays as the sample ages.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The increase of <IT>c</IT><SB>I</SB>(<IT>t</IT><SB>w</SB>,<IT>τ</IT>) at the smallest delay <IT>τ</IT> = 10 s corresponds to the growth of the intermediate plateau values of <IT>g</IT><SB>2</SB>(<IT>τ</IT>) − 1 in Fig 1 and reflects an increase of the rigidity of the gel.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The large drops observed at <IT>t</IT><SB>w</SB> ∼ 1.5 × 10<SP>5</SP> s and <IT>t</IT><SB>w</SB> ≥ 5 × 10<SP>5</SP> s thus correspond to the decrease of the relaxation time, which can be seen for large <IT>t</IT><SB>w</SB> in the inset of Fig 1.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">The TRC data, however, gives access to a more detailed view of the dynamics of a system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Remarkably, it reveals that the aging-process is not smooth and continuous, but rather results from a series of discrete rearrangement events as can be seen in magnified sections of the <IT>c</IT><SB>I</SB>(<IT>t</IT><SB>w</SB>,<IT>τ</IT>)-traces.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">An example of such a section is shown in the inset of Fig. 3(b).</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Contrary to the case of Brownian particles, which is shown in the inset of Fig. 3(a), the noise of <IT>c</IT><SB>I</SB>(<IT>t</IT><SB>w</SB>,<IT>τ</IT>) is not symmetric for the gel.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">We observe remarkable drops of the degree of correlation, which indicate that, from time to time, the particles undergo larger-than-usual movements; whenever such an anomalous motion occurs in the time lag between two images, the degree of correlation, <IT>c</IT><SB>I</SB>(<IT>t</IT><SB>w</SB>,<IT>τ</IT>), exhibits a sudden drop.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">This behavior is clearly reflected in the probability density function (PDF) of <IT>c</IT><SB>I</SB>(<IT>t</IT><SB>w</SB>,<IT>τ</IT>) shown in Fig. 3(b), which is markedly skewed towards smaller values of <IT>c</IT><SB>I</SB>(<IT>t</IT><SB>w</SB>,<IT>τ</IT>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">By contrast, we expect and find a Gaussian PDF of <IT>c</IT><SB>I</SB>(<IT>t</IT><SB>w</SB>,<IT>τ</IT>), as shown in Fig. 3(a), in the case of smooth continuous motion of Brownian particles.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">To quantify the asymmetry of the PDF compared to a Gaussian PDF, we calculate the skewness <IT>s</IT> = <IT>m</IT><SB>3</SB>/<IT>m</IT><SB>2</SB><SP>3/2</SP>, where <IT>m<SB>i</SB></IT> is the <IT>i</IT>th moment of <IT>c</IT><SB>I</SB>(<IT>t</IT><SB>w</SB>,<IT>τ</IT>) with respect to its mean.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">We analyze the development of <IT>s</IT> as a function of <IT>τ</IT> and plot the result for both the Brownian particles and the particle-gel in Fig. 3(c) and (d), respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">While the value of <IT>s</IT> fluctuates around zero for the Brownian particles, it is a strong function of the lag time for the particle-gel.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">At short lag we find <IT>s</IT> to be negative with only little dependence on <IT>τ</IT>, it then increases and reaches a value of zero as the lag time equals the relaxation time, which is denoted as a dashed line in Fig. 3(d).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">We account for this behavior by considering the scenario of rare and sudden events determining the long time dynamics of our system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The events are spaced in time by <IT>T</IT><SB>e</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">For lag times below <IT>T</IT><SB>e</SB> the events are clearly resolved in <IT>c</IT><SB>I</SB>(<IT>t</IT><SB>w</SB>,<IT>τ</IT>) and the PDF is skewed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, when <IT>τ</IT> exceeds the event spacing, the fluctuations in <IT>c</IT><SB>I</SB>(<IT>t</IT><SB>w</SB>,<IT>τ</IT>) average out and the PDF becomes Gaussian, <IT>s</IT> = 0.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The events leading to a considerable change in the speckle pattern can be interpreted as the occasional formation and rupture of bonds, affecting the elastic backbone of the network.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Because of the long-range connectivity of the backbone they lead to a rearrangement of the particle positions in a large volume and thus to a significant drop of the degree of correlation.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The agreement between the lag time at which the PDF becomes Gaussian and the final relaxation time of <IT>g</IT><SB>2</SB>(<IT>τ</IT>) − 1 persists for different ages, as shown in Fig. 4.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">This strongly suggests that the rare and sudden events are the origin of the slow dynamics of colloidal particle gels.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In conclusion, we have developed a new scheme, time resolved correlation, which enables us to explore in a detailed way the dynamics of a system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The application of this method to particle gels revealed that the slow aging dynamics of these systems is intermittent.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">We explain this behavior assuming the occasional formation or rupture of bonds within the gel, causing a rearrangement of the particle positions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">When the formation or rupture of bonds affect the elastic backbone of the network, the rearrangements are larger than average, leading to sudden drops in the degree of correlation.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Ongoing experiments on other jammed systems reveal similar intermittent dynamics,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF> thus suggesting that intermittency is a general feature of aging systems.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
