<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b308201f" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Urethane cross-linked poly(oxyethylene)/siliceous nanohybrids doped with Eu<SP>3+</SP> ionsPart 1. Coordinating ability of the host matrix</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Fourier transform mid-IR and Raman spectroscopies were extensively used to examine cation/polymer and cation/cross-link interactions, as well as hydrogen bonding, in Eu<SP>3+</SP>-doped sol–gel derived organic/inorganic materials (<IT>monourethanesils</IT>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The hybrid framework of these xerogels contains short methyl end capped polyether segments covalently bonded to a siliceous backbone through urethane groups.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The cations were incorporated as europium triflate, Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">Samples with compositions ∞ &gt; <IT>n</IT> ≥ 10 (where <IT>n</IT> indicates the ratio of (OCH<SB>2</SB>CH<SB>2</SB>) moieties per lanthanide ion) were investigated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The spectral data obtained provided unequivocal evidence that the cations coordinate exclusively to the urethane carbonyl oxygen atoms in compounds with 400 ≥ <IT>n</IT> ≥ 50.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The participation of the ether oxygen atoms of the polymer chains in the Eu<SP>3+</SP> complexation process is initiated at <IT>n</IT> = 30.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The presence of a crystalline phase was detected at <IT>n</IT> = 10.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The variation of the glass transition temperature of the monourethanesils studied with salt concentration is in perfect agreement with these claims.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The beginning of the Eu<SP>3+</SP>–polyether interaction is accompanied by a breakdown of the hydrogen bonded aggregates of the matrix, as confirmed by photoluminescence spectroscopy.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The development of advanced nanoscale organic/inorganic frameworks with potential application in many fields has attracted considerable attention in the last few years.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The combination of the hybrid strategy, that has inherited the advantages of the sol–gel chemistry, with the host–guest concept of polymer electrolytes<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2 cit3 cit4">2–4</REF> has aroused special interest in the domain of optics.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this context, a family of intensely luminescent nanohybrid xerogels with outstanding features was introduced.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6 cit7">5–7</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The hybrid host employed contains poly(oxyethylene), POE, chains of variable length grafted at both ends to a siliceous backbone through urea linkages (–NHC(O)NH–).</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">This framework (<IT>diureasil</IT>)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF> was represented by U(Y) (Y = 2000, 900 and 600), where U indicates the urea group and Y denotes the average molecular weight of the organic precursor used.</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The active constituents are in general Eu<SP>3+</SP> ions, added as a triflate salt, Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB>, whose concentration may be taken to higher levels than those normally used in conventional composite materials.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Eu<SP>3+</SP>-doped long chain diureasils, processed as highly transparent monoliths,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6a cit6b cit9 cit10">6<IT>a</IT>,6<IT>b</IT>,9,10</REF> are acceptable ion conductors<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6a cit6b cit10b">6<IT>a</IT>,<IT>b</IT>,10<IT>b</IT></REF> and behave like white-light phosphors.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6a cit6b cit9 cit11">6<IT>a</IT>,<IT>b</IT>,9,11</REF> Their most remarkable feature is the possibility of tuning their color along the Commission Internationale d'Éclairage chromaticity diagram by simply varying either the salt content or the excitation wavelength.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9c">9<IT>c</IT></REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The multifunctionality of the diureasils containing Eu<SP>3+</SP> ions derives from the coordinating ability of the hybrid matrix itself.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6d cit6e cit9 cit10">6<IT>d</IT>,<IT>e</IT>,9,10</REF> The activation of the coordinating sites of this POE/siloxane structure (the oxygen atoms of the urea carbonyl groups and the oxygen atoms of the polyether chains) can be easily controlled by changing either the salt content at constant chain length or the length of the organic segments at constant salt concentration.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6d cit6e cit10">6<IT>d</IT>,<IT>e</IT>,10</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None">In the present work urethane cross-linked xerogels doped with Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB>–a family of close analogs of the diureasils–will be thoroughly investigated with the primary goal of elucidating the structure/properties relationship.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The organic/inorganic host of these compounds (<IT>monourethanesils</IT>)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12 cit13">12,13</REF> is composed of short methyl end capped POE chains covalently bonded to a siliceous network through urethane moieties (–NH(CO)O–).</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">This matrix was designated as m-Ut(Y′) (Y′ = 2000, 750 and 350, corresponding to about 45, 17 and 7 (OCH<SB>2</SB>CH<SB>2</SB>) repeat units, respectively),<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF> where m denotes mono, Ut represents the urethane group and Y′ indicates the average molecular weight of the starting organic material.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">The creation of monohybrids, through the reduction of the number of cross-links/polymer segment from two to one, allows to simplify the complicated structure of the diureasils.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Preliminary studies of the luminescence features of the Eu<SP>3+</SP>-doped monourethanesils suggested that the local chemical environment of the cation is similar to that found in the corresponding diureasil materials.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">Thus, despite having poorer mechanical properties, the monourethanesils may be viewed as good model compounds of the diureasils in terms of cationic coordination.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, an in-depth characterization of the monourethanesil system will help to enlighten the complex behavior of the diureasils and clarify many questions that remain unanswered regarding the cationic and anionic environments in the salt-doped diurea cross-linked hybrids.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">The systematic analysis that we have decided to perform on a series of m-Ut(750)-based monourethanesil samples containing a wide concentration range of Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB> will be divided into two parts.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">Part 1 will be devoted to the study of cation/polymer and cation/cross-link interactions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fourier Transform mid-IR (FT-IR) and Raman (FT-Raman) spectroscopies will be employed extensively to check if the methyl-terminated POE chains of m-Ut(750) participate in the complexation of the Eu<SP>3+</SP> ions, since rich information regarding the cationic environment is provided by cation-induced changes in vibrational motions of conformation sensitive polymer bonds<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14 cit15 cit16 cit17 cit18 cit19 cit20 cit21 cit22 cit23">14–23</REF> and in metal ion–oxygen stretching motions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18 cit19 cit20 cit21 cit22 cit23">18–23</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The “amide I” and “amide II” regions<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF> will be also inspected to estimate the degree of hydrogen bonding in the monourethanesil materials<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25 cit26">25,26</REF> and to determine the role of the urethane carbonyl oxygen atoms in the Eu<SP>3+</SP> coordination mechanism.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27">27</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">This work will be complemented with data retrieved from photoluminescence spectroscopy and differencial scanning calorimetry.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">The scope of Part 2 will be to examine ionic association in the monourethanesil hybrids in order to gain additional insight into the local chemical environment of the lanthanide ions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Cation–anion interactions will be evaluated through the analysis of characteristic modes of the triflate ion in the FT-IR and FT-Raman spectra of the same set of samples considered in Part 1.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Results and discussion</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="1">Vibrational spectroscopy</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>Cation/polymer interactions</HEADER><P><s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Several vibrational modes of POE are extremely sensitive to the interaction of the polymer backbone with cations and can be thus employed as diagnostic tools to monitor the changes undergone by the polyether chains upon the addition of the guest salt.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Classically, two spectral regions are widely used in the field of polymer electrolytes to probe the coordination of the cations to the host polyether:<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit14 cit15 cit16 cit17 cit18 cit19 cit20 cit21 cit22 cit23">4,14–23</REF> (1) Skeleton CO stretching, <IT>ν</IT>(CO), region.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this frequency interval (1200–1000 cm<SP>–1</SP>) the solvation of the cations by the heteroatoms of the polyether chains produces a distinct shift of the intense <IT>ν</IT>(CO) band to lower wavenumbers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The magnitude of this shift depends on the strength of the interaction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">(2) CH<SB>2</SB> rocking, <IT>ρ</IT><SB>r</SB>(CH<SB>2</SB>), region.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Between 1000 and 800 cm<SP>–1</SP> the bands ascribed to a mixture of CH<SB>2</SB> rocking modes and CC stretching vibrations (from 1000 to 900 cm<SP>–1</SP>)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28">28</REF> and the bands originated from CH<SB>2</SB> rocking modes coupled with CO stretching vibrations (from 900 to 800 cm<SP>–1</SP>)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28">28</REF> are found.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Their frequency is strongly dependent on the –O–C–C–O– angle and hence on the polymer local conformation.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The room-temperature mid-IR spectra of the m-Ut(750)<SB><IT>n</IT></SB>Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB> family of materials analyzed in the present work are collected in Fig. 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The assignment of the main bands produced by the polymer chains of the same hybrid samples is given in Table 1.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 2 shows that in the <IT>ν</IT>(CO) region the IR spectrum of the non-doped monourethanesil matrix displays a peak around 1113 cm<SP>–1</SP> and a shoulder at about 1143 cm<SP>–1</SP> ascribed, respectively, to the CO stretching vibration mode and to the coupled vibration of the CO stretching and CH<SB>2</SB> rocking modes (Table 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the spectra of the m-Ut(750)<SB><IT>n</IT></SB>Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB> xerogels with 400 ≥ <IT>n</IT> ≥ 30, both the 1113 cm<SP>–1</SP> feature, characteristic of non-coordinated oxyethylene moieties, and the 1143 cm<SP>–1</SP> shoulder persist practically unchanged as increasing amounts of Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB> are incorporated into the m-Ut(750) host (Fig. 2).</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the low-frequency side of the <IT>ν</IT>(CO) envelope, the only change worth noting in the spectra of the same Eu<SP>3+</SP>-doped compounds is the growth of a shoulder near 1068 cm<SP>–1</SP> at <IT>n</IT> = 30 (Fig. 2, Table 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The further addition of Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB> (<IT>i.e.</IT>, <IT>n</IT> = 10) has, however, tremendous implications.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 2 and Table 1 clearly illustrate that the m-Ut(750)<SB>10</SB>Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB> material gives rise to a series of extraordinary changes: (1) the very strong band centered at approximately 1113 cm<SP>–1</SP> disappears; (2) the shoulder seen at about 1068 cm<SP>–1</SP> in the spectrum of m-Ut(750)<SB>30</SB>Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB> is transformed into a strong event at 1072 cm<SP>–1</SP>; (3) two new intense features are distinctly observed at 1115 and 1105 cm<SP>–1</SP>; (4) two new strong components appear at 1097 and 1057 cm<SP>–1</SP>, together with two shoulders located at 1123 and 1063 cm<SP>–1</SP>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Bernson <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF>. reported that in the case of the electrolytes formed with La(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB> and POE all the (OCH<SB>2</SB>CH<SB>2</SB>) moieties are virtually bonded to the cations at <IT>n</IT> = .9<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The characteristic band attributed to La<SP>3+</SP>-coordinated ether oxygen atoms was a single event at 1073 cm<SP>–1</SP>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">It is noteworthy that in the case of a POE-based system doped with lithium triflate, LiCF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>, a crystalline complex was formed for composition <IT>n</IT> = 3,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17a">17<IT>a</IT></REF><IT>i.e.</IT>, a composition that in terms of anionic concentration corresponds to <IT>n</IT> = 9 for a trivalent cation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Moreover, the frequency of a characteristic spectral feature of the Li<SP>+</SP>-based compound appeared at 1092 cm<SP>–1</SP>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17a">17<IT>a</IT></REF> In addition, in the spectra of the NH<SB>4</SB>CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>-based polymer electrolytes with <IT>n</IT> &lt; 8<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17b">17<IT>b</IT></REF> and in that of the POE<SB>1</SB>KCF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB> crystalline compound,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17c">17<IT>c</IT></REF> the broad <IT>ν</IT>(CO) band at 1102 cm<SP>–1</SP> was replaced by two peaks at 1116 and 1107 cm<SP>–1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Considering the remarkable coincidence between the spectral features just indicated and those of m-Ut(750)<SB>10</SB>Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB>, it seems logical to associate the new bands appearing in the <IT>ν</IT>(CO) region of the latter material to a salt-rich crystalline complex.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Further evidences of the formation of a crystalline phase in the m-Ut(750)<SB>10</SB>Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB> compound may be found in the <IT>ρ</IT><SB>r</SB>(CH<SB>2</SB>) region.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 3 shows that the main feature of the IR spectra of the monourethanesil samples with ∞ &gt; <IT>n</IT> ≥ 30 within the 980–900 cm<SP>–1</SP> region is a peak at approximately 955 cm<SP>–1</SP> and two shoulders at lower frequency (Table 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this range of compositions the incorporation of increasing amounts of lanthanide salt to the hybrid matrix does not modify the intensity and position of these three spectral events.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast, in the spectrum of m-Ut(750)<SB>10</SB>Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB> the band envelope becomes considerably stronger and a new, intense sharp feature develops at 937 cm<SP>–1</SP> (Fig. 3, Table 1), characteristic of crystalline high molecular weight poly(ethylene glycol)dimethyl ether, PEGDME.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28c">28<IT>c</IT></REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 3 also reveals that the dominant feature of the compounds with ∞ &gt; <IT>n</IT> ≥ 30 in the 900–800 cm<SP>–1</SP> interval is a band centered at approximately 847 cm<SP>–1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Several shoulders are also observed (Table 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Within this range of salt concentration the intensity and position of the bands remain essentially unaffected.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Again, the contour of the envelope is drastically modified in the spectrum of the xerogel with <IT>n</IT> = 10, the most remarkable change being the presence of a new sharp, medium intensity band located at 843 cm<SP>–1</SP> (Fig. 3, Table 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">This event was also assigned to crystalline PEGDME.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28c">28<IT>c</IT></REF> Interestingly, the crystalline complexes POE<SB>1</SB>NH<SB>4</SB>CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB> and POE<SB>1</SB>KCF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB> exhibit bands around 933 and 841 cm<SP>–1</SP><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17b">17<IT>b</IT></REF> and 936 and 843 cm<SP>–1</SP>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17c">17<IT>c</IT></REF> respectively.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although less sensitive to alterations in the backbone conformation, the CH<SB>2</SB> scissoring and CH<SB>3</SB> deformation modes, which appear in the 1500–1400 cm<SP>–1</SP> frequency interval, and the CH<SB>2</SB> wagging modes, situated in the 1400–1300 cm<SP>–1</SP> spectral range, can be also used to complement the conclusions drawn from the two spectral regions discussed above.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">A close examination of Fig. 4 and Table 1 allow us to state that, between 1500 and 1300 cm<SP>–1</SP>, the spectra of the monourethanesil compounds with <IT>n</IT> &gt; 10 closely resemble the spectrum of m-Ut(750).</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">It may be also immediately inferred that, in the same region, the spectral signature of the host hybrid is deeply modified at <IT>n</IT> = 10.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The most significant change detected between 1500 and 1400 cm<SP>–1</SP> in the spectrum of the latter sample is the presence of a new band of medium intensity at 1467 cm<SP>–1</SP> and several new shoulders (Fig. 4, Table 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the CH<SB>2</SB> wagging region of m-Ut(750)<SB>10</SB>Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB> a significant enhancement of the shoulder located at 1360 cm<SP>–1</SP> occurs (Fig. 4, Table 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The features at 1467 and 1360 cm<SP>–1</SP> are also produced by crystalline PEGDME,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28c">28<IT>c</IT></REF> thus corroborating the fact that in the most concentrated sample the disordered polyether chains of m-Ut(750) adopt regularly ordered conformations to bond to the Eu<SP>3+</SP> ions.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The intense band situated at approximately 872 cm<SP>–1</SP> in the Raman spectrum of the most concentrated xerogel (Fig. 5) represents another spectroscopic proof of the interaction between the Eu<SP>3+</SP> ions and the ether oxygen atoms of the oligopolymer chains at this salt concentration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The 872 cm<SP>–1</SP> event is visible already in the Raman spectrum of m-Ut(750)<SB>30</SB>Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB> as a very weak shoulder (Fig. 5).</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The absence of this feature in the Raman spectra of the xerogels with lower salt content (Fig. 5) suggests that the participation of the oxyethylene moieties in the cation complexation process is initiated near the composition at which the saturation of the urethane cross-links is attained, <IT>i.e.</IT>, at <IT>n</IT> = 17.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">In analogy with previous authors,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18 cit19 cit20 cit21 cit22 cit23">18–23</REF> we will associate the 872 cm<SP>–1</SP> band to a stretching vibration mode involving wrapping of the pendant oligopolyether segments of m-Ut(750) around the Eu<SP>3+</SP> ion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">This mode, represented by <IT>ν</IT>(M–O<SB><IT>n</IT></SB>) and usually termed as “oxygen breathing” mode, is typically seen in the Raman spectra of complexes of crown ethers and metal cations.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29">29</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the basis of the model proposed by Papke <IT>et al.</IT>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF> it is accepted that the formation of the cation/ether oxygen complex favors a <IT>gauche</IT> conformation of the C–C bonds.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this context it is fundamental to point out that a band indicative of the <IT>trans</IT> conformations of the –O–C–C–O– sequences<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30 cit31">30,31</REF> and centered at about 810–805 cm<SP>–1</SP> is distinctly discerned in the spectra of the doped xerogels with 400 ≥ <IT>n</IT> ≥ 30 (Fig. 5).</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The drastic reduction of the intensity of this feature in the Raman spectrum of the m-Ut(750)<SB>10</SB>Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB> material (Fig. 5) is consistent with the marked decrease in the relative amount of <IT>trans</IT> conformations that occurs at the expense of the increase of the proportion of <IT>gauche</IT> ones.</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">It should be stressed that these spectral results do not provide any information regarding the number of pendant oligopolyether chains of the monourethanesil structure that are used to coordinate each cation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Powder diffraction studies demonstrated that in the crystalline complexes POE<SB>3</SB>LiX (where X = CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit32a cit32b">32<IT>a</IT>,<IT>b</IT></REF> and N(SO<SB>2</SB>CF<SB>3</SB>)<SB>2</SB>, bis(trifluoromethanesulfonate)imide<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit32c">32<IT>c</IT></REF>), POE<SB>3</SB>NaClO<SB>4</SB><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit32b">32<IT>b</IT></REF> and POE<SB>4</SB>MSCN (where M = K, Rb and NH<SB>4</SB>)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit32b">32<IT>b</IT></REF> each polymer chain forms an isolated one-dimensional coordination complex.</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In all these structures the monovalent cations are located within the POE helix.</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">No ionic cross-linking was observed in any case.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit32a cit32b">32<IT>a</IT>,<IT>b</IT></REF> The structures were preserved on going from the crystalline to the amorphous state.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit32a cit32b">32<IT>a</IT>,<IT>b</IT></REF> There are no diffraction data available in the literature regarding POE-based complexes doped with Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">However, considering that the ionic radius of Eu<SP>3+</SP> lies between those of Li<SP>+</SP> and Na<SP>+</SP>, it seems logical to assume henceforth that “POE–Eu<SP>3+</SP> coordination” corresponds to the interaction of the lanthanide ion with several ether oxygen atoms of a single polymer chain.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">A third pronounced effect discerned in the Raman spectra reproduced in Fig. 5 helps to substantiate the formation of cation/polyether bonds in the most concentrated monourethanesil.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">It involves the growth of a series of bands between 925 and 885 cm<SP>–1</SP> in the two most concentrated samples as the content of guest lanthanide salt is increased (Fig. 5).</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">The curve-fitting performed on this region (not shown) allowed us to conclude that these new events are situated at approximately 918, 911 (shoulder), 907, 902, 896 and 893 cm<SP>–1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Furlani <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF>. also found a band centered at about 906 cm<SP>–1</SP> in the Raman spectra of PEG(400)-based electrolytes doped with Eu(N(SO<SB>2</SB>CF<SB>3</SB>)<SB>2</SB>)<SB>3</SB>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">We therefore conclude that the significant transformation of the spectral profiles in m-Ut(750)<SB>10</SB>Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB> are caused by an increase in the local order of the polymer segments arising from their interaction with the Eu<SP>3+</SP> ions and the formation of crystalline complexes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">It must be stressed that we cannot determine the extent of crystallization occurring in the system at <IT>n</IT> = 10.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">However the changes observed in the above discussed spectra unambiguously prove the presence of crystalline domains.</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore we tentatively describe the m-Ut(750)<SB>10</SB>Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB> xerogel as a material containing a significant fraction of crystalline phase(s).</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>Cation/cross-link interactions</HEADER><P><s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">We provided above strong arguments that support the claim that the cation coordination process that occurs in the m-Ut(750)-based xerogels containing Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB> closely resembles that reported for the long chain diureasil parent analogs U(2000)<SB><IT>n</IT></SB>Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10 cit11a">10,11<IT>a</IT></REF> Similarly to what happens in the latter compounds, in the monourethanesils examined in the present study the pendant methyl end capped polyether segments start to solvate the guest lanthanide ions near the cross-link saturation composition.</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">Another noteworthy similarity found between both hybrid systems is the formation of a crystalline compound at high salt content.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is important to note that the number of hydrogen donor sites present in the urethane and urea groups is not the same: the urethane linkage contains just one N–H group, whereas the urea moiety is composed of two N–H groups.</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">This implies that, while the CO moiety of a urethane group may form a single hydrogen bond with the N–H moiety of another urethane group, urea groups of neighboring molecules may be linked by means of planar bifurcated hydrogen bonds.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit33">33</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">As a consequence, the hydrogen bonding geometry of the urethane groups might be substantially different from that of the urea groups.</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Such situation resulted for instance in the tighter packing of adjacent chains observed in bis-urea compounds with respect to the bis-urethane analogues.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit33a">33<IT>a</IT></REF> The distance between the carbonyl carbon atoms of two adjacent urea molecules and two adjacent urethane molecules in these materials was found to be 4.63 and 5.10 Å, respectively.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit33a">33<IT>a</IT></REF> The hydrogen bonding behavior in the essentially amorphous diureasils and monourethanesils should be, however, quite different from that occurring in the compounds reported in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit33a">ref. 33<IT>a</IT></REF>, which are highly crystalline.</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">Indeed, the IR spectra demonstrate the presence of a large number of “free” CO groups in the matrices based on U(2000) and on the investigated m-Ut(750), as will be shown below.</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hence, we do not expect a significant difference in hydrogen bond strengths in both hybrid systems.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="New" advantage="None">To complete the description of the chemical environment around the lanthanide ions in the m-Ut(750)<SB><IT>n</IT></SB>Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB> hybrids, we will investigate in this section the spectral signature of these composites in the “amide I” and “amide II” regions, as it seems logical to presume that the Eu<SP>3+</SP> ions will very likely bond to the carbonyl oxygen atom of the urethane cross-links in the monourethanesil xerogels with 400 ≥ <IT>n</IT> ≥ 50.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa4" novelty="None" advantage="None">This study will enable us to assess in parallel the extent of hydrogen bonding in this family of xerogels.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Our analysis of the “amide I” and “amide II” bands of the Eu<SP>3+</SP>-doped monourethanesil compounds will take into account numerous spectroscopic studies of simple and segmented poly(urethane)s,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25">25</REF> of poly(urethane urea) copolymers<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26">26</REF> and of lithium-doped polymer electrolytes based on a thermoplastic polyurethane<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27a cit27b cit27c">27<IT>a</IT>–<IT>c</IT></REF> or a segmented polyether poly(urethane urea)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27d">27<IT>d</IT></REF> host.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>“Amide I” region</HEADER><P><s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The “amide I” region of poly(urethane)s<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25">25</REF> corresponds to the amide I region of polyamides.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit34">34</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The amide I mode (or simply, the carbonyl stretching mode) is a highly complex vibration that is comprised of a major contribution from the CO stretching vibration and less important contributions from the C–N stretching and C–C–N deformation vibrations.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit34">34</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">As the CO stretching vibration is sensitive to the specificity and magnitude of hydrogen bonding, the amide I envelope consists of several distinct components reflecting different environments of CO groups, usually termed as associations, aggregates or structures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hence quantitative analysis is feasible in the amide I region only if the difference in the absorption coefficients of the non-bonded and bonded carbonyl bands is taken into account.</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Band area determinations may be thus considered an adequate reflection of functional group concentration.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25d cit34">25<IT>d</IT>,34</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The “amide I” envelope of the salt-free m-Ut(750) matrix (Fig. 7) contains three distinct components centered at about 1750, 1720 and 1700 cm<SP>–1</SP> (Fig. 8).</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">The event observed near 1750 cm<SP>–1</SP> is inherent to urethane cross-links free from hydrogen bonding interactions, <IT>i.e.</IT>, urethane linkages whose N–H and CO groups remain non-bonded (Scheme 1, <B>A</B>).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25">25</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the basis of previous works,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25">25</REF> we propose that the 1720 cm<SP>–1</SP> feature is related to the absorption of hydrogen-bonded CO groups in disordered aggregates (urethane–polyether association of Scheme 1, <B>B</B>) and that the component at 1700 cm<SP>–1</SP> corresponds to the absorption of CO groups included in a much more ordered hydrogen-bonded aggregate (urethane–urethane association illustrated in Scheme 1, <B>C</B>).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 7 provides unequivocal evidence that the addition of the lanthanide salt to the m-Ut(750) hybrid matrix produces a series of pronounced changes in the “amide I” region.</annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None">In general terms, we may state that, as the amount of guest salt rises, the center of gravity of the whole “amide I” profile shifts toward lower frequencies, suggesting that the strength of the hydrogen bonds globally increases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the spectra of the monourethanesils with high salt concentration a new component located at 1665 cm<SP>–1</SP> emerges.</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs19" novelty="None" advantage="None">With the increase of Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB> content, while the intensity of this feature is markedly enhanced, that of the 1750 cm<SP>–1</SP> mode, originated from free CO groups, is significantly reduced.</annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs20" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the spectrum of the rich-salt material with <IT>n</IT> = 10 the 1665 cm<SP>–1</SP> band becomes the most prominent event and the 1750 cm<SP>–1</SP> peak disappears.</annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The spectral findings just described sustain the hypothesis that the Eu<SP>3+</SP> ions coordinate to the carbonyl oxygen atoms of the urethane cross-links over the whole range of composition studied.</annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None">Another conclusion that may be immediately drawn from the spectra reproduced in Fig. 7 is that the band position of the three components of m-Ut(750) situated at about 1750, 1720 and 1700 cm<SP>–1</SP> is totally unaffected by salt doping.</annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Van Heumen <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27b">27<IT>b</IT></REF> also observed this effect in lithium triflate-based thermoplastic polyurethanes.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Because of the lability of hydrogen bonds, it was fundamental to study the evolution of the spectra of the monourethanesils as a function of temperature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res29" novelty="None" advantage="None">As the spectra recorded at three different temperatures (see Experimental section) are coincident in the “amide I” region, we may deduce that below 85 °C the disordered and ordered hydrogen-bonded aggregates of the m-Ut(750)<SB><IT>n</IT></SB>Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB> hybrids are totally insensitive to temperature, a proof of their stability.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="Old" advantage="None">To gather additional information of the modifications undergone by the characteristic modes of the “amide I” region of the monourethanesil xerogels upon inclusion of increasing amounts of the triflate salt, we performed curve-fitting in the 1800–1630 cm<SP>–1</SP> frequency envelope.</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The complex spectral profiles were decomposed into Gaussian bands.</annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs21" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results obtained with three representative doped samples are illustrated in Fig. 8.</annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res30" novelty="None" advantage="None">The composition dependence of the area of the bands at 1750, 1720, 1700 and 1665 cm<SP>–1</SP> is shown in Fig. 9.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 9 allows to infer that the presence of a growing amount of Eu<SP>3+</SP> ions in the monourethanesil system has several important consequences:</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res32" novelty="None" advantage="None">(1) From <IT>n</IT> = 400 to 30 the fraction of non-bonded CO groups is progressively reduced.</annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res33" novelty="None" advantage="None">At <IT>n</IT> = 10 the 1750 cm<SP>–1</SP> event vanishes completely, indicating that no CO groups are left free.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res34" novelty="None" advantage="None">(2) In the 400 ≥ <IT>n</IT> ≥ 70 composition interval, the amount of hydrogen-bonded CO groups belonging to disordered regions increases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res35" novelty="None" advantage="None">At higher salt concentration, a considerable amount of these aggregates are, however, disrupted.</annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res35" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the most concentrated xerogel only weak traces of the hydrogen-bonded associations <B>B</B> (Scheme 1) are found.</annotationART></s> <s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The drastic destruction of these urethane–polyether hydrogen-bonded structures at <IT>n</IT> = 10 derives most probably from the fact that, at this salt concentration, the polymer chains are being extensively required to interact with the cations and can no longer bond to the N–H groups of urethane cross-links <IT>via</IT> hydrogen-bonding.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res36" novelty="None" advantage="None">(3) The area of the feature at 1700 cm<SP>–1</SP> suffers an increase in hybrids with 400 ≥ <IT>n</IT> ≥ 90, but decreases rapidly upon further addition of Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">This abrupt loss of band area may be interpreted as a solid indication that the introduction of the guest salt deeply perturbs the ordered aggregates <B>C</B> (Scheme 1) of the monourethanesil samples, presumably leading to their breakdown.</annotationART></s> <s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res37" novelty="None" advantage="None">A minor proportion of such hydrogen-bonded structures remains at <IT>n</IT> = 10.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs22" novelty="None" advantage="None">(4) In compounds with 70 ≥ <IT>n</IT> ≥ 30 a new component, that gradually grows with the increase of salt content, appears at approximately 1665 cm<SP>–1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs22" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the “amide I” spectral region of m-Ut(750)<SB>10</SB>Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB> this band becomes dominant.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The trend demonstrated by the various components of the “amide I” envelope of the monourethanesils confirms that the most concentrated xerogel studied is subject to a tremendous structural transition as a result of the formation of the crystalline polyether/lanthanide salt complex.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The nature of the species that give rise to the intense 1665 cm<SP>–1</SP> feature is unknown at this stage.</annotationART></s> <s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Because of its low frequency, we feel tempted to speculate that it is associated with highly ordered, strongly hydrogen-bonded aggregates, formed at the expense of the breakdown of practically all the previously existent ones (associations <B>B</B> and <B>C</B> of Scheme 2).</annotationART></s> <s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res38" novelty="None" advantage="None">The regular increase of this band with the increase of salt content reveals that the new hydrogen-bonded aggregates are strongly coordinated to the Eu<SP>3+</SP> ions.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is instructive to comment that the interpretation proposed for the “amide I” region of the monourethanesil materials relies essentially on the fact that the host hybrid m-Ut(750) matrix is only slightly hygroscopic, a result of the utmost relevance, since it indicates that in the doped samples the main species responsible for the presence of water is the guest lanthanide salt, owing to the typical great water affinity of the Eu<SP>3+</SP> species.</annotationART></s> <s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None">This explains why the almost complete removal of water from the salt-containing compounds could be easily accomplished through classical procedures, such as drying under vacuum at room temperature (see Experimental section), as confirmed by the low intensity of the characteristic broad OH stretching envelope in the high-frequency region of the FT-IR spectra reproduced in Fig. 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res39" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus any contribution of the water bending mode, which appears typically near 1640 cm<SP>–1</SP> in pure water, to the 1665 cm<SP>–1</SP> feature found in the “amide I” envelope of the m-Ut(750)<SB><IT>n</IT></SB>Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB> xerogels with <IT>n</IT> lower than 70 is considered to be negligible.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>“Amide II” region</HEADER><P><s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The “amide II” mode of poly(urethane)s is akin to the amide II feature of polyamides.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit34">34</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The amide II band (which is often simply designated as the N–H in-plane bending, <IT>δ</IT><SB>i.p.</SB> NH, band) is a mixed mode containing a major contribution from the N–H in-plane bending vibration and minor contributions from the C–N stretching and C–C stretching vibrations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is sensitive to both chain conformation and intermolecular hydrogen bonding and adequately reflects the distribution of hydrogen bond strenghts.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit34">34</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="143"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs23" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the spectra of the m-Ut(750)<SB><IT>n</IT></SB>Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB> xerogels with ∞ &gt; <IT>n</IT> ≥ 30 the “amide II” mode appears as a single broad, medium to weak band centered at approximately 1534 cm<SP>–1</SP> (Fig. 7).</annotationART></s> <s sid="144"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs24" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the spectrum of m-Ut(750)<SB>10</SB>Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB> the same feature undergoes a dramatic shift to 1568 cm<SP>–1</SP> (Fig. 7).</annotationART></s> <s sid="145"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs25" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the whole range of salt concentration analyzed we do not detect any indication of the presence of separate contributions presumably originated from hydrogen-bonded associations of various degrees of order (Fig. 7).</annotationART></s> <s sid="146"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs26" novelty="None" advantage="None">Moreover, there is no evidence for a distinct free component.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="147"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res40" novelty="None" advantage="None">The marked upshift of the “amide II” feature observed at <IT>n</IT> = 10 confirms that in this monourethanesil sample hydrogen bonding is much stronger than in the more dilute ones.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11a">11<IT>a</IT></REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="148"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res41" novelty="None" advantage="None">The coincidence of the “amide II” region of the spectra recorded at three different temperatures for each composition (see Experimental section) leads us to state that at temperatures lower than 85 °C the “amide II” mode of the monourethanesil is a temperature independent event.</annotationART></s> <s sid="149"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res41" novelty="None" advantage="None">This finding is consistent with the behavior of the materials in the “amide I” region.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2">Differential scanning calorimetry</HEADER><P><s sid="150"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Rich information regarding cation/polyether complexation may be obtained from DSC measurements.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="151"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In polymer electrolytes the interaction between the cations and the ether oxygen atoms of the polymer chains is known to be accompanied by the formation of transient ionic cross-links that partially arrest the local motion of the adjacent solvating segments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="152"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="Old" advantage="None">As a consequence the glass transition temperature, <IT>T</IT><SB>g</SB>, of the host polymer is shifted to higher temperatures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="153"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">This effect may be quite dramatic in the case of rich-salt compounds.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="154"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res42" novelty="None" advantage="None">The dependence of the <IT>T</IT><SB>g</SB> of the m-Ut(750)<SB><IT>n</IT></SB>Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB> monourethanesils with composition is in accordance with the spectroscopic data presented above.</annotationART></s> <s sid="155"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs27" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 6 clearly shows that, as expected, the <IT>T</IT><SB>g</SB> of the hybrid matrix (–48 °C) remains nearly constant in samples with <IT>n</IT> &gt; 30.</annotationART></s> <s sid="156"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res43" novelty="None" advantage="None">This result confirms once more that the pendant oligopoly(oxyethylene) chains of m-Ut(750) are not involved in the coordination of the lanthanide ions in this range of composition.</annotationART></s> <s sid="157"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res44" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, the same plot provides conclusive evidence that in xerogels with <IT>n</IT> = 30 and 10, Eu<SP>3+</SP>/polymer bonding occurs, leading to a marked increase of the <IT>T</IT><SB>g</SB> of the polyether segments (17 and 76 °C, respectively) (Fig. 6).</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3">Photoluminescence spectroscopy</HEADER><P><s sid="158"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res45" novelty="None" advantage="None">The photoluminescence studies carried out give reliable support to the spectroscopic results discussed in Section 1.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="159"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs28" novelty="None" advantage="None">The 14 K emission spectra obtained for the m-Ut(750)<SB><IT>n</IT></SB>Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB> monourethanesils with <IT>n</IT> = 200, 60 and 30 at the excitation wavelength that maximizes the cation luminescence intensity are reproduced in Fig. 10.</annotationART></s> <s sid="160"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res46" novelty="None" advantage="None">These spectra are composed of a series of yellow–red sharp lines-assigned to intra-4f transitions between the <SP>5</SP>D<SB>0</SB> and the <SP>7</SP>F<SB>0–4</SB> levels<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6a cit9a cit9e">6<IT>a</IT>,9<IT>a</IT>,<IT>e</IT></REF>-that overlap a large broad band in the purple–blue–green region.</annotationART></s> <s sid="161"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res47" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of the most dilute sample examined here (<IT>n</IT> = 200), an intra-4f self-absorption, attributed to the <SP>7</SP>F<SB>0</SB> → <SP>5</SP>D<SB>2</SB> transition, is also observed (marked with an asterisk in Fig. 10).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="162"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="Old" advantage="None">It was recently demonstrated that the broad emission which already appears in the emission spectra of the non-doped diureasil and diurethanesil host frameworks<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9d cit11b">9<IT>d</IT>,11<IT>b</IT></REF> may be expressed by the convolution of a long-lived emission from the NH groups of the urea and urethane bridges, respectively, with a short-lived component originated from electron–hole recombinations occurring in the siliceous domains.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9d">9<IT>d</IT></REF> The maximum intensity energetic position of the hybrid host emission and its relative intensity with respect to the Eu<SP>3+</SP> lines strongly depend on the amount of guest salt incorporated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="163"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs29" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 10 shows, not only that the energy band of the m-Ut(750)<SB>200</SB>Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB> xerogel is red-shifted with respect to those of the more concentrated compounds, but also that its intensity is greater than that of the ion lines.</annotationART></s> <s sid="164"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res48" novelty="None" advantage="None">We may also infer from Fig. 10 that an increase in the salt concentration from <IT>n</IT> = 200 to 30 induces an inversion in the relative intensity of the emission of the hybrid host and that of the Eu<SP>3+</SP> ions, since the yellow–red lines become clearly more intense in the spectrum of the salt-rich material.</annotationART></s> <s sid="165"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs30" novelty="None" advantage="None">Nevertheless, variations on salt content do not affect the Eu<SP>3+</SP> intra-4f lines:<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6a cit9a cit9b cit9e">6<IT>a</IT>,9<IT>a</IT>,<IT>b</IT>,<IT>e</IT></REF> the energy, shape or relative intensity of the observed transitions remain unchanged (Fig. 10).</annotationART></s> <s sid="166"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None">These observations substantiate the presence of a similar cation local coordination site within the entire concentration range considered.</annotationART></s> <s sid="167"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, as the <SP>5</SP>D<SB>0</SB> → <SP>7</SP>F<SB>2</SB> forced electric-dipole transition is stronger than the <SP>5</SP>D<SB>0</SB> → <SP>7</SP>F<SB>1</SB> magnetic-dipole one, we are led to conclude that the point symmetry group of the Eu<SP>3+</SP> ions in the m-Ut(750)-based monourethanesils does not have an inversion center,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit35">35</REF> a finding that completely discards the occurrence of a first coordination sphere for the lanthanide ions exclusively composed of water molecules.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit36">36</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="168"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None">This extremely important result is in perfect agreement with our claim that the local chemical environment of the cations in the m-Ut(750)<SB><IT>n</IT></SB>Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB> composites includes, apart from a minor number of oxygen atoms of water molecules, oxygen atoms from three different species: the urethane carbonyl moieties (in the whole range of salt composition analyzed here), the polymer oxyethylene units (in samples with <IT>n</IT> ≤ 30) and the triflate ions (see Part 2 of this series of papers).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="169"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The decrease in the relative intensity of the host broad band with respect to the Eu<SP>3+</SP> lines observed as the amount of Eu<SP>3+</SP> is increased from <IT>n</IT> = 200 to 30, already reported for similar organic/inorganic hybrids,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9a cit9b cit9e cit10a">9<IT>a</IT>,<IT>b</IT>,<IT>e</IT>,10<IT>a</IT></REF> may be explained in terms of energy transfer between the emitting centers of the matrix (donors) and the lanthanide ions (acceptors).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9e">9<IT>e</IT></REF> The energy transfer mechanism associated with the host emission component resulting from the photoinduced proton-transfer between urethane groups is enhanced as a consequence of the progressive suppression of the hydrogen bonds that occurs with the increase of salt content (as demonstrated in section 1), which leads to a delocalization of the proton, rendering the induced proton transfer between NH groups easier.</annotationART></s> <s sid="170"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None">This effect is manifested in the emission spectra through a decrease in the relative host broad band intensity.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Conclusions</HEADER><P><s sid="171"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Monourethane cross-linked poly(oxyethylene)/siloxane hybrids incorporating a wide range of europium triflate, Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB>, concentration (∞ ≥ <IT>n</IT> ≥ 10, where <IT>n</IT> is the molar ratio of (OCH<SB>2</SB>CH<SB>2</SB>) repeat units per Eu<SP>3+</SP> ion) were investigated by means of several techniques to study the cation/polymer, cation/cross-link and hydrogen bonding interactions.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="172"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The analysis of the specific vibrational modes of the POE chains, as well as of the “amide I” and “amide II” frequency envelopes, characteristic of the urethane cross-links, provided strong evidences that in these materials the coordination of the lanthanide ions takes place in the following way: (1) at <IT>n</IT> &gt; 30 the cations interact exclusively with the carbonyl oxygen atoms of the urethane linkages; (2) at <IT>n</IT> = 30 the cations start to bond to the oxygen atoms of the polyether chains; (3) at <IT>n</IT> &lt; 30 a dramatic breakdown of the matrix hydrogen-bonded aggregates occurs caused by cation entrapment; (4) at salt composition <IT>n</IT> = 10 a crystalline polymer/salt complex is formed.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="173"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res49" novelty="None" advantage="None">Photoluminescence spectroscopy clearly confirmed conclusion (3).</annotationART></s> <s sid="174"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res50" novelty="None" advantage="None">The composition dependence of the glass transition temperature of the xerogels studied corroborated conclusion (4).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="175"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The role of the anion in the coordinating behavior of the monourethanesils will be examined in Part 2 of this series of papers.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Experimental</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Synthesis</HEADER><P><s sid="176"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="Old" advantage="None">3-Isocyanatepropyltriethoxysilane (ICPTES, Fluka) and poly(ethylene glycol) methyl ether (PEGME, Aldrich, average molecular weight = 750) were used as received. tetrahydrofuran (THF, Merck) and ethanol (CH<SB>3</SB>CH<SB>2</SB>OH, Merck) were stored over molecular sieves.</annotationART></s> <s sid="177"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Europium(iii) trifluoromethanesulfonate (Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB>, Aldrich) was dried under vacuum at 90 °C for several days prior to being used.</annotationART></s> <s sid="178"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="Old" advantage="None">High purity distilled water was used in all experiments</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="179"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met14" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The preliminary stage of the preparation of the Eu<SP>3+</SP>-doped monourethanesils involved the formation of a covalent urethane linkage between the terminal hydroxyl group of a poly(ethylene glycol) methyl ether molecule containing about 17 oxyethylene units, PEGME(750), and the isocyanate group of an alkoxysilane precursor, ICPTES (Scheme 2).</annotationART></s> <s sid="180"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met15" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The second stage of the synthesis implied the addition of water and ethanol, to start to hydrolysis and condensation reaction characteristic of the sol–gel chemistry (Scheme 2).</annotationART></s> <s sid="181"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met16" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The nomenclature m-Ut(750)<SB><IT>n</IT></SB>Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB> was adopted to identify the final materials.</annotationART></s> <s sid="182"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met17" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Xerogels with <IT>n</IT> = 400, 200, 90, 70, 60, 50, 30 and 10 were prepared.</annotationART></s> <s sid="183"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met17" novelty="Old" advantage="None">An undoped sample, designated as m-Ut(750), was also obtained.</annotationART></s></P><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>Step 1: synthesis of the monourethanesil precursor, m-UtPTES(750)</HEADER><P><s sid="184"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met18" novelty="Old" advantage="None">PEGME(750) (2.5 g, 3.3 mmol) was dissolved in THF (10 mL) by stirring.</annotationART></s> <s sid="185"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met18" novelty="Old" advantage="None">ICPTES (0.823 mL, 3.3 mmol) was added to this solution in a fume cupboard.</annotationART></s> <s sid="186"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met18" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The flask was then sealed and the solution stirred for 24 h at moderate temperature (≈70 °C).</annotationART></s> <s sid="187"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res51" novelty="None" advantage="None">The structure of the transparent polydisperse oil obtained in such conditions, designated as monourethanepropyltriethoxysilane (m-UtPTES(750)), was confirmed by <SP>1</SP>H NMR, IR and HR-MS (FAB).<SP>1</SP>H NMR (400.13 MHz, CDCl<SB>3</SB>, 25 °C, TMS): <IT>δ</IT> 3.79 (q, <SP>3</SP><IT>J</IT>(H,H) = 7 Hz, 6H, H<SP>d</SP>), 3.72–3.52 (m, 68H, H<SP>g</SP>), 3.36 (s, 3H, H<SP>f</SP>), 3.18–3.12 (m, 2H, H<SP>c</SP>), 1.62–1.57 (m, 2H, H<SP>b</SP>), 1.22–1.18 (m, 9H, H<SP>e</SP>), 0.62–0.58 (m, 2H, H<SP>a</SP>); IR (KBr): 1716, 1660 cm<SP>–1</SP> (<IT>ν</IT>(CO)), 1533 cm<SP>–1</SP> (<IT>δ</IT><SB>i.p.</SB>(NH)); HR-MS (FAB) M + H<SP>+</SP>: found 984.570282, calc.</annotationART></s> <s sid="188"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res51" novelty="None" advantage="None">984.577463 for C<SB>43</SB>H<SB>90</SB>NO<SB>21</SB>Si (H<SB>3</SB>C(OCH<SB>2</SB>CH<SB>2</SB>)<SB>16</SB>O(CO)NH(CH<SB>2</SB>)<SB>3</SB>Si(OCH<SB>2</SB>CH<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB>).</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>Step 2: synthesis of the monourethanesils, m-Ut(750)<SB><IT>n</IT></SB>Eu(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB></HEADER><P><s sid="189"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met19" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Ethanol (0.776 ml, 13.3 mmol), an appropriate mass of EU(CF<SB>3</SB>SO<SB>3</SB>)<SB>3</SB> (Table 2) and water (90 µl, 5 mmol) were added to the m-UtPTES(750) solution prepared in the first stage of the synthesis procedure (molar proportion 1 ICPTES∶4 CH<SB>3</SB>CH<SB>2</SB>OH∶1.5 H<SB>2</SB>O).</annotationART></s> <s sid="190"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met19" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The mixture was stirred in a sealed flask for 30 min and then cast into a Teflon mould which was covered with Parafilm and left in a fume cupboard for 24 h.</annotationART></s> <s sid="191"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met19" novelty="Old" advantage="None">After a few hours gelation was already visible.</annotationART></s> <s sid="192"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met19" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The mould was transferred to an oven at 60 °C and the sample was aged for a period of 4 weeks.</annotationART></s> <s sid="193"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs31" novelty="None" advantage="None">Transparent monolithic xerogels with a yellowish coloration were formed.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Differential scanning calorimetry</HEADER><P><s sid="194"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">A disk section with a mass of approximately 40 mg was removed from the monourethanesil film, placed in a 40 µL aluminium can and introduced in a dessicator over phosphorus pentaoxide for at least 12 h at room temperature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="195"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">After this drying treatment the can was hermetically sealed and the thermogram of the sample was recorded with a DSC131 Setaram Differential Scanning Calorimeter equipped with a liquid-nitrogen cooling accessory.</annotationART></s> <s sid="196"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The purge gas used was high purity nitrogen supplied at a constant 35 cm<SP>3</SP> min<SP>–1</SP> flow rate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="197"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The sample was first cooled to –110 °C at 10 °C min<SP>–1</SP> and then heated up to 150 °C at the same heating rate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="198"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">It was then quenched to –110 °C at 20 °C min<SP>–1</SP> and finally heated to 150 °C at 10 °C min<SP>–1</SP>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Fourier transform IR spectroscopy</HEADER><P><s sid="199"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">FT-IR spectra were acquired under vacuum at room temperature and 40 and 85 °C using a Bruker IFS-66V Fourier transform spectrometer connected to an Oxford cryostat system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="200"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The spectra were collected over the range 4000–400 cm<SP>–1</SP> by averaging at least 150 scans at a resolution of 2 cm<SP>–1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="201"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The temperature of the samples was held constant for about 25 min before the measurement was initiated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="202"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Solid samples (2 mg) were finely ground, mixed with approximately 175 mg of dried potassium bromide (Merck, spectroscopic grade) and pressed into pellets.</annotationART></s> <s sid="203"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Prior to recording the spectra the discs were kept in an oven under vacuum at 90 °C for several days in order to reduce the levels of adsorbed water.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="204"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">To evaluate complex band envelopes and to identify underlying component bands of the spectra, the iterative least-squares curve-fitting procedure in the Peakfit<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit37">37</REF> software was used extensively throughout this study.</annotationART></s> <s sid="205"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The best fit of the experimental data were obtained by varying the frequency, bandwidth and intensity of the bands.</annotationART></s> <s sid="206"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Gaussian band shapes were employed.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Fourier transform Raman spectroscopy</HEADER><P><s sid="207"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The FT-Raman spectra were recorded at room temperature with a Bruker IFS-66 spectrometer equipped with a FRA-106 Raman module and a near-IR YAG laser with wavelength 1064 nm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="208"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The spectra were collected over the 3200–300 cm<SP>–1</SP> range at a resolution of 2 cm<SP>–1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="209"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The accumulation time for each spectrum was 4 h.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Photoluminescence spectroscopy</HEADER><P><s sid="210"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The emission spectra were recorded at room temperature using a 0.25 m KRATOS GM-252 excitation monocromator and a 1 m 1704 SPEX Czerny–Turner spectrometer coupled to a Hamamatsu R928 photomultiplier.</annotationART></s> <s sid="211"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">A 300 W xenon arc lamp was used as excitation source.</annotationART></s> <s sid="212"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">All the spectra were corrected for the spectral response of the detector.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
