<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b310952f" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Excimer probe of the binding of alkyl disulfides to gold nanoparticles and subsequent monolayer dynamics<XREF TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" /></annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">A symmetric alkyl disulfide bearing two pyrenyl chromophores allows for fluorescence monitoring of its binding to gold nanoparticles and the subsequent diffusion of the geminate thiolates on the particle surface.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER /><P><s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Metal nanoparticles protected by self-assembled monolayers (monolayer-protected clusters, MPCs) attract attention from a wide range of disciplines.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2 cit3 cit4">1–4</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">These hybrid systems indeed show a number of interesting features.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The protecting monolayer can be chemically modified, making these clusters suitable platforms for combining different functions into one entity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Another aspect of MPCs is the possibility of observing special photonic effects on attached chromophores, such as enhanced optical absorption and/or emission.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6">5,6</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">These effects are associated with the plasmon resonance of the electrons in the metal core.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Functionalised MPCs offer the potential to study such effects in chemically and structurally well-defined systems in solution using a variety of spectroscopic techniques.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In search of plasmon-related effects on chromophores on the surface of MPCs, we are interested in developing simple and flexible procedures to insert fluorescent chromophores as dopants into <IT>n</IT>-alkanethiol monolayers assembled on the surface of different types of metal nanoparticles.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The nanoparticles that we chose to begin with are “naked particles”,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF> a suspension of ∼5 nm diameter gold nanoparticles in toluene, stabilised by 0.04 M tetra-<IT>n-</IT>octylammonium bromide (TOAB).</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The suspension is obtained by the classical Brust method,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF> but omitting the thiol.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Naked particles can be functionalised afterwards by suitable thiols and disulfides, which are not exposed to the reaction conditions under which the metal particles themselves are formed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Because of their relatively large size, naked particles display a clear plasmon resonance (<IT>λ</IT><SB>max</SB> (toluene) = 528 nm) in their optical absorption spectrum.</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The suspensions have a deep red colour.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="None" advantage="Yes">As a model fluorescent dopant for self-assembled <IT>n</IT>-alkanethiol monolayers, we have synthesised disulfide <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem1">1</XREF> using commercially available 1-pyrenemethanol.<SUP TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn2" /> A concomitant advantage of the pyrenyl chromophore is that it offers the possibility to probe the binding of disulfides to nanoparticles and subsequent monolayer dynamics through its excimer emission.</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Pyrene-coated gold nanoparticles have been synthesised recently by the Brust method in the presence of pyrenyl-modified alkanethiols.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10 cit11 cit12 cit13">10–13</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="No">In these cases, the pyrene chromophores are present in high concentrations on the particle surface, potentially complicating their photophysics.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Very recently, Montalti <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF>. studied the displacement of thiols from the particle surface by observing the recovered pyrene monomer emission of fluorophores liberated from the surface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the present work, we show that the emission of symmetric disulfide <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem1">1</XREF> (Scheme 1) provides a new way of studying the binding of molecules to metal surfaces <IT>and</IT> their subsequent dynamics on these surfaces.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Disulfide <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem1">1</XREF> itself shows, in addition to pyrene monomer emission, a distinct intramolecular excimer band in its emission spectrum (Fig. 1, solid line).</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The intramolecular nature of this band is confirmed by its presence even at very low concentrations (10<SP>–7</SP> M) and by the fact that its relative intensity does not vary with concentration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The excimer band disappears in vitrified media (<IT>e.g.</IT> in methylcyclohexane at 77 K), and also when <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem1">1</XREF> is exposed to dithiothreitol, a well-known disulfide cutting reagent.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">We studied the binding of <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem1">1</XREF> to “naked” gold nanoparticles by fluorescence spectroscopy.<SUP TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn3" /> The molecule was mixed with larger amounts of di-<IT>n</IT>-octyldisulfide (typical ratio 5 ∶ 95 <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem1">1</XREF> ∶ <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem2">2</XREF>) to have it inserted as a dilute dopant in the particle protecting monolayer.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Starting from a naked particle solution, we synthesised MPCs coated either with a monolayer of 100% of di-<IT>n-</IT>octyl disulfide<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF><XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem2">2</XREF>, Au<SB><IT>n</IT></SB>(<XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem2">2</XREF>)<SB>1.00<IT>m</IT></SB>, or with a monolayer consisting of 95 mol% of <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem2">2</XREF> and 5 mol% <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem1">1</XREF>, Au<SB><IT>n</IT></SB>(<XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem2">2</XREF>)<SB>0.95<IT>m</IT></SB>(<XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem1">1</XREF>)<SB>0.05<IT>m</IT></SB>, by adding a tenfold<SUP TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn4" /> excess of disulfides.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">After one week, the volume of the solution was reduced by evaporating the toluene.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The functionalised particles were precipitated using isopropanol.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">After centrifugation, the supernatant was replaced with fresh isopropanol, and centrifugation was continued.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">This was repeated four times to wash away any remaining free ligand and TOAB.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of Au<SB><IT>n</IT></SB>(<XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem2">2</XREF>)<SB>0.95<IT>m</IT></SB>(<XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem1">1</XREF>)<SB>0.05<IT>m</IT></SB> complete removal of excess ligand was apparent from the absence of fluorescence in the two last isopropanol washings.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">After drying, the particles were redissolved in toluene and stored as such.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The UV/Vis spectra (see ESI<SUP TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" />) of Au<SB><IT>n</IT></SB>(<XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem2">2</XREF>)<SB>1.00<IT>m</IT></SB> and Au<SB><IT>n</IT></SB>(<XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem2">2</XREF>)<SB>0.95<IT>m</IT></SB>(<XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem1">1</XREF>)<SB>0.05<IT>m</IT></SB> are almost identical, except for the presence of typical pyrene related peaks (<IT>e.g.</IT> at 346 nm) in the spectrum of the latter particles.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">We observe a broad band (<IT>λ</IT><SB>max</SB> (toluene) = 528 nm) which originates from the surface plasmon resonance of the nanoparticles and whose shape is typical of thiol-modified gold nanoparticles.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Compared to the TOAB-stabilised naked particles, the plasmon of the passivated particles is less pronounced and located at slightly shorter wavelength, which agrees with the presence of thiols on the particle surface.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Interestingly, the fluorescence emission spectrum of Au<SB><IT>n</IT></SB>(<XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem2">2</XREF>)<SB>0.95<IT>m</IT></SB>(<XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem1">1</XREF>)<SB>0.05<IT>m</IT></SB> displays (Fig. 1, dashed line) a significantly altered excimer/monomer emission intensity ratio with respect to parent compound <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem1">1</XREF>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This may have several causes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The excimer emission might be selectively quenched by the metal particle core, or excimer formation may be suppressed in the monolayer on the particle surface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">It might also be that <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem1">1</XREF> dissociates after chemisorption and that the geminate thiolates migrate over the particle surface, eventually yielding isolated pyrene chromophores that do not form excimers.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">To gain more insight into this, we carried out titration experiments in which small aliquots of naked particle solution were added to solutions containing a mixture of <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem1">1</XREF> and <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem2">2</XREF> (ratios 1 ∶ 99–5 ∶ 95, total disulfide concentration 1.5 µM).</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The series of spectra in Fig. 2 shows that immediately after each addition of naked particles both monomer and excimer emission intensities are diminished.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The pyrene singlet excited state is quenched to a certain extent upon binding of <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem1">1</XREF> to gold nanoparticles, diminishing monomer fluorescence as well as the formation of excimers from this state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reduced amount of excimers formed, then, is further quenched by the nanoparticles diminishing the excimer emission intensity even more than the monomer emission.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Pyrenyl chromophores may be quenched by charge transfer to the metal particle core,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF> but energy transfer is also likely to play a role in the fluorescence quenching near metal nanoparticles.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The titration curve, obtained by plotting the integrated excimer intensity (470–670 nm) as a function of nanoparticle concentration, first descends with constant slope and then appears to slowly level off as the particle concentration is increased.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since all disulfides are expected to be rapidly and irreversibly chemisorbed by the added nanoparticles,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF> one would expect a curve that decreases with constant slope until all disulfides are bound, and then abruptly changes into a horizontal line.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The observed leveling-off suggests that the rapid chemisorption step is followed by a secondary, slower process.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The time between two additions (and hence between points in the titration curve) is about 10 minutes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">If the secondary process is not complete within this time, the shape of the titration curve may be altered.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 3 confirms that such a process is indeed present.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Immediately after addition of 1 equivalent<SUP TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn4" /> of particles, both monomer and excimer emission intensities are diminished, but as time goes by, an <IT>increase</IT> in monomer intensity is observed, accompanied by a <IT>decreasing</IT> excimer intensity.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">A plausible mechanism for the increasing monomer emission at the expense of excimer emission is a migration of the pyrenyl chromophores over the surface of the nanoparticles (Scheme 2).</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Such a mechanism is in accordance with observations by Boal and Rotello<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19">19</REF> who were able to use the migration of thiolates on gold nanoparticles to obtain self-optimised binding sites on the particle surface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="Old" advantage="None">On flat gold surfaces, diffusion of thiolates has also been observed, mainly by scanning tunneling microscopy,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20 cit21 cit22">20–22</REF> and more recently by voltammetry.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The present work indicates that excimer probes such as <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem1">1</XREF> might provide a rapid, simple and non-destructive method for gaining more information on thiolate diffusion on metal surfaces.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">A question remains why there is still some excimer fluorescence present in the emission spectrum of the 5 mol%-doped Au<SB><IT>n</IT></SB>(<XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem2">2</XREF>)<SB>0.95<IT>m</IT></SB>(<XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem1">1</XREF>)<SB>0.05<IT>m</IT></SB> particles.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">To verify our guess that this is due to a fraction of the pyrenyls still being statistically close enough to form excimers, we examined nanoparticles covered by protecting monolayers containing different doping levels of pyrenyl-modified thiolates.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">At the 1 mol% doping level, no observable excimer fluorescence remains, but as the surface concentration increases excimer fluorescence shows up (Fig. 4).</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The pyrenyl-thiolates still do migrate after chemisorption but this does not prevent them having other pyrenyl groups in their vicinity at high doping concentration.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The pyrene excimer is a well-known probe of molecular dynamics, and here we present indications that it may be used in the study of the dynamics of self-assembled monolayers on metallic nanoparticles in solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The excimer emission of <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem1">1</XREF> enables us to probe migration on the molecular scale, averaged over a large number of copies of the same system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">This averaging makes it a valuable tool to obtain kinetic data on the dynamics of thiolates on metallic surfaces.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The method may be extendable to planar metal surfaces, where the data could perhaps be combined with single-molecule data from scanning tunneling microscopy.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The migration of pyrenyl-labelled thiolates suggests that the disulfide bond is cleaved upon chemisorption to the metal surface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Evidence from surface-enhanced Raman (SERS) studies of disulfides on silver is in line with cleavage of the S–S bond.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast, grazing incidence X-ray diffraction studies suggest that chemisorbed thiols and disulfides exist as disulfides on the metal surface.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25">25</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Such bound disulfides, however, need not have the same chemical properties as disulfides in solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Exchange between neighbouring disulfide pairs on the surface may be a mechanism leading to thiol migration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None">There exists considerable controversy on the way thiols and disulfides are bound to metal surfaces.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Studies on metal nanoparticles in solution (such as those in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26">ref. 26</REF>) may give more insight on the chemical nature of gold–sulfur bonds and their dynamics.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the perspective of putting isolated fluorophores at a well-defined distance from the surface of metallic particles, an interesting result is that starting from symmetric disulfides bearing two chromophores it is still possible to obtain isolated chromophores at the surface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, at doping levels as low as 5 mol% interchromophoric interactions, in this case leading to excimer emission, already start to show up for dopant molecule <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem1">1</XREF>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Further work elaborating on the present findings is in progress.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
