<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b314692h" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Zeta potential and photocatalytic activity of nitrogen doped TiO<SB>2</SB> thin films</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Nitrogen doped TiO<SB>2</SB> films were fabricated by annealing anatase TiO<SB>2</SB> films in gaseous NH<SB>3</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Nitrogen atoms in these films were substitutionaly introduced into oxygen sites of TiO<SB>2</SB> lattice.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have evaluated the zeta potential of these films and have found that it became negative with the amount of nitrogen doping.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The photocatalytic decomposition of gaseous 2-propanol was examined under light-limited conditions, and the quantum yield (QY) was estimated while illuminating with ultraviolet (UV) and visible light (VIS).</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The QY values for the nitrogen doped TiO<SB>2</SB> film were 15.4% (UV) and 0.41% (VIS), whereas those for the pure TiO<SB>2</SB> film were 18.4% (UV) and 0% (VIS).</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In addition, the photocatalytic decomposition of ethylamine ions (CH<SB>3</SB>CH<SB>2</SB>NH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP>) was evaluated in an aqueous solution under UV illumination in a light-rich condition.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Consequently, the decomposition rate of the nitrogen doped TiO<SB>2</SB> for aqueous ethylamine ions was higher than that of the pure TiO<SB>2</SB> because the surface of the nitrogen doped TiO<SB>2</SB> film was negatively charged and cationic ethylamine ions were efficiently adsorbed on its surface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">The surface structure and the band structure of the nitrogen doped TiO<SB>2</SB> are discussed in this paper.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">When UV light is illuminated on TiO<SB>2</SB>, electron and hole pairs are generated in it and they reduce and oxidize adsorbates on the surface, respectively.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2 cit3 cit4">1–4</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Moreover, we recently reported that the surface of TiO<SB>2</SB> becomes highly hydrophilic under UV illumination.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6 cit7">5–7</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">A great deal of research has been conducted on these reactions and various TiO<SB>2</SB> coated substrates have been applied to water and air purification,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit9 cit10">8–10</REF> anti-bacterial agents,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF> and self-cleaning surfaces.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12 cit13">12,13</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus far, these techniques are mainly applied to outdoor use since the photocatalytic reaction for these applications requires sufficient UV source, which is typically provided by the sun.</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The band gap of TiO<SB>2</SB> (anatase) is 3.2 eV and the photocatalytic reaction proceeds under the UV illumination with wavelengths shorter than <IT>λ</IT> &lt; 380 nm, which corresponds to the band gap energy.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Numerous studies have attempted to extend the photosensitivity of TiO<SB>2</SB> towards the visible light region by coupling with organic dye sensitizers<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14 cit15">14,15</REF> or metal oxides,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16 cit17 cit18 cit19 cit20">16–20</REF> by doping with transition metals,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21 cit22 cit23">21–23</REF> and by reducing with hydrogen.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Recently, visible light responses have been reported by nitrogen doping into a TiO<SB>2</SB> lattice.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25">25</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">R. Asahi <IT>et al.</IT> have reported that the substitutional doping of nitrogen into TiO<SB>2</SB> lattice is effective because the N-2p states help narrow the band-gap by mixing with O-2p states.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26 cit27">26,27</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Using first-principle calculations and X-ray photoemission spectroscopy, they concluded that nitrogen doping into substitutional sites of TiO<SB>2</SB> is indispensable for band-gap narrowing and photocatalytic activity.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25">25</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">We previously reported the photocatalytic activities of nitrogen doped TiO<SB>2</SB> powders under visible light and have concluded that the isolated N-2p narrow band above the O-2p valence band is responsible for the visible light response, when nitrogen is lightly doped (up to about 1%) into oxygen sites.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28 cit29">28,29</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Nitrogen doping into TiO<SB>2</SB> lattice effectively controls the electric structure and is expected to control the surface structure of TiO<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="New" advantage="None">The present paper focuses on the zeta potential of nitrogen doped TiO<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The zeta potential depends on the atomic arrangement of TiO<SB>2</SB> surface and is crucial in controlling the adsorption properties of TiO<SB>2</SB> surfaces.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None">Substitutionally nitrogen doped TiO<SB>2</SB> films are fabricated and the zeta potentials and photocatalytic oxidation activities are evaluated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="New" advantage="None">The surface and the band structures of nitrogen doped TiO<SB>2</SB> are also discussed.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Experimental</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Preparation of thin films</HEADER><P><s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Pyrex glass plates coated with SiO<SB>2</SB> were used as substrates for preparing thin films.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Prior to coating the films, the substrates were ultrasonically degreased in ethanol for 30 min and then thoroughly rinsed with distilled water.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">These substrates were dipped into a titanium tetraisopropoxide solution (NDH-510C, Nihon Soda Co., Tokyo, Japan) and were slowly removed from the solution at a fixed rate of 15 cm min<SP>−1</SP> under dry nitrogen.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">These samples were calcined at 500 °C for 30 min in air to obtain pure TiO<SB>2</SB> films with anatase phase.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The dip-coating and calcination procedures were repeated six times, which yielded films <IT>ca</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">600 nm thick.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Afterwards, the films were annealed in gaseous ammonia (NH<SB>3</SB>) for 1 h at 400, 600, or 700 °C.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Characterization</HEADER><P><s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The crystal phases of the thin films were evaluated by the grazing angle method of X-ray diffraction with Cu Kα rays (XRD: model RINT-2100, Rigaku Co., Tokyo, Japan).</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The incident angle was fixed at 0.5° and 2<IT>θ</IT> was scanned in the range of 10–70°.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The surface morphologies and cross sections of thin films were observed using a scanning electron microscope (SEM: model S-4200, Hitachi Co., Tokyo, Japan).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">X-ray photoelectron spectroscopy with Mg Kα X-rays (XPS: model AXIS-HS, Kratos, Manchester, UK) evaluated the amount and states of the nitrogen atoms in these films.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The photoelectrons of the N-1s, Ti-2p, O-1s and C-1s orbitals were recorded with a takeoff angle of 45°.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The internal reference for the absolute binding energy was the C-1s peak of hydrocarbon contamination at 284.8 eV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The integrated peak areas of each orbital were calculated after subtracting the non-linear background.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Quantitative analysis was based on the peak area multiplied by sensitivity factors supplied by Kratos, which considered the geometric configuration of the apparatus.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, the depth profiles of each element in the thin film were measured, following Ar<SP>+</SP> ion sputtering with a 4.5 kV beam voltage.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ultraviolet-visible absorption spectra of the thin films were recorded on a spectrophotometer (UV-3100, Shimadzu Co., Kyoto, Japan).</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The absorption percentage (<IT>α</IT>, %) was obtained by measuring the transmittance (<IT>T</IT>, %) and reflectance (<IT>R</IT>, %) of the thin films, where <IT>α</IT> = 100 − (<IT>T</IT> + <IT>R</IT>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">A 60 mm integrating sphere was used for the measurement, since the scattering effect was taken into account for the film absorption.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The zeta potentials of the thin film surfaces were measured by the monitor particle method<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30">30</REF> using an electrophoretic light scattering spectrophotometer (ELS-6000, Otsuka Electronics Co., Oosaka, Japan).</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp9" novelty="None" advantage="None">A quartz cell was used to measure the electrophoretic mobility of polystylene latex reference particles, which had an average diameter of 520 nm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The cell was filled with a NaCl aqueous solution (0.1 mmol dm<SP>−3</SP>) containing latex reference particles.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The pH value was adjusted using aqueous solutions of NaOH (0.1 mmol dm<SP>−3</SP>) and HCl (0.1 mmol dm<SP>−3</SP>).</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Photocatalytic activities</HEADER><P><s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The photocatalytic activities of the thin films were evaluated by monitoring the decomposition of gaseous 2-propanol in air (25 °C).</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="None" advantage="Yes">2-Propanol was selected as the reactant because the oxidation of 2-propanol to acetone can determine the quantum yield.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit31">31</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="Old" advantage="None">A thin film, 70 × 50 mm, was placed in a 0.8 dm<SP>3</SP> Pyrex glass vessel.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="Old" advantage="None">An O<SB>2</SB>(20%)–N<SB>2</SB>(80%) gas mixture, which was passed through a 30 °C water humidifier in order to adjust the relative humidity to 50%, was filled in a vessel.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The headspace (20 cm<SP>3</SP>) of glass bottle reservoir, which contained liquid 2-propanol, was injected into the Pyrex glass vessel using a syringe.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The initial concentration of 2-propanol was adjusted to 120 ppm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The photocatalytic decomposition of gaseous 2-propanol was evaluated while illuminating with ultraviolet (UV) and visible (VIS) light.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp10" novelty="None" advantage="None">A 10-W black light bulb (Toshiba Co., Tokyo, Japan) provided the UV illumination.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The source for VIS illumination was a 250 W xenon lamp (LA-250Xe, Hayashi Watch-works Co. Ltd., Tokyo, Japan), which was used in conjunction with an optical fiber coupler, an UV cutting filter (Y-43, Toshiba Co. Ltd., Tokyo, Japan) and an IR cutting filter (V-40, Toshiba Co. Ltd., Tokyo, Japan).</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The number of absorbed photons in each film was fixed at 2.0 × 10<SP>14</SP> (quanta s<SP>−1</SP> cm<SP>−2</SP>) regardless of the illumination source.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The amount of absorbed photons (<IT>I</IT><SB>a</SB>) was determined by eqn. (1). where <IT>I</IT><SB>0</SB> and <IT>α</IT> are the incident photon flux and the absorption percentage, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The incident photon flux (<IT>I</IT><SB>0</SB>) was measured by a spectro-radiometer (USR-40D, Ushio Co., Tokyo, Japan) and the absorption percentage (<IT>α</IT>) was obtained from UV-Vis spectra.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The concentrations of 2-propanol, acetone, and carbon dioxide (CO<SB>2</SB>) were measured by a photoacoustic multi-gas monitor (model 1312, Innova, Ballerup, Denmark), which had a detection limit of approximately 0.1 ppm.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The photocatalytic decomposition of ethylamine ions (CH<SB>3</SB>CH<SB>2</SB>NH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP>) in an aqueous solution was also evaluated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Thin films were immersed in an aqueous solution of ethylamine ions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="Old" advantage="None">After bubbling N<SB>2</SB> through the solution for 30 min, ultraviolet light illuminated the films.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp14" novelty="None" advantage="None">A capillary electrophoresis system (HP-3D, Hewlett Packard Co., California, USA) measured the concentration of ethylamine ions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The initial concentration of ethylamine ions was 10 ppm and the pH value of solution was 5.5 (20 °C).</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The UV illumination was provided by a 10-W black light bulb (Toshiba Co., Tokyo, Japan).</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The light intensity of UV illumination was 0.5 mW cm<SP>−2</SP> or 1.0 mW cm<SP>−2</SP>, measured by a spectro-radiometer (USR-40D, Ushio Co., Tokyo, Japan).</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Results and discussion</HEADER><P><s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 1 shows XRD patterns for the thin films.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The crystal structures of pure TiO<SB>2</SB> and the nitrogen doped TiO<SB>2</SB> films annealed in NH<SB>3</SB> below 600 °C all exhibited a single anatase phase.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Annealing NH<SB>3</SB> at 700 °C, however, changed the nitrogen doped TiO<SB>2</SB> crystal phase to the cubic TiN phase.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 2 shows SEM images for the surface of the thin films and the cross sections of pure TiO<SB>2</SB> (<IT>E</IT>) and TiN film (<IT>F</IT>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Regardless of the annealing temperature in gaseous NH<SB>3</SB>, the surfaces exhibited nearly identical surface morphologies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The diameters of TiO<SB>2</SB> particles were approximately 30 nm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The films, which were 600 nm thick, were homogeneously deposited on glass substrates without cracks or pinholes.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">To investigate the doping density and state of nitrogen atoms, XPS spectra for N-1s band were measured (Fig. 3).</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">A peak with the binding energy of 396 eV was observed for the nitrogen doped TiO<SB>2</SB> films and the peak intensity depended on the annealing temperature in NH<SB>3</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">It has been reported that the peak at 396 eV is assigned to Ti–N bonding, whereas the peaks at 402 and 404 eV are assigned to molecularly chemisorbed N<SB>2</SB>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit32">32</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Prior to our XPS measurement, the surface of thin films was etched by Ar<SP>+</SP> ion sputtering for 1 min, which eliminated chemisorbed or physisorbed N<SB>2</SB> molecules on the surface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The XPS results indicate that the nitrogen atoms in the thin films were substitutionally doped into oxygen sites of TiO<SB>2</SB> lattice.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The doping densities of nitrogen atoms <IT>versus</IT> titanium atoms (N/Ti atom %) were 0% (pure TiO<SB>2</SB>), 0.9% (NH<SB>3</SB> 400 °C), 2.3% (NH<SB>3</SB> 600 °C), 36.4% (NH<SB>3</SB> 700 °C).</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The depth profiles of the nitrogen atoms in these films were evaluated using Ar<SP>+</SP> ion sputtering, which indicated that the oxygen atom sites were homogeneously substituted by nitrogen atoms.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 4 shows the absorption spectra of thin films.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Nitrogen doped TiO<SB>2</SB> films (annealed in NH<SB>3</SB> at 400 °C and 600 °C) had shoulder peaks in the visible light region around 390–450 nm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The pure TiO<SB>2</SB> film does not absorb the visible light since the band gap of anatase type TiO<SB>2</SB> is 3.2 eV.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit33">33</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The TiN film was not transparent, owing to its metallic property.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 5 shows the surface zeta potential <IT>versus</IT> pH for a pure TiO<SB>2</SB> film and a film annealed in NH<SB>3</SB> at 600 °C.</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The pH of the isoelectric point (IEP) for the pure TiO<SB>2</SB> film was 5.8.</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The IEP for anatase TiO<SB>2</SB> particles were previously determined by other procedures and ranged from 5.1 to 6..7<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit34 cit35 cit36 cit37">34–37</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, the value of the pure TiO<SB>2</SB> in the present paper is consistent with those measured by other procedures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the zeta potential of a nitrogen doped TiO<SB>2</SB> film negatively shifted and the IEP decreased.</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Table 1 lists the zeta potentials for each film at a pH of 5.5.</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">When the crystal phase remained anatase TiO<SB>2</SB>, the zeta potentials became more negative as the amount of nitrogen doping increased.</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">When the crystal phase was transformed to the cubic TiN phase, the zeta potential, however, aproached zero potential (−4.65 mV) at a pH of 5.5.</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Previous studies reported that the IEP for TiN particles ranged from 4.0 to 5..0<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit38 cit39 cit40">38–40</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, the IEP of the TiN film in the present study is consistent with the literature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is noteworthy that the surface zeta potentials of the nitrogen doped TiO<SB>2</SB> films were more negative than that of pure TiO<SB>2</SB>, which indicates that the surface of nitrogen doped TiO<SB>2</SB> films was highly acidic.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is known that OH groups on the TiO<SB>2</SB> surface at terminal sites and those at bridging sites act as basic and acidic sites, respectively.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit41">41</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reported p<IT>K</IT><SB>a</SB> value for OH groups at the terminal sites of TiO<SB>2</SB> is 12.7 and that for OH groups at bridging sites is 2..9<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit34 cit42">34,42</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Previous studies also reported that amounts of OH groups at terminal sites and those at bridge sites are nearly identical.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit43 cit44">43,44</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, the IEP of TiO<SB>2</SB> is a neutral value and the TiO<SB>2</SB> exhibits amphoteric properties.</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The surface of nitrogen doped TiO<SB>2</SB> films in this study, however, was highly acidic.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 6 shows a possible surface structure for nitrogen doped TiO<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our XPS results indicated that the oxygen sites in the TiO<SB>2</SB> lattice were substituted by the doped nitrogen atoms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Previous studies have reported that OH groups at terminal sites act as Brønsted acid sites on a TiO<SB>2</SB> surface.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit45">45</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The strength of the O–H bonds strongly affects the surface acidity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The strength between O–H bonding on metal oxides depends on the electronegativity of the metal ions, <IT>i.e.</IT> the strength between O–H bonding depends on the polarization of covalent electron pairs.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit46 cit47">46,47</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is presumed that the N–H bonding is weaker than the O–H bonding since the electronegativity of nitrogen (3.0) is less than oxygen (3.5).</annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, the N–H sites of the nitrogen doped TiO<SB>2</SB> surface act as acidic sites.</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to fully discuss the surface acidity of nitrogen doped TiO<SB>2</SB>, a comprehensive study on the states and amount of OH or NH groups should be conducted.</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results of zeta potentials obtained in the present study, however, indicate that nitrogen atoms play an important role in controlling the surface adsorptive properties.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj5" novelty="New" advantage="None">Next, we have evaluated the photocatalytic decomposition of gaseous 2-propanol under light-limited conditions,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit31">31</REF> to estimate the efficiency for the photocatalytically charged separation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs20" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 7 shows the concentration changes of gaseous 2-propanol, acetone, and CO<SB>2</SB> for a pure TiO<SB>2</SB> film under UV illumination.</annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met14" novelty="Old" advantage="None">After 30 min, which was the time required for equilibrium between gaseous and adsorbed 2-propanol to be achieved, UV light illumination was initiated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs21" novelty="None" advantage="None">The amount of generated acetone was equivalent to the amount of decomposed 2-propanol and very little CO<SB>2</SB> was produced.</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs22" novelty="None" advantage="None">The amount of CO<SB>2</SB> was too small and insignificant to be considered.</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The oxidation reaction from 2-propanol to acetone is not a chain reaction.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit48 cit49">48,49</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met15" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Hence, the quantum yield (QY) was calculated using eqn. (2). </annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met15" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The number of absorbed photons obtained from eqn. (1) was fixed at 2.0 × 10<SP>14</SP> (quanta s cm<SP>−2</SP>) under UV as well as VIS illumination.</annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Table 2 lists the QY.</annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">When illuminating with UV light, the pure TiO<SB>2</SB> film exhibited the highest QY and the QY decreased as the extent of nitrogen doping increased.</annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Creating electron hole recombination centers such as oxygen vacancies<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit50">50</REF> caused the decrease in QY under UV illumination because the annealing procedure in a gaseous NH<SB>3</SB> atmosphere is very reductive.</annotationART></s> <s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs23" novelty="None" advantage="None">Due to the metallic properties of the TiN film, which was obtained by annealing in NH<SB>3</SB> at 700 °C, it did not display photocatalytic activity even under UV illumination.</annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs24" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast, when illuminating with VIS light, the nitrogen doped TiO<SB>2</SB> films exhibited photocatalytic activity, but the pure TiO<SB>2</SB> film did not.</annotationART></s> <s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the QY values under VIS illumination were much lower than those obtained with UV illumination, although the number of absorbed photons was identical regardless of the illumination source.</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">These results indicate that the photogenerated holes produced by the VIS light are localized at isolated levels between the valence and conduction bands.</annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">If the N-2p levels were mixed with O-2p orbital and the band-gap narrowed, then the photogenerated holes in the valence band would diffuse to the upper edge of the valence band by a radiative process.</annotationART></s> <s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">In these conditions, the oxidation power of photogenerated holes was supposed to be identical for both UV and VIS illumination.</annotationART></s> <s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, our experimental data exhibited that the QY of the nitrogen doped TiO<SB>2</SB> film under VIS illumination was much lower than that under UV illumination.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">One possible speculation for the origin of the visible light activity is the oxygen vacancies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">A previous study reported that oxygen vacancy states of TiO<SB>2</SB> are located between 0.75 to 1.18 eV, which is below the minimum level of the conduction band.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit51">51</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, the reduced TiO<SB>2−<IT>x</IT></SB> can absorb a broad range of visible light above 500 nm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs25" novelty="None" advantage="None">Indeed, nitrogen doped TiO<SB>2</SB>, which was annealed in NH<SB>3</SB> at 600 °C, absorbed visible light above 500 nm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The QY value under UV illumination was much lower than the pure TiO<SB>2</SB> because the oxygen vacancies act as electron-hole recombination centers.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit50">50</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs26" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast, nitrogen doped TiO<SB>2</SB> annealed in NH<SB>3</SB> at 400 °C and pure TiO<SB>2</SB> did not display optical absorption above 500 nm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The UV-Vis spectrum of this film showed an absorption shoulder in the visible light region (390–450 nm), indicating that the absorption shoulder was due to isolated levels that consisted of N-2p orbitals in the band gap of TiO<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met16" novelty="Old" advantage="None">We previously reported the optical absorption properties and QY values for nitrogen doped TiO<SB>2</SB> powders and concluded that the isolated narrow band of N-2p orbitals, which is formed above the valence band, is responsible for the visible light activity.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29">29</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 8 shows the assumed band structure of nitrogen doped TiO<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The isolated levels of the N-2p orbitals are situated above the valence band.</annotationART></s> <s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, holes produced by the VIS illumination are localized and have a slower mobility than those produced by UV illumination.</annotationART></s> <s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Consequently, the photocatalytic activity under VIS illumination is much lower than that under UV illumination.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although the QY of the nitrogen doped TiO<SB>2</SB> under VIS illumination was much lower than that under UV illumination, we have found the intriguing property of its surface acidity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The surface acidity plays an important role in determining its adsorptive property.</annotationART></s> <s sid="143"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met17" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Finally, we have evaluated the photocatalytic decomposition of aqueous ethylamine ions (CH<SB>3</SB>CH<SB>2</SB>NH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP>) under light-rich conditions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="144"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs27" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 9 shows the changes in ethylamine ions under UV illumination for pure TiO<SB>2</SB> and nitrogen doped TiO<SB>2</SB> (annealed in NH<SB>3</SB> at 400 °C).</annotationART></s> <s sid="145"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met18" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Previous studies reported that TiO<SB>2</SB> photocatalyst could decompose ethylamine ions and produce several intermediates.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit52">52</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="146"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met19" novelty="Old" advantage="None">It has also been reported that these intermediates could be completely mineralized into CO<SB>2</SB>, H<SB>2</SB>O, and HNO<SB>3</SB> under UV illumination.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit52">52</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="147"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met19" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In the previous study, the decomposition rate of the nitrogen doped TiO<SB>2</SB> film was faster than those of the pure TiO<SB>2</SB> film.</annotationART></s> <s sid="148"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met19" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In either film the decomposition rate was independent of the light intensity, indicating that the photocatalytic reaction proceeds under light-rich condition.</annotationART></s> <s sid="149"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs28" novelty="None" advantage="None">As listed in Table 1, the zeta potentials at pH of 5.5 for pure TiO<SB>2</SB> and nitrogen doped TiO<SB>2</SB>, which was annealed at 400 °C, were +15.5 and −46.9 mV, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="150"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">The p<IT>K</IT><SB>a</SB> value of ethylamine is 10.63, thus almost all the ethylamine molecules (CH<SB>3</SB>CH<SB>2</SB>NH<SB>2</SB>) were dissociated into ethylamine ions (CH<SB>3</SB>CH<SB>2</SB>NH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP>) in an aqueous solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="151"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">Ethylamine ions are positively charged in an aqueous solution at a pH of 5.5 and are supposed to be preferentially adsorbed onto the negatively charged surface of the nitrogen doped TiO<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="152"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">The concentration of ethylamine ions was very low (10 ppm), thus, the photocatalytic decomposition of these ions was provided by the light-rich conditions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="153"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">Under light-rich conditions, decomposition rates depend on the adsorptive property on the surface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="154"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, it is reasonable that the decomposition rate of the nitrogen doped TiO<SB>2</SB> was higher than that of the pure TiO<SB>2</SB> under UV illumination, even though the QY value of the nitrogen doped TiO<SB>2</SB> (15.4%) obtained by the oxidation reaction of gaseous 2-propanol was slightly less than that of the pure TiO<SB>2</SB> (18.5%) under UV illumination with the light-limited conditions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="155"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">These results are quite interesting from not only a scientific standpoint, but also from an industrial one.</annotationART></s> <s sid="156"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Besides ethylamine ions, it is possible that nitrogen doped TiO<SB>2</SB> can decompose other compounds and this photocatalyst has potential applications in water or air purification.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Conclusion</HEADER><P><s sid="157"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have fabricated nitrogen doped TiO<SB>2</SB> films and have discovered that their zeta potentials became negative with the amount of nitrogen doping.</annotationART></s> <s sid="158"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The zeta potential of photocatalysts plays an important role in the adsorption property of aqueous contaminants.</annotationART></s> <s sid="159"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met20" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The effects of negatively charged nitrogen doped TiO<SB>2</SB> surfaces were investigated by evaluating the photocatalytic decomposition of aqueous cations (CH<SB>3</SB>CH<SB>2</SB>NH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP>) under UV illumination with light-rich conditions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="160"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">The decomposition rate of nitrogen doped TiO<SB>2</SB> was higher than that of the pure TiO<SB>2</SB> because aqueous cations preferentially adsorbed onto the negatively charged surface of nitrogen doped TiO<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="161"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None">To date surface state details of nitrogen doped TiO<SB>2</SB> are unclear, but are currently under intensive investigation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="162"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The present study, however, is quite valuable because it has the potential for scientific and industrial applications.</annotationART></s> <s sid="163"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Nitrogen doped TiO<SB>2</SB> can efficiently adsorb the cations, owing to its negatively charged surface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="164"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, it is possible that this unique material will be used for water or air purification.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
