<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b314764a" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Surface micelles of semifluorinated alkanes in Langmuir–Blodgett monolayers<XREF TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" /></annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">We have studied the molecular patterns formed in Langmuir–Blodgett (LB) films of semifluorinated alkanes C<SB><IT>n</IT></SB>F<SB>2<IT>n</IT>+1</SB>C<SB><IT>m</IT></SB>H<SB>2<IT>m</IT>+1</SB> (F<IT>n</IT>H<IT>m</IT> diblocks, <IT>n</IT> = 6, 8, 10, <IT>m</IT> = 14, 16, 18, 20) by atomic force microscopy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">All the compounds investigated formed surface micelles whose shape and dimensions varied with the molecular structure of the F<IT>n</IT>H<IT>m</IT> diblocks.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Except for F6H16 and F8H14, which produced exclusively circular micelles, all of the other diblocks also formed elongated micelles that coexisted with circular micelles.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The mean diameter of the circular micelles increased with the length of the hydrogenated segment of the diblocks.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">By contrast, increasing the length of the fluorinated segments did not have any detectable effect on the diameter.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The elongated micelles became more numerous and longer for longer F<IT>n</IT>H<IT>m</IT> (both the length of the hydrogenated and of the fluorinated segments had a strong effect).</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The surface pressure of transfer had an influence on the morphology of the elongated micelles, the latter becoming fewer and shorter for higher surface pressures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">A detailed X-ray reflectivity study conducted on F8H16 LB films showed that the hydrogenated segments are directed towards the silicon wafer, while the fluorinated segments point outwards toward the air.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">A disc-like model is proposed for the surface micelles.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Colloidal systems involving semifluorinated alkanes C<SB><IT>n</IT></SB>F<SB>2<IT>n</IT>+1</SB>C<SB><IT>m</IT></SB>H<SB>2<IT>m</IT>+1</SB> (F<IT>n</IT>H<IT>m</IT> diblocks) have recently focussed attention owing to their potential applications in the biological and materials sciences.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2">1,2</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">These nonpolar, nonetheless amphiphilic molecules were shown to impart specific properties (increased stability, reduced permeability, reduced fusion rate, <IT>etc.</IT>) to various colloidal systems of biological interest including vesicles (liposomes),<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3 cit4">3,4</REF> fluorocarbon-in-water emulsions<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6">5,6</REF> and hydrocarbon-in-fluorocarbon emulsions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">One of our objectives is to exploit the mutual antipathy between fluorinated and hydrogenated chains for the elaboration of nanopatterned surfaces.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Compression of Langmuir monolayers and Langmuir–Blodgett (LB) films of combinations of F<IT>n</IT>H<IT>m</IT> diblocks and phospholipids provided evidence for both lateral and vertical phase separation.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9 cit10">9,10</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Precise control of the shape, size and molecular organization of the molecular clusters decorating the solid substrates is necessary to achieve mastered construction of 2D supramolecular architectures.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Despite several studies conducted on Langmuir monolayers of semifluorinated alkanes,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11 cit12 cit13">11–13</REF> the molecular orientation of the diblock molecules at the air/water interface has remained controversial.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="None" advantage="None">We present here an investigation by atomic force microscopy (AFM) of the morphology of Langmuir monolayers of a series of F<IT>n</IT>H<IT>m</IT> diblocks (<IT>n</IT> = 6, 8, 10 and <IT>m</IT> = 14, 16, 18, 20) after transfer onto silicon wafers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The AFM images were analyzed using an image analysis software (Visilog®).</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Experimental section</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Materials</HEADER><P><s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">F<IT>n</IT>H<IT>m</IT> diblocks were synthesized according to <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">ref. 14</REF> and were thoroughly purified by repeated crystallization from acetone.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Their purity (&gt;99%) was determined by TLC, NMR and elemental analysis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Spreading solutions of F<IT>n</IT>H<IT>m</IT> (1 mmol L<SP>−1</SP>) were prepared in chloroform (analytical grade).</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Water was purified using a Millipore system (surface tension: 72.1 mN m<SP>−1</SP> at 20 °C, resistivity: 18.2 MΩ cm).</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Monolayer isotherms–monolayer transfer</HEADER><P><s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Surface pressure <IT>versus</IT> molecular area (<IT>π</IT>–<IT>A</IT>) isotherms were recorded on a Langmuir minitrough (Riegler &amp; Kirstein, Germany) equipped with two movable barriers (compression speed: 0.1 nm<SP>2</SP> min<SP>−1</SP>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The surface pressure π was measured using the Wilhelmy plate method.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Temperature was regulated at 20.0 ± 0.5 °C.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">25 μL of F<IT>n</IT>H<IT>m</IT> solution were spread on the water surface and 5 min were allowed for solvent evaporation.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The monolayers were compressed up to the desired surface pressure and transferred onto a silicon wafer treated with piranha solution (conc. H<SB>2</SB>SO<SB>4</SB> + 30% H<SB>2</SB>O<SB>2</SB> 3∶1), using the LB technique (one monolayer transferred, lift speed of 5 mm min<SP>−1</SP>).</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>AFM images–X-ray reflectivity</HEADER><P><s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The transferred films were analyzed with an atomic force microscope (NanoScope III) in tapping mode.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The cantilever (Olympus) was fitted with a very sharp tip (5 nm).</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The resonance frequency was 300 kHz and the spring constant 42 mN m<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The digitized AFM images were analyzed with Visilog® Image Analysis Software (Noesis, France) using filtering techniques, a morphological gradient method, mathematical morphology functions, and adaptive thresholding.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The grazing incidence X-ray studies of the transferred films of F8H16 were performed with an EXPERT-MPD device from Philips (divergence slit 1/32°, parallel plate collimator, flat Ge monochromator and Xe detector).</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">A Cu Kα beam at wavelength 0.1542 nm was used.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The data were analyzed using Parratt32 software (version 1.6.0)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Results and discussion</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="1.">Surface pressure–molecular area (<IT>π</IT>–<IT>A</IT>) compression isotherms of F<IT>n</IT>H<IT>m</IT> diblocks</HEADER><P><s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The isotherms of the F<IT>n</IT>H<IT>m</IT> diblocks investigated indicate that, except for F6H16, the shortest diblock, which is also the less fluorinated one, all the other diblocks form stable Langmuir monolayers (Fig. 1), as shown in .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">ref. 11</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The longer the F<IT>n</IT>H<IT>m</IT> molecule, the higher the surface pressure of collapse, <IT>π</IT><SP>c</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Moreover, by comparing two diblocks of same length, the most fluorinated one gave the most stable monolayer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">For example, F10H16 had a higher <IT>π</IT><SP>c</SP> (∼22 mN m<SP>−1</SP>) than F8H18 (∼15 mN m<SP>−1</SP>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">All the monolayers formed by the F<IT>n</IT>H<IT>m</IT> diblocks (except F6H16) had a similar extrapolated molecular area of about 0.31 nm<SP>2</SP>, corresponding to the cross-section of a perfluorinated chain, which is larger than the cross-section of a typical hydrogenated chain (<IT>ca.</IT> 0.20 nm<SP>2</SP>).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Because the van der Waals radius of fluorine is larger than half the C–C bond distance, steric hindrance causes the chain to adopt a (15/7) helical conformation, and renders the carbon backbone rigid.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The isotherms were reversible, without hysteresis, upon compression–expansion cycles.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.">Influence of the F<IT>n</IT>H<IT>m</IT> molecular structure on the shape of the micelles: circular <IT>vs.</IT> elongated</HEADER><P><s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The monolayers of F<IT>n</IT>H<IT>m</IT> diblocks were investigated by AFM after transfer onto silicon wafers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">All the F<IT>n</IT>H<IT>m</IT> diblocks formed surface micelles.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Two-dimensional surface micelles have been visualized by AFM in monolayers of partially fluorinated carboxylic acids spread on a cadmium acetate subphase and transferred on cover glass.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19">19</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The shape and dimensions of the F<IT>n</IT>H<IT>m</IT> surface micelles varied with the molecular structure of the diblock.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">As illustrated in Fig. 2, some diblocks, <IT>e.g.</IT> F8H16, led principally to circular micelles, while in the AFM images of other diblocks (<IT>e.g.</IT> F8H20), elongated micelles that coexisted with circular micelles were clearly visible.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The variation of the sum area fraction of the long micelles, as determined by the image analysis software Visilog®, is plotted on Fig. 3a–c as a function of the lengths of the F<IT>n</IT> and Hm segments and of the total length of the diblock molecule.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The monolayers were transferred at 5 mN m<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results showed that the area fraction of the elongated micelles increased from 0 to 10% with the length of the diblock molecule.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both the lengths of F<IT>n</IT> and Hm segments had a strong effect.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Further studies are presently underway to determine whether the shape of the micelles is changing from circular to elongated, or whether circular domains coalesce to form elongated domains.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.">X-ray reflectivity study of F8H16 LB films</HEADER><P><s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although F6H16 and F8H14 exclusively produced circular micelles (Fig. 2), they did not lead to LB films stable enough to carry out an X-ray analysis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">F8H16 was therefore selected for this study because of the stability of its LB films, and because it led to a monodisperse population of circular micelles with only a very limited number of long micelles (fraction area of ∼3%).</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="New" advantage="None">The F8H16 monolayer, compressed at 7 mN m<SP>−1</SP>, was analyzed by X-ray specular reflectivity after transfer onto a silicon wafer.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19">19</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The experimental curve was fitted with a two-layer model that provided an excellent agreement with the data.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The electron density distribution of the two-layer model (Fig. 4) consisted of an upper layer with a thickness of 1.0 nm and an electron density of 487 e nm<SP>−3</SP> (a fluorinated layer) and of a lower layer with a thickness of 1.93 nm and an electron density of 290 e nm<SP>−3</SP> (a hydrogenated layer).</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The total thickness of the monolayer was 2.93 nm, close to the length of a fully extended F8H16 molecule (3.32 nm).</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">These results definitely demonstrate that the hydrogenated segments of the F8H16 molecules are directed toward the substrate, while the fluorinated segments are pointing outwards toward air.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Altogether, the results of the AFM and X-ray reflectivity showed that the size of the surface micelles is controlled by the density mismatch between the fluorinated and hydrogenated segments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">A disc-like shape model was proposed for the circular micelles formed by F8H16 (Scheme 1)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.">Influence of the F<IT>m</IT>H<IT>n</IT> molecular structure on the dimensions of the surface micelles</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="a.">Diameter of the circular micelles</HEADER><P><s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 5a–c displays the variations of the mean diameter of the circular micelles as a function of the lengths of F<IT>n</IT>, H<IT>m</IT>, and of the overall molecule.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The monolayers of F<IT>n</IT>H<IT>m</IT> diblocks were transferred at 5 mN m<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is noteworthy that, for a given length of the H<IT>n</IT> segment, increasing the length of the F<IT>n</IT> segment did not significantly influence the diameter of the micelles (Fig. 5a).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the other hand, the diameter of the circular micelles increased strongly with the H<IT>m</IT> segment length for a given F<IT>n</IT> length (Fig. 5b).</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">As a consequence, for a given carbon number, increasing the weight of the fluorinated part of the F<IT>n</IT>H<IT>m</IT> diblocks resulted in a decrease of the size of the micelles (Fig. 5c).</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="b.">Length of the elongated micelles</HEADER><P><s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 6a–c displays the variations of the length of the elongated micelles, as determined by Visilog®, as a function of the length of the F<IT>n</IT> segment, the length of the H<IT>m</IT> segment, and the overall length of the F<IT>n</IT>H<IT>m</IT> molecule.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">It can be seen that the longer the H<IT>m</IT> segment and/or F<IT>n</IT> segment, the longer the elongated micelles.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is noteworthy that both the hydrogenated and fluorinated segments have an impact on the length of the elongated micelles.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="5.">Influence of the surface pressure of transfer on the elongated micelles</HEADER><P><s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although the surface pressure of transfer, <IT>π</IT><SB>t</SB>, of the monolayer onto the silicon wafer had no significant influence on the diameter of the circular micelles,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF> it had a substantial impact on the morphology of the long micelles.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The higher <IT>π</IT><SB>t</SB>, the smaller the area fraction of the elongated micelles.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None">This was observed for both the sum area fraction (Fig. 7) and for the average area fraction of one single domain (data not shown).</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None">It was also observed that the higher <IT>π</IT><SB>t</SB>, the shorter the length of the elongated micelles (Fig. 8).</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">This suggests that the elongated micelles are transformed into circular micelles at high <IT>π</IT><SB>t</SB>, providing a more regular arrangement.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The long micelles may either break or curl to rearrange into circular micelles.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Conclusions</HEADER><P><s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have demonstrated that monolayers of semifluorinated alkanes C<SB><IT>n</IT></SB>F<SB>2<IT>n</IT>+1</SB>C<SB><IT>m</IT></SB>H<SB>2<IT>m</IT>+1</SB> (F<IT>n</IT>H<IT>m</IT>, <IT>n</IT> = 6, 8, 10, <IT>m</IT> = 14, 16, 18, 20) transferred onto silicon wafers consist of surface micelles.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The shape of the micelles, circular or elongated, depends on the F<IT>n</IT>H<IT>m</IT> molecular structure; the longer the H<IT>m</IT> segment, the larger the diameter of the circular micelles.</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">By contrast, the length of the F<IT>m</IT> segment does not influence the diameter significantly.</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The elongated micelles are more numerous and longer for the longer F<IT>n</IT>H<IT>m</IT>, both the F<IT>n</IT> and H<IT>m</IT> segments having a strong effect.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The surface pressure of transfer influences the shape and the length of the elongated micelles; the higher the surface pressure, the smaller their area fraction and the shorter their length.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">This work implicates that semifluorinated alkanes may be used to decorate surfaces with molecular clusters of controlled shape and predetermined size in the nanometer range.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
