<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b314882c" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Dissociative recombination of C<SB>2</SB>H<SP>+</SP> and C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP>: Absolute cross sections and product branching ratios</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Dissociative recombination (DR) of the hydrocarbon ions C<SB>2</SB>H<SP>+</SP> and C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP> has been examined at the heavy-ion storage ring CRYRING (Manne Siegbahn Laboratory, Stockholm, Sweden).</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Absolute DR cross sections were measured for center-of-mass collision energies between 1 meV and 0.1 eV for both ions, giving cross sections at 1 meV of 7.6 × 10<SP>−13</SP> cm<SP>2</SP> for C<SB>2</SB>H<SP>+</SP> and 1.7 × 10<SP>−12</SP> cm<SP>2</SP> for C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The dissociative recombination branching ratios were determined at minimal collision energy, showing that the carbon bond is broken in 57% of the dissociative recombination events for C<SB>2</SB>H<SP>+</SP>, while this happens in only 7% of the events for C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP>, three-particle breakup into C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>2</SB> and 2H is the dominant product channel with a branching ratio of 66%.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">The present results are compared with previous DR measurements made at CRYRING for DR of C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP> and C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP>.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Dissociative recombination (DR), the process whereby a molecular ion captures a free electron and then stabilizes the capture by dissociating into neutral fragments, plays an important role in determining the chemical composition of plasmas cold enough to contain a molecular component.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Kinetic modeling of such plasma environments requires knowledge of both the energy dependent DR cross sections and the product branching ratios.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">For most triatomic and larger systems, the rate constants for recombination are expected to be large (&gt;10<SP>−7</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> s<SP>−1</SP> at 300 K).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2">1,2</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Until recently, however, there has been little known about the product distributions that result from recombination.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Calculating the DR product branchings for polyatomic ions from first principles has proven to be exceedingly challenging, due to the difficulty of treating molecular dissociation of such a highly excited species along multidimensional potential surfaces.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ability to study DR reactions experimentally has improved considerably with the advent of storage rings<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3 cit4 cit5">3–5</REF> where both energy dependent rate constants and product distributions can be measured.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">We have examined the recombination of several small hydrocarbon ions at the CRYRING heavy ion storage ring.</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None">In this paper we present absolute cross sections and product branching ratios for the dissociative recombination of two hydrocarbon ions, C<SB>2</SB>H<SP>+</SP> and C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">The results are compared to previously reported measurements of C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP> and C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6 cit7">6,7</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="New" advantage="None">The significance of these results is discussed with respect to modeling the abundance of various molecular species in interstellar clouds<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF> and also to the modeling of plasma-enhanced combustion environments<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9 cit10">9,10</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Experiment</HEADER><P><s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The experiments were carried out at the heavy-ion storage ring CRYRING at the Manne Siegbahn Laboratory in Stockholm, Sweden.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The experimental apparatus has been described previously.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both ions were produced in a hot-cathode discharge ion source, using ethylene as the precursor compound, and extracted with a translational energy of 40 keV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">After mass selection, the ions were injected into the storage ring, which has a circumference of 51.6 m.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Using a radiofrequency accelerator system, the ions were further accelerated in the ring to 3.43 MeV (C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP>) and 3.84 MeV (C<SB>2</SB>H<SP>+</SP>), which is the maximum beam energy as limited by the magnetic rigidity of the ring.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ring's vacuum system maintained the pressure below 10<SP>−11</SP> torr, minimizing beam losses from collisions with residual gas molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The beam lifetime was in both cases measured to be 2.9 s.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">After acceleration, the ions were merged with a monoenergetic, magnetically-confined electron beam over a length of 85 cm in one of the 12 straight sections of the ring.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The transversal temperature of the electrons was reduced to about 1–2 meV in this electron cooler section <IT>via</IT> adiabatic expansion of the electron beam.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Heat is transferred from the ion beam to the electron beam, resulting in a reduction of the momentum spread of the ions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The 85 cm long interaction region also serves as the electron target during the recombination measurements.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The neutral products resulting from recombination were detected with ion implanted surface barrier detectors at a distance of approximately 3.4 m from the electron cooler.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">At that distance, it is possible for the transversal spread of the fragments to be larger than the radius of the 900 mm<SP>2</SP> detector; therefore, a larger detector with an area of 3000 mm<SP>2</SP> was also used.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although the larger detector has a higher collection efficiency, it has poorer energy resolution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The detector's output signal is proportional to the energy of the incoming particle, and this signal was amplified and read by a multichannel analyzer (MCA) to give a pulse height spectrum.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The count rate as a function of storage time was measured by recording the amplified signal by means of a multichannel scaler (MCS) <IT>via</IT> a single channel analyzer (SCA).</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Results</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Cross section measurements</HEADER><P><s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Cross section measurements were started 5 s after the ions were produced, which allowed time for the ions to relax into the ground vibrational state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">During this time, the electron energy was held at the cooling voltage, which implies zero center-of-mass collision energy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The center-of-mass energy, <IT>E</IT><SB>cm</SB>, can be deduced from the electron energy, <IT>i.e.</IT> cathode voltage, <IT>E</IT><SB><IT>e</IT></SB> through where <IT>E</IT><SB><IT>e</IT><SB>cool</SB></SB> is the laboratory electron energy at cooling, which is at minimal collision energy due to the energy spread.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In order to measure the dissociative recombination cross section, the cathode voltage was systematically detuned to give an energy relative to the ions of 1 meV to 1 eV in the center-of-mass frame.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">As shown in Fig. 1a, the cathode voltage was first increased rapidly from the cooling energy to a voltage corresponding to 1 eV center-of-mass collision energy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">It was then decreased linearly to a voltage below the cooling energy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The output from the MCS, shown in Fig. 1b, represents a measure of the DR signal from the detector.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the cathode voltage was detuned linearly, the time scale corresponds to the cathode voltage.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">At collision energies near 1 eV (times corresponding to 5 s and 6.5 s in Fig. 1), the DR cross section is very low.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Signals at those energies are considered to originate solely from background processes<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF> and were used to determine the exponential decay of the background, which was subtracted from the signal.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">During the cross section measurement, the ion current was intentionally kept low in order to prevent saturation of the surface barrier detectors.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Consequently, the ion current intensity could not be monitored directly during the measurement; instead, neutral fragments arising from collisions between the stored ion beam and the residual gas molecules were monitored with a scintillation detector, consisting of a BaF<SB>2</SB>-window and a photomultiplier tube, in another straight section of the storage ring.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">After the measurement with the surface barrier detectors, the ion current was increased and could then be measured directly with a current transformer, which essentially measures the weak magnetic field created by the stored ion beam, while the background was measured with the scintillation detector in the same way as during the previous measurement.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">These two background measurements could then be related to each other to give an absolute value for the cross section.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The experimental DR rate coefficient in the interaction region at a given center-of-mass energy, 〈<IT>vσ</IT>〉, is determined by where <IT>C</IT> is the circumference of the storage ring, <IT>l</IT> the length of the electron cooler, and <IT>n</IT><SB><IT>e</IT></SB> the electron density.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None"><IT>N</IT><SB>DR</SB> and <IT>N</IT><SB>b</SB> are the signals resulting from DR processes and background processes, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The destruction rate per ion per unit time, <IT>R</IT><SB>b</SB>, is given bywhere <IT>v</IT><SB>i</SB> is the velocity of the ions, and <IT>I</IT><SB>i</SB> is the ion current.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The absolute DR cross sections are obtained by dividing the measured rate coefficient by the electron velocity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The center-of-mass collision energy was corrected for the effect of electron space charge.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In the two toroidal sections of the electron cooler, where the electrons are steered in and out of the beam path, the collision energy is different than in the straight section.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Thus, some of the events measured at a specific center-of-mass energy actually result from processes occurring at other energies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Corrections have been made to account for this effect.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The measured cross sections for C<SB>2</SB>H<SP>+</SP> and C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP> are both shown in Fig. 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both ions exhibit large DR cross sections at low collision energy, with no resonances observed over the energy range from 1 to 100 meV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">At a collision energy of 1 meV, the cross sections are 7.6 × 10<SP>−13</SP> cm<SP>2</SP> and 1.7 × 10<SP>−12</SP> cm<SP>2</SP> for C<SB>2</SB>H<SP>+</SP> and C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP>, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The error bars indicate the statistical uncertainties.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">There are also systematic errors arising from the uncertainty in the length of the electron cooler, the circumference of the storage ring, the ion beam current, and the electron density.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">These combined errors are estimated to be 12%.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Integrating the energy dependent cross section, <IT>σ</IT>(<IT>E</IT><SB>cm</SB>), over an isotropic Maxwellian electron velocity distribution, gives the thermal rate coefficient <IT>α</IT> (in cm<SP>3</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>) as a function of the electron temperature <IT>T</IT><SB><IT>e</IT></SB>: The extracted thermal rate coefficients are shown in Fig. 3 for temperatures between 20 K and 1000 K. The 300 K rate coefficients for DR were found to be 2.7 × 10<SP>−7</SP> cm<SP>3</SP>s<SP>−1</SP> for C<SB>2</SB>H<SP>+</SP> and 5.6 × 10<SP>−7</SP> cm<SP>3</SP>s<SP>−1</SP> for C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP>, with both ions exhibiting a DR rate dependence on <IT>T</IT><SB><IT>e</IT></SB> of −0.76.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The error bars given in Fig. 3 originate from the statistical error of the cross section.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Branching ratio measurements</HEADER><P><s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the dissociative recombination of C<SB>2</SB>H<SP>+</SP> the following channels are energetically accessible: where the indicated kinetic energy release is the maximum, which assumes all products are formed in their ground state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP> ion, the following channels are energetically accessible: </annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In order to measure the branching ratios of the molecular ions as they dissociatively recombine with electrons into the various product channels shown above, a stainless steel grid with a transmission<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF> of 0.297 ± 0.015 was placed in front of the surface barrier detector.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The signal from the detector was recorded with an MCA to give the energy spectra shown in Figs. 4a and 5a for C<SB>2</SB>H<SP>+</SP> and C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP>, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The background signal, originating from collisions with the rest gas, is recorded with the electrons turned off.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">These spectra are shown in Figs. 4b and 5b.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Simultaneously with the two measurements for each ion, a background signal is recorded with the scintillation detector, making it possible to normalize the measurements and subtract the background.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The background-subtracted DR signals for C<SB>2</SB>H<SP>+</SP> and C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP> are shown in Figs. 4c and 5c, respectively.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met14" novelty="Old" advantage="None">From these spectra, it is possible to determine the amount of each neutral fragment detected by fitting the spectra to Gaussian curves and determining the area.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met14" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The energy scale is linear, and since the energy is proportional to the mass, each peak can be assigned to a particular fragment or sum of fragments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met14" novelty="Old" advantage="None">A set of linear equations is then used in order to assign the detected fragments to the different dissociation channels.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Consider the relatively straightforward example of C<SB>2</SB>H<SP>+</SP> shown in eqn. (5).</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fragments resulting from dissociation events in channel α pass through the grid with probability <IT>T</IT> (transmission) and are detected as 2C + H, 2C, or H with probabilities <IT>T</IT><SP>2</SP>, <IT>T</IT>(1 − <IT>T</IT>), and <IT>T</IT>(1 − <IT>T</IT>), respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The remaining channels are analyzed the same way, yielding the following probability matrix where <IT>N</IT>(2<IT>C</IT> + <IT>H</IT>) is the signal corresponding to detection of 2C + H fragments, and <IT>N</IT>(<IT>α</IT>) is the number of events occurring through channel <IT>α</IT>, <IT>etc.</IT> With the larger detector, the single hydrogen peak cannot be resolved, so that fragment is excluded from the analysis of the spectra.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met15" novelty="Old" advantage="None">As discussed above, not all the high-energy neutral fragments are collected with the smaller detector.</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met15" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In order to estimate the particle loss, a spectrum was recorded without the grid in front of the detector.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met15" novelty="Old" advantage="None">All neutral fragments originating from the same DR event should then appear at an energy corresponding to the full ion beam energy (3.43 MeV and 3.84 MeV respectively).</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met15" novelty="Old" advantage="None">However, in the case of lost hydrogen atoms the fragments are detected at a slightly lower energy corresponding to the ion beam energy minus the energy of a hydrogen atom.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is shown in Fig. 6 for the DR of C<SB>2</SB>H<SP>+</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met16" novelty="Old" advantage="None">A loss coefficient, <IT>c</IT>(H), representing the probability that a hydrogen atom is not detected, can then be determined.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">For C<SB>2</SB>H<SP>+</SP> the loss coefficient is given by where <IT>N</IT>(2C + H) is the number of counts in the 2C + H peak <IT>etc.</IT> This coefficient was determined to be 0.15 ± 0.02 for C<SB>2</SB>H<SP>+</SP> and 0.26 ± 0.02 for C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">For C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP> it is also possible that H<SB>2</SB>-molecules from channel β miss the detector.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">This was found to be the case in 4% of the DR events.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met17" novelty="Old" advantage="None">For C<SB>2</SB>H<SP>+</SP>, only hydrogen from channel α can have the kinetic energy required to miss the detector; the probability for a hydrogen atom from that channel to be lost is given by where <IT>n</IT>(α) is the branching ratio for channel α.</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met18" novelty="Old" advantage="None">This loss factor could be implemented in the analysis through an iterative procedure by modifying the equation system in the following way </annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met18" novelty="Old" advantage="None">For C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP>, H can be lost from both channel α and γ, while only the total number of lost fragments can be determined from the data.</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met18" novelty="Old" advantage="None">However, in the analysis it could be determined that there are undetected hydrogen atoms coming from both channels, since fragments coming only from channel α could not contribute in a sufficient amount to the number of lost fragments.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The DR branching fraction for each channel is obtained after normalization, <IT>i.e.</IT>The product distributions resulting from the dissociative recombination of C<SB>2</SB>H<SP>+</SP> and C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP> at minimum collision energy are both shown in Table 1, together with previously reported results for C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF> and C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The present measurements demonstrate that the carbon–carbon bond is broken in 57% of the DR events for C<SB>2</SB>H<SP>+</SP>, while the carbon–carbon bond breaking channels account for only 7% of all products for C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP>, three-particle fragmentation, into C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>2</SB> and two hydrogen atoms, dominates the DR process with a branching ratio of 66%.</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met19" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In order to determine if the undetected fragments were correctly accounted for, the larger detector was used to complement these measurements.</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The branching fractions obtained with the small detector agreed with the data taken with the large detector.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Discussion</HEADER><P><s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Comparing the present cross section measurements for C<SB>2</SB>H<SP>+</SP> and C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP> with that previously reported for C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF> demonstrates that at collision energies between 1 meV and 0.l eV the cross sections for C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP> and C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> are approximately the same while that for C<SB>2</SB>H<SP>+</SP> is lower.</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">All three ions show similar energy dependences, −1.1, −1.4, and −1.2 for C<SB>2</SB>H<SP>+</SP>, C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP>, and C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP>, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met20" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In the so-called direct mechanism of DR, which was first proposed by Bates,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF> the electron is captured directly into a repulsive potential curve, which crosses the ionic potential curve near its minimum.</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met21" novelty="Old" advantage="None">When the direct process of DR dominates, the cross section is proportional to <IT>E</IT>−1cm at low collision energies due to the Coulomb attraction between the molecular ion and the electron.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met22" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Bardsley introduced the indirect mechanism of DR in order to account for experimental rate coefficients that depart from the temperature dependence suggested by the direct mechanism.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met22" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The indirect mechanism involves a sequence of two radiationless transitions, where the electron is first captured into a vibrationally excited Rydberg state, which is then subsequently predissociated by the same state that is reached in the direct process.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The present measurements are in good agreement with the single pass merged beams experiment for C<SB>2</SB>H<SP>+</SP>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19 cit20">19,20</REF> which yielded a cross section of 7 × 10<SP>−14</SP> cm<SP>2</SP> at 10 meV collision energy with an energy dependence of <IT>E</IT>−1cm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">(Note that the results in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19">ref. 19</REF> have been corrected in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">ref. 20</REF>, and thereby reduced by a factor of two.) The corresponding thermal rate measured in the single pass merged beams experiment was 2.7 × 10<SP>−7</SP>(<IT>T</IT><SB><IT>e</IT></SB>/300)<SP>−0.5</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although the 300 K rate coefficients are in very good agreement, the two experiments exhibit slightly different temperature dependences, the present measurements showing the somewhat steeper temperature dependence.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">No previous measurements have been made to determine the products that result from DR of C<SB>2</SB>H<SP>+</SP> and C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">As noted previously, the complexity of the DR process makes it difficult to develop a general theory capable of predicting branching ratios for DR of polyatomic molecular ions, and there have been relatively few theoretical attempts at understanding the fragmentation mechanism.</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met23" novelty="Old" advantage="None">One often cited model developed by Bates<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF> argues that the most favored dissociative channels would be those necessitating the fewest rearrangements of valence bonds, implying the most likely product channel in the recombination of C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>n</SB><SP>+</SP> ions would be loss of a single hydrogen atom.</annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Previously reported branching measurements for C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP> and C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> have generally shown a higher degree of fragmentation than predicted by the Bates model,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6 cit7">6,7</REF> and this appears to be the case for both C<SB>2</SB>H<SP>+</SP> and C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP> as well.</annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">For C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP>, a single channel does dominate the DR process, but it is the loss of two hydrogen atoms to form the very stable C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>2</SB> product.</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is not known whether the mechanism involves a concerted loss of two hydrogen atoms or whether this is a two-step process in which sufficient energy remains in the initially formed DR products such that secondary decomposition occurs.</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Similarly, it is not known whether the complete dissociation of the C<SB>2</SB>H<SP>+</SP> ion into 2C + H products results from a concerted or a sequential mechanism.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">One use of the DR results presented here is inclusion into the chemical models used to predict abundances of complex molecular species in the dense interstellar clouds.</annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The abundances derived from various models are shown to depend on a number of variables including the choice of product channels and branching ratios for DR of complex ions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">For ions of the form XH<SB><IT>n</IT></SB><SP>+</SP>, two leading chemical models both assume dissociation product distributions in which loss of H and loss of 2H (or H<SB>2</SB>) occur in equal probability for <IT>n</IT> &gt; 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">For species <IT>n</IT>≤2, the model of Millar and Nejad<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF> considers only loss of H while the model of Herbst and Leung<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF> also allows for strong bond breaking channels, a difference that has implications for the growth of carbon chain species in molecular clouds, for example.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Experiments on XH<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP>, <IT>i.e.</IT><IT>n</IT> = 2 species, in storage rings have shown that complete fragmentation is the dominant pathway,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25">25</REF> suggesting that the model of Herbst and Leung is more appropriate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have examined a series of small hydrocarbon molecular ions of the form C<SB>2</SB>H<SB><IT>n</IT></SB><SP>+</SP> from <IT>n</IT> = 1–4 and find that the smaller species (<IT>n</IT> = 1–2) do in fact undergo significant C–C bond breaking during recombination, while 90–95% of the DR process for the <IT>n</IT> = 3–4 species is attributed to loss of H or 2H (or H<SB>2</SB>).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results presented here are of importance not only to the modeling of reactions in interstellar molecular clouds,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit24">8,24</REF> but also to the modeling of plasma-enhanced combustion reactions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">This modeling shows that by introducing plasma into a hydrocarbon fuel reactor, the combustion is enhanced due to a reduction in ignition delay.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9 cit10">9,10</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Because the primary factor in the enhancement is the increased formation of free radicals following dissociative recombination of hydrocarbon ions, accurate modeling of the hydrocarbon combustion depends on knowledge of the neutral product distributions in dissociative recombination.</annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In earlier models, the two-body fragmentation of molecular ions in dissociative recombination was assumed to be the dominant dissociation channel.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26">26</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, this has been found to disagree with experiments for a majority of polyatomic systems,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25">25</REF> which indicated three-body fragmentation channels are more dominant than first expected.</annotationART></s> <s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">When the molecule dissociates into three fragments, the total number of radicals produced is larger than in the two-body fragmentation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus the combustion efficiency is enhanced when these experimental results are included in combustion models.</annotationART></s> <s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">The average number of radicals produced for C<SB>2</SB>H<SP>+</SP> and C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP> is 2.2 and 1.9 respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">For C<SB>2</SB>H<SP>+</SP>, the result is well in line with the results for C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP> (2.3),<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF> and C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> (2.2),<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF> while the result for C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP> is somewhat lower compared to the earlier measurements.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
