<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b315034h" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Formation and characterization of aromatic selenol and thiol monolayers on gold: <IT>in-situ</IT> IR studies and electrochemical measurements</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Adsorption processes and electrochemical properties of benzeneselenol and benzenethiol on gold electrodes were investigated by surface-enhanced IR absorption spectroscopy (SEIRAS) and electrochemical measurements.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">From the IR spectroscopic measurements, it was confirmed that benzeneselenol molecules adsorbed on the gold surface as benzeneselenolate–Au.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">SEIRAS measurements revealed that benzeneselenol took a much longer time to adsorb on a gold surface than benzenethiol.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Electrochemical reductive desorption of these monolayers in alkaline solution proved that benzeneselenoate chemisorbed on gold surfaces were more stable compared to benzenethiolate, since the reduction peak potential of benzeneselenolate shifted to more than 200 mV negative potential than that of benzenethiolate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The total amounts of adsorbed benzeneselenol molecules were smaller than the case of benzenethiol.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">It has been well known that organosulfur compounds can chemisorb to metal surfaces and form ordered monolayers.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2">1,2</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Modification of gold surfaces by self-assembled monolayers of organosulfur compounds such as alkanethiols and dialkyl disulfides have been widely studied and applied for improvement of surface properties and constructing functional films on metals.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">2</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Adsorbed thiolates on gold are stable enough to form nanometer scale fabrications by selective electrochemical desorption.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3 cit4 cit5 cit6">3–6</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">To construct desirable functional monolayers on the nano-order scale, not only selection of functional (tail) groups but also investigation of head (anchor) groups will be important.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Recently, monolayer formation using chemical bonds between metals and heavy chalcogens have been reported.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7 cit8 cit9 cit10 cit11 cit12 cit13 cit14">7–14</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Adsorptivity and stability of organoselenol and diselenide on gold and silver surfaces were studied by surface-enhanced Raman spectroscopy (SERS), X-ray photoelectron spectroscopy (XPS), and other methods,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7 cit8 cit9 cit10 cit11 cit12 cit13 cit14">7–14</REF> however, the most important fundamental features of organoselenoate monolayers such as adsorption kinetics, number of adsorbates on the surface, and detailed electrochemical properties, have not been investigated sufficiently yet.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="New" advantage="None">In this study, we chose benzeneselenol as a model compound as an alternative of thiols to construct stable monolayers on gold.</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">We investigated adsorption properties, adsorbed molecular orientation, stabilities, and other features of benzeneselenol on gold compared with benzenethiol by <IT>in situ</IT> surface-enhanced IR absorption spectroscopy (SEIRAS) and electrochemical measurements.</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">SEIRAS is one of the powerful tools to evaluate monolayer structures and orientations on the metal surface because its sensitivity is higher than the ordinary IR reflection–absorption spectroscopy method and shows negligible interference from the bulk solution.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15 cit16">15,16</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">From the SEIRAS measurement, it became clear that benzeneselenol took a much longer time to adsorb on a gold surface than benzenethiol.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Reductive desorptive measurements of monolayers in alkaline solution<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3 cit4 cit6 cit17 cit18 cit19">3,4,6,17–19</REF> disclosed the difference of affinities between thiolate/selenolate species with gold electrodes and the total amounts of benzenethiolate/benzeneselenolate adsorbed on gold.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Experimental</HEADER><P><s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Benzeneselenol (Fluka, 97%) and benzenethiol (Sigma-Aldrich, 99%) were used without further purification.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reagents for the electrolyte solution were extra-pure grade.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Millipore water (Milli-Q SP, Millipore Co.) was used to prepare electrolyte solutions.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">A gold thin film, which was evaporated on a hemi-cylindrical silicon prism, was used as the substrate for IR measurements.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The thickness of the gold film was 20 nm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Spectra were measured by using an FTIR spectrometer (DIGILAB FTS-6000e) with a liquid-nitrogen cooled MCT detector and was operated at a resolution of 4 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The acquisition time of each spectrum was <IT>ca.</IT> 10 s.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The incident angle of the IR beam was 80° with respect to the surface normal.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Further details of experimental procedures are referred to in the literature.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">An Au(111) plane mechanically polished with successively finer grades of alumina pastes was used for electrochemical measurements.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Au(111) electrode was annealed in a hydrogen–oxygen flame and quenched quickly into ultra-pure water saturated with hydrogen.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Electrochemical measurements were conducted in a three-electrode configuration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Ag/AgCl (3 M NaCl) and Pt wire were used as the reference and auxiliary electrodes, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">A potentiostat–galvanostat (Hokuto Denko: HA-502) was used to control the potential of the working electrode.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">A function generator (Hokuto Denko: HA-105) was used to provide an external potential.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Cyclic voltammograms (CVs) of the gold electrode for the reductive desorption of the adsorbed monolayers were recorded in 0.5 M KOH solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Electrochemical measurements were carried out at room temperature after the solution was deaerated by flowing Ar gas.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Results and discussion</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Adsorption kinetics of benzeneselenol and benzenethiol</HEADER><P><s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 1 shows a series of IR spectra of the gold surface measured in pure water after injecting benzeneselenol solution (total concentration 0.1 mM).</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The reference was the spectrum of a gold electrode measured in pure water without benzeneselenol.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">When the gold surface is modified by organosulfur analogues, organic solvents such as ethanol and methanol are commonly used.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">We adopted an aqueous solution for the adsorption experiments to avoid multilayer depositions of aromatic sulfur/selenide compounds.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">IR spectra changed gradually after adding benzeneselenol.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Three positive going bands appeared at 1572, 1470 and 1439 cm<SP>−1</SP> in the spectral region between 1300 and 1700 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">These bands are assigned to phenyl ring modes of benzeneselenol adsorbed on gold.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11 cit21">11,21</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">This result indicates that benzeneselenol molecule was gradually adsorbed on the gold electrode surface and the phenyl ring part was oriented to near the surface normal.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The adsorption of benzeneselenol was also supported by the rise of the baseline level of the spectrum.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Molecule–substrate and molecule–molecule interactions were constant during the adsorption process because no peak shifts were observed in this adsorption period.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 2 shows the adsorption behavior of benzenethiol molecules on gold by IR measurement.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">At the beginning of adsorption, the spectrum around 1650 cm<SP>−1</SP>, which was assigned as water molecules on the electrode surface<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22 cit23">22,23</REF> and a small shoulder around 1450 cm<SP>−1</SP> were observed, however, adsorption of benzenethiol on gold was complete within a few minutes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Finally, three positive going bands appeared at 1574, 1470 and 1439 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">These bands did not shift in this adsorption process.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">These were assigned to phenyl ring modes of benzenethiolate on gold.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11 cit21 cit24">11,21,24</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rise of the baseline level of the spectrum was also evidenced by the adsorption of benzenethiol.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Benzenethiol molecules adsorbed on the gold surface with the phenyl ring part oriented near perpendicular to the surface, similarly as benzeneselenol.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 3(a) shows the relation between the adsorption time and the intensity of the 1470 cm<SP>−1</SP> band of benzeneselenol on gold.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">To compare the adsorption properties of benzenselenol with benzenethiol, the band intensities of the 1470 cm<SP>−1</SP> of benzenethiol on gold are also shown (Fig. 3(b)).</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of benzenethiolate, the band intensity saturated within a few minutes and then increased gradually.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">This result was quite similar to that in previous literature.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast, the band intensity of benzeneselenoate increased gradually and approached a saturated value after around 40 min.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Benzeneselenol molecules needed a much longer time to reach the saturated adsorption value than that of benzenethiol.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Adsorption structure of benzeneselenol molecules on gold</HEADER><P><s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 4(a) shows the spectrum extracted from Fig. 1, which was collected 25 min after benzeneselenol injection.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">For comparison, the transmission spectrum of benzeneselenol (KBr) is also shown in Fig. 4(b).</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the spectrum of the modified electrode (Fig. 4(a)), the 2305 cm<SP>−1</SP> band, corresponding to the Se–H stretching mode,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25">25</REF> disappeared completely.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Frequencies of phenyl-ring modes changed slightly after benzeneselenol adsorption.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">A few bands, such as at 3070 and 1580 cm<SP>−1</SP> in the bulk spectrum, disappeared and the 1477 cm<SP>−1</SP> band shifted to lower frequency.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Adsorption of diphenyl diselenide on to a gold surface was reported by Huang <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In their SERS study, the <IT>ν</IT>(Se–Se) vibration was absent after adsorption and the Se–Se bond cleaved on the gold surface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">On the other hand, Bandyopadhyay <IT>et al.</IT> reported that the Se–Se bond was retained even after formation of a monolayer in their Raman study.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">In our investigation, benzeneselenol was attached on the gold surface as benzeneselenoate–Au since the Se–H stretching mode disappeared completely.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is similar to the adsorption of thiolates on gold.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In SEIRAS measurement, bands which have perpendicular dipole moments to the gold surface are observed strongly.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The twist angle between the benzeneselenol molecular plane and the surface plane was quite small on the grounds that band intensities depend upon tilt angle (bands of 3070, 1580 and 1439 cm<SP>−1</SP> which were assigned as symmetries of the phenyl ring vibrations in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24 cit26">refs. 24 and 26</REF>) became relatively weak after benzeneselenol molecular adsorption.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">It was suggested that the phenyl ring of benzeneselenol was oriented to near the upright direction on the gold surface as bands originating from the phenyl ring were observed clearly.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In the case of benzenethiol, it has been reported that the phenyl ring plane was tilted about 30° from the surface normal.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The tilt angle of the benzeneselenol molecule from the surface normal should be small, similarly to benzenethiol, however, it can not be determined accurately because IR measurements were insufficient to analyze much lower frequency regions in which molecular orientations are strongly reflected.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Electrochemical reductive desorption of benzeneselenoate and benzenethiolate monolayers</HEADER><P><s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 5 shows cyclic voltammograms (CVs) for reductive desorption of benzeneselenolate and benzenethiolate monolayers on Au(111) in 0.5 M KOH.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Porter and co-workers suggested that alkanethiolates on gold and other metal electrodes were desorbed in alkaline solution through a one-electron reductive path (RS–Au + e<SP>−</SP> → RS<SP>−</SP> + Au).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17 cit18">17,18</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The electrochemical desorption of monolayers from gold and other metal surfaces has been widely used for the characterization of thiolate monolayers.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3 cit4 cit6 cit17 cit18 cit19 cit27 cit28 cit29 cit30 cit31">3,4,6,17–19,27–31</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In the case of selenolate layers, a similar result was also considered for reductive desorption (RSe–Au + e<SP>−</SP> → RSe<SP>−</SP> + Au).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Benzeneselenolate and benzenethiolate monolayers showed clear desorption peaks at −0.82 and −0.61 V <IT>vs</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Ag/AgCl, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The charge and concentration of benzeneselenolates were 37.6 μC cm<SP>−2</SP> and 3.9 × 10<SP>−10</SP> mol cm<SP>−2</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of benzenethiolates, the charge and concentration were 51.2 μC cm<SP>−2</SP> and 5.3 × 10<SP>−10</SP> mol cm<SP>−2</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The result for benzenethiolate in this study is very close to previous results reported by Zhong <IT>et al.</IT>(52 μC cm<SP>−2</SP>)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit31">31</REF> and by Wan <IT>et al.</IT> (51 μC cm<SP>−2</SP>) for the same molecule.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Bandyopadhyay <IT>et al.</IT> showed the surface coverage of diphenyl diselenide on polycrystalline gold was 99% by impedance, electrochemical, and XPS measurements, however, total numbers of adsorbed molecules were not mentioned.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="Old" advantage="None">It was reported that thiolate chemisorbed more strongly than selenolate, on the basis of the bond strengths (Au–Se &lt; Au–S).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10 cit32 cit33">10,32,33</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="Old" advantage="None">It was also observed that the adsorption of selenolates on gold or silver was more favorable than that of thiolates from SERS results.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11 cit12">11,12</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" advantage="None">In our experimental results, the reductive desorption peak of benzeneselenolate was 0.21 V more negative than that of benzenethiolate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Differences in desorption potentials reflect differences in the binding strength of the compounds.</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">There are two possibilities for this: differences in the mode of binding of selenol/thiol to gold or differences in packing densities of adsorbed molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The latter case reflects small contributions to differences of binding strength.</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">If thiolate/selenoate which have long alkyl chains are used for modification, lateral interactions between alkyl chains became larger, so that the packing density will be important when considering the difference of binding strength.</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reductive desorptive potential of dodecaneselenol on gold was −1.2 V, which was quite similar to that of dodecanethiol.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit34">34</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is feasible that the difference of reductive desorption potential is caused by a difference in binding of (benzene)thiolate and (benzene)selenoate to gold.</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our experimental result demonstrated clearly that the benzeneselenoate monolayer was more stable than benzenethiolate monolayer on gold.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Conclusion</HEADER><P><s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">We investigated the formation process and electrochemical properties of benzeneselenolate and benzenethiolate monolayers on gold by SEIRAS and electrochemical measurements.</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">SEIRAS measurements revealed that benzeneselenol took a much longer time to adsorb on the gold surface than benzenethiol.</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">Benzeneselenol molecules adsorbed on the gold surface as benzeneselenolate–Au.</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Electrochemical reductive desorption of these monolayers proved that benzeneselenoate chemisorbed on a gold surface more strongly compared with benzenethiolate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Total amounts of adsorbed benzeneselenol molecules were smaller than in the case of benzenethiols.</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">This phenomenon will be applicable to construct nano-scale domains.</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">STM studies on the morphologies of both monolayers are under way.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
