<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b315626p" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Untangling the formation of the cyclic carbon trioxide isomer in low temperature carbon dioxide ices</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">The formation of the cyclic carbon trioxide isomer, CO<SB>3</SB>(X <SP>1</SP>A<SB>1</SB>), in carbon-dioxide-rich extraterrestrial ices and in the atmospheres of Earth and Mars were investigated experimentally and theoretically.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Carbon dioxide ices were deposited at 10 K onto a silver (111) single crystal and irradiated with 5 keV electrons.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Upon completion of the electron bombardment, the samples were kept at 10 K and were then annealed to 293 K to release the reactants and newly formed molecules into the gas phase.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">The experiment was monitored <IT>via</IT> a Fourier transform infrared spectrometer in absorption-reflection-absorption (solid state) and through a quadruple mass spectrometer (gas phase) on-line and <IT>in situ</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our investigations indicate that the interaction of an electron with a carbon dioxide molecule is dictated by a carbon–oxygen bond cleavage to form electronically excited (<SP>1</SP>D) and/or ground state (<SP>3</SP>P) oxygen atoms plus a carbon monoxide molecule.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">About 2% of the oxygen atoms react with carbon dioxide molecules to form the <IT>C</IT><SB>2v</SB> symmetric, cyclic CO<SB>3</SB> structure <IT>via</IT> addition to the carbon–oxygen double bond of the carbon dioxide species; neither the <IT>C</IT><SB>s</SB> nor the <IT>D</IT><SB>3h</SB> symmetric isomers of carbon trioxide were detected.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the addition of O(<SP>1</SP>D) involves a barrier of a 4–8 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> and the reaction of O(<SP>3</SP>P) with carbon dioxide to form the carbon trioxide molecule <IT>via</IT> triplet-singlet intersystem crossing is endoergic by 2 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>, the oxygen reactant(s) must have excess kinetic energy (suprathermal oxygen atoms which are not in thermal equilibrium with the surrounding 10 K matrix).</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">A second reaction pathway of the oxygen atoms involves the formation of ozone <IT>via</IT> molecular oxygen.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">After the irradiation, the carbon dioxide matrix still stores ground state oxygen atoms; these species diffuse even at 10 K and form additional ozone molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Summarized, our investigations show that the cyclic carbon trioxide isomer, CO<SB>3</SB>(X <SP>1</SP>A<SB>1</SB>), can be formed in low temperature carbon dioxide matrix <IT>via</IT> addition of suprathermal oxygen atoms to carbon dioxide.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the solid state, CO<SB>3</SB>(X <SP>1</SP>A<SB>1</SB>) is being stabilized by phonon interactions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the gas phase, however, the initially formed <IT>C</IT><SB>2v</SB> structure is rovibrationally excited and can ring-open to the <IT>D</IT><SB>3h</SB> isomer which in turn rearranges back to the <IT>C</IT><SB>2v</SB> structure and then loses an oxygen atom to ‘recycle’ carbon dioxide.</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This process might be of fundamental importance to account for an <SP>18</SP>O enrichment in carbon dioxide in the atmospheres of Earth and Mars.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="1">Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Ever since the first tentative characterization of the carbon trioxide molecule in photolyzed ozone–carbon dioxide ices at 77 K,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF> the CO<SB>3</SB> species has been a subject of various spectroscopic and theoretical studies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Moll <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF>. and Jacox <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">2</REF>. assigned four fundamentals at 2045 cm<SP>−1</SP> (CO stretch), 1073 cm<SP>−1</SP> (O–O stretch), 972 cm<SP>−1</SP> (C–O stretch), 593 cm<SP>−1</SP> (C–O stretch), and 568 cm<SP>−1</SP> (O–CO stretch) in low temperature carbon dioxide matrices; in argon matrices, these absorptions were shifted to 2053 cm<SP>−1</SP>, 1070 cm<SP>−1</SP>, 975 cm<SP>−1</SP>, and 564 cm<SP>−1</SP>;<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF> no feature around 593 cm<SP>−1</SP> was identified in solid argon.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Absorptions at 1894 cm<SP>−1</SP> (argon matrix) and 1880 cm<SP>−1</SP> (carbon dioxide matrix) were tentatively assigned as a Fermi resonance of the 2045 cm<SP>−1</SP> band with an overtone of the 972 cm<SP>−1</SP> fundamental.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Jacox <IT>et al.</IT> conducted also a normal coordinate analysis and suggested a <IT>C</IT><SB>2v</SB> bridged structure (Fig. 1(1)); in strong contrast, LaBonville <IT>et al.</IT> allocated a <IT>C</IT><SB>s</SB> symmetric structure of the carbon trioxide molecule (Fig. 1(2)).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The interest in the carbon trioxide molecule has been also fueled by the complex reaction mechanisms of carbon oxides (carbon monoxide and carbon dioxide) with atomic oxygen in the Martian atmosphere.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6 cit7 cit8">5–8</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Carbon dioxide, CO<SB>2</SB>(X <SP>1</SP>Σ+g), presents the major constituent (95.3% by volume); nitrogen (2.7%), argon (1.6%), carbon monoxide (0.7%), molecular oxygen (0.13%), water (150–200 ppm), and ozone (0.03 ppm) make up the rest.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">It has been suggested that the photodissciation of carbon dioxide by solar photons (<IT>λ</IT> &lt; 2050 Å) produces carbon monoxide and atomic oxygen.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Near the threshold, only ground state O(<SP>3</SP>P) atoms are produced; shorter wavelengths supply also O(<SP>1</SP>D).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The primary fate of electronically excited oxygen atoms is thought to be quenching to form O(<SP>3</SP>P); the detailed process is not known and has been postulated to proceed <IT>via</IT> a carbon trioxide molecule.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Once O(<SP>3</SP>P) and carbon monoxide has been formed, it is difficult to restore carbon dioxide, since the reversed reaction is spin forbidden.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Detailed photochemical models suggest that the oxygen atoms rather react to molecular oxygen and ultimately to ozone.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The CO<SB>3</SB> molecule has been also implied as an important intermediate in the <SP>18</SP>O isotope enrichment of carbon dioxide in the atmospheres of Earth and Mars.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10 cit11">10,11</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Computations and laboratory experiments indicate that the <SP>18</SP>O enrichment in ozone might be transferable to carbon dioxide,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12 cit13">12,13</REF> possibly <IT>via</IT> a CO<SB>3</SB> intermediate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">On Earth, photolysis of stratospheric ozone generates O(<SP>1</SP>D), which in turn might react with carbon dioxide to form a carbon trioxide molecule.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the gas phase, the latter was postulated to fragment to carbon dioxide and atomic oxygen, possibly inducing an isotopic enrichment in carbon dioxide <IT>via</IT> isotopic scrambling.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the explicit structure of the CO<SB>3</SB> intermediate has not been unraveled yet.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Various kinetic measurements have been carried out to determine the temperature-dependent rate constants of the reaction of electronically excited oxygen atoms, O(<SP>1</SP>D), with carbon dioxide.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">At room temperature, rate constants of a few 10<SP>−10</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> s<SP>−1</SP> have been derived.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15 cit16 cit17">15–17</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">This order of magnitude suggest that the reaction has no or only little activation energy, proceeds with almost unit efficiency, and most likely involves a reaction intermediate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, neither reaction products nor the nature of the intermediate were determined.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the other hand, a CO(X <SP>1</SP>Σ<SP>+</SP>) + O<SB>2</SB>(X <SP>3</SP>Σ−g) exit channel was found to have an activation energy between 15 and 28 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> in the range of 300–2500 K.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">This finding correlates also with a theoretical investigation of the singlet and triplet potential energy surfaces of the CO<SB>3</SB> system.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19">19</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Froese and Goddard suggested that the barrier-less, spin-forbidden quenching pathway to form ground state oxygen atoms and carbon dioxide (Δ<SB>R</SB><IT>G</IT> = −190.0 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>) dominates over the formation of CO(X <SP>1</SP>Σ<SP>+</SP>) plus O<SB>2</SB>(X <SP>3</SP>Σ−g) (Δ<SB>R</SB><IT>G</IT> = −157.5 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>) and CO(X <SP>1</SP>Σ<SP>+</SP>) plus O<SB>2</SB>(a <SP>1</SP>Δ<SB>g</SB>) (Δ<SB>R</SB><IT>G</IT> = −63.3 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Further theoretical calculations indicated that the CO<SB>3</SB> isomer identified in the carbon dioxide and argon matrices might be the <IT>C</IT><SB>2v</SB> symmetric bridged molecule.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">A <IT>D</IT><SB>3h</SB> structure was identified as a local minimum, too, but lies 16.8 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> higher in energy than the cyclic isomer (Fig. 1, (3)); according to calculations, both structures are connected <IT>via</IT> a transition state located 36 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> above the cyclic molecule.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">At temperatures higher than 100 K, the cyclic CO<SB>3</SB> isomer was predicted to decay to carbon dioxide and ground state oxygen atoms <IT>via</IT> singlet-triplet transitions.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Despite this information on the reaction of carbon dioxide with atomic oxygen, an incorporation of these data into homogeneous gas phase models still fails to reproduce the observed abundances of carbon dioxide, carbon monoxide, oxygen, and ozone in the Martian atmosphere quantitatively.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Atreya <IT>et al.</IT> pointed out the necessity to include heterogeneous reactions on aerosols or carbon dioxide ice particles in the Martian air.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21 cit22 cit23">21–23</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, these processes have not been investigated in the laboratory so far.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Also, the explicit structure and the actual formation mechanism of the CO<SB>3</SB> isomer and its role in the <SP>18</SP>O isotopic enrichment in stratospheric carbon dioxide remain to be solved.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">In this paper, we present a detailed experimental and theoretical investigation on the formation mechanism of carbon trioxide in low temperature carbon dioxide ices and the implications for gas phase chemistry.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="New" advantage="None">Reactive oxygen atoms are generated <IT>via</IT> electronic energy loss of high energy electrons to the carbon dioxide molecule in the solid sample.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our first goal is to identify the infrared absorption features of the carbon trioxide molecule, to resolve the true nature of the 1880 cm<SP>−1</SP> absorption of the carbon trioxide molecule unambiguously, and to assign the structure of the newly formed species.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Secondly, reaction mechanisms to synthesize the carbon trioxide molecule together with other newly formed species will be derived combining our experimental data with electronic structure calculations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">Finally, important implications of these results to planetary and atmospheric chemistry are addressed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that these studies also have important implications to planetary, cometary, and interstellar chemistry since carbon dioxide has been identified as a major component of ices on Mars, in comets such as Halley,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF> and of low temperature grain mantles in cold molecular clouds like the Taurus Molecular Cloud (TMC-1)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25">25</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2">Theoretical calculations</HEADER><P><s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The geometries of various local minima and transition states on three potential energy surfaces (PESs) of carbon trioxide, CO<SB>3</SB>, including the lowest triplet and two lowest singlet electronic states, have been optimized using the multireference complete active space self-consistent field (CASSCF) method<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26 cit27">26,27</REF> with the 6-311G(d) basis set.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The active space in the CASSCF calculations included 16 electrons distributed over 13 orbitals, <IT>i.e.</IT>, this was the full-valence active space excluding 2s lone pairs on three oxygen atoms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Vibrational frequencies and infrared (IR) intensities have been also computed at the CASSCF(16,13)/6-311G(d) level of theory.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Single-point energies for various species have been subsequently refined employing internally-contracted multireference configuration interaction MRCI method<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28 cit29">28,29</REF> with the same (16,13) active space and the larger 6-311+G(3df) basis set.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">All calculations were carried out using the MOLPRO 2002<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30">30</REF> and DALTON<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit31">31</REF> programs.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3">Experimental</HEADER><P><s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The experiments were carried out in a contamination-free ultrahigh vacuum (UHV) chamber; the top view of this machine is shown in Fig. 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This setup consists of a 15 l cylindrical stainless steel chamber of 250 mm diameter and 300 mm height which can be evacuated down to 2 × 10<SP>−10</SP> torr by a magnetically suspended turbopump backed by an oil-free scroll pump.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">A two stage closed cycle helium refrigerator-interfaced to a differentially pumped rotary feedthrough is attached to the lid of the machine and holds a polished silver (111) single crystal.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This crystal is cooled to 10.4 ± 0.3 K, serves as a substrate for the ice condensate, and conducts the heat generated from the impinging electrons to the cold head.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">To minimize the radiative heat transfer from the chamber walls to the target, a 40 K aluminum radiation shield is connected to the second stage of the cold head and surrounds the crystal.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ice condensation is assisted by a precision leak valve.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">During the actual gas condensation, the deposition system can be moved 5 mm in front of the silver target.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This setup guarantees a reproducible thickness and composition of the frosts.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">To allow a selection of the target temperature, a temperature sensor, cartridge heater, and a programmable controller are interfaced to the target.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The carbon dioxide ices were prepared at 10 K by depositing carbon dioxide gas onto the cooled silver crystal.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Blank checks of the pure gas (BOC Gases, 99.999%) <IT>via</IT> a quadrupole mass spectrometer and of the frosts <IT>via</IT> a Fourier transform infrared spectrometer were also carried out.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 3 depicts a typical infrared spectrum of the frost; the absorptions are compiled in Table 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">To determine the ice composition quantitatively, we integrated numerous absorption features and calculated the column density, <IT>i.e.</IT> the numbers of absorbing molecules per cm<SP>2</SP>, <IT>n</IT>, <IT>via</IT> the Lambert–Beer relationship (1) and eqns. (2)–(3).</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The integrated absorption features, the corresponding integral absorption coefficients, and the column densities are summarized in Table 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">These data suggest a column density of (1.1 ± 0.3) × 10<SP>18</SP> molecules cm<SP>−2</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Considering a density of 1.7 g cm<SP>−3</SP> at 10 K,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit32">32</REF> this translates into an averaged target thickness of 0.48 ± 0.11 μm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">We would like to stress that the integrated absorption coefficients have been taken in transmission experiments,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit47">47</REF> but the experiment has been carried out in an absorption–reflection–absorption mode.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">This probably causes the large variations in the film thicknesses estimated from different absorption features.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None"><IT>I</IT>(<IT></IT>) = <IT>I</IT><SB>0</SB>(<IT></IT>)e<SP>−<IT>ε</IT>(<IT></IT>)<IT>n</IT></SP>with the intensity of the IR beam after, <IT>I</IT>(<IT></IT>), and before absorption, <IT>I</IT><SB>0</SB>(<IT></IT>), at a wavenumber <IT></IT>, the wavenumber dependent absorption coefficient <IT>ε</IT>(<IT></IT>) in units of cm<SP>−2</SP> and the number of absorbing species per cm<SP>2</SP>, <IT>n</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Reformulating eqn. (1) with <IT>A</IT>(<IT></IT>) = lg(<IT>I</IT><SB>0</SB>(<IT></IT>)/<IT>I</IT>(<IT></IT>)) gives <IT>A</IT>(<IT></IT>) = <IT>ε</IT>(<IT></IT>)<IT>n</IT>/ln 10.Integrating from <IT></IT><SB>1</SB> to <IT></IT><SB>2</SB> yields with the integrated absorption <SB><IT></IT><SB>1</SB></SB>∫<SP><IT></IT><SB>2</SB></SP><IT>A</IT>(<IT></IT>)d<IT></IT> in cm<SP>−1</SP> and the integral absorption coefficient <IT>A</IT><SB>exp</SB> = <SB><IT></IT><SB>1</SB></SB>∫<SP><IT></IT><SB>2</SB></SP><IT>ε</IT>(<IT></IT>)d<IT></IT> in cm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The factor cos(75°) accounts for angle between the surface normal of the silver wafer and the infrared beam, whereas the division by two corrects for the ingoing and outgoing IR beams.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">These ices were irradiated isothermally at 10 K with electrons of 5 keV kinetic energy generated in an electron gun at beam currents of 100 nA (60 min) by scanning the electron beam over an area of 3.0 ± 0.4 cm<SP>2</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Accounting for the extraction efficiency of 78.8% and the irradiation time, this exposes the target to 1.77 × 10<SP>15</SP> electrons.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Higher beam currents, which increase the temperature of the frost surface, should be avoided.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">After the actual irradiation, the sample was kept isothermally at 10 K and heated then by 0.5 K min<SP>−1</SP> to 293 K.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">To guarantee an identification of the reaction products in the ices and those subliming into the gas phase on line and <IT>in situ</IT>, two detection schemes are incorporated: (<IT>i</IT>) a Fourier transform infrared spectrometer (FTIR), and (<IT>ii</IT>) a quadrupole mass spectrometer (QMS).</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The chemical modification of the ice targets is monitored during the experiments to extract time-dependent concentration profiles and hence production rates of newly formed molecules and radicals in the solid state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The latter is sampled <IT>via</IT> a Nicolet 510 DX FTIR spectrometer (6000–500 cm<SP>−1</SP>) operating in an absorption–reflection–absorption mode (reflection angle <IT>α</IT> = 75°; Fig. 2); spectra were accumulated for 2.5 min at a resolution of 2 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The infrared beam is coupled <IT>via</IT> a mirror flipper outside the spectrometer, passes through a differentially pumped potassium bromide (KBr) window, is attenuated in the ice sample prior and after reflection at a polished silver waver, and exits the main chamber through a second differentially pumped KBr window before being monitored <IT>via</IT> a liquid nitrogen cooled detector (MCTB).</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The gas phase is monitored by a quadrupole mass spectrometer (Balzer QMG 420) with electron impact ionization at 90 eV electron energy of the neutral molecules in the residual gas analyzer mode.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The raw data, <IT>i.e.</IT> the temporal development of the ion currents of distinct mass-to-charge ratios, are processed <IT>via</IT> matrix interval algebra to compute absolute partial pressures of the gas phase molecules.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit33">33</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Since, for example, carbon dioxide can fragment to molecular oxygen and also to carbon monoxide in the ionizer of the quadrupole mass spectrometer, different molecular species add to one mass to charge ratio (<IT>m</IT>/<IT>z</IT>) of, <IT>e.g.</IT> 32 (O<SB>2</SB>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Therefore, we must perform the raw data processing <IT>via</IT> matrix interval algebra to calculate the actual partial pressures of the molecules in the gas phase.</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Briefly, <IT>m</IT>/<IT>z</IT> ratios are chosen to result in an inhomogeneous system of linear equations including the measured ion current (right hand vector), partial pressures (unknown quantity), and calibration factors of fragments of individual gaseous species determined in separate experiments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Since all quantities are provided with experimental errors, matrix interval arithmetic, <IT>i.e.</IT> an IBM high accuracy arithmetic subroutine defining experimental uncertainties as intervals, is incorporated in the computations to extract individual, calibrated components of gas mixtures.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4">Results</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.1">Computational results</HEADER><P><s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our calculations suggest that two minima exist on the lowest singlet CO<SB>3</SB> potential energy surface (PES): a <IT>C</IT><SB>2v</SB>-symmetric three-member cyclic structure <B>s1</B> and a <IT>D</IT><SB>3h</SB>-symmetric isomer <B>s2</B> (Fig. 4). <B>s1</B> and <B>s2</B> have similar energies and reside 197.5 and 197.1 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> lower than the O(<SP>1</SP>D) + CO<SB>2</SB>(X <SP>1</SP>Σ+g) asymptote, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">These two singlet isomers can rearrange to each other by ring opening/ring closure and are separated by a low barrier of 18.4 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> with respect to <B>s1</B> occurring at transition state <B>s-TS1</B>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The cyclic structure <B>s1</B> can be produced in a reaction between O(<SP>1</SP>D) and CO<SB>2</SB>(X <SP>1</SP>Σ+g).</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The calculations suggest that the reactants first form a weakly bound complex (∼2.9 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>) <B>s5</B>, which then rearranges to <B>s1</B> with a barrier <IT>via</IT><B>s-TS2</B> of 5.6–7.6 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> relative to O(<SP>1</SP>D) + CO<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the triplet electronic state, separated O(<SP>3</SP>P) and CO<SB>2</SB> have the lowest energy, while the <IT>C</IT><SB>2v</SB> isomer <B>t1</B> (<SP>3</SP>B<SB>2</SB>) resides 96.3 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> higher. <B>t1</B> has a structure rather similar to that of <B>s2</B>, except that the three C–O bond lengths are not equal; there are one double (1.201 Å) and two single (1.343 Å) bonds.</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Isomer <B>t1</B> can decompose to O(<SP>3</SP>P) + CO<SB>2</SB> overcoming a barrier 51.5 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> at transition state <B>t-TS1</B>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the reverse direction, the barrier for the O(<SP>3</SP>P) + CO<SB>2</SB>(X <SP>1</SP>Σ+g) → <B>t1</B> reaction is calculated to be as high as 147.7 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Interestingly, we were able to locate a minimal energy crossing point (MSX) between the lowest triplet and singlet electronic states in a close vicinity of <B>t-TS1</B>, both the geometry and energy of MSX are similar to those for the triplet transition state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Another possible isomer of triplet CO<SB>3</SB>, <IT>C</IT><SB>s</SB>-symmetric OCOO <B>t2</B> (<SP>3</SP>A″) is much less favorable and lies 260.7 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> higher in energy than O(<SP>3</SP>P) + CO<SB>2</SB>(X <SP>1</SP>Σ+g).</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, we found two local minima on PES of the first excited singlet electronic state, which have lower energies than O(<SP>1</SP>D) + CO<SB>2</SB>(X <SP>1</SP>Σ+g).</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">For instance, <B>s3</B> (<IT>C</IT><SB>2v</SB>, <SP>1</SP>A<SB>2</SB>) is a complex of O(<SP>1</SP>D) with carbon dioxide and stabilized by 27.6 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> relative to the separated species.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The structure of <B>s4</B> (<IT>C</IT><SB>s</SB>, <SP>1</SP>A″) is similar to that of <B>s2</B>, however, all three C–O bonds and OCO angles are slightly unequal.</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Transition state <B>s-TS2</B> separating <B>s3</B> and <B>s4</B> lies 46.4 and 159.8 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> above O(<SP>1</SP>D) + CO<SB>2</SB>(X <SP>1</SP>Σ+g) and <B>s4</B>, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Table 3 summarizes the infrared absorptions of <B>s1</B>, <B>s2</B>, and <B>t2</B>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.2">Infrared spectroscopy</HEADER><P><s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The FTIR spectra are analyzed in three steps.</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">First, we investigate the new absorptions qualitatively and assign their carriers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Hereafter, the temporal developments of these absorptions upon electron irradiation are investigated quantitatively as outlined in Section 3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Finally, these data are fitted to calculate production rates of synthesized molecules in units of molecules cm<SP>−2</SP> (column density), molecules per impinging electron, and absorbed electron volt (eV) per target molecule (dose).</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The integration routine of the absorption features is accurate to ±10%.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit34">34</REF></annotationART></s></P><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.2.1">Qualitative analysis</HEADER><P><s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The effects of the electron irradiation of the carbon dioxide target are displayed in Figs. 5–11.</annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">A comparison of the pristine sample (Fig. 3) with the irradiated ice at 10 K clearly shows new absorption features of carbon monoxide at 2139 cm<SP>−1</SP> (<IT>ν</IT><SB>1</SB>(CO stretching); Fig. 5; Table 4)) and the corresponding isotopic pattern of <SP>13</SP>CO at 2092 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">These data are in close agreement to matrix isolation studies of the carbon monoxide molecule.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit35">35</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">We were also able to detect four fundamentals of the <IT>C</IT><SB>2v</SB> symmetric, cyclic CO<SB>3</SB> structure at 2045 cm<SP>−1</SP> (<IT>ν</IT><SB>1</SB>), 1068 cm<SP>−1</SP> (<IT>ν</IT><SB>2</SB>), 973 cm<SP>−1</SP> (<IT>ν</IT><SB>5</SB>), and 565 cm<SP>−1</SP> (<IT>ν</IT><SB>6</SB>) (Fig. 6).</annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The position of all peaks is in excellent agreement with earlier matrix isolation studies (Section 1) and with our calculated, scaled frequencies (Table 3).</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that although the unobserved <IT>ν</IT><SB>3</SB> and <IT>ν</IT><SB>4</SB> modes have larger absorption coefficients than the detected <IT>ν</IT><SB>6</SB> transition, the <IT>ν</IT><SB>4</SB> absorption overlaps with the broad <IT>ν</IT><SB>2</SB> band of the carbon dioxide reactant; the <IT>ν</IT><SB>3</SB> band of carbon trioxide is too close to the cut-off of the MCTB detector to be observable.</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Finally, we detected also a transition at 1879 cm<SP>−1</SP>, which was assigned tentatively as a Fermi resonance of the 2044 cm<SP>−1</SP> band with an overtone of the 973 cm<SP>−1</SP> fundamental.</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The calculated symmetry of the carbon trioxide modes (Table 3) confirm this tentative assignment.</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the <IT>ν</IT><SB>5</SB> at 973 cm<SP>−1</SP> has b<SB>1</SB> symmetry, the overtone (2<IT>ν</IT><SB>5</SB>) holds an a<SB>1</SB> symmetry (b<SB>1</SB> ⊗ b<SB>1</SB> = a<SB>1</SB>), the latter has the same symmetry as the <IT>ν</IT><SB>1</SB> fundamental; this can give rise to the Fermi resonance as observed at 1879 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">These data make it exceptionally clear that the observed carbon trioxide molecule has a cyclic, <IT>C</IT><SB>2v</SB> symmetric structure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Neither the <IT>C</IT><SB>s</SB> nor the <IT>D</IT><SB>3h</SB> symmetric structures of carbon trioxide were observed.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Besides the carbon monoxide and the carbon trioxide molecules, we were also able to identify the ozone molecule (Fig. 7).</annotationART></s> <s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Two absorptions at 1042 cm<SP>−1</SP> (<IT>ν</IT><SB>3</SB>, anti symmetric stretch) and the weaker bending mode at 704 cm<SP>−1</SP> (<IT>ν</IT><SB>2</SB>) were identified.</annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">These data agree very well with previous assignments<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit36">36</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.2.2">Quantitative analysis</HEADER><P><s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Figs. 8–11 compile the temporal development of the column densities of the carbon dioxide reactant and of the products (carbon monoxide, carbon trioxide, and ozone) during the irradiation at 10 K, the consecutive equilibration period at 10 K, and the heating phase.</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">During the irradiation of the carbon dioxide ice, the column density of the CO<SB>2</SB> molecules decreases only slightly from 1.188 × 10<SP>18</SP> cm<SP>−2</SP> to 1.158 × 10<SP>18</SP> cm<SP>−2</SP> (Fig. 8); note that these data are afflicted with an error of ±25% (Table 2).</annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">This means that only 3.01 × 10<SP>16</SP> cm<SP>−2</SP>, <IT>i.e.</IT> 2.5%, of the carbon dioxide molecules are destroyed at the end of the irradiation (Table 5).</annotationART></s> <s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">Accounting for the target surface and the electron beam current, we can conclude that each implanted electron destroys 17 ± 4 CO<SB>2</SB> cm<SP>−2</SP>, <IT>i.e.</IT> 51 ± 13 carbon dioxide molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">As expected, the carbon dioxide column density stays constant during the isothermal phase.</annotationART></s> <s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">With increasing temperature the CO<SB>2</SB> molecules sublime; as the temperature is raised from 10 K to 20 K, strengths of all carbon dioxide absorptions start to diminish; at 94 K, no solid carbon dioxide is left on the silver waver.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">With decreasing carbon dioxide column density, new absorptions arise from carbon monoxide (Fig. 9) and carbon trioxide (Fig. 10).</annotationART></s> <s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The carbon monoxide column density rises almost linearly with increasing irradiation time to 3.5 ± 0.4 × 10<SP>16</SP> cm<SP>−2</SP>, <IT>i.e.</IT> an average production rate of 60 ± 6 carbon monoxide molecules per implant, <IT>i.e.</IT> 20 ± 2 CO cm<SP>−2</SP>; the integral absorption coefficient for the 2139 cm<SP>−1</SP> band of 1.1 × 10<SP>−17</SP> molecules cm<SP>−1</SP> is accurate to ±10%.</annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the other hand, the carbon trioxide column density rises quickly but starts to saturate toward the end of the experiment at 1.8 × 10<SP>15</SP> cm<SP>−2</SP> (2044 cm<SP>−1</SP>), 1.5 × 10<SP>15</SP> cm<SP>−2</SP> (1067 cm<SP>−1</SP>), and 1.1 × 10<SP>15</SP> cm<SP>−2</SP> (972 cm<SP>−1</SP>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">These data translate to a synthesis of 2.5 ± 0.5 carbon trioxide molecules per electron (0.8 ± 0.2 CO<SB>3</SB> cm<SP>−2</SP> per electron; production rates are averaged over those obtained from three CO<SB>3</SB> fundamentals).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Based on these information, we can now investigate the carbon balance of the target.</annotationART></s> <s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Based on our integration routine, 3.0 ± 0.8 × 10<SP>16</SP> CO<SB>2</SB> cm<SP>−2</SP> lead to the formation of 3.5 ± 0.4 × 10<SP>16</SP> CO cm<SP>−2</SP> and 1.5 ± 0.3 × 10<SP>15</SP> CO<SB>3</SB> cm<SP>−2</SP>, <IT>i.e.</IT> destruction of 3.0 ± 0.8 × 10<SP>16</SP> cm<SP>−2</SP><IT>versus</IT> formation of 3.7 ± 0.4 × 10<SP>16</SP> cm<SP>−2</SP>; within the error limits, we can conclude that the carbon budget is conserved in the experiment.</annotationART></s> <s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">This strongly correlates with our experimental findings that carbon dioxide and carbon trioxide are the only newly formed carbon-bearing species in our experiment.</annotationART></s> <s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that whereas the carbon monoxide column density stays constant during the isothermal phase at 10 K, the carbon trioxide column density seems to decrease slightly by 5%.</annotationART></s> <s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, since the integration is accurate only to 10%, the drop of the 2044 cm<SP>−1</SP> absorption might be within the experimental error limits: similar the increasing carbon monoxide column density upon warming the matrix to 20 K; alternatively we might conclude that the carbon trioxide molecule starts to decompose even at 10 K. Upon heating the target, both the carbon monoxide and carbon trioxide column densities decrease.</annotationART></s> <s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note, however, that whereas the carbon dioxide absorptions disappear at 94 K, no carbon monoxide and carbon trioxide bands were observed at temperatures higher than 91 K. At 91 K, a column density of 5.6 ± 1.2 × 10<SP>17</SP> CO<SB>2</SB> cm<SP>−2</SP> remains (0.21 ± 0.04 μm CO<SB>2</SB> ice).</annotationART></s> <s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the carbon dioxide matrix sublimes in layers, those layers exposed to the vacuum sublime first.</annotationART></s> <s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">Considering an initial column density of 1.188 × 10<SP>18</SP> cm<SP>−2</SP> CO<SB>2</SB> cm<SP>−2</SP> (0.48 ± 0.11 μm CO<SB>2</SB> ice), we can conclude that the newly synthesized molecules are formed within the first 0.28 ± 0.09 μm of the sample, <IT>i.e.</IT> those layers which are subliming first into the vacuum.</annotationART></s> <s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">Once these layers have been released, the remaining carbon dioxide ice of 0.20 ± 0.04 μm does not contain any newly formed molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="143"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">This in turn indicates that the 5 keV electrons are absorbed and induce radiation damage within the first 0.28 ± 0.09 μm of the carbon dioxide sample.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="144"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Compared to the carbon oxides, the temporal development of ozone depicts striking differences (Fig. 11).</annotationART></s> <s sid="145"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ozone column density increases after 60 min irradiation time to 9.3 ± 1.3 × 10<SP>15</SP> cm<SP>−2</SP>; data has been calculated with an integral absorption coefficient of 1.4 ± 0.2 × 10<SP>−17</SP> molecules cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="146"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">This requires a destruction of 2.8 ± 0.4 × 10<SP>16</SP> CO<SB>2</SB> cm<SP>−2</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="147"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" advantage="None">Statistically, each electron generates 15 ± 3 O<SB>3</SB> molecules in the sample.</annotationART></s> <s sid="148"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the formation of a single ozone molecule requires the destruction of three carbon dioxide molecules to initiate three oxygen atoms, 45 ± 9 carbon dioxide molecules have to be destroyed to account for the experimentally derived ozone production rate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="149"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" advantage="None">To account for the total oxygen balance after the irradiation, we have to include the newly synthesized carbon trioxide molecules (1.5 ± 0.3 × 10<SP>15</SP> cm<SP>−2</SP>), too.</annotationART></s> <s sid="150"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hence, the total oxygen column density of the freshly formed molecules calculates as the sum of the carbon trioxide column density plus three times the ozone column density; based on these considerations, a column density of 2.9 ± 0.4 × 10<SP>16</SP> cm<SP>−2</SP> has to be generated in the carbon dioxide ice by the electrons.</annotationART></s> <s sid="151"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the other hand, the decay profile of the carbon dioxide absorptions suggest that 3.0 ± 0.8 × 10<SP>16</SP> CO<SB>2</SB> cm<SP>−2</SP> have been destroyed after the irradiation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="152"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since each carbon dioxide molecule fragments to carbon monoxide and atomic oxygen upon interaction with an electron, we would expect an identical number of oxygen atoms to be incorporated inside the newly formed molecules, <IT>i.e.</IT> ozone and carbon trioxide.</annotationART></s> <s sid="153"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Within the error limits, the oxygen balance seems to hold.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="154"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">During the isothermal phase, the ozone column density slightly increases from 9.3 ± 1.3 × 10<SP>15</SP> cm<SP>−2</SP> to 1.0 ± 0.1 × 10<SP>16</SP> cm<SP>−2</SP> during the 10 K equilibration period; this suggest that oxygen atoms, which are mobile at 10 K, are present in the carbon dioxide matrix and may react with molecular oxygen to form additional ozone.</annotationART></s> <s sid="155"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have to keep in mind that this analysis only comprises the oxygen balance of the infrared active molecules, but not of infrared inactive species such as molecular and atomic oxygen.</annotationART></s> <s sid="156"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the solid state, the O<SB>2</SB> absorptions at 1591 cm<SP>−1</SP> and 1617 cm<SP>−1</SP> hold absorption coefficients of about 10<SP>−21</SP> cm molecule<SP>−1</SP> (<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit37">ref. 37</REF>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="157"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is not surprising that we were unable to detect these transitions in our experiments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="158"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, we can conclude that molecular oxygen and oxygen atoms reside inside the carbon dioxide matrix as well.</annotationART></s> <s sid="159"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" advantage="None">This effect is even more pronounced while the sample is heated to 60 K. Here, the ozone column density rises significantly by about 30% reaching a maximum at 1.3 ± 0.2 × 10<SP>16</SP> cm<SP>−2</SP> before the column density drops sharply due to the subliming carbon dioxide matrix.</annotationART></s> <s sid="160"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None">This suggests that at least 1.1 ± 0.3 × 10<SP>16</SP> cm<SP>−2</SP> of the oxygen atoms exist in the form of molecular or atomic oxygen.</annotationART></s> <s sid="161"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res29" novelty="None" advantage="None">Including the enhanced ozone column density in the oxygen balance gives a column density of generated oxygen atoms of 4.0 ± 0.6 × 10<SP>16</SP> cm<SP>−2</SP><IT>versus</IT> destruction of the carbon dioxide molecules of 3.0 ± 0.8 × 10<SP>16</SP> cm<SP>−2</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="162"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs19" novelty="None" advantage="None">At 92 K, the ozone absorption disappears completely.</annotationART></s> <s sid="163"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs19" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is interesting to compare this temperature with those where the bands of carbon monoxide 91 K, carbon trioxide 91 K, and carbon dioxide 94 K vanish.</annotationART></s> <s sid="164"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs19" novelty="None" advantage="None">As indicated in the previous section, carbon monoxide, carbon trioxide, and the oxygen atoms are formed initially in the first 0.28 ± 0.09 μm of the carbon dioxide sample.</annotationART></s> <s sid="165"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res30" novelty="None" advantage="None">As the temperature rises, oxygen atoms diffuse and could penetrate also those regions of the carbon dioxide ice which has not been penetrated by the electrons; here, the oxygen atoms could recombine to ozone.</annotationART></s> <s sid="166"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None">This could explain the presence of ozone absorptions at the temperature of 92 K where absorptions of carbon monoxide and carbon trioxide are absent due to their sublimation with the outer layers of the carbon dioxide matrix into the vacuum.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.3">Mass spectrometry</HEADER><P><s sid="167"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="Old" advantage="None">It is interesting to correlate the infrared observations with a mass spectrometric analysis of the gas phase.</annotationART></s> <s sid="168"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs20" novelty="None" advantage="None">During the annealing phase of the sample, the carbon dioxide matrix and the newly formed molecules (CO<SB>3</SB>, CO, O<SB>3</SB>) sublime into the gas phase.</annotationART></s> <s sid="169"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs20" novelty="None" advantage="None">Upon heating the sample to 25 K (180 min experimental time), the carbon dioxide matrix start to sublime (Fig. 8); similarly, the embedded carbon monoxide molecules are being released into the gas phase (Fig. 9).</annotationART></s> <s sid="170"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that the ozone column density increases upon warming the sample due to reactions of atomic oxygen with molecular oxygen (section 4.2); at 60 K (240 min experimental time), the ozone column density decreases, too.</annotationART></s> <s sid="171"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res32" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the mass spectrometric results do not correlate entirely with the infrared data.</annotationART></s> <s sid="172"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res32" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although the partial pressure of carbon monoxide begins to increase at 25 K (as expected from the infrared data), the temporal development of the partial pressure of ozone shows two distinct peaks: a small hump starting at 240 min experimental time (60 K), and a second intense peak at 291 min experimental time (Fig. 12).</annotationART></s> <s sid="173"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res33" novelty="None" advantage="None">A similar pattern has been observed for the carbon dioxide molecule, too.</annotationART></s> <s sid="174"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res32" novelty="None" advantage="None">To interpret the discrepancy between the infrared and mass spectrometric data, we have to keep in mind that the silver target (first stage) is annealed while the cold head is still in operation; this means that the outer aluminum cold shield, which is mounted to the second stage of the closed cycle helium refrigerator, is still cooled down.</annotationART></s> <s sid="175"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res32" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, the molecules subliming during the annealing phase of the silver target (first ozone peak) can actually re-condense onto the aluminum cold shield.</annotationART></s> <s sid="176"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res32" novelty="None" advantage="None">Once the heat load from the cartridge heater increase also the temperature of the second cold head stage, those molecules condensed on the aluminum shield can sublime, too (second ozone peak).</annotationART></s> <s sid="177"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res33" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that two peaks were observed only for ozone, carbon dioxide, and oxygen, but not for carbon monoxide.</annotationART></s> <s sid="178"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res32" novelty="None" advantage="None">Here, carbon monoxide does not re-condense at the 50 K aluminum cold shield since carbon monoxide ice is unstable at temperatures higher than 30 K.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="5">Discussion</HEADER><P><s sid="179"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our investigations indicate that the response of the carbon dioxide system upon the keV electron bombardment is governed by an initial formation of carbon monoxide and atomic oxygen, eqns. (3)–(4).</annotationART></s> <s sid="180"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Depending on the energy transfer form the impinging electron to the carbon dioxide molecule, the oxygen atom can be generated either in its electronic ground (<SP>3</SP>P) <IT>via</IT> inter system crossing to the triplet manifold and/or excited state (<SP>1</SP>D) on the singlet surface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="181"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None">CO<SB>2</SB>(X <SP>1</SP>Σ+g) → CO(X <SP>1</SP>Σ<SP>+</SP>) + O(<SP>3</SP>P),CO<SB>2</SB>(X <SP>1</SP>Σ+g) → CO(X <SP>1</SP>Σ<SP>+</SP>) + O(<SP>1</SP>D).</annotationART></s> <s sid="182"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res34" novelty="None" advantage="None">These reactions are endoergic by 532 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> (5.51 eV) and 732 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> (7.59 eV), respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="183"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res35" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our experiments indicate that each electron initiates 60 ± 6 CO molecules within the carbon dioxide ice (Table 5); this translates to 331 ± 33 eV and 455 ± 46 eV to form O(<SP>3</SP>P) and O(<SP>1</SP>D), respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="184"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Considering the energy of the electron of 5 keV, about 10% of its kinetic energy is utilized to cleave the carbon–oxygen bonds of the carbon dioxide molecules; note that this calculation assumes all the carbon monoxide molecules are formed in their vibrational ground states; also, the oxygen atoms have no excess translational energy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="185"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, to escape the matrix cage, the oxygen atom must have at least 0.5 eV excess kinetic energy; if its kinetic energy is less than the lattice bonding energy, at least O(<SP>1</SP>D) can react back without an entrance barrier to recycle the carbon dioxide molecule.</annotationART></s> <s sid="186"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">To fit the experimentally obtained profile of the carbon dioxide and carbon monoxide column densities, we employed the following model.</annotationART></s> <s sid="187"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The carbon monoxide molecule was assumed to ‘decay’ first order upon electron bombardment similar to a radioactive decay, <IT>i.e.</IT> it follows the velocity law (5) (the square brackets indicate the column density in cm<SP>−2</SP>; <IT>I</IT><SB>e</SB> = 4.92 × 10<SP>11</SP> s<SP>−1</SP> presents the electron current in electrons s<SP>−1</SP>): −d[CO<SB>2</SB>]/d<IT>t</IT> = <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB><IT>I</IT><SB>e</SB>[CO<SB>2</SB>] = <IT>k</IT>′1[CO<SB>2</SB>],d[CO]/d<IT>t</IT> = <IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB><IT>I</IT><SB>e</SB>[CO<SB>2</SB>] = <IT>k</IT>′2[CO<SB>2</SB>].This translates to the following temporal evolutions of the column density for carbon dioxide (7) and carbon monoxide (8) with the constant <IT>a</IT>: [CO<SB>2</SB>](<IT>t</IT>) = [CO<SB>2</SB>](<IT>t</IT> = 0)e<SP><IT>k</IT>′1<IT>t</IT></SP>,[CO](<IT>t</IT>) = <IT>a</IT>(1 − e<SP>−<IT>k</IT>′<SB>2</SB><IT>t</IT></SP>).The best fits of the carbon dioxide and carbon monoxide profiles are shown in Figs. 13 and 14, respectively, with [CO<SB>2</SB>](<IT>t</IT> = 0) = 1.19 ± 0.30 × 10<SP>18</SP> cm<SP>−2</SP>, <IT>k</IT>′1 = 7.35 ± 0.20 × 10<SP>−6</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>, <IT>a</IT> = 7.1 ± 0.7 × 10<SP>16</SP> cm<SP>−2</SP>, and <IT>k</IT>′2 = 1.93 ± 0.1 × 10<SP>−4</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="188"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res36" novelty="None" advantage="None">Accounting for the electron current, this yields <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB> = 1.5 ± 0.2 × 10<SP>−17</SP> and <IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB> = 3.9 ± 0.2 × 10<SP>−16</SP>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="189"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None">We now investigate the fate of the generated oxygen atoms quantitatively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="190"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our data indicate that the carbon trioxide molecule is formed <IT>via</IT> reaction of atomic oxygen with carbon dioxide.</annotationART></s> <s sid="191"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res37" novelty="None" advantage="None">We were able to fit the temporal development of the column density assuming that a carbon dioxide dimer decomposed to carbon dioxide, atomic oxygen, and carbon monoxide; within the matrix cage, the generated oxygen atom reacts with the non-reacted carbon dioxide to form carbon trioxide <IT>via</IT> eqns. (9) and (10): −d[(CO<SB>2</SB>)<SB>2</SB>]/d<IT>t</IT> = <IT>k</IT><SB>3</SB><IT>I</IT><SB>e</SB>[(CO<SB>2</SB>)<SB>2</SB>] = <IT>k</IT>′3[(CO<SB>2</SB>)<SB>2</SB>],d[CO]/d<IT>t</IT> = <IT>k</IT><SB>4</SB><IT>I</IT><SB>e</SB>[(CO<SB>2</SB>)<SB>2</SB>] = <IT>k</IT>′4[(CO<SB>2</SB>)<SB>2</SB>].This leads to the temporal evolution of the column density for carbon trioxide <IT>via</IT> eqn. (11):[CO<SB>3</SB>](<IT>t</IT>) = <IT>b</IT>(1 − e<SP>−<IT>k</IT>′4<IT>t</IT></SP>).Fig. 15 depicts the best fit of the carbon trioxide profile respectively, with <IT>b</IT> = 1.5 ± 0.3 × 10<SP>15</SP> cm<SP>−2</SP>, and <IT>k</IT>′4 = 1.1 ± 0.1 × 10<SP>−3</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="192"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res37" novelty="None" advantage="None">Accounting for the electron current, this yields <IT>k</IT><SB>4</SB> = 2.2 ± 0.2 × 10<SP>−15</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="193"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res38" novelty="None" advantage="None">Extrapolating eqns. (8) and (11) for <IT>t</IT> → ∞ and extracting the ratio of [CO](<IT>t</IT> = ∞)/[CO<SB>3</SB>](<IT>t</IT> = ∞) calculates the fraction of released oxygen atoms reacting with carbon dioxide to 47 ± 14.</annotationART></s> <s sid="194"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res38" novelty="None" advantage="None">This means that only 2.1 ± 0.5% of the generated oxygen atoms react to carbon trioxide.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="195"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res39" novelty="None" advantage="None">What might be the reason for the low fraction of oxygen atoms reacting to carbon dioxide?</annotationART></s> <s sid="196"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res39" novelty="None" advantage="None">The potential energy surface (Fig. 4) helps to understand this scenario.</annotationART></s> <s sid="197"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res39" novelty="None" advantage="None">First, the experiments clearly indicated the formation of the cyclic <B>s1</B> isomer; neither <B>s2</B> nor <B>t2</B> have been detected.</annotationART></s> <s sid="198"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res39" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our calculations show that in the gas phase, only the addition of O(<SP>1</SP>D) can form <B>s1</B><IT>via</IT><B>s5</B> and <B>s-TS3</B>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="199"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con15" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is a clear indication that the interaction of energetic electrons with the carbon dioxide molecules generates reactive oxygen atoms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="200"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res40" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, this reaction has to pass <B>s-TS3</B> which is located 5.6–7.6 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> above the separated reactants.</annotationART></s> <s sid="201"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res40" novelty="None" advantage="None">This requires that the O(<SP>1</SP>D) reactant has at least 5.6–7.6 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> excess kinetic energy to overcome the barrier.</annotationART></s> <s sid="202"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res41" novelty="None" advantage="None">Once <B>s1</B> has been formed in the solid state, the surrounding matrix can divert the internal energy (197.5 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>) of the carbon trioxide species; this stabilizes the latter and prevents an isomerization <IT>via</IT><B>s-TS1</B> to <B>s2</B>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="203"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res42" novelty="None" advantage="None">Non-reactive O(<SP>1</SP>D) can be quenched in the matrix easily <IT>via</IT> intersystem crossing to the <SP>3</SP>P ground state.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit38">38</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="204"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res43" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the triplet surface, ground state oxygen atoms can react solely to yield <B>t1</B>; followed by intersystem crossing, the latter can form <B>s2</B> in the carbon dioxide matrix.</annotationART></s> <s sid="205"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con16" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, since only the cyclic carbon trioxide isomer was detected, this pathway can be likely ruled out.</annotationART></s> <s sid="206"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Similarly, the electronically excited <SP>1</SP>A″ surface can be excluded to contribute to the formation of the cyclic carbon trioxide isomer since only <B>s4</B> can be formed <IT>via</IT><B>s3</B> and <B>s-TS2</B>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="207"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Instead, we located the seam of crossing (MSX) which connects the triplet to the singlet surface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="208"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con16" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the gas phase, this crossing is located close to <B>t-TS1</B>, and O(<SP>3</SP>P) with a sufficient amount of kinetic energy can surpass this barrier to form also <B>s1</B>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="209"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con16" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the solid matrix, however, the energy of MSX is likely lowered; the exact barrier height is currently under investigation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="210"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res44" novelty="None" advantage="None">Actually, the calculated equilibrium constants for the isomerization <B>s2</B> ↔ <B>s1</B> correlate with the failed observation of the <IT>D</IT><SB>3h</SB> symmetric CO<SB>3</SB> isomer in the ice matrix.</annotationART></s> <s sid="211"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res44" novelty="None" advantage="None">Here, <IT>K</IT>(10 K) = 0.002176482 means that at 10 K the concentration of <B>s1</B> should be 500 times higher than that of <B>s2</B>, if they are in equilibrium.</annotationART></s> <s sid="212"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The spectroscopic data suggest that the remaining oxygen atoms rather react <IT>via</IT> molecular oxygen to form ozone <IT>via</IT> eqns. (12)–(13).</annotationART></s> <s sid="213"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that only ground state reactants have been considered; this is certainly true for the reaction during the equilibrating phase at 10 K and the annealing program to 60 K. However, during the electron bombardment, O(<SP>1</SP>D) atoms could react, too.</annotationART></s> <s sid="214"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res45" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both reactions are exoergic by 498.5 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> and 106.5 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>, respectively and involve no entrance barrier except the diffusion energy of the oxygen atoms to migrate to the reaction site.</annotationART></s> <s sid="215"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res45" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ability of the oxygen atoms to diffuse even at 10 K and in particular at elevated temperatures has been established previously (section 4.2. and Fig. 11).</annotationART></s> <s sid="216"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The detailed formation mechanism of ozone <IT>via</IT> eqn. (13) and/or electronically excited species is currently under investigation and might involve a short-lived cyclic ozone molecule.</annotationART></s> <s sid="217"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con19" novelty="None" advantage="None">So far, we were not able to fit the temporal evolution of the ozone column density; this fit requires knowledge of the diffusion coefficient of the oxygen atom which is currently under study.</annotationART></s> <s sid="218"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con19" novelty="None" advantage="None">A simple exponential fit fails as expected since the ozone is clearly a higher-order reaction product.</annotationART></s> <s sid="219"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con17" novelty="None" advantage="None">O(<SP>3</SP>P) + O(<SP>3</SP>P) → O<SB>2</SB>(X <SP>3</SP>Σ−g),O<SB>2</SB>(X <SP>3</SP>Σ−g) + O(<SP>3</SP>P) → O<SB>3</SB>(X <SP>1</SP>A<SB>1</SB>).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="220"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res46" novelty="None" advantage="None">Finally, we would like to comment on the possibility to generate reactive carbon atoms <IT>via</IT> the interaction of energetic electrons with carbon dioxide.</annotationART></s> <s sid="221"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res46" novelty="None" advantage="None">Recall that the slight increase of the carbon monoxide column density in the equilibration phase (Fig. 9) could indicate a recombination of diffusive carbon atoms with mobile oxygen atoms, eqn. (14), a process similar to the formation of molecular oxygen according to eqn. (12).</annotationART></s> <s sid="222"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res46" novelty="None" advantage="None">C(<SP>3</SP>P) + O(<SP>3</SP>P) → CO(X <SP>1</SP>Σ<SP>+</SP>).Detailed electronic structure calculations depicted that a release of carbon atoms from a linear carbon dioxide molecule does not occur.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit39">39</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="223"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res46" novelty="None" advantage="None">Instead, the linear carbon dioxide species has to isomerize first to a cyclic structure which lies 582 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> higher in energy than the linear structure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="224"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res47" novelty="None" advantage="None">The cyclic isomer ring opens and forms a linear COO(X <SP>1</SP>Σ<SP>+</SP>) molecule which then loses a carbon atom in its excited <SP>1</SP>D state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="225"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res47" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, our experiments identify neither the cyclic carbon dioxide nor the linear COO(X <SP>1</SP>Σ<SP>+</SP>) molecule as a reactive intermediate in our matrix.</annotationART></s> <s sid="226"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con20" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the carbon budget is conserved in our experiment (section 4.2.2) we suggest that the contribution of reactive carbon atoms, if any, is only minor.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="6">Astrophysical and planetary implications</HEADER><P><s sid="227"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Carbon dioxide ice presents also a major constituent of ices as condensed on sub-micrometre sized grain particles in cold interstellar clouds.</annotationART></s> <s sid="228"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although the dust component embodies only 1% of the interstellar matter, these nuclei play a key role in the formation of new molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="229"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Deep in the interior of dense clouds, grain particles effectively shield newly synthesized molecules in the gas phase from the destructive external UV radiation field.</annotationART></s> <s sid="230"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Most important, these sub micrometer sized particles present valuable nurseries to synthesize new molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="231"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">In dense clouds, these grains have typical temperatures of 10 K.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit40 cit41">40,41</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="232"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Once molecules, radicals, or atoms from the gas phase collide with the solid particle, they are accreted on the grain surface resulting in an icy mantle up to 0.1 μm thick.</annotationART></s> <s sid="233"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">At ultralow temperatures, all species except H, H<SB>2</SB>, and He hold sticking coefficients of unity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="234"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">This means that each collision of a gas phase species with a cold surface leads to an absorption and hence thickening of the ice layer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="235"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res48" novelty="None" advantage="None">Here, solid mixtures containing H<SB>2</SB>O (100), CO (7–27), CH<SB>3</SB>OH (&lt;3.4), NH<SB>3</SB> (&lt;6), CH<SB>4</SB> (&lt;2), and CO<SB>2</SB> (15) were identified unambiguously <IT>via</IT> infrared spectroscopy towards the dense cloud TMC-1 employing the field star Elias 16 as a black body source;<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit42">42</REF> the numbers in parentheses indicate the relative abundances compared to water ice.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="236"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">These molecular clouds are interspersed with ultraviolet photons (&lt;13.2 eV) and energetic particles from T-Tauri winds, stellar jets, carbon stars, and galactic cosmic ray particles.</annotationART></s> <s sid="237"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, pristine ice mantles are processed chemically by the cosmic ray induced internal ultraviolet radiation present even in the deep interior of dense clouds (<IT>ϕ</IT> = 10<SP>3</SP> photons cm<SP>−2</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>) and in particular through particles of the galactic cosmic radiation field.</annotationART></s> <s sid="238"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">This can lead to the formation of new molecules in the solid state <IT>via</IT> non-equilibrium (non-thermal) chemistry even at temperatures as low as 10 K. The particle component of the cosmic ray radiation field consists of 97–98% protons (p, H<SP>+</SP>) and 2–3% helium nuclei (α-particles, He<SP>2+</SP>) in the low energy range of 1–10 MeV (1 MeV = 10<SP>6</SP> eV) with <IT>ϕ</IT> = 10 particles cm<SP>−2</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit43">43</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="239"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">It has been well established that cosmic ray MeV particles penetrate the ice mantles and the grain core and deposit parts of their energy inside the ices <IT>via</IT> interaction of the MeV implant and the electronic system of the ice molecules.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit44">44</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="240"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res49" novelty="None" advantage="None">Detailed dynamics simulation showed that 99.9% of the transferred energy leads predominantly to ionization and hence release of energetic (keV) electrons perpendicularly to the trajectory of the MeV implant (ultra track).</annotationART></s> <s sid="241"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con21" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, our experiments simulate also the energetic processes in the ultra track of MeV particles inside interstellar and also cometary ices.</annotationART></s> <s sid="242"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con21" novelty="None" advantage="None">Based on these considerations, we can conclude that the cyclic carbon trioxide molecule should also be present in carbon-dioxide-rich extraterrestrial ices which have been identified in interstellar clouds, comets, and also on Mars.</annotationART></s> <s sid="243"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con22" novelty="None" advantage="None">Most importantly, our experiments indicated the initial formation of suprathermal (electronically excited) oxygen atoms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="244"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">In extraterrestrial ices, the species do not react solely with the carbon dioxide ice, but with the remaining ice components.</annotationART></s> <s sid="245"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">In particular the O(<SP>1</SP>D) atoms are very reactive and may destroy newly formed, astrobiologically important molecules such as sugars and amino acids even deep inside ices.</annotationART></s> <s sid="246"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Potential organics inside the Martian soil might be degraded easily by energetic oxygen atoms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="247"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Also, the interaction of carbon dioxide ices on Mars (and in comets as well as in the interstellar medium) with MeV particles produces significant amounts of ozone.</annotationART></s> <s sid="248"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Upon warming the ices, molecules would sublime and could contribute considerably to the ozone budget in the Martian atmosphere.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="249"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con23" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our investigations help to understand a potential <SP>18</SP>O enrichment in the terrestrial and Martian atmospheres.</annotationART></s> <s sid="250"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con23" novelty="None" advantage="None">Whereas the cyclic carbon trioxide isomer is being stabilized upon reaction of electronically excited oxygen atoms with carbon dioxide in the matrix <IT>via</IT> phonon interaction, in the gas phase the cyclic carbon trioxide molecule can isomerizes to the <IT>D</IT><SB>3h</SB> isomer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="251"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con23" novelty="None" advantage="None">This could scramble the incorporated <SP>18</SP>O and hence lead to an enrichment of <SP>18</SP>O within the carbon dioxide once the carbon trioxide molecule decomposes too atomic oxygen and carbon dioxide (Fig. 16).</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="7">Conclusions</HEADER><P><s sid="252"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">We investigated the synthetic routes to form the cyclic carbon trioxide isomer, CO<SB>3</SB>(X <SP>1</SP>A<SB>1</SB>), in carbon-dioxide-rich extraterrestrial ices and in the atmospheres of Earth and Mars experimentally and theoretically.</annotationART></s> <s sid="253"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The studies indicate that the interaction of an electron with a carbon dioxide molecule is dictated by a carbon–oxygen bond cleavage to form ground state (<SP>3</SP>P) and/or electronically excited (<SP>1</SP>D) oxygen atoms plus a carbon monoxide molecule.</annotationART></s> <s sid="254"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None">About 2% of the oxygen atoms react with carbon dioxide molecules to form the <IT>C</IT><SB>2v</SB> symmetric, cyclic CO<SB>3</SB> structure, <IT>via</IT> addition to the carbon–oxygen double bond of the carbon dioxide species; neither the <IT>C</IT><SB>s</SB> nor the <IT>D</IT><SB>3h</SB> symmetric isomers of carbon trioxide were detected.</annotationART></s> <s sid="255"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con24" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the addition of O(<SP>1</SP>D) involves a barrier of 5.6–7.6 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> and the reaction of O(<SP>3</SP>P) with carbon dioxide to form the carbon trioxide molecule <IT>via</IT> triplet-singlet intersystem crossing is endoergic by 2 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>, the atomic oxygen reactant(s) must have also access kinetic energy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="256"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con24" novelty="None" advantage="None">The remaining oxygen atoms react barrier-less to form ozone <IT>via</IT> molecular oxygen.</annotationART></s> <s sid="257"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con25" novelty="None" advantage="None">In our matrix, CO<SB>3</SB>(X <SP>1</SP>A<SB>1</SB>) is being stabilized by phonon interactions to the surrounding matrix.</annotationART></s> <s sid="258"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con25" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the gas phase, however, the initially formed <IT>C</IT><SB>2v</SB> structure can ring-open to the <IT>D</IT><SB>3h</SB> isomer which in turn loses an oxygen atom to ‘recycle’ carbon dioxide.</annotationART></s> <s sid="259"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con26" novelty="None" advantage="None">The atomic oxygen exchange pathway has been confirmed in a recent crossed molecular beams experiment; however, the authors were not able to assign the nature if the CO<SB>3</SB> intermediate explicitly.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit45">45</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="260"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con27" novelty="None" advantage="None">This process could contribute significantly to an <SP>18</SP>O enrichment in carbon dioxide in the atmospheres of Earth and Mars.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
