<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b316211g" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">XAS characterization and CO oxidation on δ-alumina supported La, Mn, Co and Fe oxides</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">δ-Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> supported La, Mn, Co and Fe containing catalysts were prepared by impregnation of δ-Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> with citrate-type precursors and calcination at 1073 K. The catalysts were characterized by X-ray diffraction (XRD), UV-Vis diffuse reflectance spectroscopy (DRS), X-ray absorption spectroscopy (XAS), and BET specific surface area determination.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">XRD revealed the presence of δ-Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> in all cases and, at 30 wt.% of metal loading, of other single (α-Mn<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> and α-Fe<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB>) or mixed (LaAlO<SB>3</SB>, LaMnO<SB>3</SB>, CoAl<SB>2</SB>O<SB>4</SB> and LaFeO<SB>3</SB>) oxide phases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">XAS suggested the formation of some oxide phases also at lower loading.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In particular, all Mn and 10 wt.% La–Mn containing samples revealed the formation of α-Mn<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB>, while the 30 wt.% La–Mn bimetallic sample showed the formation of LaMnO<SB>3</SB> perovskite.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">All Co containing samples revealed the presence of CoAl<SB>2</SB>O<SB>4</SB> spinel.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fe containing samples showed the formation of α-Fe<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB>, while La–Fe containing ones, that of LaFeO<SB>3</SB> perovskite.Catalytic tests of CO oxidation were performed in the temperature range 300–800 K. The sample containing 30 wt.% of La and Mn in the form of LaMnO<SB>3</SB> perovskite dispersed on δ-Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> was found the most active among all the examined catalysts.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Most of the Co containing catalysts were found active at RT too, but they deactivated rapidly.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">None of the Fe-based samples was active at RT and these catalysts were found, on average, to be substantially less active than the Mn- and Co-based ones.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="1.">Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">A great number of modern catalysts used for industrial applications consist of mixed metal oxides.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Among them, transition metals containing perovskite oxides represent an important and very studied class of materials, owing to their great activity and thermal stability in the catalytic oxidation of hydrocarbons.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2 cit3">1–3</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Perovskite oxides with general formula ABO<SB>3</SB> have an ideal cubic structure with the larger A cation at the center of the cube 12-fold coordinated with oxygen anions and the smaller B atoms occupying the corners of the cube in a 6-fold coordination.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Orthorhombic (<IT>e.g.</IT> LaFeO<SB>3</SB>) and rhombohedral structures (<IT>e.g.</IT> LaMnO<SB>3</SB> and LaCoO<SB>3</SB>) are also known.</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The world wide interest towards these materials and their great variety of properties is due to the fact that about 90% of the metallic elements in the Periodic Table can give perovskite-type structures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">To have a stable perovskite, the only rule to be respected is an ionic rule introduced by Goldschmidt,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF> the so called tolerance factor (<IT>t</IT>, with 0.75 &lt; <IT>t</IT> &lt; 1) defined by the equation <IT>t</IT> = (<IT>r</IT><SB>A</SB> + <IT>r</IT><SB>O</SB>)/√2(<IT>r</IT><SB>B</SB> + <IT>r</IT><SB>O</SB>), where <IT>r</IT><SB>A</SB>, <IT>r</IT><SB>B</SB> and <IT>r</IT><SB>O</SB> are the ionic radii of the cations A and B and of the oxygen anions, respectively.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The preparation method based on citrate-type precursors<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6 cit7">6,7</REF> allows one to obtain perovskites with a few tens (m<SP>2</SP> g<SP>−1</SP>) of specific surface area after a thermal treatment at 1073 K. This method is currently employed in our laboratory and many perovskite systems have been prepared and characterized for their solid state properties and catalytic activity towards alkane and CO oxidation.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit9 cit10 cit11 cit12 cit13 cit14 cit15 cit16">8–16</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">In order to obtain more suitable materials for catalytic purposes, the dispersion of an active phase on a support allows the preparation of high surface area materials and increases the possibility of contacting the active sites and reactant species.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">To this purpose a project started in our laboratory with the aim of preparing and investigating the structural and catalytic properties of materials obtained by impregnation of a suitable support with La, Mn, Co and Fe containing citrate precursors and submitting the system to the same thermal treatments used to prepare the bulk perovskite.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The first support to be used was tetragonal zirconia, ZrO<SB>2</SB>, which resulted as scarcely reactive with the active phase, and therefore suitable for dispersing perovskite materials.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17 cit18 cit19">17–19</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">In the present study the investigation was extended to the alumina, δ-Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB>, support (hereafter labelled δ) which represented a more reactive material than zirconia, particularly with metal ions like cobalt and lanthanum, therefore being of great interest from the structural point of view.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="New" advantage="None">To gain information on the catalytic properties of the examined systems in an oxidation reaction, all the samples were tested for the oxidation of carbon monoxide.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">The most relevant results are reported.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.">Experimental</HEADER><P><s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="New" advantage="None">Bimetallic La–Mn, La–Co and La–Fe containing catalysts with different metal loadings [10 and 30 wt.% calculated according to the ratio perovskite/(alumina + perovskite) (where perovskite is LaMO<SB>3</SB> with M = Mn, Co or Fe)] were prepared by impregnation of δ-Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> with the appropriate amount of citrate-type precursors.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">As a comparison, monometallic La, Mn, Co and Fe containing supported materials, with the same amount of metal as in the bimetallic samples, were prepared too.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Hereafter, labels like LaM/δ (with M = Mn, Co or Fe) or M/δ (with M = La, Mn, Co or Fe) followed by a number in brackets, (10) or (30), referring to the metal loadings, were used to indicate the samples.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The δ-Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> support (surface area = 119 m<SP>2</SP> g<SP>−1</SP>) was obtained from a Pural NW CONDEA batch calcined at 1223 K.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Metals dispersion on the δ-Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> support was performed by the citrate method.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6 cit7 cit20">6,7,20</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">As already reported,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF> the use of citrate-type precursors allows the formation of the perovskite phases in mild conditions, <IT>i.e.</IT> at lower temperature with respect to the temperature reached in other kinds of preparations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Two solutions were added to an appropriate amount of δ-Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB>: an aqueous solution of citric acid was added first and then a solution containing the metal nitrates.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The molar ratio between the citric acid and the overall metal nitrates was fixed at 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Under these conditions the different metals formed a citrate complex, that easily decomposes promoting the formation of the perovskite oxides.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The resulting solution was kept at 383 K until dryness and the samples, after grinding, were calcined at 1073 K for 5 h.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="Old" advantage="None">For a phase check, unsupported LaMO<SB>3</SB> (with M = Mn, Co or Fe) perovskite-type oxides were prepared by the same citrate method.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6 cit7">6,7</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Chemical analyses for Mn, Co and Fe were performed by atomic absorption with a Varian SpectrAA-220 instrument.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The supported samples were very difficult to dissolve; the first attempt to dissolve these materials in a HCl solution failed, so a HF solution was used.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="Old" advantage="No">Also in this case, a slight problem related to incomplete solubility was revealed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="Old" advantage="None">After the analyses the sample labels were not modified and maintained the nominal metal content.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Phase analysis was performed by XRD using a Philips PW 1729 diffractometer with Ni-filtered Cu Kα radiation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Particle sizes (<IT>D</IT>) were evaluated by means of the Scherrer equation, <IT>D</IT> = <IT>K</IT><IT>λ</IT>/<IT>β</IT>cos <IT>θ</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None"><IT>K</IT> is a constant equal to 0.9; <IT>λ</IT> the wavelength of the X-ray used; <IT>β</IT> the effective linewidth of the X-ray reflection under observation, calculated by the expression <IT>β</IT><SP>2</SP> = <IT>B</IT><SP>2</SP> − <IT>b</IT><SP>2</SP> [where <IT>B</IT> is the full width at half maximum (FWHM) and <IT>b</IT> the instrumental broadening determined through the FWHM of the X-ray reflection at 2<IT>θ</IT> ≈ 28° of SiO<SB>2</SB> with particles larger than 1000 Å]; <IT>θ</IT> the diffraction angle of the considered X-ray reflection.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="Old" advantage="None">BET surface area of the samples (SA, m<SP>2</SP> g<SP>−1</SP>) was evaluated by nitrogen adsorption at 77 K in a vacuum glass apparatus.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Krypton was used instead of nitrogen for measurements of surface areas below 10 m<SP>2</SP> g<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Measurements of UV-Vis DRS were performed on Co containing samples in the 200–2500 nm wavelength range with a Varian CARY 5E spectrometer.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="Old" advantage="None">XAS measurements at the M metal K-edge (M = Mn, Co or Fe) were performed for the supported samples, and for LaMO<SB>3</SB>, α-Mn<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB>, CoAl<SB>2</SB>O<SB>4</SB>, Co<SB>3</SB>O<SB>4</SB> and α-Fe<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> as reference materials.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Collection energy ranges for the EXAFS spectra were: 6350–7400 eV for Mn (<IT>E</IT><SB>0</SB> = 6539 eV), 7550–8600 eV for Co (<IT>E</IT><SB>0</SB> = 7709 eV) and 6900–8200 eV for Fe (<IT>E</IT><SB>0</SB> = 7112 eV).</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">These measurements were collected at the beamline GILDA, ESRF, Grenoble (France) in the transmission mode.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The beamline monochromator was equipped with two Si(311) crystals; the two ion chambers were filled with Ar gas.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Powder samples were deposited on Millipore membranes or mixed to an appropriate amount of boron nitride (BN) and pressed into pellets.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">During the data collection samples were held at the liquid nitrogen temperature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The XANES part of the experimental signal was obtained by subtracting a linear pre-edge and normalizing to one in correspondence to the first EXAFS oscillation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The EXAFS analysis was performed using the complete FEFF8 package.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fourier transforms (FTs) for the signal <IT>k</IT><SP>3</SP><IT>χ</IT>(<IT>k</IT>) were calculated in the range 2.5 &lt; <IT>k</IT> &lt; 12.0 Å<SP>−1</SP> with a Kaiser window.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Structural information was obtained by fitting the FT(R) function in the 0.8–4.0 Å range.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fits were performed using the theoretical phase and amplitude functions generated by the FEFF8 code.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">These functions were calibrated by the EXAFS spectra of the reference compounds.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">For all the fits, the calculated statistical errors related to the bond distances were smaller than the uncertainty (0.02 Å) attributed to the EXAFS technique; for the coordination numbers the inaccuracy was evaluated around 0.03.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The CO oxidation with O<SB>2</SB> was studied in a flow system using 0.5 g of catalyst supported on a silica fritted disk internal to a silica reactor vertically positioned in a tubular electrical heater.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">A Ni–NiCr thermocouple was positioned in correspondence to the middle of the catalyst bed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The thermocouple signal was used both to monitor the reaction temperature and to drive an ASCON XS series proportional temperature programmer that powered the electrical heater.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The programmer was set to produce a linear temperature ramp of 1 K min<SP>−1</SP> from 300 to 800 K.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The composition and the total flow rate of the reactants were 1% CO, 20% O<SB>2</SB>, balance He by volume and 100 cm<SP>3</SP> STP.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The space velocity resulted 12 000 cm<SP>3</SP> STP h<SP>−1</SP>g<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">At time intervals of 20 min, that is every 20 K, 6 cm<SP>3</SP> of effluent from the reactor were sampled and analyzed by gas-chromatography, using an Alltech CTR 1 column and a thermal conductivity detector.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The mass balance with respect to carbon was 100 ± 2%.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Before each run a standard pretreatment with oxygen in flow (100 cm<SP>3</SP> STP) at 773 K for 1 h was carried out.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Kinetic parameters were evaluated on the basis of a first order kinetics with respect to CO and 0th pseudo-order with respect to oxygen because it was present in large excess.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The following first order kinetic constants were evaluated: where <IT>F</IT> is the reactant flow rate (mol CO h<SP>−1</SP>), <IT>W</IT> is the mass of catalyst (g), SA is the surface area of the catalyst (m<SP>2</SP> g<SP>−1</SP>), mol<SB>M</SB> are the moles of M per g of catalyst, with M = Mn, Fe, Co. X is the fractional conversion estimated by the CO<SB>2</SB> produced.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.">Results and discussion</HEADER><P><s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The colour of Mn, Co and Fe containing powder samples was brown, blue and ochre-yellow, respectively.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The δ-Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> support showed particle sizes <IT>D</IT> ≈ 100 Å.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Phase analysis, performed by XRD, revealed the presence of δ-Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> in all the samples.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The XRD patterns of the least concentrated (10% metal loading) supported samples did not reveal other phases than δ-Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the contrary, as shown in Figs. 1(a) and 1(b) where the pattern of the δ-Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> support is also reported, the samples with the highest metal loading (30%) revealed the occurrence of other oxide phases in addition to δ-Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB>: (i) α-Mn<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> (<IT>D</IT> ≈ 500 Å), α-Fe<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> (very weak reflections) and CoAl<SB>2</SB>O<SB>4</SB> (<IT>D</IT> ≈ 100 Å) are present in the Mn(30)/δ, Fe(30)/δ and Co(30)/δ samples, respectively; (ii) LaAlO<SB>3</SB> (<IT>D</IT> ≈ 250 Å), LaMnO<SB>3</SB> (<IT>D</IT> ≈ 100 Å), LaFeO<SB>3</SB> (<IT>D</IT> ≈ 130 Å) perovskites, and LaAlO<SB>3</SB> (<IT>D</IT> ≈ 330 Å) are present in the La(30)/δ, LaMn(30)/δ, LaFe(30)/δ and LaCo(30)/δ samples, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, for the samples with 30% of metal loading, XRD (not shown here) were also performed at the end of the catalytic tests, revealing that no other phases than those detected before, were formed after the catalytic process.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the δ-Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> support the BET surface area (SA) value was 119 m<SP>2</SP> g<SP>−1</SP>; all the supported samples showed SA values in the 75–121 m<SP>2</SP> g<SP>−1</SP> range.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">In Table 1 the phases detected by XRD and the SA values are reported for all the samples.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The nominal and experimental contents of transition metal (Mn, Co and Fe) are also reported in Table 1 for the supported samples.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="Old" advantage="None">For Co containing samples DRS spectra were collected with the aim of revealing the presence of Co<SP>2+</SP> and/or Co<SP>3+</SP> ionic species.</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">In fact, in Mn and Fe containing samples only trivalent ionic species were revealed, while in the case of Co containing samples the presence of Co<SP>2+</SP> in the CoAl<SB>2</SB>O<SB>4</SB> spinel phase was expected and the UV-Vis DRS is a particularly suitable technique to diagnose the presence of such ionic species.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Co<SP>2+</SP> in tetrahedral coordination exhibits three different transition bands from the ground state: the <SP>4</SP>A<SB>2</SB>(F) → <SP>4</SP>T<SB>2</SB>(F) one which lies in the IR region, the <SP>4</SP>A<SB>2</SB>(F) → <SP>4</SP>T<SB>1</SB>(F) and <SP>4</SP>A<SB>2</SB>(F) → <SP>4</SP>T<SB>1</SB>(P) ones which appear as multiple absorptions in the near infrared and visible region respectively.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 2 shows DRS spectra for the supported samples and for CoAl<SB>2</SB>O<SB>4</SB> and Co<SB>3</SB>O<SB>4</SB> used as reference compounds.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both reference materials show typical d–d transition bands which appear as a multiple absorption in the 1000–1800 nm region (with maxima at about 1230, 1370 and 1510 nm), due to the <SP>4</SP>A<SB>2</SB>(F) → <SP>4</SP>T<SB>1</SB>(F) transition of Co<SP>2+</SP> in tetrahedral coordination.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23 cit24">23,24</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, CoAl<SB>2</SB>O<SB>4</SB> shows a sharp and intense multiple d–d absorption band in the 500–700 nm range (with maxima at about 550, 580 and 625 nm), due to the <SP>4</SP>A<SB>2</SB>(F) → <SP>4</SP>T<SB>1</SB>(P) transition of tetrahedral Co<SP>2+</SP>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23 cit24">23,24</REF> while Co<SB>3</SB>O<SB>4</SB> reveals a broader and less intense absorption region in the 200–1000 nm range (with maximum at about 770 nm) due both to the <SP>4</SP>A<SB>2</SB>(F) → <SP>4</SP>T<SB>1</SB>(P) transition of tetrahedral Co<SP>2+</SP>, and to d–d transitions of octahedral Co<SP>3+</SP> ionic species.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">All Co containing samples match the absorption features of CoAl<SB>2</SB>O<SB>4</SB> but the most concentrated ones (30 wt.%) also show an absorption band starting at about 700 nm which can be attributed to a very small amount of Co<SB>3</SB>O<SB>4</SB> oxide phase that is present together with the CoAl<SB>2</SB>O<SB>4</SB> phase.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">As to the XAS analysis, the high local sensitivity of this technique allows the observation of structural characteristics of the supported phases and to make a comparison between samples with low and high metal loading.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="Old" advantage="None">To this purpose it was useful to discuss results regarding Mn, Co and Fe containing samples separately.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Tables 2, 3 and 4 report the coordination numbers (<IT>N</IT>) and bond distances (<IT>R</IT>) obtained by fitting procedures for the samples and reference materials containing Mn, Co and Fe, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The FTs of the reference compounds were fitted by fixing the main crystallographic bond distances data (α-Mn<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25">25</REF> LaMnO<SB>3</SB>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26">26</REF> CoAl<SB>2</SB>O<SB>4</SB>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27">27</REF> LaFeO<SB>3</SB><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28">28</REF> and α-Fe<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29">29</REF>) and leaving free the <IT>E</IT><SB>0</SB> shift, the <IT>S</IT>20 term and the Debye–Waller factors.</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the fitting procedure of the supported samples Debye–Waller, <IT>E</IT><SB>0</SB> and <IT>S</IT>20 parameters were fixed to the value obtained from the fit of the reference compounds.</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The coordination numbers (<IT>N</IT>) and bond distances (<IT>R</IT>) were left to vary in the fit.</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Debye–Waller factors were fixed to avoid the strong correlation with the coordination numbers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">These numbers are smaller than those expected, probably owing to a very disordered distribution of oxide phases on the surface of the δ-alumina and/or to the presence of small crystallites.</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the coordination numbers generally increase with increasing the metals content, indicating a greater degree of particles aggregation at higher loading.</annotationART></s></P><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.1.">XAS for Mn containing samples</HEADER><P><s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">For all the samples the FTs, shown in Fig. 3, reveal a first coordination shell peak in the 0.8–1.9 Å range and peaks related to the following shells in the 1.9–4.0 Å range.</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The first shell peak is due to oxygen nearest atoms, the following peaks can be attributed to farther Mn, O or eventually La atoms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fits (Fig. 3) were performed in the whole 0.8–4.0 Å region, including a multiple scattering (MS) contribution Mn–O–Mn for the LaMn(30)/δ sample in order to improve the quality of the fit.</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Results, reported in Table 2, reveal the presence of a very spread α-Mn<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> phase in all the samples except the LaMn(30)/δ one which showed the formation of a LaMnO<SB>3</SB> perovskite phase on the surface of δ-Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Evidence of the two different supported phases could be found in the different values of Mn–Mn bond distances (two distances at about 3.11 Å and 3.58 Å for α-Mn<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> and a single distance at about 3.89 Å for LaMnO<SB>3</SB>) and in the presence of a Mn–La coordination shell (at about 3.30 Å) which was revealed for LaMnO<SB>3</SB> but was obviously absent for α-Mn<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.2.">XAS for Co containing samples</HEADER><P><s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 4 shows first derivatives of the XANES spectra for the Co containing materials and the CoAl<SB>2</SB>O<SB>4</SB> spinel as a reference compound.</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">No appreciable difference can be found in the shape of these derivatives indicating that Co is almost exclusively in the Co<SP>2+</SP> ionic form which is typical for the spinel phase.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Such an evidence was supported also by the EXAFS results.</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">For all the samples the FTs, shown in Fig. 5, reveal two main peaks ranging in the 0.8–2.0 Å and 2.2–3.7 Å regions, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The first shell peak (centred on 1.5 Å) is due to oxygen nearest atoms, the following peak can be attributed to farther Co, Al or O atoms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fits (Fig. 5) were performed in the whole 0.8–3.7 Å region and revealed the presence of a very dispersed CoAl<SB>2</SB>O<SB>4</SB> phase in all the samples.</annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">In fact the typical bond lengths of the CoAl<SB>2</SB>O<SB>4</SB><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27">27</REF> spinel phase were detected (see Table 3): two different Co–O distances at about 1.95 and 3.39 Å, respectively, a Co–Al distance at about 3.36 Å and a Co–Co one at about 3.51 Å.</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">In particular, the Co–O first shell bond distance of the supported samples, ranging in the 1.94–1.97 Å interval, agrees with the sum of the ionic radii of O<SP>2−</SP> (1.38 Å, in four-fold coordination) and Co<SP>2+</SP> (0.58 Å in tetrahedral coordination) ions,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30">30</REF> which can be typically found in the CoAl<SB>2</SB>O<SB>4</SB> spinel phase.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.3.">XAS for Fe containing samples</HEADER><P><s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">For all the samples the FTs, shown in Fig. 6, reveal a first coordination shell peak in the 0.8–2.0 Å range and peaks related to the following shells in the 2.2–4.0 Å range.</annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">The first shell peak is due to oxygen nearest atoms, the following peaks can be attributed to farther Fe, O or eventually La atoms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fits (Fig. 6) were performed in the whole 0.8–4.0 Å region and revealed (see Table 4) two Fe–O bond distances in the 1.91–1.95 Å and 2.0–2.16 Å ranges, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the Fe(10)/δ and Fe(30)/δ samples, the evidence of Fe–Fe bond distances in the 2.79–2.82 Å, 2.98–3.00 Å and 3.32–3.51 Å ranges could be attributed to the presence of a very spread α-Fe<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> phase (Fe–Fe = 2.89, 2.97, 3.37 Å) on the δ-alumina surface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the LaFe(10)/δ and LaFe(30)/δ samples the evidence of Fe–La bond distances in the 3.25–3.37 Å and 3.65–3.75 Å ranges, and a Fe–Fe distance in the 3.73–3.82 Å range revealed the presence of an amorphous and very dispersed LaFeO<SB>3</SB> perovskite phase (Fe–La = 3.35, 3.76 Å; Fe–Fe = 3.93 Å).</annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" advantage="None">As we already reported in a previous work concerning LaFeO<SB>3</SB> perovskite supported on zirconia,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19">19</REF> also in this case the fits of LaFe(10)/δ and LaFe(30)/δ samples improved remarkably by adding a further Fe–Fe contribution which resulted in a short bond distance (at about 3.06 Å) with a small coordination number (<IT>N</IT> = 0.5–0.9).</annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Such a contribution could suggest the presence of a small amount of very spread α-Fe<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> which exhibits short Fe–Fe bond distances at 2.97 and 3.37 Å, respectively, and a longer one at 3.70 Å.</annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The simultaneous presence of different phases, mainly perovskite and some ferric oxide (very disordered and dispersed on the δ-alumina surface), is established also considering that the 3.70 Å Fe–Fe distance, belonging to α-Fe<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB>, could affect the values of the Fe–Fe distance found in the LaFe/δ samples.</annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None">This resulting bond length is shorter than 3.93 Å, that is the value of the Fe–Fe bond distance in LaFeO<SB>3</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore the fitted distance, found in the LaFe/δ supported samples, resulted in being an intermediate value between the Fe–Fe bond distances in the two oxide phases.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.4">CO oxidation</HEADER><P><s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The samples without transition metal ions (t.m.i.), namely the support δ-Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB>, La(10)/δ and La(30)/δ were active only at high temperature (Fig. 7).</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The contribution of the activity of support to those of the t.m.i. containing supported catalysts was therefore considered negligible.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Concerning the other catalysts, their activity data will be reported for each t.m.i. in terms of conversions (same catalyst mass: 0.5 g) and first order kinetic constants with respect to CO. The pseudo-order with respect to oxygen was assumed 0th, because this reactant was present in large excess in the reactant mixture.</annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The kinetic constants <IT>k</IT><SB>s</SB> (normalized per m<SP>2</SP> of surface area of the sample) and <IT>k</IT><SB>m</SB> (normalized per mol of t.m.i. in the sample) were calculated and their logarithms used to build up Arrhenius plots (not reported for brevity).</annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None">Acceptable straight lines were obtained up to 80% conversions data, but the <IT>E</IT><SB>a</SB> values changed in an erratic way, possibly due to temperature-dependent deactivation phenomena.</annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Some activity loss was in fact observed in experiments at constant reaction temperature and high time on stream.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, reasoning based on the kinetic constants should be regarded with prudence.</annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="Old" advantage="None">It is stressed that, for the supported samples, <IT>k</IT><SB>s</SB> represent the areal activity of the active phase only if the latter completely covers the support.</annotationART></s> <s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In the following, we will tentatively use the comparison of the log <IT>k</IT><SB>s</SB> and log <IT>k</IT><SB>m</SB> values of the unsupported and supported phases to have qualitative information on: (i) the coverage (surface area of the active phase)/(surface area of the sample) ratio, by comparison of log <IT>k</IT><SB>s</SB> values; (ii) the dispersion (accessible active phase)/(accessible + bulk active phase) ratio, by comparison of log <IT>k</IT><SB>m</SB> values.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="Old" advantage="None">A word of caution is necessary because this approach holds under the assumption that the areal activities of the unsupported and supported active phases are similar. log <IT>k</IT><SB>s</SB> and log <IT>k</IT><SB>m</SB> were determined at two temperatures, namely 400 and 500 K (Table 5) for all the examined catalysts.</annotationART></s></P><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>Mn containing catalysts</HEADER><P><s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Concerning the Mn containing catalysts, the sample LaMn(30)/δ, which has been shown to contain the LaMnO<SB>3</SB> perovskite, is active at RT already and the conversion remains the highest among all the Mn containing samples, also at higher temperature (Fig. 8).</annotationART></s> <s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is noted that decreasing the Mn loading the conversion decreases too, LaMn(10)/δ being less active than LaMn(30)/δ and Mn(10)/δ less active than Mn(30)/δ (Fig. 8).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res29" novelty="None" advantage="None">Comparing the log <IT>k</IT><SB>m</SB> values for LaMn(30)/δ (containing supported LaMnO<SB>3</SB>) and LaMnO<SB>3</SB> we can observe substantially higher values for LaMn(30)/δ (Table 5), indicating dispersion of the active phase on the supported sample.</annotationART></s> <s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res30" novelty="None" advantage="None">Accordingly, the <IT>k</IT><SB>s</SB> values of LaMnO<SB>3</SB> and LaMn(30)/δ are in a similar range, suggesting high coverage of the support by the active phase.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" advantage="None">Passing to the samples Mn(10)/δ, Mn(30)/δ, LaMn(10)/δ, in which manganese is present as α-Mn<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB>, the log <IT>k</IT><SB>m</SB> and log <IT>k</IT><SB>s</SB> values suggest, by comparison with the corresponding values for α-Mn<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB>, that both coverage and dispersion are low.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Concerning the activity of the unsupported pure oxides in terms of log <IT>k</IT><SB>s</SB>, α-Mn<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> is by far more active than the perovskite LaMnO<SB>3</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs20" novelty="None" advantage="None">α-Mn<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> is also the most active catalyst among all the examined Mn containing samples.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>Fe containing catalysts</HEADER><P><s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs21" novelty="None" advantage="None">Regarding the Fe containing materials, none of the catalysts is active at RT and Fig. 9 indicates that the Fe system is, on average, less active than the Mn system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs22" novelty="None" advantage="None">In terms of conversion, the catalyst Fe(30)/δ, containing iron as α-Fe<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB>, is the most active one, while the sample containing the same active phase, but lower Fe loading, Fe(10)/δ, shows lower activity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs23" novelty="None" advantage="None">The samples containing Fe as LaFeO<SB>3</SB>, are, on average less active.</annotationART></s> <s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs23" novelty="None" advantage="None">In fact LaFe(30)/δ is less active than Fe(30)/δ and LaFe(10)/δ less active than Fe(10)/δ.</annotationART></s> <s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs24" novelty="None" advantage="None">This picture is consistent with the notably higher activity of α-Fe<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> in comparison with LaFeO<SB>3</SB> (see Fig. 9).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res32" novelty="None" advantage="None">The log <IT>k</IT><SB>m</SB> values of α-Fe<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB>, Fe(10)/δ and Fe(30)/δ (Table 5) indicate a considerable dispersion of the active phase in the supported samples.</annotationART></s> <s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res33" novelty="None" advantage="None">The log <IT>k</IT><SB>s</SB> values for the same samples suggest that the fraction of support surface covered by the active phase is high.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res34" novelty="None" advantage="None">The log <IT>k</IT><SB>m</SB> values of LaFeO<SB>3</SB>, LaFe(10)/δ and LaFe(30)/δ indicate a notable dispersion of the active phase in the supported samples.</annotationART></s> <s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res35" novelty="None" advantage="None">The log <IT>k</IT><SB>s</SB> values suggest that the area of the supported active phase and that of the sample are similar.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>Co containing catalysts</HEADER><P><s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res36" novelty="None" advantage="None">Regarding the Co containing catalysts, most of them display a peculiar behavior because they are active at RT already, but the conversion decreases with time on stream, notwithstanding the temperature is increasing, denoting a catalyst poisoning.</annotationART></s> <s sid="143"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs25" novelty="None" advantage="None">At a given temperature a minimum is reached followed by an activity increase up to 100% conversion (Fig. 10).</annotationART></s> <s sid="144"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res37" novelty="None" advantage="None">For Co containing catalysts, the poisoning effect was already observed<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit31 cit32 cit33 cit34">31–34</REF> and it can be attributed to a strong adsorption of the CO<SB>2</SB> product as such, or, most probably, as carbonate species that at a given temperature start to decompose, thereby leading to the usual Arrhenius behavior.</annotationART></s> <s sid="145"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">An explanation of the poisoning effect related to the partial surface reduction of the catalyst and the difficulty of reoxidation can not be ruled out.</annotationART></s> <s sid="146"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs26" novelty="None" advantage="None">In terms of conversion and evaluating the activity only from the ascending part of the curves, the supported samples are substantially less active than pure Co<SB>3</SB>O<SB>4</SB> (Fig. 10).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="147"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs27" novelty="None" advantage="None">Co(10)/δ, that is not active at RT, displays the usual Arrhenius behavior, also shown by the reference compounds LaCoO<SB>3</SB> and CoAl<SB>2</SB>O<SB>4</SB> but in a very different temperature range (Fig. 11).</annotationART></s> <s sid="148"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs28" novelty="None" advantage="None">As shown before (Fig. 2), in the reflectance spectra of the samples LaCo(30)/δ and Co(30)/δ an absorption band in the 700 &lt; <IT>λ</IT> &lt; 1000 nm range, typical for Co<SB>3</SB>O<SB>4</SB>, was observed whereas this absorption was absent in Co(10)/δ.</annotationART></s> <s sid="149"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res38" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, it seems quite reasonable to attribute the activity at RT and the unusual behavior of the samples LaCo(30)/δ and Co(30)/δ to the presence of some little amounts of Co<SB>3</SB>O<SB>4</SB> on their surface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="150"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs29" novelty="None" advantage="None">In fact Co<SB>3</SB>O<SB>4</SB> shows both activity at RT and the unusual poisoning effect (Fig. 10).</annotationART></s> <s sid="151"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res39" novelty="None" advantage="None">With an analogous reasoning the absence of activity at RT and the normal Arrhenius behavior of Co(10)/δ (Fig. 11) are ascribed to the absence of Co<SB>3</SB>O<SB>4</SB> on this catalyst.</annotationART></s> <s sid="152"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res40" novelty="None" advantage="None">The activity of Co(10)/δ would be due to the CoAl<SB>2</SB>O<SB>4</SB> phase which is present in all the δ-alumina supported and Co containing catalysts.</annotationART></s> <s sid="153"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res41" novelty="None" advantage="None">The behavior of LaCo(10)/δ, which shows RT activity and deactivates (Fig. 10), is not easily rationalized, because neither reflectance spectroscopy nor XAS demonstrated the presence of Co<SB>3</SB>O<SB>4</SB> on this sample.</annotationART></s> <s sid="154"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">One could hypothesize that LaCo(10)/δ contains very small amounts of Co<SB>3</SB>O<SB>4</SB> that escaped the experimental detection.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="155"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res42" novelty="None" advantage="None">The log <IT>k</IT><SB>m</SB> and log <IT>k</IT><SB>s</SB> values (Table 5) were determined from Arrhenius plots for which only the ascending part of the curves were considered.</annotationART></s> <s sid="156"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is recalled that none of the supported catalysts contains the perovskite phase LaCoO<SB>3</SB>, whereas the main constituent is the CoAl<SB>2</SB>O<SB>4</SB> spinel.</annotationART></s> <s sid="157"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res43" novelty="None" advantage="None">Co(30)/δ and LaCo(30)/δ were found to contain also minor amounts of Co<SB>3</SB>O<SB>4</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="158"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res43" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore the comparison between supported and reference materials can not include the LaCoO<SB>3</SB> perovskite.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="159"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The log <IT>k</IT><SB>m</SB> and log <IT>k</IT><SB>s</SB> values are difficult to interpret without considering the presence of minor amounts of Co<SB>3</SB>O<SB>4</SB> together with the most abundant CoAl<SB>2</SB>O<SB>4</SB> spinel phase.</annotationART></s> <s sid="160"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In fact the latter phase has very small log <IT>k</IT><SB>s</SB> values and the presence of Co<SB>3</SB>O<SB>4</SB> is expected to boost the activity, as it is found, due to its high log <IT>k</IT><SB>s</SB>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>Comparison of all the samples towards CO oxidation</HEADER><P><s sid="161"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs30" novelty="None" advantage="None">Considering all the supported samples, the most active, in terms of either conversion or log <IT>k</IT><SB>m</SB> or log <IT>k</IT><SB>s</SB>, is LaMn(30)/δ, which is already active at RT.</annotationART></s> <s sid="162"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs31" novelty="None" advantage="None">The XRD, XAS and DRS characterization showed that LaCoO<SB>3</SB> never formed in Co containing supported samples.</annotationART></s> <s sid="163"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res44" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the absence of this datum the lower activity of LaCo(30)/δ in comparison with LaMn(30)/δ would have been hardly explainable, because LaCoO<SB>3</SB> has an activity, in terms of log <IT>k</IT><SB>s</SB>, higher than LaMnO<SB>3</SB>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="164"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res45" novelty="None" advantage="None">Finally we compare the activity of the unsupported pure compounds in terms of log <IT>k</IT><SB>s</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="165"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res45" novelty="None" advantage="None">Concerning the simple oxides, α-Mn<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> is the most active one, followed by Co<SB>3</SB>O<SB>4</SB> and then by α-Fe<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="166"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res45" novelty="None" advantage="None">α-Mn<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> is also the most active among all the examined catalysts.</annotationART></s> <s sid="167"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res45" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, when supported on alumina, α-Mn<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> is poorly dispersed under our preparation conditions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="168"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs32" novelty="None" advantage="None">Passing to the binary oxides, the resulting order of activity is: LaCoO<SB>3</SB> &gt; LaMnO<SB>3</SB> &gt; LaFeO<SB>3</SB> &gt; CoAl<SB>2</SB>O<SB>4</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="169"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs33" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is also noted that, for either Mn- or Fe- or Co-based systems, the activity (log <IT>k</IT><SB>s</SB>) of the simple oxide is higher than that of the corresponding binary oxide.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="170"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res46" novelty="None" advantage="None">It can be observed that the order of the activities for simple and perovskite oxides found in the present study of CO oxidation does match that reported for the oxidation of hydrocarbons by Seiyama.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">2</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="171"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is possibly due to differences in the reaction mechanisms and/or reaction temperature range (considerably higher especially for methane oxidation).</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.">Conclusions</HEADER><P><s sid="172"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res47" novelty="None" advantage="None">XRD analysis for the δ-alumina supported La, Mn, Co and Fe containing samples showed only the presence of δ-alumina for materials with 10 wt.% of metal loading.</annotationART></s> <s sid="173"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res48" novelty="None" advantage="None">Materials with 30 wt.% of metal loading revealed the presence of other oxide phases depending on the composition.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="174"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res49" novelty="None" advantage="None">UV-Vis DRS analysis, performed on Co containing samples, all blue-coloured, suggested the presence of the CoAl<SB>2</SB>O<SB>4</SB> spinel phase in all the samples.</annotationART></s> <s sid="175"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res50" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, the most concentrated materials showed an absorption band typical for Co<SB>3</SB>O<SB>4</SB> which was supposed to be present on the alumina surface, in a small amount, together with CoAl<SB>2</SB>O<SB>4</SB>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="176"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res51" novelty="None" advantage="None">XAS investigation gave really interesting results, particularly in the most diluted samples for which XRD gave no information.</annotationART></s> <s sid="177"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res52" novelty="None" advantage="None">In fact, the presence of different oxide phases on the alumina support was found also for materials containing 10 wt.% of metals.</annotationART></s> <s sid="178"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res53" novelty="None" advantage="None">In particular, at low loading of La and Mn on δ-Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB>, and in spite of the simultaneous presence of both metals, only the most stable α-Mn<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> phase was formed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="179"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res54" novelty="None" advantage="None">At higher loading (30 wt.%), the presence of Mn and La induced preferably the formation of the LaMnO<SB>3</SB> perovskite.</annotationART></s> <s sid="180"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res55" novelty="None" advantage="None">δ-Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> supported cobalt reacted with the support leading to the formation of the CoAl<SB>2</SB>O<SB>4</SB> spinel phase in all the Co containing samples, also at the lowest loading, being CoAl<SB>2</SB>O<SB>4</SB> the most stable phase in these conditions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="181"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res56" novelty="None" advantage="None">δ-Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB> supported iron led to the formation of α-Fe<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB>; the simultaneous presence of Fe and La on the surface of the support, both at the highest and at the lowest metal loading, induced preferably the formation of the LaFeO<SB>3</SB> perovskite, probably the most stable with respect to the LaMnO<SB>3</SB> and LaCoO<SB>3</SB> perovskite phases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="182"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res57" novelty="None" advantage="None">Materials with low metal loading showed the greatest degree of particles dispersion on the alumina surface.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="183"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res58" novelty="None" advantage="None">As for the CO catalytic oxidation results, the LaMn(30)/δ sample displayed the highest activity (in terms of both conversion and log <IT>k</IT><SB>m</SB> or log <IT>k</IT><SB>s</SB>) among all the investigated supported catalysts, demonstrating the advantage of dispersing the LaMnO<SB>3</SB> perovskite on the alumina support.</annotationART></s> <s sid="184"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res59" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of the Fe-based system, the corresponding LaFe(30)/δ sample, containing the LaFeO<SB>3</SB> perovskite, had lower activity in comparison with Fe(30)/δ which contained α-Fe<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="185"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res60" novelty="None" advantage="None">Concerning the Co-based system, the LaCoO<SB>3</SB> perovskite never formed on the alumina surface because of the reaction between cobalt and alumina leading to the formation of the CoAl<SB>2</SB>O<SB>4</SB> spinel phase that is poorly active.</annotationART></s> <s sid="186"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res60" novelty="None" advantage="None">The activity of the LaCo(30)/δ and Co(30)/δ samples also reflected the presence of minor amounts of highly active Co<SB>3</SB>O<SB>4</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="187"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res60" novelty="None" advantage="None">Consequently, these samples were active also at RT, but deactivated rapidly.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
