<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b404889j" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Laser spectrometry and kinetics of selected elementary reactions of the acetonyl radical</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The laser induced fluorescence excitation spectrum (LIF) and the ultraviolet absorption spectrum (TA) of the acetonyl radical (CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB>) were remeasured by using the time-resolved fast discharge flow (DF) and laser flash photolysis (LP) experimental techniques (<IT>T</IT> = 298 K).</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The absorption cross section of <IT>σ</IT>(acetonyl, 207 nm) = (3.16 ± 0.61) × 10<SP>−18</SP> cm<SP>2</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> was determined calibrated against the acetyl-peroxyl radical (CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)O<SB>2</SB>) in LP/TA measurements.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The kinetics of the reactions of CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB> with the open shell reaction partners O<SB>2</SB> (1), NO (2), NO<SB>2</SB> (3) and H (4) were studied by using the DF method with LIF detection of the acetonyl radical at 298 ± 1 K and 2.85 ± 0.05 mbar He pressure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rate constants for the overall reactions were determined in units of cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP> to be <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB> = (3.49 ± 0.51) × 10<SP>−13</SP>, <IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB> = (1.04 ± 0.19) × 10<SP>−11</SP>, <IT>k</IT><SB>3</SB> = (3.25 ± 0.65) × 10<SP>−11</SP> and <IT>k</IT><SB>4</SB> ≥ 3 × 10<SP>−10</SP> with 2<IT>σ</IT> accuracy given.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The acetonyl radical was found to react similarly to alkyl radicals by comparison with literature results.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">A reduced reactivity was observed toward O<SB>2</SB> and NO that might be attributed to the resonance stabilisation of the acetonyl radical.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">No such effect was observed for the NO<SB>2</SB> and H atom reactions.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="1.">Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Kinetic studies of the reactions of acetonyl radical, CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB>, are of interest for both practical and fundamental reasons.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">One of the practical reasons is related to atmospheric chemistry.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The acetonyl radical is an important primary intermediate formed in the atmospheric degradation of acetone, CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>3</SB>, which has recently been found in surprisingly high concentration in the atmosphere.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2">1,2</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The oxidative degradation of acetone contributes significantly to the global budget of HO<IT><SB>x</SB></IT> (HO and HO<SB>2</SB>) radicals, particularly in the upper troposphere.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2">1,2</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Atmospheric loss processes for acetone are photolysis<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF> and reaction with OH,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit5">4,5</REF> the relative importance of which depends on season, location and altitude.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3 cit4 cit5">3–5</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the OH-reaction, the acetonyl radical is formed <IT>via</IT> hydrogen abstraction:OH + CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>3</SB> → CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB> + H<SB>2</SB>OThe further fate of CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB> is determined essentially by its reaction with O<SB>2</SB> in the atmosphere.</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The acetonyl radical has relevance to combustion chemistry as well as through the reactions of oxygen atoms with butenes, <IT>e.g.</IT> it is formed in the reaction:<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6 cit7">6,7</REF>CH<SB>2</SB> = C(CH<SB>3</SB>)CH<SB>3</SB> + O(<SP>3</SP>P) → CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB> + CH<SB>3</SB>The fundamental interest stems substantially from the recognition that the radical site in acetonyl is partially delocalized over the carbonyl double bond.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit9 cit10 cit11">8–11</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">This property of the acetonyl radical may give rise to unusual kinetic features allowing the investigation of structure–activity relationships.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Despite this importance and interest, only few studies have been performed so far on the kinetics of the reactions of the acetonyl radical.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12 cit13 cit14 cit15">12–15</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">As part of an ongoing wider program, we have studied the reactivity of the acetonyl radical toward open shell molecules and report here the results for reactions (1)–(4) at room temperature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None">We report also a reassessment of the optical spectra of the acetonyl radical<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6 cit7 cit12 cit16">6,7,12,16</REF> with the main objective of characterising them for the purpose of further kinetic studies.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="New" advantage="None">This paper is organised as follows: First, the experimental techniques are presented in quite some detail because they contain several new elements to our previous publications.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None">The absorption and fluorescence spectra of the acetonyl radical are discussed next, together with the determination of the absorption cross section at a single wavelength.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">The rate constants for reactions (1)–(4) are reported after that and are compared with literature data.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj5" novelty="New" advantage="None">Finally, some of the reactivity properties of the acetonyl radical are discussed and compared with those of the alkyl and alkoxyl radicals from the literature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">One of the conclusions from our current work is that the CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB> radical behaves similarly in its reactions to the alkyl radicals and therefore we prefer its name as “acetonyl” instead of the more common “methylvinoxyl” which implies more an alkoxyl radical character.CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB> + O<SB>2</SB> → productsCH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB> + NO → productsCH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB> + NO<SB>2</SB> → productsCH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB> + H → products</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.">Experimental section</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.1">The discharge flow apparatus</HEADER><P><s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Kinetics of the reactions (1)–(4) were investigated with the discharge flow method (DF) coupled with laser induced fluorescence (LIF) detection of CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">A diagram of the DF/LIF apparatus is shown in Fig. 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Characteristic for our set-up is the vertically positioned flow-tube which is equipped with a moveable injector and operated by a versatile gas-handling and vacuum system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The flow-tube was constructed of Pyrex and had an inner diameter of 40.3 mm and an overall length of 600 mm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Its internal surface was coated with halocarbon wax (Halocarbon Corporation, Series 1200) or a thin film of Teflon (DuPont, 856-200 FEP) to reduce the effect of heterogeneous wall reactions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Wall coatings were prepared similarly to the methods described by Kaufman in his classic work, <IT>e.g.</IT> in .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">ref. 17</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">A thermostatting jacket surrounded the reactor through which temperature-regulated fluids could be circulated by means of a thermostat (Julabo, F81); in the present work the reactor was thermostatted to room temperature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reaction pressure was measured using a calibrated capacitance manometer (MKS Baratron, 10 Torr head) at the downstream end of the flow-tube.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The sliding Pyrex double-injector consisted of an outer tube of 16 mm o.d. surrounding a coaxial shorter tube of 6 mm o.d.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Gases entered the flow-tube from the injector through a Teflon cap with radially directed holes to ensure rapid mixing.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Two flexible stainless steel tubes (1 m × 12 mm i.d.) connected the injector to the gas-handling manifold.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Acetonyl radicals were produced by reacting fluorine atoms with acetone in the flow reactor when the LIF spectra were recorded and inside the moveable injector during the kinetic experiments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">The latter arrangement had the advantage of providing constant initial acetonyl concentration at each position of the injector, which was moved to achieve time resolution in the kinetic measurements.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">F atoms were generated at the upper end of the injector in an alumina-lined quartz tube by microwave discharge of F<SB>2</SB> highly diluted in He.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">The alumina insert tube prevented the formation of contaminating transient species in the discharge and increased the effective degree of dissociation of the fluorine molecule.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">A double-discharge arrangement was applied for the investigation of the kinetics of reaction CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB> + H (4) by discharging H<SB>2</SB>/He in a quartz side-arm at the upstream end of the flow-tube.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The microwave energy was obtained from 2450 MHz microwave generators (Medical Supplies, Microtron 200 or AHF-Analysentechnik, GMW 24-303 DR) feeding 40–50 W power into the discharges.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The flow-tube was coupled to an Al-block fluorescence cell which was black-anodised to reduce scattered light.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The acetonyl radicals were detected by tunable pulsed-laser excitation using a frequency-doubled dye laser (Continuum, ND-6000+UVX doubler) pumped by a Nd:YAG laser (Continuum, Surelite II-10).</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The laser was operated at a repetition rate of 10 Hz with a power of 5–20 mW in the wavelength range of 330–365 nm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Two laser dyes, Pyridin-1 (Radiant Dyes Chemie) and Oxazin-170 (Lambda Physik), were used to cover this wavelength range.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The pulse energy was continuously monitored with a UV-photodiode (EG&amp;G, FND100Q).</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The excitation laser beam entered the detection cell through a Brewster-angled window and a series of blackened baffles.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The induced fluorescence was collected at right angles to both the laser beam and the gas stream and imaged onto the photocathode of a photomultiplier (EMI, 9781B); a Wood’s horn light trap was positioned opposite the photomultiplier tube port.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The photomultiplier viewed the acetonyl fluorescence through a combination of glass filters (Schott, 2 mm BG-12 + 3 mm GG-385 + 3 mm KV-418) comprising a band-pass filter with the optical properties of <IT>λ</IT><SB>max</SB> = 436 nm, <IT>T</IT><SB>max</SB> = 48% and FWHM = 50 nm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">All optical windows and lenses both in the DF and LP set-ups were made of non-fluorescing fused silica (Heraeus, Suprasil).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The output current from the photomultiplier tube was fed into a purpose-built gated boxcar-integrator/data-acquisition system (constructed by Peter A. Halford-Maw, The University of Leeds).</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Q-switch output of the Nd:YAG laser was used to trigger the gate; the delay, with respect to the laser, and the gate-width were adjustable.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The analogue signal was digitalized and transferred to a laboratory PC for averaging and further processing.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Typically 1000 laser shots were averaged.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp10" novelty="None" advantage="None">In some of the experiments, the LIF signal was observed with a 100 MHz digital storage oscilloscope (Hewlett-Packard, HP54601A) when the signal strength was equated with the maximum of the averaged fluorescence traces corrected for background.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Helium was the carrier gas which was passed through liquid-nitrogen cooled activated silicagel traps for further purification (two traps in series in each He line).</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The main gas flows were regulated and monitored by mass-flow controllers (Tylan, FC-260) calibrated by bubble flow meters.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Reactant flows were regulated by needle valves (Hoke, Micromite) and measured by timing the pressure rise of the gas in a calibrated volume by means of a pressure transducer (Data Instruments, Model SA) connected to a strip-chart recorder.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp11" novelty="None" advantage="None">One-stage rotary vacuum pumps (Edwards, E1M40 and E1M80) were used for passing the bulk gas flow through the reactor.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The overall volumetric flow rate was in the range 17–48 standard cm<SP>3</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The gas-handling vacuum system was operated with two-stage rotary vacuum pumps (Tungsram, BP-8 and BP-25) which also served for the evacuation of the flow-tube section between sets of experiments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp11" novelty="None" advantage="None">All vacuum pumps were connected to the apparatus through large N<SB>2</SB>(l)-cooled traps to prevent back-diffusion of oil vapour.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The vacuum-tightness of the system was monitored with a Pirani gauge (Edwards, AGD 101M).</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The vacuum lines were grease-free and metal parts were avoided wherever possible.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Glass tubings were cleaned with 5% HF solution and rinsed with distilled water before installation.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.2">The laser flash photolysis apparatus</HEADER><P><s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 2 shows our recently installed laser flash photolysis (LP) apparatus which is furnished with UV-VIS transient absorption (TA) and pulsed laser induced fluorescence (LIF) monitoring assemblies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Here we present a detailed description of only the LP/TA part of the apparatus which was used to obtain the absorption spectrum of the acetonyl radical.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp13" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the purpose of the LP/TA studies, the CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB> radicals were generated by laser flash photolysis of Cl<SB>2</SB>/acetone/He mixtures using the 351 nm XeF line of an excimer laser (Lambda Physik, Compex 201).</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The generation of radicals and their detection were carried out in a 1020 mm cylindrical Pyrex cell of 25 mm internal diameter which was surrounded by a thermostatting gown and equipped with Suprasil end-windows at Brewster’s angle.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp14" novelty="None" advantage="None">As seen in Fig. 2, the laser beam was reflected into the cell and passed longitudinally in a single path along its axis by using a 351 nm dielectric mirror (Laseroptik, HT: 200–340 nm).</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp14" novelty="None" advantage="None">A second dielectric mirror behind the cell prevented the laser radiation from entering the analytical light source.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Only the central homogeneous section of the laser beam was employed for photolysis to ensure homogeneous radical distribution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The repetition rate of the laser was (1/6)–(1/3) Hz and the pulse energy delivered to the reactor was typically 20–40 mJ pulse<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The monitoring light source was a 150 W Xe arc lamp (Oriel, Model 6356) housed in a ventilated projector housing (Oriel, Model 6137) and powered by a low-ripple power supply (Oriel, Model 68806).</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The photolysis beam and the collimated analysis beam were counter-propagating and overlapped along the cell axis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The analysis beam leaving the cell was focused onto the entrance slit of a 640 mm focal length Czerny–Turner monochromator (Jobin-Yvon, HR 640) with a 1200 lines mm<SP>−1</SP> grating blazed at 250 nm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both the entrance and exit slits were set to 0.5 mm resulting in a spectral resolution of 0.6 nm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The monochromator was calibrated regularly against the 253.64 nm line of a low-pressure Hg lamp (Ultraviolet Products, Pen Ray).</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The dispersed probe light was viewed by a photomultiplier (EMI, 9783R) and the arising transient voltage signal was captured by a 500 MHz digital-storage oscilloscope (Tektronix, TDS 640 A) and then digitised and transferred to a personal computer for averaging and analysis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The digitised oscilloscope trace consisted of 2000 data points.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The 200–400 points constituting the pre-trigger baseline were averaged at each laser shot and this value was subtracted from the decay points to obtain the transient light absorption of the acetonyl radical (<IT>I</IT><SB>t</SB>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The transmitted analysis light intensity in the absence of the transient (<IT>I</IT><SB>0</SB>) was obtained before the laser flash by transferring the PMT signal to the PC <IT>via</IT> an interface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The signal-to-noise ratio was improved by signal averaging: typically 400–2000 acetonyl decay traces were averaged.</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The measurement was automated by means of an integrated hardware and software system (H-Interorg Ltd., Budapest).</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The experimental observable in the LP/TA investigations was the time- and wavelength resolved absorbance with the averaged intensities <IT>Ī</IT><SB>0</SB>(<IT>λ</IT>) and <IT>Ī</IT><SB>t</SB>(<IT>λ</IT>), that is <IT>A</IT><SB>t</SB>(<IT>λ</IT>) = ln (<IT>Ī</IT><SB>0</SB>(<IT>λ</IT>) / <IT>Ī</IT><SB>t</SB>(<IT>λ</IT>)) was recorded from the measurements.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The photolysis cell was attached to a conventional vacuum line which was equipped with Teflon valves, operated with a two-stage rotary pump (Tungsram, BPL-25) through a liquid-nitrogen cooled trap and monitored with a vacuum indicator (MLW Labortechnik, Pirani-Vakuummeter).</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Acetone and acetaldehyde gas mixtures in helium were prepared manometrically on the vacuum line and stored in blackened 10 litre bulbs.</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The gas mixtures were prepared and the reaction pressure was set by means of a 1000 Torr absolute pressure gauge (MKS Baratron, 122A).</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The photolysis gas mixture was slowly flown in the cell in order to avoid the accumulation of the reaction products.</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The overall flow rate of the gases was such that the content of the photolysis cell was replenished in every 4–12 laser shots.</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp16" novelty="None" advantage="None">All gas flows were regulated by needle valves (Hoke, Micromite and Millimite) and were mixed-up in the main line of the vacuum system before entering the photolysis cell.</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The composition of the photolysis mixture was established from the partial flows and the overall pressure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The partial flows were determined by measuring the rate of pressure rise in the cell using the MKS pressure gauge.</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The concentrations of Cl<SB>2</SB>, acetone and acetaldehyde were checked also by absorption measurements performed at 330, 274 and 281 nm, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The two methods gave results in good agreement.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp17" novelty="None" advantage="None">In a few instances, we applied both the TA and LIF detection methods simultaneously for monitoring of the acetonyl radical in time-resolved laser flash photolysis experiments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp17" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this case, the kinetic apparatus shown in Fig. 2 was used in its full extension and the time delay between the pump and probe laser pulses was varied by means of a pulse generator (EMG, TR0361).</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.3">Chemicals</HEADER><P><s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The suppliers and purity of the gases used were as follows: He (Linde, 99.996%), H<SB>2</SB> (Messer-Griesheim, 99.9995%), O<SB>2</SB> (Messer-Griesheim, 99.995%), F<SB>2</SB> (Messer-Griesheim, 5% in 99.9995% purity He), Cl<SB>2</SB> (Matheson, 2% in 99.996% purity He), NO (Messer-Griesheim, &gt;99%), and NO<SB>2</SB> (Messer-Griesheim, 98%).</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp19" novelty="None" advantage="None">NO and NO<SB>2</SB> were purified by repeated trap-to-trap distillations in vacuum until the colour of the samples frozen at N<SB>2</SB>(l) became ‘off-white’ and ‘bright-white’, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp20" novelty="None" advantage="None">Acetone (Aldrich, 99.9+% HPLC grade) and acetaldehyde (Fluka, &gt;99.5%) were carefully degassed by freeze–pump–thaw cycles prior to use.</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp21" novelty="None" advantage="None">Further chemicals used in some test runs were Ar (Linde, 99.9990%), acetone-<IT>d</IT><SB>6</SB> (Aldrich, 99.9 atom% D) and 2,5-hexadione (Loba Chemie, puriss).</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.">Results and discussion</HEADER><P><s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">All experiments were carried-out at room temperature (<IT>T</IT> = 298 ± 1 K) in He buffer gas.</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The reaction pressure was <IT>P</IT> = 2.85 ± 0.05 mbar and <IT>P</IT> ≈ 200 mbar in the DF/LIF and LP/TA investigations, respectively.</annotationART></s></P><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.1">Absorption and fluorescence spectra of the acetonyl radical</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.1.1">TA spectrum of CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB></HEADER><P><s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In the present work, we have measured the transient absorption spectrum for the acetonyl radical in the wavelength range of 200–340 nm and determined the absorption cross section at 207 nm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="Old" advantage="None">As described in the experimental section, the acetonyl radical was generated by the pulsed laser photolysis of Cl<SB>2</SB> at 351 nm in the presence of acetone.</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The following main reactions occurred in the photolysis system:Cl<SB>2</SB> + h<IT>ν</IT> (351 nm) → 2 ClCl + CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>3</SB> → CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB> + HClCH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB> + Cl<SB>2</SB> → CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB>Cl + Cl2 CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB> → CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)(CH<SB>2</SB>)<SB>2</SB>C(O)CH<SB>3</SB>CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB> → productsUnder our experimental conditions the laser-generated Cl atoms were converted completely to CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Acetonyl radicals were consumed predominantly in the self-combination reaction (8); the fast chain propagation step (7) regenerates Cl atoms and so does not lead to acetonyl consumption.</annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Reaction (9) represents essentially the diffusion loss of CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB> out of the detection volume.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">A representative absorbance <IT>vs</IT>. reaction time profile as obtained in one of the LP/TA experiments of acetone/Cl<SB>2</SB>/He mixtures is presented in Fig. 3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">As it is seen in Fig. 3, the absorbance decayed first fast, as a result of the dominance of the self-combination reaction (8), but levelled-off at longer reaction times due, at least in part, to the formation of secondary absorbing species.</annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">At long reaction times (above ∼3 ms) and below about 220 nm and at around 280 nm detection wavelengths, a residual signal was observed that amounted to about 5–15% of the initial absorbance (see also in Fig. 3).</annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Probably, the combination product 2,5-hexadione (acetonyl-acetone) caused this residual light absorption as it was established by UV-spectrometric measurements of 2 mbar samples of pure acetonyl–acetone in a static system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Acetonyl-acetone has been found to show the characteristic absorption spectrum of a carbonyl compound with absorption cross-sections of, e.g., <IT>σ</IT> (acetonyl-acetone, 207 nm) ≈ 1.5 × 10<SP>−19</SP> cm<SP>2</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> and <IT>σ</IT> (acetonyl-acetone, 275 nm) ≈ 4 × 10<SP>−20</SP> cm<SP>2</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In order to construct the absorption spectrum of the acetonyl radical, the absorbance values at zero reaction time (<IT>A</IT><SB>0</SB>) are required where the light absorption is only due to CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="Old" advantage="None"><IT>A</IT><SB>0</SB> values were obtained by extrapolating second-order fits of the measured absorbance–time profiles at low-percentage depletion of CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB> back to <IT>t</IT> = 0.</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The extrapolation was done over a period of 100–200 μs after the laser pulse, where the complications due to secondary absorbing species are minimised.</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">While this extrapolation procedure did serve well to obtain the initial absorbances, the rate constant, <IT>k</IT><SB>8</SB>, derived by the second-order plots increased with acetonyl concentration, contrary to the fact that the second-order kinetics were always obeyed well at the short observation times.</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, only a lower limit of <IT>k</IT><SB>8</SB> &gt; 1.8 × 10<SP>−11</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP> is proposed from our present study.</annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">A more accurate value could have been obtained by working at larger CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB> concentrations and performing rate parameter estimation by computer modelling of a complex reaction mechanism.</annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="Old" advantage="None">We are aware of a single other determination of the rate constant for reaction (8) by direct means which is <IT>k</IT><SB>8</SB> = (4.8 ± 0.3) × 10<SP>−11</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP> (<IT>T</IT> = 298 K).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The scaled absorption spectrum of CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB> constructed by the initial absorbances is shown in Fig. 4.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The absorption cross section of the acetonyl radical was determined at a single wavelength in time-resolved spectrometric measurements calibrated against the acetyl-peroxyl radical, CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)O<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)O<SB>2</SB> radicals were generated in separate flash photolysis experiments by replacing acetone for acetaldehyde and O<SB>2</SB>, whereupon the following main reactions took place:Cl + CH<SB>3</SB>CHO → CH<SB>3</SB>CO + HClCH<SB>3</SB>CO + O<SB>2</SB> + M → CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)O<SB>2</SB> + M2 CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)O<SB>2</SB> → productsCH<SB>3</SB>C(O)O<SB>2</SB> → productsThe spectrometric experiments were made back-to-back by maintaining the same Cl<SB>2</SB> concentrations, laser intensity, gas flow-rate, <IT>etc</IT>., in the acetonyl and acetyl-peroxyl runs, so that the Cl atom concentrations were equal.</annotationART></s> <s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">In fact, reaction (11) is not the only possible channel for CH<SB>3</SB>CO + O<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">As reported by Blitz <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF>. and Tyndall <IT>et al</IT>.,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19">19</REF> this reaction also has a channel that generates OH radicals.</annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The yield is pressure dependent, and is a few percent at moderate pressures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the OH radicals that might be formed were converted in a fast reaction with acetaldehyde to CH<SB>3</SB>CO and subsequently to CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)O<SB>2</SB> in our acetyl-peroxyl system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, no correction was needed to get [CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)O<SB>2</SB>]<SB>0</SB> for the calibration of the absorption cross section of the acetonyl radical (see the concentrations below).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The measurements were performed at 207 nm analysis wavelength which corresponds to the site of the maximum for the stronger absorption band of the acetyl-peroxyl radical.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20 cit21">20–21</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Typical concentrations in the back-to-back experiments were the following (all in molecule cm<SP>−3</SP>): [Cl<SB>2</SB>] ≈ 1 × 10<SP>16</SP>, [acetone] ≈ 4 × 10<SP>16</SP>, [CH<SB>3</SB>CHO] ≈ 5 × 10<SP>16</SP>, [O<SB>2</SB>] ≈ 6 × 10<SP>17</SP> and [CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB>]<SB>0</SB> = [CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)O<SB>2</SB>]<SB>0</SB> ≈ (1–4) × 10<SP>13</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">At these concentrations the laser-generated Cl atoms were converted within a few microseconds to CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB> and CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)O<SB>2</SB> in the acetonyl and acetyl-peroxyl systems, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Examples of transient CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB> and CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)O<SB>2</SB> absorbance profiles are given in Fig. 5, where the corresponding second-order transforms of <IT>A</IT><SB><IT>t</IT></SB><SP>−1</SP><IT>vs. t</IT> are also presented.</annotationART></s> <s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The absorption cross section of CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB> was obtained by the Lambert–Beer law for a single absorbing species using the expressionwhere <IT>A</IT><SB>0</SB>(acetonyl, 207 nm) and <IT>A</IT><SB>0</SB>(acetyl-peroxyl, 207 nm) are the extrapolated absorbances at <IT>t</IT> = 0 in the CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB> and CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)O<SB>2</SB> systems, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The initial absorbance values for the reference acetyl-peroxyl radical had to be extrapolated back to time zero also from short observation times (Fig. 5) because the secondary absorbing radicals CH<SB>3</SB>O<SB>2</SB> and HO<SB>2</SB> began to build up as CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)O<SB>2</SB> consumed (see also in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">ref. 20</REF>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Altogether six pairs of back-to-back experiments were carried out with the variation of the Cl<SB>2</SB> concentration, laser intensity and laser repetition rate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Neither of them was found to systematically influence the derived spectrometric results.</annotationART></s> <s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have accepted the well-established absorption cross-section of <IT>σ</IT>(acetyl-peroxyl, 207 nm) = 6.75 × 10<SP>−18</SP> cm<SP>2</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> recommended by Tyndall <IT>et al</IT>. for the reference radical in a recent review paper.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this way, we have obtained (3.16 ± 0.31) × 10<SP>−18</SP> cm<SP>2</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> absorption cross section for the acetonyl radical, where the error given is 2<IT>σ</IT> statistical uncertainty of the average of the experimental determinations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Propagating an estimated 10% uncertainty for the acetyl-peroxyl radical and adding an estimated 8% error to account for possible systematic errors in our experiments, an overall uncertainty of ∼20% can be assigned to the absorption cross section of the acetonyl radical.</annotationART></s> <s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">That is,<IT>σ</IT>(acetonyl, 207 nm) = (3.16 ± 0.61) × 10<SP>−18</SP> cm<SP>2</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP>is proposed from our current study with an accuracy given at the 95% confidence level.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ultraviolet absorption spectrum of CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB> obtained in the present work, and displayed in Fig. 4, is composed of a weak band with a maximum at around 315 nm and a stronger band below about 230 nm excitation wavelength.</annotationART></s> <s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The longer-wavelength absorption band corresponds to the B̃ ← X̃ electronic transition that can be viewed as a Π* ← Π transition on the carbonyl group of the radical.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16 cit22">16,22</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="143"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">This same transition is involved in the LIF spectrum of the acetonyl radical (see below).</annotationART></s> <s sid="144"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The strong absorption band at short wavelengths has not yet been assigned to our knowledge.</annotationART></s> <s sid="145"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">This might involve excitation to a higher-lying electronic state, C̃, in analogy with the unsubstituted vinoxyl radical (CH<SB>2</SB>C(O)H).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="146"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The absorption spectrum of the acetonyl radical determined in the present work agrees favourably with the spectrum reported by Cox <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="147"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met14" novelty="Old" advantage="None">They applied the technique of pulsed radiolysis combined with multipath transient absorption spectrometry and determined an absorption cross section of <IT>σ</IT>(acetonyl, 310 nm) = (8.73 ± 0.50)×10<SP>−19</SP> cm<SP>2</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="148"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The relative absorption cross section we have obtained at 310 nm converts to ∼7×10<SP>−19</SP> cm<SP>2</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> absolute value.</annotationART></s> <s sid="149"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">This data may be subject to significant uncertainty because of the poor signal-to-noise ratio of our measurements at this wavelength.</annotationART></s> <s sid="150"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Extrapolation of the scaled absorption spectrum by Cox <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF>. to 207 nm supplies an acetonyl cross section value of ∼4 × 10<SP>−18</SP> cm<SP>2</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> which agrees well with our result.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.1.2">LIF spectrum of CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB></HEADER><P><s sid="151"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 6 shows the laser induced fluorescence excitation spectrum of the acetonyl radical observed in the region of 330–365 nm when acetone was reacted with fluorine atoms in the DF apparatus (the CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB> concentration was approximately 2 × 10<SP>12</SP> molecule cm<SP>−3</SP> in these experiments).F<SB>2</SB> + MW-discharge → 2FF+CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>3</SB> → CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB> + HFThe spectrum presented in Fig. 6 is corrected for variations in laser intensity and the peaks designated through “c” to “r” correspond to the assignment reported by Williams <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="152"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">The LIF spectrum we have obtained for the CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB> radical is very similar to that reported by Washida and coworkers<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF> at higher pressures also from room temperature studies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="153"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">It consists of numerous overlapping vibrational–rotational bands of substantial intensity which are superimposed on a diffuse background.</annotationART></s> <s sid="154"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The shortest-wavelength fluorescence is observed at 333.6 nm (29981 cm<SP>−1</SP>) laser excitation (peak “r”), whereas significant absorption still occurs in a wide range below this wavelength (<IT>cf</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="155"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 4).</annotationART></s> <s sid="156"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">This cut-off in LIF intensity is a strong indication of the onset of a non-radiative photochemical or photophysical process of the B̃ electronic state as discussed.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16 cit22">16,22</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="157"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The 0-0 band of the B̃ ← X̃ transition of the acetonyl radical is at 366.5 nm (27282.5 cm<SP>−1</SP>)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF> that lies just beyond our detection range; the longest-wavelength measurable absorption occurs approximately at this band origin.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="158"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met15" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The B̃ ← X̃ laser-induced fluorescence excitation spectrum of CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB> was first published by Williams <IT>et al</IT>. from seeded supersonic molecular beam spectroscopy investigations<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF> and very soon after that by Washida and co-workers<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF> from laser flash photolysis experiments under bulk conditions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="159"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met16" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Washida <IT>et al</IT>. have reported the LIF spectra of five methyl-substituted vinoxyl radicals including acetonyl (1-methylvinoxyl).</annotationART></s> <s sid="160"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met16" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The authors have convincingly assigned the spectra to the corresponding radicals by using various sources of each radical.</annotationART></s> <s sid="161"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met17" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The jet-cooled LIF spectrum of the acetonyl radical reported by Williams <IT>et al</IT>. contains more than 50 discrete vibronic bands.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="162"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met17" novelty="Old" advantage="None">This complexity and the unusual intensity pattern of the spectrum were explained by a change in the preferred orientation of the methyl rotor upon electronic excitation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="163"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met18" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In a subsequent publication, Williams and co-workers have presented a detailed assignment of the LIF spectrum of the jet-cooled acetonyl radical and an analysis of the dynamic features of the B̃ ← X̃ electronic transition which was supported also by high-level <IT>ab initio</IT> computations.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="164"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">To conclude this section, we note that the wavelengths of peaks “c”–“r” listed by Williams <IT>et al</IT>. for their jet-cooled LIF spectrum of the acetonyl radical<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF> agree well with those we have established for a hotter version of the spectrum (Fig. 6).</annotationART></s> <s sid="165"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, these wavelengths can serve as fingerprints for identification of the acetonyl radical in complex chemical systems by LIF detection.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.1.3">Reaction kinetics application</HEADER><P><s sid="166"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both the laser induced fluorescence and UV transient absorption methods can be used favourably for the detection of the acetonyl radical in direct kinetic experiments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="167"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met19" novelty="Old" advantage="None">To this end we note that several well-established methods are available for the generation of this free radical including chemical reactions, such as F/Cl + CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>3</SB> (<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">ref. 6</REF> and this work) as well as laser flash photolysis of acetone,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF> chloro-acetone,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF> 2,4-pentadione<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6 cit15 cit24">6,15,24</REF> and 2-methoxy-propene.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6 cit16">6,16</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="168"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met20" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In a previous kinetic study<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25">25</REF> we applied peak “n” and in the present work peak “e” for the detection of the acetonyl radical at 341.5 and 358.7 nm laser excitation wavelengths, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="169"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">As it is seen in Fig. 6, these are the strongest transitions observed by us allowing sensitive and selective monitoring of CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="170"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">The detection sensitivity for the CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB> radical was ∼2 ×10<SP>9</SP> molecule cm<SP>3</SP> both in the DF and LP investigations (the sensitivity is defined at the signal-to-noise ratio of 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="171"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">In Fig. 6 the XeF excimer laser line (351 nm) and the third-harmonic generation wavelength of a Nd:YAG laser (355 nm) are also indicated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="172"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">We did observe strong LIF signals with these fixed-wavelength lasers, but the signal-to-noise ratio was much poorer compared with the frequency-doubled dye laser excitation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="173"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met21" novelty="Old" advantage="None">There is also the possibility of detecting the perdeutero acetonyl radical, CD<SB>3</SB>C(O)CD<SB>2</SB>, by LIF and in this way to perform kinetic isotope effect studies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="174"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met21" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In a few trial experiments we reacted F atoms with acetone-<IT>d</IT><SB>6</SB> in the flow reactor and observed strong fluorescence at and around 336.8 nm, 340.7 nm and 357.6 nm laser excitation wavelengths.</annotationART></s> <s sid="175"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">The LIF signal-strengths of the deutero-acetonyl radicals were found to be about three times larger than those observed for the undeuterated radicals providing an excellent detection sensitivity.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="176"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met22" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In the experimental arrangement shown in Fig. 2 we have compared the laser induced fluorescence and transient UV-absorption detection methods of the acetonyl radical.</annotationART></s> <s sid="177"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">In conformity with the general picture known for free radicals, the LIF technique was observed to be more selective and about fifty times more sensitive compared with the UV-absorption method.</annotationART></s> <s sid="178"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">We note, however, that the TA detection of CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB> is also well suited for kinetic studies at around and below 207 nm, the absorption cross section being fairly large and because the absorption of many of the potentially disturbing radicals (<IT>e.g.</IT> alkyl-, acyl- and alkyl-peroxyl radicals) decreases significantly towards these short wavelengths.</annotationART></s> <s sid="179"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Finally we mention that a combined application of the LIF and TA detection techniques has proven particularly advantageous in a series of recent kinetic studies in our laboratory on the reactions of the acetonyl radical where a knowledge of absolute radical concentrations is required<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.2">Rate constants for reactions (1)–(4)</HEADER><P><s sid="180"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met23" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The rate constants, <IT>k</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB>, for the overall reactionsCH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB> + R(<IT>i</IT>) → productswith R(<IT>i</IT>) = O<SB>2</SB>(1), NO(2), NO<SB>2</SB>(3) and H(4), were determined with the DF/LIF technique by monitoring the depletion of the CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB> concentration along the flow reactor for different positions of the moveable injector in the absence and the presence of an excess of the reactant R(<IT>i</IT>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="181"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met23" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The initial acetonyl concentration was typically [CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB>]<SB>0</SB> ≈ 6 × 10<SP>11</SP> molecule cm<SP>−3</SP> in these kinetic experiments.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="182"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the absence of reactants, the heterogeneous reactionCH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB> + wall → productswas the major acetonyl loss process with a small contribution of the homogeneous self-combination reaction2 CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB> → products (2,5-hexadione)The depletion of the CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB> concentration without the reactants could be described by an effective first-order “wall rate constant”, <IT>k</IT><SB>w</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="183"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Values were measured, with the exception of the NO<SB>2</SB> reaction (see below), in the range of <IT>k</IT><SB>w</SB> = 11–41 s<SP>−1</SP> (<IT>P</IT> = 2.85 mbar) showing only a small increase with the initial acetonyl concentration which was varied by a factor of about 20 in the experiments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="184"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None">These wall rate constants are of the usual magnitude observed for organic free radicals in discharge flow reactors coated with PTFE or halocarbon wax.</annotationART></s> <s sid="185"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the presence of the reactants R(<IT>i</IT>), the corresponding homogeneous gas-phase reactions (1)–(4) were the major consumption reactions of the acetonyl radical.</annotationART></s> <s sid="186"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res29" novelty="None" advantage="None">No indications for the occurrence of interfering parallel or consecutive reactions were found at low [CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB>]<SB>0</SB> applied in the investigations.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="187"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Pseudo-first-order kinetics were presumed on evaluating the experimental observables.</annotationART></s> <s sid="188"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, the consumption rate of acetonyl radicals is given byor, with the premise that the wall activity is the same in the presence and absence of the reactants R(<IT>i</IT>)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26">26</REF> and assuming the validity of plug-flow conditions, by</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="189"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Where <IT>S</IT><SB>on</SB> and <IT>S</IT><SB>off</SB> are, respectively, the amplitudes of the CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB> LIF signals with and without added R(<IT>i</IT>), <IT>z</IT> is the length of the reaction zone, <IT>v</IT> is the linear flow velocity (varied between 530 and 1510 cm s<SP>−1</SP>), <IT>k</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB>′ (=<IT>k</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB> [R(<IT>i</IT>)]) is the pseudo-first-order rate constant and <IT>t</IT> is the reaction time.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="190"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res30" novelty="None" advantage="None">The semilogarithmic decay plots constructed according to eqn. (III) obeyed straight lines, with the exception of the H atom reaction (4) (see below), indicating the validity of first-order kinetics; the pseudo-first-order rate constants were determined as linear least-squares slopes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="191"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met24" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The bimolecular rate constants were obtained from plots of <IT>k</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB>′ <IT>vs</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="192"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met24" novelty="Old" advantage="None">[R(<IT>i</IT>)].</annotationART></s> <s sid="193"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" advantage="None">The inset in Fig. 7 shows some typical semilogarithmic decay plots measured for reaction (1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="194"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the main panel of Fig. 7, a plot of <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB><IT>vs</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="195"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" advantage="None">[O<SB>2</SB>] is displayed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="196"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met24" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The straight line going through the origin represents a least-squares fit to the data points the slope of which gives the bimolecular rate constant <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="197"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met24" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In the present work we have not corrected the rate constants for viscous pressure drop and diffusion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="198"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met24" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Instead, an 8% contribution to account for such effects was included in the error margins.</annotationART></s> <s sid="199"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met24" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In previous studies with similar systems, we found the corrections to amount to about 2–8%.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="200"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res32" novelty="None" advantage="None">The experimental conditions and kinetic results are summarised in Table 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="201"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res33" novelty="None" advantage="None">The F<SB>2</SB> concentrations listed are approximately equal to [CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB>]<SB>0</SB> as estimated by the degree of dissociation of fluorine in the microwave discharge (∼70%) and an estimated loss of acetonyl radicals inside the moveable injector.</annotationART></s> <s sid="202"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res34" novelty="None" advantage="None">The error bars attached to the <IT>k</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB> values in Table 1 are the overall uncertainties based on the observed statistical errors and the estimated systematic errors.</annotationART></s> <s sid="203"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res34" novelty="None" advantage="None">The overall uncertainties are proposed to represent 2<IT>σ</IT>.</annotationART></s></P><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.2.1">Reaction CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB> + O<SB>2</SB> (1)</HEADER><P><s sid="204"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res35" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rate constant we have determined for the overall reaction between CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB> and O<SB>2</SB> is <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB>(298 K, 2.85 mbar He) = (3.49 ± 0.51) ×10<SP>−13</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="205"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is the first determination of <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB> in the low-pressure regime providing further evidence for the fall-off behaviour of the reaction in comparison with literature data that were reported from kinetic studies at higher pressures.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12 cit14">12,14</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="206"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met25" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The pressure dependence was first established by Oguchi <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF>. who studied the CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB> + O<SB>2</SB> reaction in the range of 20.3–449.3 mbar in He buffer at room temperature by using the LP/LIF experimental method.</annotationART></s> <s sid="207"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met25" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In order to analyse and interpret the experimental rate data, they performed RRKM calculations based on DFT(B3LYP)-estimation of molecular and energetic parameters yielding the limiting high-pressure rate constant of <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB><SP>∞</SP>(298 K) = (9.8 ± 0.8) × 10<SP>−13</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="208"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met25" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Oguchi <IT>et al</IT>. have derived the fall-off parameters according to Troe’s formalism<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27">27</REF> as well from which a <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB> value of 2.36 × 10<SP>−13</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP> is obtained for the pressure of our present investigation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="209"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None">This rate constant is about 30% smaller than the one we have determined, but the agreement is satisfactory in view of the fact that Oguchi <IT>et al</IT>. carried out the experiments in a region where the reaction displayed only weak pressure dependence and therefore the extrapolation to lower pressures might have substantial uncertainty.</annotationART></s> <s sid="210"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The observed fall-off kinetics point to the dominance of a three-body combination between CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB> and O<SB>2</SB>:CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB> + O<SB>2</SB> + M → CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB>O<SB>2</SB> + MΔ<SB>r1a</SB><IT>H</IT>°<SB>298</SB> = −129 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28">28</REF>Further studies are required to decide whether other reaction channels also occur in the reaction between CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB> and O<SB>2</SB>, such as the formation of the products CH<SB>2</SB>CO + CH<SB>2</SB>O + OH and HO<SB>2</SB> + CO + C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>4</SB> which are thermochemically accessible being exothermic by about −86 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> and −11 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="211"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Analogous reaction channels have been reported for the reactions alkyl + O<SB>2</SB><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29">29</REF> and vinoxyl + O<SB>2</SB>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30 cit31">30,31</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="212"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None">As noted in the Introduction, a major part of the atmospheric degradation of acetone involves the acetonyl radical formed by OH hydrogen abstraction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="213"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The further fate of acetonyl is determined entirely by reaction (1) which is orders of magnitude faster than any of the competing processes due to its fairly large rate constant and the high O<SB>2</SB> concentration in the atmosphere.</annotationART></s> <s sid="214"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None">While this condition means simplification for atmospheric modelling studies, it is to be noticed that the reaction of CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB> with O<SB>2</SB> should be treated as pressure dependent practically over the whole <IT>T</IT> and <IT>P</IT> ranges in the troposphere and lower stratosphere.</annotationART></s> <s sid="215"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Up to now, the kinetics of this important atmospheric reaction have been studied only at room temperature, over a limited range of pressures.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.2.2">Reaction CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB> + NO (2)</HEADER><P><s sid="216"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res36" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rate constant of <IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB>(298 K, 2.85 mbar He) = (1.04 ± 0.19) × 10<SP>−11</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP> is proposed from our present work for the overall reaction of the acetonyl radical with nitric oxide.</annotationART></s> <s sid="217"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None">This value is consistent with the results of recent experimental<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13 cit15">13,15</REF> and theoretical<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF> studies, indicating the dominance of a pressure dependent combination reaction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="218"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reaction most likely leads to the formation of nitroso-acetone, CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB>NO:<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF>CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB> + NO + M → CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB>NO + MΔ<SB>r2a</SB><IT>H</IT>°<SB>298</SB> = −151 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28">28</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="219"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None">(The reaction enthalpy we have estimated for reaction (2a) above agrees well with a very recent G2 computational result<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF> of −148 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>.) The disproportionation reaction between acetonyl and NO giving HNO and <IT>c</IT>-propanone is considerably endothermic (by about 50 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>) and so it has no contribution to the overall rate at room temperature.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="220"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met26" novelty="Old" advantage="None">A major part of our knowledge on the kinetics and mechanism of the reaction of acetonyl radical with NO arises from the combined experimental and theoretical work published very recently by Delbos and co-workers.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="221"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met26" novelty="Old" advantage="None">These authors applied the complementary DF/LIF and LP/LIF experimental techniques to study the temperature and pressure dependencies of the acetonyl + NO and vinoxyl + NO reactions between 298 and 447 K in the wide pressure range of 0.8–900 mbar in He buffer gas.</annotationART></s> <s sid="222"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met26" novelty="Old" advantage="None">They explored the potential energy surface of the reactions using <IT>ab initio</IT> molecular orbital computations at the G2 level of theory and utilised the <IT>ab initio</IT> data obtained for the stationary structures in unimolecular rate theory computations<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit32">32</REF> to estimate rate parameters.</annotationART></s> <s sid="223"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met26" novelty="Old" advantage="None">These rate parameters were employed then to set the fall-off parameters for the analysis of the experimental rate constants in terms of Troe’s fitting procedure.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27">27</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="224"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met26" novelty="Old" advantage="None">From the final fall-off parameters Delbos <IT>et al</IT>. report, one obtains <IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB><SP>∞</SP> (298 K) = 3.2 × 10<SP>−11</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP> and <IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB> (298 K, 2.85 mbar He) = (1.3 ± 0.5) × 10<SP>−11</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="225"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res37" novelty="None" advantage="None">The latter value is in satisfactory agreement with our experimental determination.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.2.3">Reaction CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB> + NO<SB>2</SB> (3)</HEADER><P><s sid="226"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res38" novelty="None" advantage="None">Quite unexpectedly, the kinetic study of the reaction between CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB> and NO<SB>2</SB> was complicated by heterogeneous effects.</annotationART></s> <s sid="227"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the first trial experiment a very large consumption of the acetonyl radicals was observed on the wall of the reactor.</annotationART></s> <s sid="228"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res39" novelty="None" advantage="None">This was accompanied by hysteresis: the wall consumption was found to be different when determined in measurements from short-to-long reaction time or <IT>vice</IT><IT>versa</IT> (halocarbon wax was the wall coating in the NO<SB>2</SB> experiments).</annotationART></s> <s sid="229"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res40" novelty="None" advantage="None">Even under such conditions, however, the “reagent NO<SB>2</SB> on–off” technique has corrected very well for the heterogeneous wall reactions at deriving the bimolecular rate constant for reaction (3) as it is seen by the linearity of the semilogarithmic decay plot presented in Fig. 8.</annotationART></s> <s sid="230"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The hysteresis could be completely eliminated by a 30 min conditioning of the reactor with the reaction itself prior to the kinetic runs.</annotationART></s> <s sid="231"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res41" novelty="None" advantage="None">The wall consumption was also reduced, but still remained significantly larger (<IT>k</IT><SB>w</SB> ≈ 70 s<SP>−1</SP>) than observed with the other reaction systems.</annotationART></s> <s sid="232"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res42" novelty="None" advantage="None">The pseudo-first-order kinetics were obeyed well in all experiments conducted in the pre-treated reactor providing the bimolecular rate constant of <IT>k</IT><SB>3</SB> (298 K) = (3.25 ± 0.65) × 10<SP>−11</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="233"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met27" novelty="Old" advantage="None">As far as we are aware, there is a single other determination of <IT>k</IT><SB>3</SB> reported in the literature.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="234"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met27" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Sehested <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF>. used pulse radiolysis combined with transient UV-absorption spectrometry to study the kinetics of the reaction between CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB>/CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB>O<SB>2</SB> radicals and both NO and NO<SB>2</SB> at 295 K in the presence of a large excess of SF<SB>6</SB> (∼1000 mbar).</annotationART></s> <s sid="235"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met27" novelty="Old" advantage="None">They determined <IT>k</IT><SB>3</SB> = (1.6 ± 0.4) × 10<SP>−11</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP> which is only half of the value we have obtained with the DF/LIF experimental technique.</annotationART></s> <s sid="236"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None">At present, we can not offer any reasonable explanation for the large disparity in the results.</annotationART></s> <s sid="237"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Heterogeneous effects were found to be significant in our study, but were controlled in the regular experiments and therefore we believe them not to give rise to a significant systematic error.</annotationART></s> <s sid="238"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Sehested <IT>et al</IT>. carried out the experiments at very large acetonyl concentration (∼1 × 10<SP>15</SP> molecule cm<SP>−3</SP>) that might have led to complications through secondary chemistry.</annotationART></s> <s sid="239"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None">One would expect, however, the secondary reactions to result rather in an overestimation of the rate constant.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="240"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None">No experimental or theoretical information is available on the product channels of the reaction between CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB> and NO<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="241"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met28" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Barnhard and co-workers<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit33">33</REF> studied the related C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>3</SB>O (vinoxyl) + NO<SB>2</SB> reaction by using the LP/LIF method in the temperature and pressure ranges of 295–374 K and 3.3–133 mbar (N<SB>2</SB>), respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="242"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met28" novelty="Old" advantage="None">They found no pressure dependence which might indicate that the nitro-acetaldehyde adduct did not stabilise in their reaction system.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit33">33</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="243"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, it is not unreasonable to assume that the CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB> + NO<SB>2</SB> reaction occurs also not just <IT>via</IT> a simple radical–radical recombination mechanism in contrast to the O<SB>2</SB>- and NO reactions discussed above.</annotationART></s> <s sid="244"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con16" novelty="None" advantage="None">One possibility is that there exists a fast open reaction pathway <IT>via</IT> a series of chemical activation reaction steps (reaction (3b)).</annotationART></s> <s sid="245"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The intermediate (CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB>O)*, if it is formed, is expected to undergo a fast decomposition reaction.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit34">34</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="246"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The radical disproportionation (reaction (3c)) is also feasible thermochemically.</annotationART></s> <s sid="247"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con17" novelty="None" advantage="None">CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB> + NO<SB>2</SB> + M → CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB>NO<SB>2</SB> + M Δ<SB>r3a</SB><IT>H</IT>°<SB>298</SB> = −238 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28">28</REF> CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB> + NO<SB>2</SB> → (CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB>NO<SB>2</SB>)* (CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB>NO<SB>2</SB>)* → (CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB>O)* + NO (CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB>O)* → CH<SB>3</SB>C(O) + CH<SB>2</SB>O Overall: CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB> + NO<SB>2</SB> → CH<SB>3</SB>C(O) + CH<SB>2</SB>O + NO Δ<SB>r3a</SB><IT>H</IT>°<SB>298</SB> = −29 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB> + NO<SB>2</SB> → c-propanone + HNO<SB>2</SB> Δ<SB>r3a</SB><IT>H</IT>°<SB>298</SB> = −86 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP></annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.2.4">Reaction CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB> + H (4)</HEADER><P><s sid="248"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met29" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Double-discharge experiments were carried out to study the kinetics of the reaction of CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB> with H atoms (see Fig. 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="249"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met29" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The absolute hydrogen atom concentration was determined by the well-established gas-titration method with NO<SB>2</SB><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit35">35</REF> by observing the equivalence point in the reaction H + NO<SB>2</SB> → OH + NO with LIF detection of OH.</annotationART></s> <s sid="250"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs19" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have found this reaction of the acetonyl radical to be extremely fast, in fact beyond the limit of measurability with the available gas pumping capacity in the current study.</annotationART></s> <s sid="251"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res43" novelty="None" advantage="None">The semilogarithmic acetonyl decay plots determined in the experiments showed level-off with increasing reaction time indicating a significant consumption of the excess component H atom in the reaction ([H]<SB>0</SB>/[CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB>]<SB>0</SB> ≈ 5 was the initial concentration ratio).</annotationART></s> <s sid="252"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res43" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, only the lower limit of <IT>k</IT><SB>4</SB> (298 K) ≥ 3 × 10<SP>−10</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP> can be proposed from our present study for the rate constant of reaction (4).</annotationART></s> <s sid="253"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reaction is believed to proceed <IT>via</IT> a radical–radical recombination mechanism to form acetone: CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB> + H + M → CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>3</SB> + M Δ<SB>r4a</SB><IT>H</IT>°<SB>298</SB> = −402 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP></annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.2.5">Reactivity of the acetonyl radical</HEADER><P><s sid="254"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The unpaired electron in the acetonyl radical forms a partially delocalized π-electronic system with the carbonyl double bond portrayed as a resonance electronic structure between two localised states, the alkyl form “acetyl-methyl” <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem1">(1)</XREF> and the alkoxyl form “propenyl-oxyl” <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem2">(2)</XREF>:<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit9 cit10 cit11">8–11</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="255"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">A measure of electron delocalisation is the resonance stabilisation energy (RSE) which has recently been suggested to be 17 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> for the acetonyl radical.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="256"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that the “prototype” resonance stabilised allyl radical has 51 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> RSE.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29">29</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="257"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The resonance stabilisation is expected to give rise to reduced reactivity and the question arises whether the acetonyl radical behaves more like an alkyl radical or rather like an alkoxyl radical in its reactions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="258"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res44" novelty="None" advantage="None">These issues are examined in some detail in Table 2 where the acetonyl reactions are compared with analogous reactions of alkoxyl, alkyl and allyl radicals.</annotationART></s> <s sid="259"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met30" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Radicals of roughly comparable size to acetonyl have been used in the comparison whenever possible.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="260"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">During the discussion of the kinetic results above we have presumed that the O<SB>2</SB> molecule adds to the CH<SB>2</SB>-end of acetonyl forming the acetonyl-peroxyl radical (CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB>OO).</annotationART></s> <s sid="261"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">This adduct radical has indeed been found and identified by its UV-absorption spectrum in the reaction.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12 cit24">12,24</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="262"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The alternative alkoxyl mechanism can practically be excluded on the grounds of the relatively small rate constants of the alkoxyl + O<SB>2</SB> reactions and the instability of the trioxy radical that might be formed if the oxygen is added to the alkoxyl site of the acetonyl radical.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29 cit36">29,36</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="263"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The high-pressure limiting rate constant of the CH<SB>3</SB>C(O)CH<SB>2</SB> + O<SB>2</SB> reaction is about ten times smaller than that of the <IT>n</IT>-C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>7</SB> + O<SB>2</SB> reaction <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29 cit37">29,37</REF> which may be taken as an indication of the reduction of the reactivity of the acetonyl radical by resonance stabilisation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="264"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The allyl radical has much higher degree of resonance stabilisation and hence is expected to be even less reactive than the acetonyl radical, but the <IT>k</IT><SP>∞</SP> values for the acetonyl + O<SB>2</SB> and allyl + O<SB>2</SB> reactions are not very different.</annotationART></s> <s sid="265"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res45" novelty="None" advantage="None">In other words, there is no apparent correlation with the bond dissociation energy of the R-O<SB>2</SB> bond formed in the reactions (Table 2).</annotationART></s> <s sid="266"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">A further indication of the effect of resonance stabilisation is provided by the observation that the pressure dependent region is shifted to higher pressures in the case of the acetonyl + O<SB>2</SB> and allyl + O<SB>2</SB> reactions compared with the alkyl+O<SB>2</SB> reactions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7 cit29 cit37 cit38">7,29,37,38</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="267"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The NO molecule is believed to add to the carbon radical site of the acetonyl radical similarly to O<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="268"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met31" novelty="Old" advantage="None">This mechanism has been supported by a recent <IT>ab initio</IT> computation, although the authors noted that addition to the oxygen radical site and a subsequent isomerisation to nitroso-acetone could not be entirely excluded.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="269"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met31" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Similarly to the respective O<SB>2</SB> reactions, the fall-off regimes of the acetonyl + NO and allyl + NO reactions are shifted to higher pressures.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15 cit39">15,39</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="270"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met31" novelty="Old" advantage="None">That is, the observations indicate an efficient reformation of the energised adducts to the reactants in the third-body combination mechanisms of the acetonyl and allyl radicals with both O<SB>2</SB> and NO.</annotationART></s> <s sid="271"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The picture is different, however, concerning the high-pressure limiting rate constants.</annotationART></s> <s sid="272"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">In analogy with the O<SB>2</SB> reactions, one would expect smaller <IT>k</IT><SP>∞</SP> values for the acetonyl + NO and allyl + NO reactions than for the C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>5</SB>+NO reaction, but this is apparently not the case (Table 2).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="273"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The alkoxyl radicals undergo combination reaction with NO<SB>2</SB> forming organic nitrates, while the alkyl radicals are known to react <IT>via</IT> O-transfer.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29 cit41">29,41</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="274"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The resonance stabilised allyl radical reacts also by oxygen atom transfer with NO<SB>2</SB> as it was verified experimentally by the identification of the allyl-oxyl radical (C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>5</SB>O) in the reaction.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit42">42</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="275"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con19" novelty="None" advantage="None">This result provides further argument for the validity of the chemical activation mechanism (3b) we have proposed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="276"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con19" novelty="None" advantage="None">There is no indication for the effect of resonance stabilisation on the kinetics of the NO<SB>2</SB> reactions listed in Table 2.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="277"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con20" novelty="None" advantage="None">The disproportionation-to-recombination rate constant ratios available from the literature indicate that the alkoxyl radicals react mainly by direct hydrogen atom transfer, while the alkyl and allyl radicals <IT>via</IT> a combination mechanism in their reactions with H atoms.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit43 cit44 cit45">43–45</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="278"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res46" novelty="None" advantage="None">The alkyl and allyl reactions have significantly larger rate constants as well.</annotationART></s> <s sid="279"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con21" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, based on the observed large <IT>k</IT><SB>4</SB> value, we assume that the H atom adds to the CH<SB>2</SB> moiety of the acetonyl radical to form acetone in a fast recombination reaction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="280"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res47" novelty="None" advantage="None">There is no sign whatsoever of an effect of resonance stabilisation on the kinetics of the compared H atom reactions.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="281"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con22" novelty="None" advantage="None">In summary, the kinetics features presented in Table 2 clearly show that the acetonyl radical behaves like a carbon centered radical and not like an alkoxyl radical in its reactions with molecules with unpaired electrons.</annotationART></s> <s sid="282"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con22" novelty="None" advantage="None">No general statement can be formulated, however, concerning the reduction of reactivity due to resonance stabilisation; the effect varies from significant to non-existent at all depending on the reaction partner.</annotationART></s> <s sid="283"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res48" novelty="None" advantage="None">Interestingly, the acetonyl and allyl radicals show very similar reactivity contrary that the allyl radical possesses a much higher degree of electron delocalisation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="284"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res49" novelty="None" advantage="None">Most of the reactions compared in Table 2 are radical–radical recombinations, the high-pressure limiting rate constant of which provide the rate constants for the association steps in the third-body combination mechanisms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="285"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res49" novelty="None" advantage="None">These rate constants are seen in Table 2 to vary over a wide range including more than two orders of magnitude variation of the acetonyl data.</annotationART></s> <s sid="286"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con23" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the absence of electronic barriers, the differences in the rates of the association reactions of alkyl and allyl radicals have been explained by dynamic features of the reacting systems and the topology of the potential energy surfaces.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit37 cit46 cit47">37,46–47</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="287"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con23" novelty="None" advantage="None">These include, for instance, the effect of anisotropic long-range potential in the entrance valley of the PES,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit46">46</REF> mixing of the neutral potential energy surface with the charge transfer surface<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit37">37</REF> and the involvement of non-dissociative triplet-state complexes in the dynamics of the reactions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit47">47</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="288"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con24" novelty="None" advantage="None">It would be of considerable interest to perform theoretical studies on the non-barrier effects for the acetonyl reactions as well in order to explain the large differences in the reactivities observed experimentally.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
