<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b404604h" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Threshold photoelectron photoion coincidence study of the fragmentation of valence states of CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> and CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB>F<SP>+</SP> in the range 12–24 eV<XREF TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" /></annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Using tunable vacuum-ultraviolet radiation from a synchrotron source, threshold photoelectron photoion coincidence spectroscopy has studied the unimolecular decay dynamics of the valence electronic states of CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> and CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB>F<SP>+</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Threshold photoelectron spectra and fragment ion yield curves of CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB> and CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB>F have been recorded in the range 12–24 eV, electrons and ions being detected by a threshold electron analyser and a linear time-of-flight mass spectrometer, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the dissociation products of (CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP>)* and (CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB>F<SP>+</SP>)* formed <IT>via</IT> cleavage of a single covalent bond, the mean translation kinetic energy releases have been measured and compared with the predictions of statistical and impulsive mechanisms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None"><IT>Ab initio</IT> G2 calculations have determined the minimum energies of CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB> and CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB>F and their cations, with their geometries optimised at the MP2(full)/6-31G(d) level of theory.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The nature of the valence orbitals of both neutral molecules has also been deduced.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Enthalpies of formation of both titled molecules and all fragment ions and neutrals observed by dissociative photoionisation have also been calculated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">Combining all experimental and theoretical data, the fragmentation mechanisms of the ground and excited states of CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> and CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB>F<SP>+</SP> are discussed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ground state of both ions, formed by electron removal from the C–C σ-bonding highest occupied molecular orbital, is stable only over a narrow range of energies in the Franck–Condon region; it dissociates by C–C bond cleavage with a small fractional translational energy release.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Low-lying excited states of both ions, produced by electron removal from F 2pπ nonbonding orbitals, show some evidence for isolated-state behaviour, with impulsive dissociation by cleavage of a C–F bond and a larger fractional translational energy release into the two fragments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">For energies above <IT>ca</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">16 eV smaller fragment ions, often resulting from cleavage of multiple bonds and HF elimination, are observed; for both molecules with <IT>hν</IT> &gt; 18 eV, CF–CH<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP> is the dominant fragment ion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">New experimental values are determined for the enthalpy of formation at 298 K of CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB> (−751 ± 10 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>) and CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB>F (−671 ± 12 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>), with upper limits being determined for CF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> (≤546 ± 11 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>) and CHF–CH<SB>2</SB>F<SP>+</SP> (≤663 ± 13 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>).</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="1.">Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">An international effort is underway to replace chlorofluorocarbons (CFCs) with environmentally-acceptable alternatives,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2 cit3">1–3</REF> and hydrofluorocarbons (HFCs) are likely to become the accepted CFC replacement in many industrial applications.</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Specifically, several fluorinated ethanes are already being used, including 1,1 difluoroethane (R152a), 1,1,1,2 tetrafluoroethane (R134a) and pentafluoroethane (R125).</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">1,1,1,2 tetrafluoroethane, for example, has been used for many years as a replacement for CF<SB>2</SB>Cl<SB>2</SB> in air-conditioning systems of cars.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">HFCs are being used as CFC alternatives because they lack the chlorine atoms which catalyse the depletion of ozone from the stratosphere.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">HFCs still pose an environmental threat as they contribute to global warming,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF> but the presence of C–H bonds cause them to react faster than CFCs with OH radicals, thereby reducing their lifetime in the earth’s atmosphere.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rate constant at room temperature for the reactions of the two titled HFCs with OH is <IT>ca</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">1.2 × 10<SP>−15</SP> (for CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB>) and 1.6 × 10<SP>−14</SP> (for CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB>F) cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>, respectively.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6 cit7">6,7</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The atmospheric lifetime of these two trifluoroethanes will then be as low as <IT>ca</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">25 or 2 years, assuming an average OH concentration of 10<SP>6</SP> molecule cm<SP>−3</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Removal by photoionisation and photodissociation processes in the mesosphere, therefore, is only likely to play a small role in the overall loss of these molecules from the atmosphere, and is unlikely to be dominant.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, a knowledge of the vacuum-UV (VUV) photochemistry of HFCs that might take place in this region of the atmosphere is needed, and might be important in the determination of the atmospheric lifetime.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our group is investigating the decay dynamics of halocarbon and HFC cations containing at least two carbon atoms, using threshold photoelectron-photoion coincidence (TPEPICO) spectroscopy and synchrotron radiation as a tunable VUV photoionisation source.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">To date, we have studied saturated and unsaturated perfluorocarbons, C<SB><IT>x</IT></SB>F<SB><IT>y</IT></SB><SP>+</SP>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit9">8,9</REF> and three HFCs; pentafluoroethane,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF> and the two isomers of tetrafluoroethane.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">In this paper we report data for the two isomers of the trifluoroethane cation; CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> (R143a, labelled 1,1,1 in this paper) and CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB>F<SP>+</SP> (R143 and labelled 1,1,2 here).</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Preliminary results for the 1,1,1 isomer have been reported elsewhere.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Research carried out on these two isomers of trifluoroethane to date has focussed on the structure, conformational stability, and spectroscopy of the neutral molecule.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">These investigations include infrared and Raman studies,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF> electron diffraction,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF> and <IT>ab initio</IT> calculations.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15 cit16 cit17 cit18 cit19">15–19</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">A microwave spectrum has been reported only for the 1,1,1 isomer,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF> and recommended values for the structure, vibrational frequencies and standard enthalpy of formation for this isomer have been published.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The only papers describing properties of the ionised trifluoroethanes report He I photoelectron and electron-impact mass spectrometric studies of the 1,1,1 isomer.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22 cit23">22,23</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In the latter paper, appearance energies of the fragment ions were measured.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">To our knowledge, there are no equivalent data for the 1,1,2 isomer.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">In this paper we describe the results of a TPEPICO study of CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB> and CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB>F from the onset of ionisation (<IT>ca</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">12 eV) up to 24 eV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The threshold photoelectron spectrum (TPES) and state-selected fragmentation studies of the parent ions are presented.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Breakdown diagrams, yielding the formation probability of fragment ions as a function of photon energy, are obtained.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The mean translational kinetic energy releases for unimolecular fragmentation proceeding <IT>via</IT> a single-bond cleavage are determined, and compared with the predictions of statistical and dynamical impulsive models.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Enthalpies of formation at 298 K for the two neutral isomers and some fragment ions are also determined.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">These experimental results are complemented and compared with <IT>ab initio</IT> calculations of the structure of the two isomers of trifluoroethane, their ionisation energies, and the enthalpy of formation of several fragment ions.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.">Theoretical and experimental methods</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.1">Computational methods</HEADER><P><s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="New" advantage="None">Using Gaussian 98, <IT>ab initio</IT> molecular orbital calculations have been performed for CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB> and CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB>F, both in their neutral ground states and in the ground states of the parent cations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="New" advantage="None">Calculations have also been performed for fragments produced by VUV dissociative photoionisation (<IT>e.g</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="New" advantage="None">CF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Structures for all species were optimised using the second-order Møller–Plesset theory (MP2) with the 6-31G(d) basis set, and all electrons were included at the MP2(full)/6-31G(d) level.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The MP2(full)/6-31G(d) structures were then employed for energy calculations according to the Gaussian-2 (G2) procedure.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This procedure involves single-point total energy calculations at the MP4/6-311G(d,p), QCISD(T)/6-311g(d,p), MP4/6-311G(d,p), MP4/6-311G(2df,p), and MP2/6-311G(3df,2p) levels.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">A small empirical correction is employed to include the high-level correlation effects in the calculations of the total electronic energies (EE).</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The HF/6-31G(d) harmonic vibrational frequencies, scaled by 0.8929, are applied for zero-point vibrational energy (ZPVE) corrections to obtain the total energies at 0 K (<IT>E</IT><SB>0</SB> = EE + ZPVE).</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The enthalpies of formation at 298 K (Δ<SB>f</SB><IT>H</IT>°<SB>298</SB>) for molecular species are calculated using total energies and the scaled HF/6-31G(d) harmonic frequencies, leading to predicted enthalpies of unimolecular reactions (<IT>e.g</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB>F → CHF–CH<SB>2</SB>F<SP>+</SP> + F + e<SP>−</SP>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The agreement between G2 and experimental results is usually well within ±0.2 eV (or ±20 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.2">Experimental methods</HEADER><P><s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The TPEPICO apparatus has been described in detail elsewhere.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11 cit25">11,25</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Synchrotron radiation from the 2 GeV electron storage ring at the Daresbury Laboratory is energy-selected using a 1 m Seya monochromator equipped with two gratings, covering the energy range <IT>ca</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">8–40 eV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The majority of the experiments for CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB> were performed using the higher-energy grating (range 105–30 nm (12–40 eV), blazed at <IT>ca</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">55 nm) with an optical resolution of 0.3 nm; this corresponds to an energy resolution of 0.035 and 0.140 eV at 12 and 24 eV, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">For CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB>F, most experiments used the lower-energy grating (range 150–60 nm (8–21 eV), blazed at <IT>ca</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">90 nm) with the same resolution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">With the higher-energy grating, the effects of second-order radiation are insignificant for <IT>λ</IT> &lt; 95 nm, and for the lower-energy grating insignificant for <IT>λ</IT> &lt; 120 nm.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The VUV radiation is admitted into the interaction region through a glass capillary, and the photon flux is monitored using a photomultiplier tube <IT>via</IT> the visible fluorescence from a sodium salicylate-coated window.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Threshold photoelectrons and fragment cations produced by photoionisation are extracted in opposite directions by a 20 V cm<SP>−1</SP> electric field applied across the interaction region, and detected by a single channel electron multiplier and microchannel plates, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The design of threshold electron analyser and time-of-flight mass spectrometer are described elsewhere.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11 cit25">11,25</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Following discrimination and pulse shaping, signals from the electron and ion detectors pass to a time-to-digital converter (TDC) configured in the multi-hit mode and mounted in a PC.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The electrons provide the ‘start’, the ions the ‘stop’ pulses, allowing signals from the same ionisation process to be detected in delayed coincidence.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">TPEPICO spectra are recorded either continuously as a function of photon energy or at a fixed energy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In the scanning-energy mode, flux-normalized TPEPICO spectra are recorded as three-dimensional, false-colour maps of coincidence count <IT>vs.</IT> ion flight time <IT>vs.</IT> photon energy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="Old" advantage="None">A cut through the map at a fixed photon energy yields the time of flight mass spectrum (TOF-MS), which identifies the fragment ions formed in the dissociative photoionisation at that energy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Alternatively, a background-subtracted cut taken through the histogram at a fixed flight time, corresponding to a mass peak in the TOF-MS, gives an ion yield curve.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In this mode of operation, the TOF resolution is degraded to 64 ns so that <IT>all</IT> the fragment ions are observed simultaneously.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The threshold electron and total ion counts are also recorded, yielding the TPES and total ion yield curve, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In the fixed-energy mode, time-of-flight spectra (later referred to as TPEPICO-TOF spectra) are measured at <IT>single</IT> energies corresponding to peaks in the TPES.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Now a TOF resolution as high as the signal level permits is employed, typically 8 ns, and usually only one fragment ion is observed per spectrum.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">Fragment ions often have enough translational energy for the peaks comprising the TPEPICO-TOF spectra to be substantially broadened.</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">From an analysis of the peak shape, it is then possible to obtain kinetic energy release distributions (KERDs) and hence mean kinetic energy releases, 〈KE〉<SB>T</SB>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26 cit27">26,27</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The sample gases, CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB> and CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB>F, were obtained commercially (Fluorochem Ltd., UK), with a stated purity of &gt;99% and used without further purification.</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The operating pressure was <IT>ca</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">5 × 10<SP>−5</SP> mbar, with a chamber base pressure of <IT>ca</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">5 × 10<SP>−8</SP> mbar.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.">Energetics of the dissociation channels</HEADER><P><s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The energetics of the dissociation channels of CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> and CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB>F<SP>+</SP> into fragment ions are given in Table 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The enthalpies of reaction at temperature <IT>T</IT>, Δ<SB>r</SB><IT>H</IT>°<SB><IT>T</IT></SB>, associated with the unimolecular reaction AB → A<SP>+</SP> + B + e<SP>−</SP>, where AB refers to the parent molecule, are determined by calculating the difference between the enthalpies of formation of products and reactants.</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="Old" advantage="None">We have used Δ<SB>f</SB><IT>H</IT>° data at 298 K for neutrals taken from the Janaf tables,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28">28</REF> for ions from Lias <IT>et al.</IT>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29">29</REF> and these values, in units of kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>, are shown in brackets in column 1 of the table.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Where values different from these compilations are used, they are referenced later.</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The values used for the two parent molecules, −751 ± 10 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> for CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB> and −671 ± 12 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> for CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB>F, are discussed in Section 5.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None">Our experiment measures appearance energies at 298 K (AE<SB>298</SB>) of fragment ions, and some discussion is pertinent on how these data are measured and how they relate to Δ<SB>r</SB><IT>H</IT>°<SB>298</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Columns 2 and 3 of Table 1 give AE<SB>298</SB> and Δ<SB>r</SB><IT>H</IT>°<SB>298</SB> values for the <IT>major</IT> fragment ions; a major ion is defined as one produced by a single bond fission.</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met14" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The AE<SB>298</SB> of each fragment ion has been determined from the extrapolation of the linear portion of the ion yield to zero signal.</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met14" novelty="Old" advantage="None">At the optical resolution of our experiment, this is equivalent to the first onset of signal.</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met14" novelty="Old" advantage="None">No corrections have been made for exit channel barriers or kinetic shifts, and AEs determined in this way can only be regarded as upper limits.</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met14" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The procedure of Traeger and McLoughlin<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30">30</REF> has been used to convert the AE<SB>298</SB> into Δ<SB>r</SB><IT>H</IT>°<SB>298</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met14" novelty="Old" advantage="None">For the reaction AB → A<SP>+</SP> + B + e<SP>−</SP>, Traeger and McLoughlin have shown that:As above, the upper limit for Δ<SB>r</SB><IT>H</IT>°<SB>298</SB> arises due to the fact that there may be an exit channel barrier and/or a kinetic shift; if both are zero, then the equality sign in eqn. (1) applies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met14" novelty="Old" advantage="None">This equation assumes the validity of the stationary electron convention that, at threshold, the electron has zero translational energy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met14" novelty="Old" advantage="No">If the last three terms in eqn. (1) are ignored, a significant error may be introduced in equating the measured AE<SB>298</SB> into an upper limit for Δ<SB>r</SB><IT>H</IT>°<SB>298</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met14" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The second and third terms on the right-hand side of eqn. (1), equivalent to <IT>H</IT>°<SB>298</SB> − <IT>H</IT>°<SB>0</SB> for A<SP>+</SP> or B, contain contributions from translational (2.5<IT>RT</IT>), rotational (1.5<IT>RT</IT>) and vibrational (<IT>N</IT><SB>A</SB><IT>hν</IT>/[exp(<IT>hν</IT>/<IT>k</IT><SB>B</SB><IT>T</IT>) − 1] per vibrational mode) motion, evaluated at <IT>T</IT> = 298 K. The error is greater the larger the number of vibrational modes, and hence the number of atoms in A<SP>+</SP> and B. Vibrational frequencies of A<SP>+</SP> and B are taken from standard sources.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28 cit31">28,31</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met14" novelty="Old" advantage="None">If they are not available, they are estimated by comparison with isoelectronic molecules.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met14" novelty="New" advantage="None">For the <IT>minor</IT> fragment ions, defined as ions caused by a fission of multiple bonds, column 3 of Table 1 gives the values of Δ<SB>r</SB><IT>H</IT>°<SB>298</SB> calculated from the enthalpy of formation of products minus that of reactants, using the values in column 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met14" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Column 2 shows the AE<SB>298</SB> of the minor ion, and we have not converted this value into an upper limit for Δ<SB>r</SB><IT>H</IT>°<SB>298</SB><IT>via</IT> the procedure of Traeger and McLoughlin.</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met14" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Comparison of the values in Columns 2 and 3 can suggest what neutral partner(s) form with the minor fragment ion.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.">Theoretical results</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.1">Structure of CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB> and CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP>, and orbital character</HEADER><P><s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The optimised geometries of CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB> and CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> (Table 2) have been obtained at the MP2(full)/6-31G(d) level.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both have a staggered <IT>C</IT><SB>3v</SB> symmetry, and the geometry for the neutral is very close to that from electron diffraction<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF> and microwave<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF> studies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The highest occupied molecular orbital (HOMO) has mainly C–C σ character (Fig. 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Loss of an electron from this orbital yields the ground state of CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> which is predicted to have a lengthened C–C bond.</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The orbitals of next lowest energy (labelled HOMO − 1(a) and HOMO − 1(b) in Fig. 1) are degenerate π orbitals with a node on different C–C–H planes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">They are largely localised on the CH<SB>3</SB> group with some C–H bonding character, and give rise to two bands due to Jahn–Teller splitting following ionisation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The next two orbitals, labelled HOMO − 2 and HOMO − 3, are mainly F 2pπ nonbonding in character.</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">We note that ionisation from these orbitals will give rise to excited states of CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> which are expected to dissociate <IT>via</IT> F-loss to CF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> + F, provided dissociation follows a rapid impulsive mechanism.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">At this level of theory, the main geometry changes upon ionisation from the HOMO of CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB> are a C–C bond length increase of 0.42 Å, a C–F bond length decrease of 0.06 Å, and a transition from non-planar to planar geometry for the CF<SB>3</SB> and CH<SB>3</SB> groups where the positive charge is localised.</annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">G2 energies are computed for the ground states of CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB> and CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">From the difference, an adiabatic ionisation energy (AIE) of 12.51 eV at 0 K, 12.54 eV at 298 K, is obtained.</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The unfavourable Franck–Condon factors at the onset of the first photoelectron band will almost certainly lead to an experimental onset of signal which is significantly greater than this <IT>ab initio</IT> value.</annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">A vertical ionisation energy (VIE) of 13.92 eV was deduced from the ground state of CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB>, using the G2 energy for CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> calculated with its geometry constrained to that of CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.2">Structure of CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB>F and CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB>F<SP>+</SP>, and orbital character</HEADER><P><s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The minimum energy geometries of CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB>F and CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB>F<SP>+</SP> have also been determined at the MP2(full)/6-31G(d) level (Table 3).</annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the neutral, the trans structure with a symmetry of <IT>C</IT><SB>1</SB> is more stable, in agreement with the conclusions reported through analysis of infrared/Raman spectra and electron diffraction.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13 cit14">13,14</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">For CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB>F<SP>+</SP>, the main structural change after ionisation is an increase of 0.43 Å in the C–C bond length, a decrease of 0.07 Å in the C–F bond length, and an increase in the ∠FCF, ∠FCH and ∠HCH bond angles in both the CHF<SB>2</SB> and CH<SB>2</SB>F groups.</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, both the CHF<SB>2</SB> and CH<SB>2</SB>F groups adopt a more planar structure upon ionisation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">There is also a small rotation about the C–C bond upon ionisation that leads to four atoms FCCF being approximately located in a plane.</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met15" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The AIE of CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB>F was calculated through the G2 energy difference between the ground state of the neutral molecule and its cation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">A value of 11.68 eV is then deduced at 298 K. As with CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB>, the poor Franck–Condon factor in the threshold region will almost certainly lead to an overestimation of the adiabatic ionisation energy from the onset of signal in the threshold photoelectron spectrum compared to this <IT>ab initio</IT> value.</annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The VIE of CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB>F was not determined.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The structure of the neutral molecule and the five highest valence molecular orbitals (MOs) are shown in Fig 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">At this level of theory, the HOMO consists of mainly C–C σ bonding and C–H σ* antibonding character, consistent with the changes in geometry after ionisation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The orbital of next highest energy (<IT>i.e.</IT> HOMO − 1) is a π* orbital localized on the CH<SB>2</SB>F group, with C–H σ bonding character.</annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The (HOMO − 2) orbital is a hybrid orbital largely localized on the CHF<SB>2</SB> group, consisting of C–H σ bonding and F 2pπ lone-pair character.</annotationART></s> <s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both of the next two higher excited valence orbitals (HOMO − 3 and HOMO − 4) are mainly composed of F 2pπ lone-pair nonbonding orbitals.</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The removal of an electron from this type of orbital is expected to result in C–F bond fission, <IT>i.e.</IT> fragmention to C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>3</SB>F<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP> + F, provided the dissociation follows an impulsive mechanism.</annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that if this mechanism is operative, the electron density maps of the orbitals (Fig. 2) suggest that F loss from the (HOMO − 3) orbital should produce predominantly the isomer CHF–CH<SB>2</SB>F<SP>+</SP>, whereas F loss from (HOMO − 4) will yield both CHF–CH<SB>2</SB>F<SP>+</SP> and CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.3">Calculation of Δ<SB>r</SB><IT>H</IT>°<SB>298</SB> for dissociative photoionisation reactions</HEADER><P><s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met16" novelty="Old" advantage="None">As described earlier, the enthalpies of formation at 298 K of both isomers of C<SB>2</SB>F<SB>3</SB>H<SB>3</SB> and all the neutral and fragment ions observed by dissociative photoionisation have been calculated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met16" novelty="Old" advantage="None">It is therefore possible to calculate the enthalpy of reaction at this temperature for all the observed reactions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">For reactions involving production of a major fragment ion, these values are shown in column 4 of Table 1, and we should note that these G2 calculations refer specifically to reactants and products whose energies have been determined with optimised geometries.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="5.">Experimental results and discussion</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="5.1">Threshold photoelectron spectra of CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB> and CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB>F</HEADER><P><s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met17" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The threshold photoelectron spectrum (TPES) of CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB> was measured in the range 13–22 eV at an optical resolution of 0.3 nm (Fig 3).</annotationART></s> <s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The vertical ionisation energies of the six peaks, labelled as the X̃, Ã, B̃, C̃, D̃ and Ẽ states of the parent ion, are 14.56, 15.19, 16.03, 16.91, 19.00 and 20.23 eV, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The onset of ionisation is 12.98 ± 0.04 eV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">A notable feature of this spectrum is that the ground electronic state of CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> partially overlaps that of the first excited state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">This observation is different from CHF<SB>2</SB>-CF<SB>3</SB>, CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB>F and CHF<SB>2</SB>–CHF<SB>2</SB>, and CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10 cit11 cit12">10–12</REF> where these molecules all have broad but well-separated first photoelectron bands following electron removal from the HOMO.</annotationART></s> <s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">These four molecules also show an increase in the energy of the onset of ionisation as the number of fluorine atoms increases, an effect already noted by Sauvageau <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF>. from He I photoelectron spectra.</annotationART></s> <s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, corresponding bands of higher energy in their TPES shift to higher energy with an increase in the number of fluorine atoms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">These observations are consistent with the perfluoro effect, arising from the higher effective nuclear charge of a fluorine compared to a hydrogen atom and the corresponding stabilisation of the σ orbitals in fluorinated ethanes.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit32">32</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The anomalous behaviour of CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB>, with its unusually high onset of ionisation giving rise to overlap of the first and second photoelectron bands, may arise due to the higher symmetry of this molecule, although the same behaviour is observed for CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB>F which has lower symmetry (see later).</annotationART></s> <s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that the <IT>ab initio</IT> calculations described in Section 4 show that the energy difference between the HOMO of CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB> and the degenerate π orbitals is small, only 0.6 eV at the MP2/6-31G(d) level.</annotationART></s> <s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">As with all the other hydrofluorocarbons, electron removal from the strong C–C σ-bonding HOMO will yield a broad photoelectron band.</annotationART></s> <s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, the overlap of the first and second photoelectron bands in the (T)PES of CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB> is not surprising.</annotationART></s> <s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The two bands centred around 16 and 17 eV in the TPES of CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB> are likely to be due to removal of an electron from the (HOMO − 2) and (HOMO − 3) molecular orbitals of F 2pπ lone pair character.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="143"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The band positions reported by Sauvageau <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF>. from the He I photoelectron spectrum of CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB> are similar to those of the TPES reported here, but the relative intensities of the bands are different.</annotationART></s> <s sid="144"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">This difference could be due either to a change in the relative ionisation cross section between excitation at threshold and excitation above threshold with non-resonant radiation, or to autoionisation effects.</annotationART></s> <s sid="145"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met18" novelty="Old" advantage="None">As noted in our previous papers on small perfluorocarbons,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit9">8,9</REF> a comparison of the total ion yield and the integrated TPES can reveal the peaks in the TPES that arise <IT>via</IT> autoionisation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="146"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">There is excellent agreement between the integrated TPES and the total ion yield of CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit33">33</REF> indicating that no autoionisation processes occur in this energy area.</annotationART></s> <s sid="147"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is likely, therefore, that for CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB> the former explanation is correct.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="148"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The onset of ionisation, 12.98 ± 0.04 eV, is 0.28 eV lower than that reported by electron impact ionisation,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF> but 0.44 eV higher than the <IT>ab initio</IT> calculation at 298 K (Section 4.1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="149"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">This latter difference must be due to the near-zero Franck–Condon factor at the onset of the first photoelectron band due to the large geometry change upon ionisation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="150"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Combining the experimental onset with the value for Δ<SB>f</SB><IT>H</IT>°<SB>298</SB>(CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB>) of −751 ± 10 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> (see later), we determine Δ<SB>f</SB><IT>H</IT>°<SB>298</SB>(CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP>) &lt; 501 ± 11 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="151"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The threshold photoelectron spectrum of CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB>F was also measured with an optical resolution of 0.3 nm (Fig 4).</annotationART></s> <s sid="152"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The vertical ionisation energies of the eight observed peaks (or shoulders) in the range 12–25 eV are determined to be 13.03, 13.75, 14.96, 15.97, 17.51, 18.62, 19.17 and 22.26 eV, and these are labelled as ionisation to the X̃, Ã, B̃, C̃, D̃, Ẽ, F̃ and G̃ states of the parent ion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="153"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The band corresponding to the ground ionic state is relatively weak and broad, consistent with the large change in geometry following electron removal from the HOMO of C–C σ-bonding character.</annotationART></s> <s sid="154"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The next two bands, labelled Ã and B̃ at 13.75 and 14.96 eV respectively, are assigned to mainly C–H σ-bonding orbitals localised on the CH<SB>2</SB>F and CHF<SB>2</SB> groups, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="155"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that, as with CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB>, the X̃ and Ã bands are not well separated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="156"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">At higher energy the TPES of CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB>F shows two relatively narrow peaks centred at 15.97 and 17.51 eV, labelled C̃ and D̃.</annotationART></s> <s sid="157"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Narrow peaks in photoelectron spectra with unresolved vibrational structure often relate to the removal of a non-bonding electron, confirming that the (HOMO − 3) and (HOMO − 4) molecular orbitals of this molecule are essentially F 2pπ nonbonding in character.</annotationART></s> <s sid="158"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is shown later that 15.97 eV corresponds to the photon energy leading to the maximum intensity of the fragment ion CHF–CH<SB>2</SB>F<SP>+</SP> produced by breaking a C–F bond.</annotationART></s> <s sid="159"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">This phenomenon of isolated state-selected behaviour in the hydrofluorocarbon cations is relatively common, and has been observed by us and others in C<SB>2</SB>F<SB>4</SB>H<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP>, C<SB>2</SB>F<SB>5</SB>H<SP>+</SP> and C<SB>2</SB>F<SB>6</SB><SP>+</SP>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10 cit11 cit34">10,11,34</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="160"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The observed onset of signal in the TPES occurs at 11.88 ± 0.04 eV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="161"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">This experimental ionisation threshold is 0.20 eV higher than the calculated AIE of CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB>F from the G2 calculation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="162"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">This difference is due to the very low Franck–Condon factor in the threshold region, and the observed ionisation threshold should only be regarded as an upper limit.</annotationART></s> <s sid="163"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Combining the observed IE with a value for Δ<SB>f</SB><IT>H</IT>°<SB>298</SB>(CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB>F) of –671 ± 12 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> (see later), we determine Δ<SB>f</SB><IT>H</IT>°<SB>298</SB>(CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB>F<SP>+</SP>) &lt; 475 ± 13 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="164"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None">As with CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB>, the excellent agreement between the integrated TPES and the total ion yield suggests that autoionisation is not an important process in this energy range.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit33">33</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="165"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">We note no published HeI photoelectron spectrum exists to compare the relative peak intensities to the spectrum recorded under threshold conditions (Fig. 4).</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="5.2">Scanning-energy TPEPICO spectra</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="5.2.1">Coincidence ion yields of CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP></HEADER><P><s sid="166"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met19" novelty="Old" advantage="None">A TPEPICO spectrum in the scanning-energy mode was recorded for CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB> from 12–22 eV at a wavelength resolution of 0.3 nm and an ion TOF resolution of 64 ns.</annotationART></s> <s sid="167"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The parent ion and the fragments CF<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP>, CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP>, CF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> and CF–CH<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP> were detected as the strongest five ions, and their yields are shown in Fig. 5.</annotationART></s> <s sid="168"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The parent ion appears weakly at the lowest energy, then with increasing energy the three major fragment ions CF<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP>, CF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> and CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> are observed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="169"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">These four ions are the main fragments within the energy range 12–17 eV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="170"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">At higher energy, an ion of mass 45 u, almost certainly CF–CH<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP>, appears gradually and becomes the dominant fragment in the range 18–21 eV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="171"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Very weak minor fragment ions are also observed with masses of 33 u (CH<SB>2</SB>F<SP>+</SP>) and 64 u (CF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP>), but their yields are not shown in Fig. 5.</annotationART></s> <s sid="172"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">We comment that as with CHF<SB>2</SB>-CF<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF> but unlike both isomers of C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>2</SB>F<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF> we did not observe any signal due to CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP>, corresponding to C–H bond fission.</annotationART></s> <s sid="173"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met19" novelty="Old" advantage="No">Note that by using a TOF resolution of only 64 ns, a definitive determination of the number of hydrogen atoms in a fragment ion can be problematic, but we are confident of these assignments.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="174"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Within the energy range of the ground ionic state, the cation CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> is observed with an appearance energy of 12.98 ± 0.04 eV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="175"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">This signal is relatively weak and appears over a narrow energy range, suggesting that the X̃ state of CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> is bound only for a small range of low vibrational levels in the Franck–Condon envelope.</annotationART></s> <s sid="176"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The slow rise of the ion yield in the threshold region is due to the small Franck–Condon factor at threshold.</annotationART></s> <s sid="177"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Electron impact studies have observed an ionisation threshold of 13.26 eV.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="178"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met19" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">Due to the electron energy resolution being significantly inferior, the results from our photon-impact experiment should be more accurate.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="179"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The CF<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> fragment ion has an AE<SB>298</SB> of 13.25 ± 0.05 eV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="180"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None">This fragment is the most intense and dominates until 15.5 eV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="181"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">Using the procedure of Traeger and McLoughlin,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30">30</REF> this value of AE<SB>298</SB> converts into an upper limit of 13.41 ± 0.05 eV for Δ<SB>r</SB><IT>H</IT>°<SB>298</SB> for the reaction CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB> → CF<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> + CH<SB>3</SB> + e<SP>−</SP> (Table 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="182"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">C–C bond cleavage can also produce CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> as the fragment ion, where we measure AE<SB>298</SB> to be 14.25 ± 0.05 eV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="183"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">As above, this value can be used to determine an upper limit of Δ<SB>r</SB><IT>H</IT>°<SB>298</SB> for the reaction CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB> → CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> + CF<SB>3</SB> + e<SP>−</SP> to be 14.41 ± 0.05 eV (Table 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="184"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">G2 calculations predict Δ<SB>r</SB><IT>H</IT>°<SB>298</SB> for these two reactions to be very similar, 13.52 and 14.28 eV, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="185"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met20" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Our experimental values can be used to determine an average Δ<SB>f</SB><IT>H</IT>°<SB>298</SB> for the parent neutral molecule.</annotationART></s> <s sid="186"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">Using literature values of Δ<SB>f</SB><IT>H</IT>°<SB>298</SB> for CH<SB>3</SB>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28">28</REF> CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit35">35</REF> CF<SB>3</SB><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit36">36</REF> and CF<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit37">37</REF> a lower limit of −751 ± 10 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> is determined for Δ<SB>f</SB><IT>H</IT>°<SB>298</SB>(CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="187"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">This value is in excellent agreement with −771 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> from our G2 calculation, and independent theoretical values of −746 ± 2 and −755 from Chen <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF>. and Zachariah <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="188"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met21" novelty="Old" advantage="None">By assuming that there are no exit channel barriers or kinetic shifts in either reaction we equate our lower limit value with the absolute value.</annotationART></s> <s sid="189"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met21" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Henceforth, therefore, we use Δ<SB>f</SB><IT>H</IT>°<SB>298</SB>(CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB>) = −751 ± 10 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="190"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">The CF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> fragment ion signal appears with a threshold of 14.10 eV ± 0.05 eV, corresponding to an upper limit of Δ<SB>r</SB><IT>H</IT>°<SB>298</SB> for the reaction CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB> → CF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> + F + e<SP>−</SP> of 14.26 eV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="191"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The signal increases slowly, then rises rapidly from approximately 15.5 eV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="192"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" advantage="None">From 14.1–17.8 eV, the peaks in the ion yield of CF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> match the bands in the TPES.</annotationART></s> <s sid="193"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">An interesting point is that the emergence of the second threshold at 15.5 eV corresponds to the onset of the B̃-state band in the TPES.</annotationART></s> <s sid="194"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">The <IT>ab initio</IT> calculation shows that this band is associated with the electronic state caused largely by electron loss from the (HOMO − 2) F 2pπ nonbonding orbital.</annotationART></s> <s sid="195"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">The (HOMO − 3) orbital also has F 2pπ nonbonding character.</annotationART></s> <s sid="196"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The similarity of the ion signal with the shape of the B̃ and C̃ bands in the TPES suggest that CF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> is produced directly <IT>via</IT> C–F bond cleavage by an impulsive mechanism from these electronics states of the parent cation without prior internal energy conversion to the ground state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="197"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">From the upper limit of Δ<SB>r</SB><IT>H</IT>°<SB>298</SB>, we determine Δ<SB>f</SB><IT>H</IT>°<SB>298</SB>(CF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP>) ≤ 546 ± 11 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="198"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None">We were not able to measure the kinetic energy release in the dissociation CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> → CF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> + F (Section 6), but by analogy with the 1,1,2 isomer we can asssume that it may be considerable.</annotationART></s> <s sid="199"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is likely, therefore, that the true enthalpy of formation of this ion is significantly lower than this value.</annotationART></s> <s sid="200"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" advantage="None">A G2 calculation, for instance, predicts Δ<SB>f</SB><IT>H</IT>°<SB>298</SB>(CF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP>) to be 443 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>, and Lias <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29">29</REF>. give an indirect value of 458 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="201"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None">These data are therefore self-consistent, and suggest that the AE<SB>298</SB>(CF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP>) lies well above the thermochemical threshold energy of CF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> + F + e<SP>−</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="202"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The daughter ion is therefore likely to be formed with the release of significant kinetic energy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="203"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con15" novelty="None" advantage="None">We comment that, in principle, it should be possible to determine experimentally the <IT>absolute</IT> value of Δ<SB>f</SB><IT>H</IT>°<SB>298</SB>(CF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP>) by measuring the kinetic energy release into CF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> + F as a function of photon energy, and extrapolating the linear graph to determine the photon energy at which the kinetic energy release would be zero.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit38">38</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="204"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None">This procedure would then yield the dissociative ionisation energy, <IT>i.e.</IT> Δ<SB>r</SB><IT>H</IT>°<SB>0</SB> for the reaction CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB> → CF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> + F + e<SP>−</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="205"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Unfortunately, whilst this experiment has been successfully employed for the <IT>ground</IT> electronic state of polyatomic cations which are repulsive in the Franck–Condon region (<IT>e.g</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="206"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None">CF<SB>4</SB><SP>+</SP> and SF<SB>6</SB><SP>+</SP>),<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit38">38</REF> we have not been able to yield equivalent data for repulsive, <IT>excited</IT> electronic states.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10 cit11">10,11</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="207"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Possible reasons for the failure of such experiments are described elsewhere.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10 cit11">10,11</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="208"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None">We can, therefore, only confirm an experimental upper limit for Δ<SB>f</SB><IT>H</IT>°<SB>298</SB>(CF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP>) of 546 ± 11 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="209"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Above 17 eV, minor ions are observed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="210"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The strongest is CF–CH<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP> which appears with a threshold of 17.1 ± 0.1 eV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="211"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Energetically, this minor ion can only form with HF + F as neutrals (Table 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="212"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con16" novelty="None" advantage="None">As the direct three-body dissociation CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB> → CF–CH<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP> + HF + F + e<SP>−</SP> seems unlikely, we propose a two-step mechanism to form CF–CH<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="213"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The first step involves the loss of a F atom to produce CF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP>, the second step (CF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> → CF–CH<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP> + HF) proceeds <IT>via</IT> a tight transition state and HF elimination.</annotationART></s> <s sid="214"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ion yield curves of CF–CH<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP> and CF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> support this suggestion, since the increase of the CF–CH<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP> signal corresponds exactly to the decrease of the CF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> signal.</annotationART></s> <s sid="215"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The second step will almost certainly involve a barrier in the exit channel, and could explain why the AE<SB>298</SB> of CF–CH<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP> bears no relation to the energy of the dissociation channel CF–CH<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP> + HF + F + e<SP>−</SP>; the former lies <IT>ca</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="216"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con16" novelty="None" advantage="None">1.5 eV higher in energy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="217"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Such a three-body dissociation through a sequential two-step mechanism has already been suggested to explain the products of dissociative photoionisation of CFCl<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit39">39</REF> and CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit40">40</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="218"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs20" novelty="None" advantage="None">Above 18 eV, CF–CH<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP> becomes the dominant ion fragment.</annotationART></s> <s sid="219"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs21" novelty="None" advantage="None">Very weak signals due to the minor ions CF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP> (mass 64 u) and CH<SB>2</SB>F<SP>+</SP> (mass 33 u) are also observed above 16.5 eV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="220"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con17" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the latter case, the most likely accompanying neutral fragment is CHF<SB>2</SB>, so these products can only form <IT>via</IT> both H- and F-migration across the C–C bond.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="5.2.2">Coincidence ion yields of CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB>F<SP>+</SP></HEADER><P><s sid="221"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met22" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The TPEPICO spectrum in the energy range 11.8–24.0 eV was measured with an optical resolution of 0.3 nm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="222"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs22" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ion yields are shown in Fig. 6.</annotationART></s> <s sid="223"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs23" novelty="None" advantage="None">The parent ion appears at lowest energy from the ground ionic state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="224"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs24" novelty="None" advantage="None">As the photon energy increases, a C–C bond fragmentation reaction takes place, followed at higher energy by cleavage of a C–F bond.</annotationART></s> <s sid="225"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs24" novelty="None" advantage="None">This can be seen in the ion yields for CHF<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP>, CH<SB>2</SB>F<SP>+</SP>, and CHF–CH<SB>2</SB>F<SP>+</SP> or CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="226"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs25" novelty="None" advantage="None">As with the 1,1,1 isomer, C–H bond cleavage is not observed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="227"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res29" novelty="None" advantage="None">These four major ions are the dominant fragments until 16 eV, when a new reaction channel involving two or more bond cleavages opens, possibly with intra-molecular proton transfer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="228"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs26" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fragment CF–CH<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP> gradually becomes the dominant ion in the higher photon energy region, and we note that an ion of mass 45 u was also dominant with <IT>hν</IT> &gt; 18 eV for 1,1,1 trifluoroethane (Section 5.2.1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="229"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met23" novelty="Old" advantage="None">As for CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB>, we have used the procedure of Traeger and McLoughlin<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30">30</REF> to convert the AE<SB>298</SB> of the major fragment ions, determined from an extrapolation of the linear portion of the ion yield to the baseline, into an upper limit for the enthalpy of the unimolecular reaction at 298 K, Δ<SB>r</SB><IT>H</IT>°<SB>298</SB>, in order to determine unknown values of enthalpies of formation at this temperature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="230"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met23" novelty="Old" advantage="None">For the minor ions, we only compare AE<SB>298</SB>(CF–CH<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP>) with Δ<SB>r</SB><IT>H</IT>°<SB>298</SB> for the possible dissociation reactions to infer what the accompanying neutrals may be.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="231"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res30" novelty="None" advantage="None">From the onset of ionisation, 11.88 eV, up to <IT>ca.</IT> 12.5 eV, the parent ion forms exclusively, implying that low vibrational levels of the ground state of the parent cation are bound and lie below the first dissociation threshold.</annotationART></s> <s sid="232"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs27" novelty="None" advantage="None">The parent ion intensity decreases sharply when the fragmentation channel to produce CHF<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP> becomes energetically allowed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="233"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" advantage="None">CHF<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP> has an AE<SB>298</SB> of 12.50 ± 0.04 eV, and is the predominant ion from <IT>ca.</IT> 12.8 to 16.0 eV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="234"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res32" novelty="None" advantage="None">The AE<SB>298</SB> can be converted into an upper limit of the enthalpy change for the reaction CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB>F → CHF<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP> + CH<SB>2</SB>F + e<SP>−</SP> at 298 K of 12.65 ± 0.04 eV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="235"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res32" novelty="None" advantage="None">This value is in excellent agreement with the value of Δ<SB>r</SB><IT>H</IT>°<SB>298</SB>, 12.76 eV, derived by us from G2 calculations for the enthalpy of formation of reactants and products of this reaction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="236"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res33" novelty="None" advantage="None">The other possible ionic product from cleavage of the C–C bond, CH<SB>2</SB>F<SP>+</SP>, has an AE<SB>298</SB> of 13.19 ± 0.04 eV, corresponding to Δ<SB>r</SB><IT>H</IT>°<SB>298</SB> ≤ 13.34 ± 0.04 eV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="237"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res33" novelty="None" advantage="None">This latter value is only in reasonable agreement with our G2 calculation for the enthalpy change for the reaction CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB>F → CHF<SB>2</SB> + CH<SB>2</SB>F <SP>+</SP> + e<SP>−</SP> of 13.08 eV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="238"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res34" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both CHF<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP> and CH<SB>2</SB>F<SP>+</SP> form by cleavage of the C–C bond, and are the expected products for dissociation by removing a σ electron from the HOMO of CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB>F. As with the 1,1,1 isomer, the good agreement of both energies with theory implies no exit channel barriers or kinetic shifts in either fragmentation channel.</annotationART></s> <s sid="239"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res35" novelty="None" advantage="None">Combining these experimental values of Δ<SB>r</SB><IT>H</IT>°<SB>298</SB> with literature values for the enthalpies of formation of CHF<SB>2</SB> (−237 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>), CH<SB>2</SB>F (−33 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>), CH<SB>2</SB>F<SP>+</SP> (833 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29">29</REF> and CHF<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP> (604 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>),<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF> a refined, average enthalpy of formation at 298 K for CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB>F of −671 ± 12 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> is deduced.</annotationART></s> <s sid="240"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res35" novelty="None" advantage="None">This value is in excellent agreement with our G2 calculation, −680 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>, and other literature values in the range −656 to −665 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16 cit41">16,41</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="241"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs28" novelty="None" advantage="None">At a photon energy of 14.51 ± 0.05 eV, corresponding to Δ<SB>r</SB><IT>H</IT>°<SB>298</SB> ≤ 14.65 ± 0.05 eV,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30">30</REF> the signal from an ion of mass 65 u increases rapidly.</annotationART></s> <s sid="242"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs29" novelty="None" advantage="None">This signal, corresponding to F-atom loss from the parent ion, approximately matches the drop in the ion signal of CHF<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="243"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs30" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is not possible to differentiate the two isomers CHF–CH<SB>2</SB>F<SP>+</SP> or CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP> in the TOF-MS.</annotationART></s> <s sid="244"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res36" novelty="None" advantage="None">G2 calculations predict Δ<SB>r</SB><IT>H</IT>°<SB>298</SB> to be 13.72 eV for the reaction CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB>F → CHF–CH<SB>2</SB>F<SP>+</SP> + F + e<SP>−</SP> and 12.42 eV for the reaction CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB>F → CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP> + F + e<SP>−</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="245"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res36" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both channels are therefore open at the AE<SB>298</SB> threshold of 14.51 eV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="246"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res37" novelty="None" advantage="None">Formation of the other isomer with mass 65 u, CF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP>, involves both fission of a C–F bond and H-atom migration, and seems unlikely.</annotationART></s> <s sid="247"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res38" novelty="None" advantage="None">The energy of 14.51 eV is close to the onset of the (HOMO − 3) C̃ excited state of CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB>F<SP>+</SP> centred at 15.97 eV, and the yield of this fragment ion follows closely the threshold photoelectron signal of the C̃ state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="248"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res39" novelty="None" advantage="None">Molecular orbital calculations predict that the C̃ state of CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB>F<SP>+</SP> is produced by electron removal from a F 2pπ non-bonding orbital localised predominantly on the CHF<SB>2</SB> group (Section 4.2).</annotationART></s> <s sid="249"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con18" novelty="None" advantage="None">It seems likely, therefore, at least near threshold, that CHF–CH<SB>2</SB>F<SP>+</SP> is the dominant component and arises from the dissociation CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB>F → CHF–CH<SB>2</SB>F<SP>+</SP> + F + e<SP>−</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="250"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res40" novelty="None" advantage="None">Careful analysis of the ion yield shows a two-step increase, with a second threshold at <IT>ca</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="251"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res40" novelty="None" advantage="None">15.2 eV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="252"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con19" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is possible that this second threshold is due either to rapid dissociative ionisation from a different electronic state of the parent ion or to formation of a different isomer of C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>3</SB>F<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP>; we note that ionisation from the (HOMO − 4) orbital followed by impulsive F-atom loss may lead to significant production of the isomer CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="253"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res41" novelty="None" advantage="None">From Δ<SB>r</SB><IT>H</IT>°<SB>298</SB> ≤ 14.65 ± 0.05 eV, we determine Δ<SB>f</SB><IT>H</IT>°2<SB>98</SB> (CHF–CH<SB>2</SB>F<SP>+</SP>) ≤ 663 ± 13 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="254"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res41" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, since the dissociation CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB>F<SP>+</SP> → CHF–CH<SB>2</SB>F<SP>+</SP>+F has a considerable kinetic energy release (Fig. 7 and Section 5.3), it is likely that the absolute enthalpy of formation of this ion is significantly lower than this value.</annotationART></s> <s sid="255"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res41" novelty="None" advantage="None">A G2 calculation, for example, predicts Δ<SB>f</SB><IT>H</IT>°<SB>298</SB>(CHF–CH<SB>2</SB>F<SP>+</SP>) to be 565 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>, and Lias <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29">29</REF>. quote 543 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> determined from the proton affinity of CHFCHF.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="256"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con20" novelty="None" advantage="None">As observed in the dissociative photoionisation of other fluorine-substituted ethanes,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10 cit11 cit34">10,11,34</REF> a rapid impulsive mechanism involving cleavage of the C–F bond often occurs when the molecular orbital from which the electron has been removed has mainly F 2pπ lone pair character.</annotationART></s> <s sid="257"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con20" novelty="None" advantage="None">If this mechanism is occurring, the fragment ion + F atom will have considerable translational kinetic energy, and can lead to a large difference between the observed dissociative ionisation threshold and the calculated energy of reaction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="258"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con20" novelty="None" advantage="None">From the calculated electron densities of the molecular orbitals, and the fact that a large fraction of the available energy is deposited into translation kinetic energy of fragments in the CHF–CH<SB>2</SB>F<SP>+</SP> or CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP> + F decay channel (Table 4), it seems likely that CHF–CH<SB>2</SB>F<SP>+</SP> or CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP> is produced directly and impulsively from the C̃ and/or D̃ excited electronic states of CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB>F<SP>+</SP> without prior internal conversion to the ground state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="259"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con20" novelty="None" advantage="None">These states of the parent ion are then showing the characteristics of isolated-state behaviour, a phenomenon which is expected in small cations but is unexpected in polyatomic cations with as many as eight atoms.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="260"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs31" novelty="None" advantage="None">At higher photon energies, the ion CF–CH<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP> (possibly with a very small component of ions with mass 44 and 46 u) gradually increases, and for photon energies above <IT>ca</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="261"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs31" novelty="None" advantage="None">17 eV this ion becomes dominant.</annotationART></s> <s sid="262"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs32" novelty="None" advantage="None">This ion was also the dominant, minor ion for dissociative photoionisation of CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB> with <IT>hν</IT> &gt; 18 eV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="263"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res42" novelty="None" advantage="None">The observed AE<SB>298</SB> of the ion, 16.21 ± 0.05 eV, is significantly higher than the only possible thermochemical reaction energy, 14.76 eV, for the three-body fragmentation CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB>F → CF–CH<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP> + F + HF + e<SP>−</SP>; fragmentation to CF–CH<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP> + F<SB>2</SB> + H + e<SP>−</SP> at 19.07 eV, or even to CF–CH<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP> + 2F + H + e<SP>−</SP> at 20.71 eV, are both forbidden energetically As with the 1,1,1 isomer, the increase of the CF–CH<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP> signal roughly matches the decrease of the C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>3</SB>F<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP> signal.</annotationART></s> <s sid="264"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con21" novelty="None" advantage="None">This may imply that CF–CH<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP> is formed <IT>via</IT> a two-step mechanism.</annotationART></s> <s sid="265"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con21" novelty="None" advantage="None">First, a fluorine atom is lost from the C̃ or D̃ excited states of the parent ion through an impulsive mechanism as described above to form an isomer of C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>3</SB>F<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP>, then formation of CF–CH<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP> occurs from C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>3</SB>F<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP><IT>via</IT> a tight transition state, an exit channel barrier, and HF elimination.</annotationART></s> <s sid="266"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con21" novelty="None" advantage="None">We note that the difference between the AE<SB>298</SB>(CF–CH<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP>) and the energy of the dissociation channel CF–CH<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP> + HF + F + e<SP>−</SP> is <IT>ca</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="267"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con21" novelty="None" advantage="None">1.5 eV, the same value as with HF + F elimination from the 1,1,1 isomer (Section 5.2.1).</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="5.3.">Kinetic energy releases</HEADER><P><s sid="268"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met24" novelty="Old" advantage="None">TPEPICO-TOF spectra at a resolution of 8 ns have been recorded for the major fragment ions at photon energies corresponding to the Franck–Condon maxima of the valence states of CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> and CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB>F<SP>+</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="269"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met24" novelty="Old" advantage="None">These measurements include the parent ion spectra, where the peaks are predicted to be Gaussian in shape with a full width at half maximum (fwhm) proportional to (<IT>MT</IT>)<SP>1/2</SP>/<IT>E</IT>, where <IT>M</IT> is the mass of the parent ion (84 u in this case), <IT>T</IT> is the temperature (298 K), and <IT>E</IT> is the extraction field from the interaction region (20 V cm<SP>−1</SP>).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit42 cit43">42,43</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="270"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs33" novelty="None" advantage="None">The observation of good fits to the experimental data for both CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> and CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB>F<SP>+</SP><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit33">33</REF> with the correct fwhm indicate that spatial focussing is operating correctly in the TOF mass spectrometer.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit44">44</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="271"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met24" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Fragment ions, however, often have enough translational energy for the TOF peak to be broadened from that expected for a thermal source.</annotationART></s> <s sid="272"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met24" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Analysis of the shape of such peaks allows a determination of the kinetic energy release distribution (KERD), and the total mean translational kinetic energy, 〈KE〉<SB>T</SB>, associated with a particular single-bond dissociation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="273"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs34" novelty="None" advantage="None">For example, Fig. 7 shows the TPEPICO-TOF spectrum of CHF–CH<SB>2</SB>F<SP>+</SP> from the C̃ state of the parent ion CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB>F<SP>+</SP> accessed at 16.02 eV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="274"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res43" novelty="None" advantage="None">A fit to the peak by a procedure described elsewhere<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26 cit27">26,27</REF> yields 〈KE〉<SB>T</SB> = 0.82 ± 0.04 eV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="275"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met24" novelty="Old" advantage="No">The values of 〈KE〉<SB>T</SB> are sometimes insensitive to the exact form of the KERD, and the error quoted is probably unrealistically low.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="276"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met25" novelty="Old" advantage="None">〈KE〉<SB>T</SB> can be divided by the available energy, <IT>E</IT><SB>avail</SB>, to determine the fraction of the available energy, <IT>f</IT><SB>T</SB>, being channelled into translational energy of the two fragments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="277"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met25" novelty="Old" advantage="None"><IT>E</IT><SB>avail</SB> is given by the photon energy plus the thermal energy of the parent molecule at 298 K minus the AE<SB>298</SB> of the daughter ion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="278"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met25" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Experimental values of <IT>f</IT><SB>T</SB> can be compared with those expected if the dissociation follows a pure statistical<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit45">45</REF> or a pure impulsive<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit46">46</REF> model.</annotationART></s> <s sid="279"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met25" novelty="Old" advantage="None">These two limiting models are described elsewhere.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10 cit47">10,47</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="280"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res44" novelty="None" advantage="None">(Note that if dissociation follows the modified-impulsive model,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit47 cit48">47,48</REF> values of <IT>f</IT><SB>T</SB> may be greater than those calculated for the pure-impulsive model.) Values of 〈KE〉<SB>T</SB> and <IT>f</IT><SB>T</SB> are shown in Table 4, together with calculated values of <IT>f</IT><SB>T</SB> for these two models.</annotationART></s> <s sid="281"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met26" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Since some of the vibrational wavenumbers of the fragment ions are unknown, statistical values for <IT>f</IT><SB>T</SB> were calculated according to the lower limit value of 1/(<IT>x</IT> + 1), where <IT>x</IT> is the number of vibrational degrees of freedom in the transition state of the unimolecular reaction.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit49">49</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="282"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met27" novelty="Old" advantage="None">For CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB>, spectra were measured for the dissociation reaction CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> → CF<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> + CH<SB>3</SB> at photon energies of 14.50, 14.95, 18.99 and 20.16 eV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="283"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met27" novelty="Old" advantage="None">These energies correspond to the initial formation of the X̃, Ã, D̃ and Ẽ states of the parent ion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="284"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met28" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Spectra were also measured for CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> → CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> + CF<SB>3</SB> at 16.00, 18.99 and 20.16 eV, corresponding to formation of the B̃, D̃ and Ẽ states of the parent ion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="285"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res45" novelty="None" advantage="None">The experimental and predicted data are shown in the top half of Table 4.</annotationART></s> <s sid="286"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs35" novelty="None" advantage="None">For dissociation to CF<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP>, assuming dissociation always occurs to the ground electronic state of the fragments, low values of <IT>f</IT><SB>T</SB> are observed at all energies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="287"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res46" novelty="None" advantage="None">The value of <IT>f</IT><SB>T</SB> at 14.95 eV may be anomalously high because there is a minor component of CF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> signal in the CF<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> peak.</annotationART></s> <s sid="288"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs36" novelty="None" advantage="None">For dissociation to CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP>, low values of <IT>f</IT><SB>T</SB> again are observed at all excitation energies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="289"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs37" novelty="None" advantage="None">No measurements could be made for CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> → CF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> + F at the peak of either the B̃ or C̃ states of the parent ion, because the fragment ion signal (65 u) shows weak blends from CF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP> (64 u) and CF<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> (69 u).</annotationART></s> <s sid="290"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met29" novelty="Old" advantage="None">For CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB>F, spectra were also measured for the corresponding dissociation reactions at photon energies corresponding to initial formation of the electronic states of the parent ion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="291"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs38" novelty="None" advantage="None">The same pattern for fractional translational energy release is observed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="292"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs38" novelty="None" advantage="None">That is, low values of <IT>f</IT><SB>T</SB>, always less than 0.10, are observed at all energies for dissociation to either CHF<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP> + CH<SB>2</SB>F or CH<SB>2</SB>F<SP>+</SP> + CHF<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="293"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res47" novelty="None" advantage="None">The values are close to that predicted for statistical decay.</annotationART></s> <s sid="294"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs39" novelty="None" advantage="None">The signal at mass 65 u due to F-atom loss from dissociative photoionisation of CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB>F is now unblended because CF<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> is not observed as a fragment ion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="295"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res48" novelty="None" advantage="None">The large value of 〈KE〉<SB>T</SB>, 0.82 ± 0.04 eV, when the molecule is excited into the C̃ state of the parent ion was noted in Section 5.2.2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="296"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res48" novelty="None" advantage="None">The corresponding value of <IT>f</IT><SB>T</SB>, 0.51, is almost exactly that predicted by the pure-impulsive dissociation model.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit46">46</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="297"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con22" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although this pattern of low values of <IT>f</IT><SB>T</SB> for C–C bond and high values for C–F bond cleavage has been observed before in other HFC cations,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10 cit11">10,11</REF> the absolute values of <IT>f</IT><SB>T</SB> should be treated with some caution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="298"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con22" novelty="None" advantage="None">They depend upon the values used for <IT>E</IT><SB>avail</SB>, which themselves depend on a precise determination of the AE<SB>298</SB> of the daughter ion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="299"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con22" novelty="None" advantage="None">Certainly for C–F bond fission, the AE<SB>298</SB> of the daughter ion may be much higher than the dissociation energy to fragment ion + F. Nevertheless, the high value of <IT>f</IT><SB>T</SB> for F-atom loss from CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB>F<SP>+</SP> is consistent with isolated-state behaviour for the C̃ (and possibly D̃) states of the parent ion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="300"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con22" novelty="None" advantage="None">Dissociation then proceeds along a pseudo-diatomic exit channel of the potential energy surface of the initially excited state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="301"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con22" novelty="None" advantage="None">The two atoms of the breaking C–F bond recoil with such force that a relatively large fraction of the available energy is converted into translational energy of the two fragments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="302"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con23" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although we were not able to measure <IT>f</IT><SB>T</SB>, we predict the same behaviour for the B̃ and C̃ states of CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="303"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con24" novelty="None" advantage="None">By contrast, the much lower values of <IT>f</IT><SB>T</SB> for C–C bond cleavage in both CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> and CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB>F<SP>+</SP> suggest that the initially-excited state of the parent ion decays non-radiatively by internal conversion to the bound parts of the ground state, then dissociation occurs in a statistical manner from this surface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="304"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con25" novelty="None" advantage="None">An alternative explanation is that the C–C bond <IT>does</IT> break in an impulsive manner, but the much lower values of 〈KE〉<SB>T</SB> and <IT>f</IT><SB>T</SB> than either impulsive model suggests arise because one of the bond lengths or bond angles in the fragment ion is considerably changed from its value in the parent ion.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit50">50</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="305"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con25" novelty="None" advantage="None">Such an <IT>intramolecular</IT> mechanism of fragmentation would result in the daughter ion and/or neutral partner having significant amounts of vibrational energy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="306"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con25" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since CF<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP>, CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP>, and presumably CHF<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP> and CH<SB>2</SB>F<SP>+</SP>, are planar in the isolated ion but approximately pyramidal when located in the parent ion, this model could explain the low values of <IT>f</IT><SB>T</SB> for C–C bond cleavage, with the <IT>ν</IT><SB>2</SB> umbrella bending mode of these daughter ions incorporating much of the available energy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="307"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con26" novelty="None" advantage="None">From the kinetic energy data alone, therefore, we are not able to distinguish these two mechanisms for how the central C–C bond breaks in either isomer of the trifluoroethane cation.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="6.">Conclusions</HEADER><P><s sid="308"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con27" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have recorded the threshold photoelectron and threshold photoelectron photoion coincidence spectra of the two isomers of trifluoroethane, CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB> and CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB>F, in the range 12–24 eV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="309"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res49" novelty="None" advantage="None">Ion yield curves have been determined, and the breakdown diagrams are shown elsewhere.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit33">33</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="310"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con28" novelty="None" advantage="None">The mean translational kinetic energy releases into fragment ions involving a single bond cleavage from selected valence states of CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> and CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB>F<SP>+</SP> have been measured, and compared with the predictions of statistical and pure-impulsive models.</annotationART></s> <s sid="311"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con29" novelty="None" advantage="None"><IT>Ab initio</IT> G2 calculations have determined the minimum energies of CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB> and CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB>F and their cations, with their geometries optimised at the MP2(full)/6-31G(d) level of theory.</annotationART></s> <s sid="312"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con30" novelty="None" advantage="None">The nature of the valence orbitals of both neutral molecules has also been deduced.</annotationART></s> <s sid="313"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con31" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, enthalpies of formation at 298 K of CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB>, CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB>F, and the major and minor ions observed by dissociative photoionisation have been calculated at this level of theory.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="314"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con32" novelty="None" advantage="None">Combining experimental and theoretical data, the decay mechanism of the ground and low-lying excited valence states of CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> and CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB>F<SP>+</SP> have been discussed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="315"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con32" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both molecules have ground electronic states of the parent cation which are stable only over a narrow range of energies corresponding to the lower vibrational levels.</annotationART></s> <s sid="316"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con32" novelty="None" advantage="None">As the photon energy increases, the fractional yield of the parent cation decreases from unity, and C–C bond cleavage produces CF<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> and CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> from CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB>, CHF<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP> and CH<SB>2</SB>F<SP>+</SP> from CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB>F. It is assumed that these four ions all turn on at their thermochemical threshold with no activation barrier in the exit channel.</annotationART></s> <s sid="317"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con33" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have converted these energy thresholds into upper limits for the enthalpy of the corresponding reactions at 298 K,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30">30</REF> and thus determined new values for the enthalpy of formation at this temperature of CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB> and CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB>F. Only a low fraction of the available energy, <IT>f</IT><SB>T</SB> &lt; 0.1, is channelled into translational energy of the fragment ion and polyatomic neutral.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="318"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con34" novelty="None" advantage="None">At higher energy, C–F bond cleavage is associated with electron removal from the (HOMO − 2) and (HOMO − 3) 2pπ nonbonding orbitals of CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="319"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con35" novelty="None" advantage="None">Impulsive dissociation from the B̃ and C̃ states of CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP><IT>via</IT> C–F bond cleavage then leads to production of CF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> + F. Although not measured experimentally, we infer that a much larger fraction of the available energy is now channelled into product translation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="320"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con36" novelty="None" advantage="None">Decay from the C̃ and D̃ states of CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB>F<SP>+</SP>, formed by electron removal from the F 2pπ nonbonding (HOMO − 3) and (HOMO − 4) orbitals of the neutral molecule, also leads to C–F bond cleavage, and production of either CHF–CH<SB>2</SB>F<SP>+</SP> or CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP> + F. Now a large value of <IT>f</IT><SB>T</SB> is measured experimentally, and confirms that these states display isolated-state behaviour and decay impulsively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="321"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con37" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is also likely that the geometry of the daughter ion will not differ significantly from that of the corresponding group in CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB>F<SP>+</SP>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit46 cit47">46,47</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="322"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con38" novelty="None" advantage="None">For both molecules, the AE<SB>298</SB> of the daughter ion with mass 65 u lies significantly higher in energy than the thermochemical energy of the dissociation channel, so only an upper limit for the enthalpy of formation at 298 K of CF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP> and CHF–CH<SB>2</SB>F<SP>+</SP> or CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP> is determined.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="323"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res50" novelty="None" advantage="None">Several examples of minor fragment ions caused by more complicated unimolecular reactions are observed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="324"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res51" novelty="None" advantage="None">For both isomers of trifluoroethane, CF–CH<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP> is observed, and indeed for h<IT>ν</IT> &gt;<IT>ca</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="325"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con39" novelty="None" advantage="None">18 eV this ion is the dominant fragment from dissociative photoionisation of both CF<SB>3</SB>–CH<SB>3</SB> and CHF<SB>2</SB>–CH<SB>2</SB>F. A two-step mechanism, fluorine-atom loss then HF elimination, is suggested to explain its presence.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
