<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b406051b" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Studies of unusual adsorption and diffusion behaviour of benzene in silicalite-1</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">The adsorption and diffusion properties of benzene in silicalite-1 have been investigated using gravimetric techniques, molecular simulation methods and the frequency response (FR) approach.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Two steps at loadings of <IT>ca.</IT> 4 and 6 molecules per unit cell (m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP>), respectively, and a hysteresis loop between loadings from 6 to 8 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP> can be found in the isotherms of benzene in silicalite-1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">These stepped isotherms could be classified as showing type VI isotherm behaviour but in this system the reasons behind the steps are of a new and novel nature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The anomalous adsorption behaviour has been ascribed to the subtle interplay of increased sorbate–sorbate interactions and decreases in the entropy of sorption due to the energetically heterogeneous surfaces which are present in the adsorbent.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The diffusivity of benzene in silicalite-1 also displays an unusual behaviour.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">At loadings lower than 4 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP>, only a pure, single diffusion process can be observed, while at higher loadings, two diffusion processes are found.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The former case can be ascribed to the movement of the sorbed benzene molecules mainly down the straight channel direction, whereas the latter case has been associated with diffusion processes involving (a) benzene molecules which are part of clusters and (b) molecules which are not clustered, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is an entropic driving force which causes the faster diffusivity of the clustered molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both the adsorption and diffusion properties of this system depend on the composition and structure of the silicalite-1 samples.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The adsorption and diffusion properties of aromatics in MFI zeolites have been of increasing interest over the past two decades due to the fundamental and industrial importance of these properties in catalysis and separation processes.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2 cit3 cit4 cit5 cit6 cit7 cit8 cit9 cit10 cit11 cit12 cit13 cit14 cit15 cit16 cit17 cit18 cit19 cit20">1–20</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Various techniques, including gravimetric adsorption measurements,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6 cit8 cit13 cit14 cit18 cit21 cit22 cit23 cit24">6,8,13,14,18,21–24</REF> sorption uptake rates,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit13 cit14 cit21 cit23 cit25">8,13,14,21,23,25</REF> calorimetric techniques,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10 cit26 cit27">10,26,27</REF> temperature programmable desorption (TPD)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28">28</REF> or differential thermal gravimetry (DTG),<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF> NMR,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11 cit12 cit17">11,12,17</REF> magnetic resonance imaging (MRI),<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29">29</REF> FTIR and Raman spectroscopy,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30 cit31 cit32 cit33">30–33</REF> X-ray and neutron diffraction,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit5 cit34 cit35 cit36 cit37">4,5,34–37</REF> frequency response (FR),<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16 cit17 cit18">16–18</REF> zero length column chromatography (ZLC),<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7 cit38">7,38</REF> and molecular simulations,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2 cit3 cit39 cit40 cit41 cit42 cit43">1–3,39–43</REF> have been used in these investigations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reported results are, however, not conclusive, and sometimes even contradictory, due to the complexity of the systems.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Experimental isotherms of benzene in silicalite-1 measured previously are not always consistent with one another.</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">One conclusion, however, can be drawn from the higher temperature isotherms which all show a Langmuir shape with a maximum adsorption capacity of 4 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The isotherms of Talu <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit44">44</REF>. and Tsikoyiannis and Wei<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF> at lower temperatures display a step or kink around 4 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP> and then rise to a final plateau at somewhat below eight molecules per unit cell.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Lee and Chiang<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF> reported two inflections at <IT>ca.</IT> 4 and 6 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP>, respectively, in benzene isotherms at temperatures of 283, 293 and 303 K but only one inflection at 273 K. Wu and co-workers,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF> and Shah and co-workers<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF> reported isotherms with saturation values around 8 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP> without any step.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thamm<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF> reported an isotherm with two steps at loadings of <IT>ca.</IT> 4 and 6 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP> at 303 K. In addition, a hysteresis loop was found in this isotherm between loadings of about 6 to 8 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP> Thamm<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10 cit26">10,26</REF> also found that the heat of adsorption of benzene in silicalite-1 showed a characteristic behaviour which was dependent on the temperature and the amount adsorbed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Tsikoyiannis and Wei<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF> reported a hysteresis loop, but only for samples with higher aluminium contents.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Efforts have been made to study the spatial distribution of benzene molecules within the silicalite-1 framework<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit3 cit4 cit5 cit11 cit12 cit13 cit32 cit34 cit35 cit36 cit37 cit39 cit40 cit43 cit45">1,3–5,11–13,32,34–37,39,40,43,45</REF> using different methods in order to interpret the anomalous adsorption behaviour.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">It has generally been accepted that at loadings ≤4 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP>, benzene molecules are localised in the intersections of the two channel networks of silicalite-1 although Talu has suggested that the straight channel segments are the preferential adsorption sites for benzene molecules inside the silicalite-1 lattice.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit40">40</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the packing arrangements of benzene molecules in silicalite-1 at loadings higher than 4 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP> are still in doubt.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, most of the previous studies presented only the energetically preferable adsorption sites or the probability for the sorbed benzene molecules being in certain sites rather than the detailed spatial conformation of the sorbate molecules inside the host lattice.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">As to the diffusivities of benzene in silicalite-1, most of the experimental data reported in the literature at specific temperatures are within one, or at most, two orders of magnitude.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="No">These experimental diffusivity values were mostly measured at low loadings.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="No">At high concentrations, the diffusivities are, however, much less documented due to the very strong sorbate–sorbate interactions between the sorbed benzene molecules at high loadings which make the measurements difficult and with some techniques impossible.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The FR technique used in this study is a quasi-steady state relaxation technique in which a parameter influencing the equilibrium state of the system is perturbed periodically at a particular frequency.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">An outstanding advantage of the frequency-response technique is its ability to characterise multi-kinetic processes which may be present in a FR spectrum over a broad range of time constants.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Over the past decade, the FR technique has been extensively studied both experimentally and theoretically and has proved to be a powerful method for determining intracrystalline mass transfer of molecules through zeolite crystals.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16 cit17 cit18 cit46 cit47 cit48 cit49 cit50 cit51 cit52">16–18,46–52</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The primary objective of this study is to give an insight into the fundamental adsorption and diffusion behaviour of benzene in silicalite-1 at loadings up to the saturation capacity 8 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP> using a gravimetric adsorption method, the frequency-response technique, and molecular simulation calculations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">The effect of differing chemical compositions, hydroxyl nests, <IT>etc.</IT>, of the samples on the adsorption and diffusion properties of the systems has also been investigated.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Theoretical</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="1.">Model and computational procedures</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="1.1">Solid docking</HEADER><P><s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Simulations of the configurations of benzene inside silicalite-1, using Monte Carlo (MC), energy minimization (EM) and molecular dynamics (MD) procedures, were carried out using the Solid_Docking package of the commercial InsightII software which by rapid searches is able to locate possible low-energy binding sites/packing arrangements for guest molecules within a host lattice.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The unit cell of silicalite-1 used has an orthorhombic <IT>Pnma</IT> space group with <IT>a</IT> = 20.022 Å, <IT>b</IT> = 19.899 Å, <IT>c</IT> = 13.383 Å containing 96 silicon and 192 oxygen atoms and the zeolite framework was assumed to be rigid during all runs.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The simulation box was defined as a single crystallographic unit cell to which periodic boundary conditions were applied in order to simulate the infinite zeolite structure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The cff91_czeo forcefield, belonging to the cff91 forcefield, was used to describe the interactions in both the host framework lattice and the guest sorbate molecules.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">More details for the methodology used in this study can be found in .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit53">ref. 53</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The calculations were performed on a Silicon Graphics workstation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The focus of these simulations is on structural rather than thermodynamic properties of the sorbate molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">These simulations are much less computationally demanding and more efficient for simulating configurations of the systems when large molecules and high loadings are involved in a zeolite framework.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="1.2">Adsorption simulations</HEADER><P><s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to understand the behaviour of the sorbed benzene molecules in terms of the temperature-dependence of their binding and mobility in the MFI zeolite channels, the adsorption simulations of a single benzene molecule in silicalite-1 were performed at different temperatures using the rapid Monte Carlo statistical simulation, the canonical ensemble Monte Carlo (fixed loading) simulation in which the Metropolis scheme was used.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The simulations were started by choosing the initial coordinates of the sorbate molecule in a sinusoidal channel segment, a straight channel segment and an intersection of these two channels, respectively.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Sorption module of Accelrys’ Cerius<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">2</REF> 4.2 software was used to carry out the simulations on a Silicon Graphics workstation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both the benzene molecules and the zeolite framework were treated as rigid units.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The only permitted degrees of freedom are the three translational and three rotational variables associated with the sorbate molecule.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Electrostatic interactions were not included in all of the simulations due to the very low loading and the pure silica framework involved.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The unit cell of silicalite-1 used is the same as that described in section 1.1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The simulation box was defined as two crystallographic unit cells to which periodic boundary conditions were also applied in order to simulate the infinite zeolite structure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The various Monte Carlo step sizes for the simulations were adjusted in order to obtain a 50% acceptance probability.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The interaction cutoff distance was fixed at 9.9 Å, which is slightly less than half the smallest parameter for the simulation cell, so it accounts for all of the necessary interactions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">At least 4 million simulation steps were performed and the equilibration of the system was monitored by measuring the configuration energy as a function of Monte Carlo steps.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Sorption Demontis,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit54">54</REF> Burchart-Dreiding<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit55">55</REF> and PCFF<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit56">56</REF> Force Fields were applied in the simulations, respectively.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="1.3">Dynamic simulations</HEADER><P><s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The energy minimisation and molecular dynamics methods supplied in the Cerius<SP>2</SP> 4.2 software were applied to calculate the minimum energies of benzene down the straight channels of silicalite-1 by using the Burchart-Dreiding forcefield.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The initial position of benzene molecules was in the middle of one straight channel segment.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The framework structure and the dimension of the simulation box are the same as those used in the sorption calculations described above.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">During the simulations, the framework is assumed to be rigid, whereas all the atoms of the sorbate molecules are flexible.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The sorbate molecule is forced to diffuse stepwise along the straight channel axis at steps of 0.2 Å.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">At each step, the energy minimisation was followed by a quenched molecular dynamics in which 5 short dynamic runs (0.1 ps, 300 K) were applied and the system was re-minimised after each dynamic run.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The minimum energies at each step were recorded to reflect on different orientations and internal degrees of freedom of the sorbate molecules inside the channels.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The periodic boundary conditions were also applied for these simulations.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Molecular dynamics (MD) was also used to simulate the diffusivities of benzene in silicalite-1 framework.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">This simulation was carried out by using the Materials Studio software supplied by Accelrys.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The same framework structure and simulation box as those used in the sorption calculations described above were, again, applied.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">During the simulations, however, both the framework and the sorbate molecules were allowed to vibrate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Only one benzene was loaded in the simulation box and initially located at one of the intersections between the two channels.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The PCFF Force Field was selected and both van der Waals interactions and electrostatic interactions were included in non-bond interactions with summation methods of atom-based and Ewald for these two kinds of interactions, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The interaction cutoff value was set to 12.5 Å with a spline width of 3.0 Å and a buffer width of 1.0 Å.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the coulomb term calculations, a dielectric constant of 1.0 was used.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The constant-temperature, constant-volume ensemble (NVT), <IT>i.e.</IT>, the canonical ensemble, was specified in the simulations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Again, all the simulations had the periodic boundary conditions applied.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The time step used in MD runs was 0.5 fs with total simulation time of 1.0 ns.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Prior to the MD runs, an energy minimisation and an equilibration stage with a simulation time of 10 ps were utilised.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.">The FR method</HEADER><P><s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In our frequency response method an equilibrium state is perturbed by applying a square-wave modulation to the volume of the gas phase.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The theoretical solutions of the frequency-response technique have been comprehensively developed over the past decade.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The full FR parameters (phase lag and amplitude) are experimentally derived from a Fourier transformation of the volume and pressure square-waves.</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The phase lag <IT>Φ</IT><SB><IT>Z</IT>−<IT>B</IT></SB> = <IT>Φ</IT><SB><IT>Z</IT></SB> − <IT>Φ</IT><SB><IT>B</IT></SB> is obtained, where <IT>Φ</IT><SB><IT>Z</IT></SB> and <IT>Φ</IT><SB><IT>B</IT></SB> are the phase lags determined in the presence and the absence of zeolites, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The amplitude is embodied in the ratio <IT>P</IT><SB><IT>B</IT></SB>/<IT>P</IT><SB><IT>Z</IT></SB>, where <IT>P</IT><SB><IT>B</IT></SB> and <IT>P</IT><SB><IT>Z</IT></SB> are the pressures response to the ±1% volume perturbations in the absence and presence of sorbents, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">From the solution of Fick's second law for the diffusion of a single diffusant in a solid subjected to a periodic, sinusoidal surface concentration modulation, the following equations can be obtained<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit47">47</REF>in-phase: (<IT>P</IT><SB><IT>B</IT></SB>/<IT>P</IT><SB><IT>Z</IT></SB>) cos <IT>Φ</IT><SB><IT>Z</IT>−<IT>B</IT></SB> − 1 = <IT>Kδ</IT><SB>in</SB> + <IT>S</IT>out-of-phase: (<IT>P</IT><SB><IT>B</IT></SB>/<IT>P</IT><SB><IT>Z</IT></SB>) sin <IT>Φ</IT><SB><IT>Z</IT>−<IT>B</IT></SB> = <IT>Kδ</IT><SB>out</SB>where <IT>K</IT> is a constant related to the gradient of the adsorption isotherm, <IT>S</IT> is a constant that represents a very rapid adsorption/desorption process, which may co-exist with the diffusion process being measured, <IT>δ</IT><SB>in</SB> and <IT>δ</IT><SB>out</SB> are the overall in-phase and out-of-phase characteristic functions, respectively, which depend on the theoretical models describing the overall kinetic processes of a system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">These theoretical models have been comprehensively developed over the past decade<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit46 cit47 cit49 cit50 cit57">46,47,49,50,57</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Experimental</HEADER><P><s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">A gravimetric balance (Sartorius) was used to measure the isotherms of benzene in <IT>ca.</IT> 200 mg of the silicalite-1, which had been outgassed under a vacuum of &lt;10<SP>−3</SP> Pa at 673 K for more than 20 h prior to the sorption measurements.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The isotherm temperature was controlled by a Eurotherm temperature controller.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The pressures were determined using two high-accuracy Baratron pressure transducers of type MKS 626 (0–10 Torr) and type MKS 220CA (0–1000 Torr), respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The zero drift of the apparatus was always found to be negligible.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Buoyancy corrections were found to be insignificant in this balance at the equilibrium pressures involved in the measurements.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">A more accurate, fully automated and computer controlled gravimetric system [IGA (Intelligent Gravimetric Analyzer), Hiden Analytical Ltd., Warrington, UK] was also employed in this study.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">A sensitive microbalance (resolution of 0.1 μg) is mounted in a thermostated enclosure and thus provides higher accuracies and stabilities.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The sample temperature was regulated to ±0.1 °C by either a water bath or a furnace.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The IGA system has been used to carry out temperature programmable desorption (TPD) measurements for benzene sorbed in silicalite-1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this method a sorbate gas is brought into adsorption equilibrium with the sorbent at room temperature at a specified pressure which was chosen from the isotherm to give the required loading.</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The system was then heated at rates of 5 to 20 K min<SP>−1</SP> from room temperature to <IT>ca.</IT> 653 K. The above equilibrium pressure was maintained during the heating.</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The weight of the sorbent was recorded as a function of temperature from which TG (Thermal Gravimetry) and DTG data could be derived.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The principal features of the FR apparatus developed in our group have been previously described.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit51">51</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">An accurately known amount of zeolite sample is scattered in a plug of glass wool and outgassed at a pressure of &lt;10<SP>−3</SP> Pa and 623 K overnight.</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">A dose of purified benzene is brought into sorption equilibrium with the zeolite in the sorption chamber at a chosen pressure and temperature.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">A square-wave modulation of ±1% was then applied to the gas phase equilibrium volume, <IT>V</IT><SB>e</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The pressure response to the volume perturbation was recorded with a high-accuracy differential Baratron pressure transducer (MKS 698A11TRC) at each frequency over three to five square-wave cycles (256 readings per cycle) after the periodic steady-state had been established.</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The volume, <IT>V</IT><SB>e</SB>, is 80 cm<SP>3</SP> in the FR system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">A frequency range of 0.001 to 10 Hz was scanned over some 30 increments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The conversion rate of the analogue-to-digital converter in the interface unit must be fast enough to cope with the 1 to 4 ms response time of the pressure transducer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The pressure response to the volume change over the whole frequency range was measured in the absence (blank experiment) and presence of sorbent samples to eliminate time constants associated with the apparatus.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The FR spectra were derived from the equivalent fundamental sine-wave perturbation by a Fourier transformation of the volume and pressure square-wave forms.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The silicalite-1 zeolite samples used in this study are summarised in Table 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Silicalite-1 (A) was synthesised by Van-Den-Begin <IT>et al.</IT> from a gel containing a TPA-water solution (20 wt.% TPAOH) and a Ludox solution (40 wt.% colloidal SiO<SB>2</SB>).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit52">52</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Silicalite-1 (B) is a commercial zeolite, RD 1051/87, produced by LAPORTE Inorganic.</annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The sample was separated by sedimentation in a column of water to produce a narrow distribution of particle size prior to the diffusion measurements.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">All of the samples were used for the adsorption and the FR studies after calcination at 823 K for 10 h in an oven.</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The crystals were heated in air from room temperature to 823 K at 2 K min<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">X-ray diffraction patterns and SEM micrographs showed that these zeolite samples were highly crystalline and contained crystals of nearly uniform size.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Benzene was supplied by the National Physical Laboratory, UK, with a purity of 99+%.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Results and discussion</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="1.">Adsorption</HEADER><P><s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The isotherms of benzene in silicalite-1 (A) and silicalite-1 (B) at higher temperatures are shown in Fig. 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">A marked inflection can be seen in the isotherm in silicalite-1 (B) at 323 K at loadings above 4 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP>, while no step is found in the isotherms of silicalite-1 (A), suggesting that the conflicting isotherms reported in the literature, as mentioned above, may result from differences in the samples used.</annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The synthesis gel composition for silicalite-1 (A) sample had no aluminium present and, thus, the Si/Al ratio of the product should be almost infinite.</annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The large number of internal silanol groups (<IT>cf.</IT> Table 1), measured by <SP>1</SP>H-MAS NMR,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit52">52</REF> existing in the bulk phase of the silicalite-1 (A) crystals induced by the presence of TPA ions during the pentasil-type synthesis is, therefore, the most probable factor influencing the adsorptive properties.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit58">58</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The adsorption behaviour of the system is also influenced by the Si/Al ratios of the samples.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10 cit18 cit27">10,18,27</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is worth noting that the defect effect is more pronounced, for the case of aromatics/MFI systems, than that for <IT>n</IT>-alkanes/MFI systems due to the fact that an additional interaction between sorbate molecules and the sorbent framework will be involved in the aromatics/MFI systems compared with the simple dispersion/repulsion forces which are involved with the alkanes.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 2 presents the isotherms of benzene in both silicalite-1 samples at lower temperatures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results reported by Lee and Chiang<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF> that two steps at <IT>ca.</IT> 4 and 6 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP>, respectively, in each benzene isotherm at temperatures of 283, 293 and 303 K and only one step at 273 K were confirmed in this study using the silicalite-1 (B) sample.</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">A hysteresis loop which appeared in the isotherm of Thamm<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF> can also be observed in the isotherm at 303 K. However, the isotherm in silicalite-1 (A) at 273 K levels off at about 9 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP> without any inflection.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Step-like isotherms have been attributes to phase transitions occurring in the sorbent induced by sorption of the sorbate molecules.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit6 cit31 cit59 cit60">1,6,31,59,60</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">This suggestion was discarded in our previous study<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF> as (i) the phase transitions can occur at loadings in the range <IT>ca.</IT> 0–2 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6 cit45 cit59 cit61 cit62">6,45,59,61,62</REF> where no steps are found; and (ii) the symmetry changes also occur on change of temperature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The higher the temperature, the lower the loading at which the phase transition takes place.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit59 cit63">59,63</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the loadings at which the steps are found are independent of temperature in most cases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thirdly, a phase transition of silicalite-1 from monoclinic to orthorhombic was observed when trichloroethene was sorbed in silicalite-1 at a loading of <IT>ca.</IT> 7 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP> using an <IT>in situ</IT> neutron diffraction technique,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit35">35</REF> but no inflection in the isotherm was found.</annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Finally, the transformation of silicalite-1 from monoclinic to orthorhombic symmetry involves only minor displacements of the atomic positions within the framework structure which, under appropriate conditions, are highly reversible and cause only very small changes in size and shape of the channel system.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit36 cit64">36,64</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fact that the structural differences between the topologically equivalent orthorhombic and monoclinic forms of MFI framework are very small is generally overlooked by many workers who ascribed the changes in the adsorptive properties simply to these phase transitions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Neutron diffraction investigations give further support to this argument.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit35 cit36">35,36</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">As mentioned in the Introduction section, the intersections of the two channel systems of silicalite-1, of which there are four per unit cell, are the most preferred sorption sites for benzene, which is consistent with the fact that a step occurs in the isotherm when the loading increases above 4 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thamm<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF> has ascribed the inflections of the benzene isotherms in silicalite-1 to the redistribution and/or reorientation of benzene molecules occurring in the system at the loadings where the steps occur.</annotationART></s> <s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">These redistribution and/or reorientation processes will result in a large entropy loss in the adsorbed phase, as shown in Fig. 3b, but this entropy decrease is balanced by the large increases in the corresponding heats of adsorption, as shown in Fig. 3a.</annotationART></s> <s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results displayed in Fig. 3 are in good agreement with Thamm’s calorimetric data.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10 cit26">10,26</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The simulation results presented in the following section justify these arguments and elucidate explicitly at molecular levels the factors which cause the anomalous steps and the hysteresis loop in the isotherms of this system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Neutron diffraction studies<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit35">35</REF> also suggested that the steps observed in the isotherms of benzene in silicalite-1 are not signatures of phase transitions of the sorbent structure but are related to three stages in the filling process induced by the three kinds of sites present in silicalite-1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">One can, therefore, conclude that the unusual isotherms of benzene in silicalite-1 can be attributed to energetically heterogeneous surfaces which are present in the adsorbent.</annotationART></s> <s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">These heterogeneities, arising from sorbate–sorbent and sorbate–sorbate interactions, cause spatial configuration changes as the loading increases.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is interesting to point out that the isotherms in Figs. 1 and 2 which show one or more steps are examples of Type VI isotherms.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit65">65</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, these inflections are not due to the accepted mechanism for such steps, <IT>i.e.</IT> second and third layer adsorption on very homogeneous surfaces but are due to adsorption on different sets of sites where heat/entropic factors introduce distinct differences to the sorption process at well-defined adsorbate concentrations.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.">Simulation calculations</HEADER><P><s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The configurations of benzene within silicalite-1 with the lowest potential energies at loadings from 4 to 8 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP>, derived from the solid docking simulations, are presented in Figs. 4 and 5.</annotationART></s> <s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The structures displayed here can explain explicitly the unusual adsorption isotherms of the system and the diffusivity discussed in the subsequent section even though these simulations determine the arrangements for a temperature of 0 K.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">At loadings up to 4 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP>, the molecules are located in the intersections with the aromatic-ring plane normal to the <IT>x</IT>–<IT>z</IT> plane (<IT>cf</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 4(a,4) and 4(b,4)).</annotationART></s> <s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The sorbate–sorbate interactions will be negligible at these loadings.</annotationART></s> <s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 6 displays the mass distributions of benzene adsorbed initially in a sinusoidal channel segment and a straight channel segment of silicalite-1 at 673 K calculated using the adsorption simulation technique.</annotationART></s> <s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Dots indicate the centre of mass of the benzene molecules sorbed during the simulation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="143"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is clearly shown that the intersections are still preferred positions for the sorbed benzene molecules at high temperature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="144"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Similar simulation configurations were obtained using the different forcefields listed in section 1.2 but the heat of adsorption calculated on applying the Burchart-Dreiding forcefield is more consistent with the experimental results<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26">26</REF> than the other two forcefields.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit66">66</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="145"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">At a loading of 5 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP>, however, a dramatic change occurs in the structure of the system as shown in Fig. 4(a,5) and (b,5).</annotationART></s> <s sid="146"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Four molecules are distributed in the intersection and the straight channel segments forming a cluster along the straight channel direction with those molecules in the intersections now parallel to the <IT>x</IT>–<IT>z</IT> plane.</annotationART></s> <s sid="147"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fifth molecule which does not join the chain remains in an intersection site of an adjacent straight channel and retains the same orientation as observed at the loadings ≤4 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="148"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">At a loading of 6 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP>, the chain remains unchanged but now there are two molecules located in the intersection sites of the adjacent straight channels as shown in Fig. 4(a,6) and (b,6).</annotationART></s> <s sid="149"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The formation of such strong sorbate–sorbate chains of molecules has been proposed by Sacerdote and Mentzen <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF>. by comparing X-ray powder diffraction data and calorimetrically determined differential adsorption heats, with computer simulated atom–atom interactions for this system at a loading of 8 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="150"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">As the loading increases to 7 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP>, the chain still exists but now the seventh molecule does not go into the remaining straight channel site to form another chain down the straight channel adjacent to the one with the existing chain, as suggested by the X-ray researchers,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF> but resides in one of the sinusoidal channel segments to form a side-chain along the sinusoidal channel direction (<IT>cf</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="151"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 5(a,7) and 5(b,7)).</annotationART></s> <s sid="152"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">At a loading of 8 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP>, a similar configuration can be seen with the eighth molecule located in another sinusoidal channel segment at a site opposite to that of the seventh molecule as can be seen in Fig. 5(a,8) and 5(b,8).</annotationART></s> <s sid="153"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, one can conclude that the configuration of benzene in silicalite-1 at a loading of 8 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP> consists of clusters down the straight channels with side chains along the sinusoidal channel direction.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="154"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">These findings confirm, again, the statements made by Thamm<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF> from his calorimetric data that redistribution and/or reorientation occurs twice in the system at loadings of <IT>ca.</IT> 4 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP> and 6 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP>, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="155"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">As mentioned above, for lower loadings (up to 4 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP>), the configuration of the sorbed benzene molecules in silicalite-1 resulted from this study is in fair agreement with those reported in the literature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="156"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">For loadings higher than 4 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP>, the locations of the molecules derived from different studies are inconsistent.</annotationART></s> <s sid="157"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">X-ray and FT-Raman investigations<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit5 cit32">4,5,32</REF> presented a conformation of benzene molecules sorbed in silicalite-1 at loadings between 4 and 6 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP> with four molecules located at the intersections and the other added molecules occupying the sinusoidal channel segments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="158"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">For loadings higher than 6 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP>, four molecules remain in the intersections and the rest of the benzene molecules move to the straight channel segments forming infinite chains in the straight channels.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="159"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Neutron diffraction studies<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit35">35</REF> showed that up to a loading of 4 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP>, the sorbed benzene molecules fill the intersections.</annotationART></s> <s sid="160"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="Old" advantage="None">At a loading of 6 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP>, the two additional molecules are located in the straight and sinusoidal channel segments, respectively, to form dimers with the molecules already in the intersections.</annotationART></s> <s sid="161"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The sorbed benzene molecules at the higher loading of 8 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP> occupy the three types of sites in a new arrangement of interconnected chains.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="162"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Obviously, the configurations obtained from this study are different from those mentioned above.</annotationART></s> <s sid="163"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, all display a three-stage process of porosity filling, suggesting that the three types of adsorption sites are energetically heterogeneous.</annotationART></s> <s sid="164"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The two steps observed in the above sorption isotherms can then be ascribed to the dramatic change of the spatial configurations of the system at loadings of around 4 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP> and 6 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP>, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="165"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The discrepancies might be ascribed to the difference in temperature for different studies or/and to the different silicalite-1 samples used in the experiments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="166"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">As far as the hysteresis loop is concerned, however, the conformation of benzene molecules presented in Figs. 4 and 5 are the most plausible, as discussed below.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="167"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">The saturation adsorption capacity for benzene in silicalite-1 determined experimentally (<IT>cf</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="168"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 2) is <IT>ca.</IT> 8 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP>, which is consistent with previously reported data.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit10 cit67 cit68">8,10,67,68</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="169"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">This value is much smaller than the theoretical value of 12 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP> based on the crystallographic data for silicalite-1 and the liquid density of benzene.</annotationART></s> <s sid="170"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">The spatial configuration of the sorbed benzene at a loading of 8 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP> (<IT>cf</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="171"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 5(a,8) and (b,8)) shows that there are still two straight channel segments and two sinusoidal channel segments per unit cell left available, implying that the adsorption occurs on energetically preferred centers rather than a process of volume filling within the microporous network.</annotationART></s> <s sid="172"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">As mentioned above, a large entropy loss is involved at high loadings.</annotationART></s> <s sid="173"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">This entropy decrease can, however, be balanced by the large increase in the corresponding heats of adsorption (<IT>cf.</IT> Fig. 3).</annotationART></s> <s sid="174"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" advantage="None">For loadings in excess of 8 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP>, a further entropy loss would occur due to the very tight packing of the sorbed benzene molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="175"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None">The corresponding heats of adsorption will, nevertheless, decrease at very high loadings and are not able to balance the entropy decrease.</annotationART></s> <s sid="176"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The saturated adsorption capacity of <IT>ca.</IT> 8 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP> is, therefore, controlled by both the entropy and enthalpy effects of the sorbed benzene molecules.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="177"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the light of the solid docking simulation results, a possible interpretation of the hysteresis loop found in the isotherm of benzene in silicalite-1 (B) at 303 K is proposed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="178"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">At loadings lower than 6 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP>, the sorbed molecules are associated with one another only <IT>via</IT> the straight channel direction as shown in Figs. 4 and 5.</annotationART></s> <s sid="179"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the hysteresis loop region, the sorbed benzene molecules form a large sorbate–sorbate cluster throughout the framework channels, leading to strong sorbate–sorbate interactions which can be seen from the heat of adsorption of this system, as shown in Fig. 3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="180"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">On increasing the loading some reorientation and relocation of the molecules already sorbed may occur to give clusters with maximum sorbate–sorbate interaction energy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="181"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">At maximum loading the final sorbed benzene molecule is sorbed on the least preferred sites, <IT>i.e.</IT> a sinusoidal segment site.</annotationART></s> <s sid="182"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">On desorbing from this maximum loaded state, molecules have to be removed from these strongly bound clusters, <IT>i.e.</IT>, the first molecule will be removed along the straight channel which offers the minimum diffusional resistance, thus, adsorption and desorption involves different processes and paths, resulting in two different configurations with essentially identical free energies at the same partial pressure and hysteresis occurs.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Diffusion</HEADER><P><s sid="183"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Some FR spectra of benzene in the silicalite-1 (A) and silicalite-1 (B) at lower loadings (&lt;4 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP>) are shown in Fig. 7.</annotationART></s> <s sid="184"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None">An excellent agreement between the theoretical model for a single diffusion constant and the experimental data for the two silicalite samples indicates that the mass transfer of benzene in the MFI zeolite network is dominated by a pure, single diffusion process at lower loadings.</annotationART></s> <s sid="185"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None">This pure, single diffusion process could arise either from the movement of the sorbed benzene molecules along only one channel direction, most probably down the straight channel direction, or from an average single diffusion process along the two channel systems.</annotationART></s> <s sid="186"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">XRD and NMR studies show that benzene is an almost perfect spherical rotator at the intersections of the two channels in the MFI structure,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11 cit12 cit45 cit52">11,12,45,52</REF> indicating that the sorbed benzene molecules could diffuse readily along either of the two channel networks resulting in an average single diffusion coefficient at lower loadings.</annotationART></s> <s sid="187"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res29" novelty="None" advantage="None">The energy minimization simulations of the sorbed benzene molecule in silicalite-1 show, however, that the energy barrier for the benzene molecule diffusing down the straight channel direction (29.6 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>) is in good agreement with the experimental activation energy (28.8 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>),<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18 cit66">18,66</REF> implying that the single diffusion process measured, at high temperatures or lower loadings, by the FR method may result from the sorbed benzene molecules moving mainly along the straight channel direction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="188"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res30" novelty="None" advantage="None">Results obtained from an MD simulation run, shown in Fig. 8, support this assumption since the mass transport down the straight channel direction greatly overweighs the transport processes along the other two directions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="189"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None">One can conclude, then, that the single peak in the FR signal at low loadings results from the sorbed benzene molecules being transported along the straight channels rather than an average single diffusion process along both channel systems.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="190"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">At low temperatures and loadings &gt;4 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP>, pronounced and, very much unexpected, bimodal FR spectra were observed for benzene diffusing in silicalite-1 with a new peak appearing at a frequency much higher than that observed at low loadings, as shown in Fig. 9.</annotationART></s> <s sid="191"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" advantage="None">It does not seem rational to assign the new peak to either the effect of the dissipation of the adsorption heat or to a finite-rate mass exchange between transport channels and stationary storage channels because, in both cases, no bimodal behaviour would be observed in the FR spectra when the rate of the diffusion is slower than the rates of these two processes.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit49 cit50">49,50</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="192"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res32" novelty="None" advantage="None">Two thermodesorption processes were observed at high loadings in DSC (differential scanning calorimetry) and DTG<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF> studies, implying that more than one mass transfer process take place in the system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="193"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">NMR measurements<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11 cit12 cit69">11,12,69</REF> also detected two types of motion of the sorbed benzene molecules at higher loadings and no evidence from the line shapes of exchange between these two types could be observed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="194"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is, therefore, reasonable to propose that the bimodal FR spectra can be ascribed to two independent diffusion processes taking place in the system.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit47 cit48">47,48</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="195"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None">As discussed above, sorbed benzene molecules diffuse down the straight channels at lower loadings.</annotationART></s> <s sid="196"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None">At high loadings, it is unreasonable to assign the new high frequency peak of the FR spectra to the transport of the sorbed molecules along the sinusoidal channel direction as (i) there are no molecules sorbed in the sinusoidal channel segments at loadings of 5 and 6 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP> according to the solid docking results shown in Fig. 4 and (ii) diffusion down the sinusoidal channel direction should be energetically more difficult than that along the straight channel direction as the benzene molecules suffer a large repulsive interaction when located in the sinusoidal channel segments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="197"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The two observed diffusion processes must, therefore, be associated with two different states of the sorbed benzene molecules in silicalite-1 channels at high loadings.</annotationART></s> <s sid="198"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res33" novelty="None" advantage="None">The solid docking simulation results, as presented in Figs. 4 and 5, show that some of the sorbed molecules are clustered at high loadings, leading to two different states of the sorbed benzene molecules existing in the framework, <IT>i.e.</IT> a clustered state and an unclustered state, respectively.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="199"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 10 displays the DTG profiles of benzene molecules sorbed in silicalite-1 derived from the temperature programmed desorption results at various adsorption loadings measured using the IGA apparatus.</annotationART></s> <s sid="200"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Only a single high temperature peak was observed in these DTG profiles when the initial adsorption loadings were lower than 4 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP>, whereas at higher loadings two peaks were found.</annotationART></s> <s sid="201"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res34" novelty="None" advantage="None">The new lower temperature peak can, therefore, be associated with the desorption of molecules sorbed above a loading of 4 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP> The results clearly demonstrate that the initial 4 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP> sorbed in the preferred channel intersection sites require higher temperatures before desorption occurs compared to molecules sorbed in the other sites at loadings in excess of 4 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP> As these latter molecules are sorbed with higher heats of adsorption (<IT>cf.</IT> Fig. 3), mainly from increased sorbate–sorbate interactions, the ease with which they are desorbed must be due to gains in entropy on desorption as the main driving force.</annotationART></s> <s sid="202"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In Fig. 10 the higher temperature peak in the DTG curves for molecules sorbed in the channel intersection sites increase in temperature from <IT>ca</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="203"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">343 K for a loading of 1.5 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP> to <IT>ca</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="204"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">403 K for a loading of 8 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP> This increase arises from the increase in equilibrium pressure that is maintained in these DTG measurements as the loading increases (see Experimental section for the conditions used in the IGA apparatus).</annotationART></s> <s sid="205"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The experimental results also showed that changing the heating rate had little or no effect on the TG and DTG profiles.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="206"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The TG and DTG profiles of the benzene molecules sorbed in silicalite-1 (B) with a initial loadings of 6 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP> are shown in Fig. 11a.</annotationART></s> <s sid="207"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The complete desorption of the two molecules in excess of 4 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP> occurs over the temperature range of 298–323 K. If the initial equilibrium system is heated to 323 K the molecules in excess of 4 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP> will, thus, be removed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="208"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res35" novelty="None" advantage="None">Following this low temperature heating if the system is cooled to room temperature and then a second temperature programmed desorption is initiated but now using the reduced equilibrium pressure over the sorbent appropriate for a loading of 4 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP> The resulting TG and DTG profiles, presented in Fig. 11b, match exactly the profiles generated previously starting with the sorbent loaded only with 4 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP> This perfect match indicates that when the benzene molecules sorbed in excess of 4 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP> are removed, the remaining 4 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP> will be redistributed back to their preferred intersection sorption sites.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="209"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None">These thermogravimetric findings support the concept that the bimodal FR spectra at high loadings should be ascribed to two diffusion processes arising from the two states of the sorbed benzene molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="210"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The additional high frequency peak at low temperatures and high loadings should be related to the diffusion process of the sorbed benzene molecules associated with the cluster state and the low frequency peak, which has a similar time constant to that for the single frequency peak at high temperatures and low loadings, should be associated with the diffusion of the sorbed molecules located in the intersection sites and not part of the clusters.</annotationART></s> <s sid="211"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None">With increasing the loading, more molecules will be in the clustered state and fewer molecules will remain in the unclustered state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="212"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res36" novelty="None" advantage="None">This conclusion is supported by the FR spectra displayed in Fig. 9 where the intensity of the lower frequency peak decreases as loading increases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="213"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">It can also be seen from Fig. 9 that the formation of the clusters of the sorbed benzene molecules in silicalite-1 depends on temperature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="214"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res37" novelty="None" advantage="None">At the same loading, more molecules will be in the clustered state at lower temperature than those at higher temperature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="215"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is worth noting that the Darken equation may be invalid at such high loadings because of the complex nature of the adsorption isotherm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="216"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res38" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus only transport diffusivities are presented in Table 2 instead of self-diffusivities at these loadings.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="217"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res39" novelty="None" advantage="None">The diffusivities of benzene in silicalite-1 (A) and silicalite-1 (B) zeolite samples obtained from the FR measurements in this study are summarized in Table 2 and Figs. 7, 9, 12 and 13.</annotationART></s> <s sid="218"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">At low loadings or high temperatures, the diffusivities of benzene in both samples are similar with a single diffusion process being observed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="219"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">As is commonly observed in zeolite systems,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit70">70</REF> the intracrystalline self-diffusion coefficients of benzene in silicalite-1, obtained by the use of Darken equation, decreases with increasing loading, while the transport diffusivities increase slightly as the loading increases for both samples.</annotationART></s> <s sid="220"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">At high loadings or low temperatures remarkable discrepancies in the diffusivities between these two samples can be observed, as shown in Figs. 9 and 13.</annotationART></s> <s sid="221"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The FR bimodal behaviour can be obtained at loadings of just above 4 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP> for silicalite-1 (B) sample (<IT>cf.</IT> Fig. 9) while for silicalite-1 (A) sample, this bimodal phenomenon cannot be observed until loading higher than 8 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP> (<IT>cf.</IT> Fig. 13).</annotationART></s> <s sid="222"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">This FR bimodal behaviour for silicalite-1 (A) is not as distinct as that for silicalite-1 (B).</annotationART></s> <s sid="223"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res40" novelty="None" advantage="None">All these findings indicate that the heterogeneity of the channel networks and the formation of clusters of benzene sorbed in silicalite-1 (A) are decreased.</annotationART></s> <s sid="224"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, the diffusivities of benzene in the silicalite-1 (A) sample are higher than those in the silicalite(B) sample.</annotationART></s> <s sid="225"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res41" novelty="None" advantage="None">Apart from differences in morphology, the major difference between these two samples is the chemical or structural differences of the framework, as mentioned above.</annotationART></s> <s sid="226"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The results deduced by <SP>13</SP>C CP NMR spectra clearly showed an increase in the molecular mobility of the sorbed benzene in MFI zeolites with a high concentration of structural defects.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit71">71</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="227"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Obviously, structural defects handicap the formation of clusters.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="228"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The increase in diffusivity of benzene in silicalite-1 with increase in loading was detected by Shah <IT>et al.</IT> using a gravimetric technique and large crystals.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="229"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="Old" advantage="No">This technique is, however, not able to distinguish different kinetic processes occurring in the system and the explanation for this phenomenon offered by Shah <IT>et al.</IT> is not satisfying.</annotationART></s> <s sid="230"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The present study demonstrates once again that the FR technique is a very powerful, more useful one for measuring the complicated processes occurring in some sorbate/sorbent systems.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Conclusions</HEADER><P><s sid="231"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res42" novelty="None" advantage="None">Molecular simulations show that the intersections of the two channel networks of silicalite-1 are the energetically preferred adsorption sites for the sorbed benzene molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="232"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res42" novelty="None" advantage="None">After all, the intersections are fully occupied by benzene molecules, <IT>i.e.</IT> loading approaches 4 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP>, further adsorption will cause a redistribution or rearrangement of the sorbed molecules with some molecules forming strongly sorbate–sorbate bonded chains.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="233"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Sorption isotherms of benzene in silicalite-1 show two interesting steps which occur at loadings of <IT>ca.</IT> 4 and 6 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP>, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="234"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res43" novelty="None" advantage="None">Such steps have been shown to occur after the first 4 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP> to be sorbed have filled the four, energetically preferred, channel intersection sites.</annotationART></s> <s sid="235"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The steps are due to the subtle interplay of increased sorbate–sorbate interactions and decreases in the entropy of sorption when molecules, at loadings in excess of 4 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP>, have to occupy sinusoidal and straight channel segment sites.</annotationART></s> <s sid="236"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Such stepped isotherms could be classified as showing type VI isotherm behaviour.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="237"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The hysteresis loop found in the isotherm of this system results from the strong sorbate–sorbate interactions, the energetically heterogeneous surfaces of the sorbent framework and the close packing of the sorbed benzene molecules, which lead to packing differences of the sorbed molecules on adsorption and desorption branches of the isotherm.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="238"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res44" novelty="None" advantage="None">The adsorption behaviour of this system is affected by the chemical nature of the silicalite-1 samples.</annotationART></s> <s sid="239"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res45" novelty="None" advantage="None">Structural defects can result in the disappearance of the steps in the isotherms.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="240"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con17" novelty="None" advantage="None">One of the important features of the FR method is its ability to distinguish processes with different time constants which are simultaneously operating in the system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="241"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con17" novelty="None" advantage="None">This method is capable, therefore, of detecting the different diffusivities of different states of sorbed benzene molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="242"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con17" novelty="None" advantage="None">At loadings lower than 4 m. u.c.<SP>−1</SP>, the sorbed benzene molecules diffuse mainly down the straight channels, while at higher loadings, the sorbed benzene molecules which belong to a cluster diffuse faster than the unclustered sorbed molecules because of an entropic driving force for the molecules sorbed in clusters.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="243"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Temperature programme desorption studies and simulation calculations, using Accelrys software, have helped greatly to elucidate the underlying features controlling the diffusion of benzene molecules sorbed in the two types of channel networks present in silicalite-1.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
