<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b407512a" hasDoc="yes" version="1184" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Theoretical analysis of the [Mn<SB>2</SB>(μ-oxo)<SB>2</SB>(μ-carboxylato)<SB>2</SB>]<SP>+</SP> core</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The first example of a dinuclear manganese complex containing two oxo and two carboxylate bridges, [Mn<SB>2</SB>(μ-O)<SB>2</SB>(μ-O<SB>2</SB>CAr<SP>Tol</SP>)<SB>2</SB>(bpy)<SB>2</SB>]<SP>+</SP> (where bpy = 2,2′-bipyridine, and Ar<SP>Tol</SP>CO<SB>2</SB><SP>−</SP> = 2,6-di(<IT>p–</IT>tolyl)benzoate), was reported recently (<IT>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</IT> 2003, <B>125</B>, 13010).</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">X-ray crystallographic analysis performed on this complex reveals a trapped mix-valence species as evidenced, for example, by very different metal–ligand bond distances at the Mn<SP>III</SP> and Mn<SP>IV</SP> centers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The fact that there are rather bulky bridging carboxylate ligands present in this recently reported dinuclear species raises the question as to whether they affect the extent of valence trapping and the metrical parameters in general.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Specifically, it was thought that intramolecular nonbonded contacts could play an important role.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In the work reported here, density functional theory calculations were used to address this issue.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Structural parameters obtained from calculations on a model compound bearing sterically small bridging carboxylates, [Mn<SB>2</SB>(μ-O)<SB>2</SB>(μ-O<SB>2</SB>CH)<SB>2</SB>(bpy)<SB>2</SB>]<SP>+</SP>, are in good agreement with the experimentally determined single crystal X-ray structure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, the sterically large carboxylate bridges in [Mn<SB>2</SB>(μ-O)<SB>2</SB>(μ-O<SB>2</SB>CAr<SP>Tol</SP>)<SB>2</SB>(bpy)<SB>2</SB>]<SP>+</SP> appear not to have a significant effect on the metal–ligand bond distances and angles.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">There is calculated to be minimal Mn⋯Mn bonding despite contraction of the Mn⋯Mn distance relative to related complexes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">In addition to calculations on the mixed-valence Mn<SP>III</SP>Mn<SP>IV</SP> complex, various electronic configurations of the corresponding Mn<SP>III</SP>Mn<SP>III</SP> and Mn<SP>IV</SP>Mn<SP>IV</SP> complexes are explored.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although our calculations support assignment of [Mn<SB>2</SB>(μ-O)<SB>2</SB>(μ-O<SB>2</SB>CH)<SB>2</SB>(bpy)<SB>2</SB>]<SP>+</SP> as a valence-trapped Mn<SP>III</SP>Mn<SP>IV</SP> configuration involving high-spin Mn<SP>III</SP>, a delocalized configuration arising from low-spin Mn<SP>III</SP> is calculated to lie very close in energy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The energetic proximity of the delocalized configuration is attributed to an effective crossed-exchange mechanism, which permits mixing of an e<SB>g</SB>-based orbital (nominally on high-spin Mn<SP>III</SP>) with a vacant t<SB>2g</SB>-based orbital (nominally on Mn<SP>IV</SP>).</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Metalloenzymes containing manganese at their active sites are plentiful.</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Manganese-dependent ribonucleotide reductase, C. <IT>ammoniagenes</IT> RRase<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2">1,2</REF> and superoxide dismutase<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF> were shown to contain a single Mn ion at the reaction center, whereas dimanganese active sites are found in bacterial catalase,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit5">4,5</REF> rat liver arginase, aminopeptidase P and in dinitrogen reductase-activating glycohydrolase.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">An oxo-bridged tetramanganese cluster (Mn<SB>4</SB>), present at the active site of Photosystem II (PSII) Water Oxidase (WO), catalyzes the light induced water-to-oxygen conversion, the process that is responsible for existence of aerobic life on the earth.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7 cit8 cit9 cit10 cit11 cit12 cit13">7–13</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the catalytic process the Mn<SB>4</SB> cluster cycles through five intermediate states, known as S<SB><IT>i</IT></SB> (<IT>i</IT> = 0–4) states, oxygen being evolved during the S<SB>3</SB> to S<SB>0</SB> state conversion <IT>via</IT> the transient S<SB>4</SB> state.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Structural information regarding the Mn<SB>4</SB> cluster is unclear and contentious at this point, mainly due to the lack of high resolution X-ray crystal data.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Electron density for metal ions, assigned as four Mn atoms, has been located recently in the crystal structures of the dark-adapted S<SB>1</SB> state of <IT>Thermosynechococcus elongates</IT> and <IT>Thermosynechococcus vulcanus</IT> at resolutions of 3.5–3.8 Å.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14 cit15 cit16">14–16</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the assignments greatly differ in the most recent 3.5 Å structures,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF> where a Mn<SB>3</SB>Ca cubane core, linked to a mono-oxo-bridged Mn center has been proposed for the WO catalyst.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast, in the previously reported two structures, three Mn atoms were roughly placed at three corners of an isosceles triangle and the fourth Mn was found to be at the center of the triangle obtruding towards the lumenal surface of the membrane.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14 cit15">14,15</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Locations of the essential cofactors, calcium and chloride ions, have not been resolved beyond doubt in these latter structures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, these aforementioned studies do not address the questions regarding the structural properties of the Mn<SB>4</SB> cluster at the higher S states.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, in the absence of sufficient crystallographic information the Mn<SB>4</SB> species has been conjectured in all of its kinetically accessible oxidation states (S<SB>0</SB> to S<SB>3</SB>) with the aid of spectroscopic modes, most commonly X-ray absorption fine structure (EXAFS) and electron paramagnetic resonance (EPR) techniques.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9 cit17 cit18 cit19 cit20 cit21">9,17–21</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Based on the findings from these studies and manganese oxide mineral structures, several possible arrangements comprising oxo-bridged dinuclear and trinuclear structural motifs have been put forward for the different S states of the PSII Mn<SB>4</SB> cluster.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9 cit22">9,22</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast, the structures of non-heme manganese-containing catalases have been determined at high resolution.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit23">5,23</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Catalase promotes the disproportionation of toxic H<SB>2</SB>O<SB>2</SB> in aerobic organisms to H<SB>2</SB>O and O<SB>2</SB>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The dimanganese center in this enzyme exists in four oxidation states: reduced Mn<SP>II</SP><SB>2</SB>, mixed-valent Mn<SP>II</SP>Mn<SP>III</SP>, oxidized Mn<SP>III</SP><SB>2</SB>, and super-oxidized Mn<SP>III</SP>Mn<SP>IV</SP> forms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Mn⋯Mn separations were found to be 3.13 Å in the reduced form,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF> and 3.03 Å in the oxidized form,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25">25</REF> as deduced from X-ray crystallography.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The super-oxidized form has yet to be characterized crystallographically; however, EXAFS data suggests a 2.70 Å distance between the manganese centers.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26">26</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Additionally, X-ray absorption, EPR and electronic spectroscopic studies on the Mn<SB>2</SB><SP>III</SP> and Mn<SP>III</SP>Mn<SP>IV</SP> states have garnered a great deal of knowledge that aids the biomimetic studies of this enzyme to a great extent.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24 cit26 cit27 cit28">24,26–28</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Most of these aforementioned multinuclear manganoenzymes harbor carboxylate-bridged Mn centers along with histidine N-donor ligands.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Many synthetic efforts aimed at obtaining suitable structural replicas for these enzyme active sites, especially catalase and the PSII WO, resulted in the isolation of a number of di-, tri-, and tetranuclear complexes supported largely by pyridine-based N-donor and commercially available carboxylate ligands.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Among them, dimanganese complexes containing [Mn<SB>2</SB>(μ-O)<SB>2</SB>], [Mn<SB>2</SB>(μ-O)<SB>2</SB>(μ-carboxylato)] and [Mn<SB>2</SB>(μ-O)(μ-carboxylato)<SB>2</SB>] cores are common, [Mn<SB>2</SB>(μ-O)<SB>2</SB>(bpy)<SB>4</SB>](ClO<SB>4</SB>)<SB>3</SB> (<XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem1">1</XREF>) being the first member in this family.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac20" novelty="None" advantage="None">Some of the synthetic complexes are closely relevant to the dinuclear manganese enzymes, yet none have been shown to replicate the spectroscopic features of the PSII tetramanganese cluster.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac21" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, a dinuclear complex where the metal centers are bridged simultaneously by a pair of oxo groups and a pair of carboxylato groups was unknown in transition metal chemistry until recently.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">We reported the first example of such a case in the complex, [Mn<SB>2</SB>(μ-O)<SB>2</SB>(μ-O<SB>2</SB>CAr<SP>Tol</SP>)<SB>2</SB>(bpy)<SB>2</SB>]<SP>+</SP> (where bpy = 2,2′-bipyridine, and Ar<SP>Tol</SP>CO<SB>2</SB><SP>−</SP> = 2,6-di(<IT>p–</IT>tolyl)benzoate) (<XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem2">2</XREF>), which incorporates a sterically hindering carboxylate ligand.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29">29</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Complex <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem2">2</XREF> was obtained by ligand substitution on <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem1">1</XREF>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The di-oxo di-carboxylato core discussed herein could conceivably be present as a segment of the PSII active site.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac22" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, since one of the glutamate residues (glu 178) is close to the dimanganese site in the <IT>Lactobacillus plantarum</IT> structure, there exists the possibility that, in another super-oxidized form, it joins glu 66 in spanning the dimanganese core.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac22" novelty="None" advantage="None">If this were the case, the native core would resemble that of <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem2">2</XREF>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Complex <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem2">2</XREF> has been structurally characterized with X-ray crystallography.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The [Mn<SB>2</SB>(μ-O)<SB>2</SB>(bpy)<SB>2</SB>] moiety in <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem2">2</XREF> is approximately planar, as shown in Fig. 1, while two carboxylate ligands bridge between Mn centers, one from above and one from below this plane.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The Mn<SP>III</SP> and Mn<SP>IV</SP> centers are found to be valence-trapped in <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem2">2</XREF> in the solid state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The Mn–O<SB>carboxylate</SB> bond lengths for the Mn<SP>III</SP> center are markedly longer than those of the Mn<SP>IV</SP> center, av 2.317 Å <IT>vs.</IT> av 1.943 Å, respectively, as they are along the <IT>Jahn–Teller</IT> axis of elongation for the Mn<SP>III</SP> center.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Other dinuclear Mn(iii, iv) complexes exhibit valence trapping in the solid state, however the Mn-axial ligand bond distances are not so dramatically different.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Complex <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem2">2</XREF> has a Mn⋯Mn distance of 2.505(1) Å and Mn–O–Mn angles averaging 88.3°, the shortest distance and smallest angles reported for any dimanganese species containing the [Mn<SB>2</SB>(μ-O)<SB>2</SB>] core to date.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The fourth bridging group between Mn centers is likely responsible for the resulting unusual distance and angles.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Several previous theoretical studies on oxygen-bridged Mn<SP>III</SP>Mn<SP>IV</SP> complexes, with a variety of bridging motifs, have been reported.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">For purposes of structural comparison, we have previously reported Becke–Perdew (BP) calculations on such complexes featuring the cores Mn<SB>2</SB>(μ-O)<SB>2</SB>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30">30</REF> Mn<SB>2</SB>(μ-O)<SB>2</SB>(O<SB>2</SB>CH), and Mn<SB>2</SB>(μ-O)(O<SB>2</SB>CH)<SB>2</SB>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit31">31</REF> for which Mn–Mn distances of 2.783, 2.667, and 3.269 Å were obtained.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Results from studies by other groups,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit32 cit33">32,33</REF> on di-μ-oxo-bridged Mn<SP>III</SP>Mn<SP>IV</SP> complexes, have yielded broadly similar structural results to our own,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30">30</REF> while a study by Noodleman and co-workers<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit34">34</REF> on a complex featuring a Mn<SB>2</SB>(μ-O)<SB>2</SB>(O<SB>2</SB>CH) core with an additional bridging RHNCH<SB>2</SB>CH<SB>2</SB>NHR ligand, possessed a Mn–Mn distance ranging from 2.55 to 2.62 Å depending on the level of theory employed.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None">Here, we report detailed density functional theory calculations performed on this newly formed dimanganese core in order to determine the electronic and steric effects of the sterically encumbering carboxylate ligands.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Mn<SP>III</SP> and Mn<SP>IV</SP> centers are found to be strongly antiferromagnetically coupled in all other dinuclear complexes.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13 cit35 cit36 cit37 cit38 cit39 cit40">13,35–40</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="New" advantage="None">We report the outcome of calculations on the [Mn<SB>2</SB>(μ-O)<SB>2</SB>(μ-O<SB>2</SB>CH)<SB>2</SB>(bpy)<SB>2</SB>]<SP>+</SP> core to predict the nature of the intramolecular exchange interaction between the manganese centers.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Theoretical methods</HEADER><P><s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Density functional theory calculations were performed on Linux-based Pentium IV computers using the Amsterdam Density Functional (ADF) program, version ADF 2002.03,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit41">41</REF> developed by Baerends <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit42 cit43">42,43</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Calculations on [Mn<SB>2</SB>(μ-O)<SB>2</SB>(μ-O<SB>2</SB>CH)<SB>2</SB>(bpy)<SB>2</SB>] structures, in various charge states, were performed in <IT>C</IT><SB>2v</SB> symmetry (or, in some cases as identified, in higher symmetry) using the Becke–Perdew (BP) gradient-corrected density functional approach.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit44 cit45">44,45</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Slater orbital basis sets used in all calculations were of triple-<IT>ξ</IT> quality (TZP).</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Electrons in orbitals up to and including 1s {C, N, O} and 2p {Mn} were treated in accordance with the frozen-core approximation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Optimized geometries were obtained using the gradient algorithm of Versluis and Ziegler.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit46">46</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">All calculations were performed in a spin-unrestricted fashion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">For calculations on antiferromagnetically coupled structures, the broken symmetry (BS) approach of Noodleman<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit47">47</REF> was affected using the <IT>ModifyStartPotential</IT> key to introduce an initial spin inhomogeneity between the two metal atoms.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Results and discussion</HEADER><P><s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Density functional theory calculations on the model compound [Mn<SB>2</SB>(μ-O)<SB>2</SB>(μ-O<SB>2</SB>CH)<SB>2</SB>(bpy)<SB>2</SB>]<SP>+</SP> reproduce the crystallographic structure very satisfactorily.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our geometry optimization on the <IT>S</IT> = 1/2 ‘broken symmetry’ (BS) state of the model compound, in <IT>C</IT><SB>2v</SB> symmetry, yields a structure for which all of the key bond lengths and bond angles, summarized in Table 1 and Fig. 2, agree with the crystallographic data to within ±2.5%.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In particular, the BS calculation demonstrates that the asymmetry in bond lengths between Mn atoms and the carboxylate O atoms arises through electronic effects rather than through steric considerations, since the bulky carboxylate substituent of the crystallographically isolated species is replaced with H in our model compound.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The important structural features of the BS geometry are also evident in the geometry optimized for the <IT>S</IT> = 7/2 state in <IT>C</IT><SB>2v</SB> symmetry, although the Mn–Mn bond length found in this ferromagnetically coupled structure is over 0.1 Å longer than the experimental value.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj5" novelty="New" advantage="None">In addition to these <IT>C</IT><SB>2v</SB> symmetry optimizations, calculations were also pursued on moderately distorted geometries in <IT>C</IT><SB>s</SB> symmetry (with the mirror plane coincident with the carboxylate ligands and Mn atoms).</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">These optimizations commenced in <IT>C</IT><SB>s</SB> symmetry but spontaneously converged towards the <IT>C</IT><SB>2v</SB> optimized geometries for both the <IT>S</IT> = 1/2 and <IT>S</IT> = 7/2 states.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast, calculations on the <IT>S</IT> = 7/2 state in <IT>D</IT><SB>2h</SB> symmetry led to a structure with enforced delocalization of all of the Mn-based electrons.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">As well as (understandably) failing to reproduce the observed intermetallic asymmetry, the <IT>S</IT> = 7/2 <IT>D</IT><SB>2h</SB> calculations yielded a total energy markedly higher than either the <IT>S</IT> = 1/2 or <IT>S</IT> = 7/2 <IT>C</IT><SB>2v</SB> optimized geometries (see Table 2), thereby underlining the energetic preference for a ‘valence-trapped’ d<SP>3</SP>d<SP>4</SP> (Mn<SP>IV</SP>Mn<SP>III</SP>) configuration rather than a ‘delocalized’ d<SP>3.5</SP>d<SP>3.5</SP> configuration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj6" novelty="New" advantage="None">The <IT>S</IT> = 7/2 <IT>C</IT><SB>2v</SB> structure is necessarily high-spin on Mn<SP>III</SP>; we have investigated also a <IT>S</IT> = 5/2 <IT>C</IT><SB>2v</SB> configuration, which corresponds to ferromagnetically-coupled Mn<SP>IV</SP> with low-spin Mn<SP>III</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The latter calculation spontaneously converges to a structure of <IT>D</IT><SB>2h</SB> symmetry, indicating that in this mode of coupling a delocalized configuration is preferred.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The total energy for this configuration is only 14 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> above that of the <IT>S</IT> = 1/2 <IT>C</IT><SB>2v</SB> (BS) optimized geometry.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj7" novelty="New" advantage="None">We have also explored a <IT>D</IT><SB>2h</SB> configuration for an unnaturally symmetric <IT>S</IT> = 1/2 species with a delocalized <IT>α</IT>-spin electron combined with <IT>α</IT>-spin <IT>versus β</IT>-spin dominance of the two metal centers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">While the latter species does not describe a tenable solution to the Mn<SP>III</SP>Mn<SP>IV</SP> complex’s electronic configuration, its relative energy (only 19 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> above that of the <IT>S</IT> = 1/2 <IT>C</IT><SB>2v</SB> (BS) optimized geometry) emphasizes that the energetic preference for the <IT>C</IT><SB>2v</SB> geometry, with distinctly different coordination environments around the two metal atoms, is really rather slight.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj8" novelty="New" advantage="None">In addition to calculations on the mixed-valence Mn<SP>III</SP>Mn<SP>IV</SP> complex, we have also explored various electronic configurations of the corresponding Mn<SP>III</SP>Mn<SP>III</SP> and Mn<SP>IV</SP>Mn<SP>IV</SP> complexes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj8" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">These calculations allow direct comparison with the results of DFT studies on Mn<SB>2</SB> complexes with bridging motifs such as (μ-O)<SB>3</SB>, (μ-O)<SB>2</SB>(μ-O<SB>2</SB>), and (μ-O)(μ-O<SB>2</SB>) which have been investigated in the Mn<SP>III</SP>Mn<SP>III</SP> and /or Mn<SP>IV</SP>Mn<SP>IV</SP> oxidation states, but not in the Mn<SP>III</SP>Mn<SP>IV</SP> configuration.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit48 cit49 cit50">48–50</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Analysis of the optimized structures from those studies and from our earlier examples of μ-oxo-bridged Mn<SP>III</SP>Mn<SP>IV</SP> complexes,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30 cit31">30,31</REF> leads to the conclusion that the (μ-O)<SB>2</SB>(μ-O<SB>2</SB>CR)<SB>2</SB> bridging combination leads innately to a Mn–Mn distance which is markedly smaller than that found for any of the bridging motifs yet explored except for that of Mn<SP>IV</SP>(μ-O)<SB>3</SB>Mn<SP>IV</SP>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit49">49</REF> for which our calculated metal–metal separation of 2.320 Å is only 0.1 Å shorter than the corresponding distance in the Mn<SP>IV</SP>Mn<SP>IV</SP> structure explored in the present work.</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In particular, it is apparent that removal of either one μ-oxo, or of one μ-carboxylato, bridge from the Mn(μ-O)<SB>2</SB>(μ-O<SB>2</SB>CH)<SB>2</SB>Mn core leads to a considerable lengthening of the metal–metal axis regardless of the oxidation states on the two Mn atoms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">This tendency is fully consistent with comparisons between the crystalline geometry of <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem2">2</XREF> and of related Mn<SB>2</SB>(μ-O)<SB>2</SB> and Mn<SB>2</SB>(μ-O)<SB><IT>i</IT></SB>(μ-O<SB>2</SB>CR)<SB><IT>j</IT></SB> (<IT>i</IT> + <IT>j</IT> = 3) complexes, as noted above.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Total bond energies and relative energies, for the various electronic configurations of [Mn<SB>2</SB>(μ-O)<SB>2</SB>(μ-O<SB>2</SB>CH)<SB>2</SB>(bpy)<SB>2</SB>]<SP><IT>n</IT>+</SP> (<IT>n</IT> = 0, 1, 2) are given in Table 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the d<SP>4</SP>d<SP>4</SP> (Mn<SP>III</SP>Mn<SP>III</SP>) dinuclear complex, valid single-determinant descriptions are possible for BS (<IT>M</IT><SB><IT>S</IT></SB> = 0) and for <IT>S</IT> = 1, 2, 3, and 4.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The <IT>S</IT> = 4 configuration explored corresponds to a ferromagnetically coupled, high-spin Mn<SP>III</SP> dimer, while the <IT>S</IT> = 2 configuration consists of two low-spin Mn<SP>III</SP> centers which are ferromagnetically coupled.</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Mixed high-spin/low-spin dimers are represented in the <IT>S</IT> = 1 and <IT>S</IT> = 3 configurations which are, respectively, antiferromagnetically and ferromagnetically coupled, while the <IT>M</IT><SB><IT>S</IT></SB> = 0 (broken symmetry, BS) configuration is an antiferromagnetic coupling of equivalent Mn<SP>III</SP> centers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Within the broken symmetry framework, each Mn<SP>III</SP> center in the BS configuration can be either high-spin or low-spin.</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our calculations show that there is a considerable energetic preference for low-spin Mn<SP>III</SP>, which contrasts with the results of our previous calculations on di-μ-oxo-bridged (and mixed oxo-/carboxylato-bridged) Mn<SP>III</SP> dimers for which high-spin Mn<SP>III</SP> is preferred.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30 cit31">30,31</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="Old" advantage="None">For the d<SP>3</SP>d<SP>3</SP> (Mn<SP>IV</SP>Mn<SP>IV</SP>) dinuclear complex, we have explored only the <IT>M</IT><SB><IT>S</IT></SB> = 0 (BS) and <IT>S</IT> = 3 configurations which correspond, respectively, to antiferromagnetic and ferromagnetic coupling of two Mn<SP>IV</SP> centers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Again, the antiferromagnetic broken-symmetry solution is the preferred (lower-energy) description of this dinuclear complex.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is also worthwhile to compare the geometries of the homonuclear Mn<SP>III</SP>Mn<SP>III</SP> and Mn<SP>IV</SP>Mn<SP>IV</SP> complexes with that of the broken-symmetry Mn<SP>III</SP>Mn<SP>IV</SP> minimum; the central bond lengths and bond angles for all of these structures are included in Table 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">There is very good agreement between the calculated Mn<SP>III</SP>Mn<SP>IV</SP> geometry and the optimized Mn<SP>IV</SP>Mn<SP>IV</SP> structures, insofar as the coordination around the Mn<SP>IV</SP> center (Mn<SP>B</SP>) of the mixed-valence complex is concerned.</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the agreement between geometric parameters featuring Mn<SP>A</SP> (the identified Mn<SP>III</SP> center of the mixed-valence complex) and the Mn<SP>III</SP> centers in the broken-symmetry Mn<SP>III</SP>Mn<SP>III</SP> geometry is much poorer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">Better general agreement with the geometry surrounding Mn<SP>A</SP> is seen for the ferromagnetically coupled, high-spin (<IT>S</IT> = 4) Mn<SP>III</SP>Mn<SP>III</SP> structure also summarized in Table 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note, however, that all of the ferromagnetically-coupled structures detailed in Table 1 have metal–metal separations which significantly exceed those of the antiferromagnetically-coupled (broken-symmetry) minima, and of the crystallographically-isolated complex.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">How can we rationalize the contraction in the Mn–Mn separation when the coupling mode is switched from ferromagnetic to antiferromagnetic?</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, what can be established for the lowest-energy electronic configuration for the Mn<SP>III</SP>Mn<SP>IV</SP> species, namely the BS (<IT>S</IT> = 1/2) <IT>C</IT><SB>2v</SB> geometry?</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">A detailed perusal of the composition of the metal-based molecular orbitals (MOs) in the BS geometry of the Mn<SP>III</SP>Mn<SP>IV</SP> complex (see Tables 3–5) reveals that none of the magnetic electrons is strongly delocalized between both metal centers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" advantage="None">Instead, the 39a<SB>1</SB> (↑), 17b<SB>2</SB> (↑), and 10a<SB>2</SB> (↑) MOs show strong mixing between Mn<SP>A</SP> and the oxo bridges, with the corresponding spin-down MOs similarly mixed between Mn<SP>B</SP> and the oxo bridges.</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None">The remaining occupied valence metal-based orbital, 40a<SB>1</SB> (↑), shows a modest degree (14%) of Mn<SP>B</SP> character but is principally identifiable as Mn<SP>A</SP> with mixing from the immediately attached oxygens of the carboxylate ligands.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None">The intermetallic interaction here is an example of ‘crossed exchange’ involving the <IT>J</IT><SB><IT>x</IT><SP>2</SP>−<IT>y</IT><SP>2</SP>/<IT>z</IT><SP>2</SP></SB> pathway, resulting in transfer of charge from a majority-spin, e<SB>g</SB>-derived orbital on Mn<SP>III</SP> (here d<SB><IT>x</IT><SP>2</SP>−<IT>y</IT><SP>2</SP></SB>) to a minority-spin, t<SB>2g</SB>-derived orbital on Mn<SP>IV</SP> (here d<SB><IT>z</IT><SP>2</SP></SB>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is tempting to alternatively interpret the mixture of <IT>α</IT>-spin Mn<SP>A</SP> and Mn<SP>B</SP> content in the 40a<SB>1</SB> orbital, with Mn<SP>A</SP> dominant, as an indication of the balance between the ‘high-spin Mn<SP>III</SP>’ d<SP>4</SP>d<SP>3</SP> (Mn<SP>III</SP>Mn<SP>IV</SP>) description of this state, in which the excess <IT>α</IT>-spin electron is localized on <IT>α</IT>-spin-dominant Mn<SP>A</SP>, and the ‘low-spin Mn<SP>III</SP>’ d<SP>3</SP>d<SP>4</SP> (Mn<SP>IV</SP>Mn<SP>III</SP>) configuration with the excess <IT>α</IT>-spin electron localized on otherwise <IT>β</IT>-spin-dominant Mn<SP>B</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">We conclude that the BS minimum for the Mn<SP>III</SP>Mn<SP>IV</SP> complex is best described as an antiferromagnetic coupling between high-spin Mn<SP>III</SP> and Mn<SP>IV</SP>, with a modest degree of delocalization between metal atoms being evident in only one occupied valence molecular orbital.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is broadly consistent with previous studies, both experimental<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit13">8,13</REF> and theoretical,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit31 cit32 cit33 cit34 cit48 cit49 cit50">31–34,48–50</REF> which generally find Mn<SP>III</SP>Mn<SP>IV</SP> complexes featuring oxo bridges to adopt antiferromagnetically coupled configurations with some degree of valence trapping.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">This analysis of the MO composition from the <IT>S</IT> = 1/2 structure suggests that the direct Mn–Mn bonding contribution to the bond length is minor compared to the constraints of the oxo and carboxylato bridges.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res29" novelty="None" advantage="None">Composition of the occupied 39a<SB>1</SB>, 10a<SB>2</SB>, and 17b<SB>2</SB> orbitals, as detailed in Table 3, clearly shows that the magnetic exchange between metal atoms is dominated by superexchange <IT>via</IT> the oxo bridges, in keeping with the results of our earlier investigations of di-<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30">30</REF> and tri-μ-oxo-<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit49">49</REF> and mixed oxo- and carboxylato-bridged<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit31">31</REF> Mn<SP>III</SP>Mn<SP>IV</SP> dinuclear complexes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res30" novelty="None" advantage="None">In fact, the di-μ-oxo-bridged species [(NH<SB>3</SB>)<SB>4</SB>Mn<SP>III</SP>(μ-O)<SB>2</SB>Mn<SP>IV</SP>(NH<SB>3</SB>)<SB>4</SB>]<SP>3+</SP>, which we have previously studied,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30">30</REF> is seen to bear a very close resemblance to the species under investigation in the present work.</annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res30" novelty="None" advantage="None">This resemblance is reflected both structurally, in the elongation of bonds from the Mn<SP>III</SP> atom to the μ-oxo bridges, and the more pronounced elongation of bonds from Mn<SP>III</SP> to the axially-coordinated atoms (respectively, the N of NH<SB>3</SB>, or the O of the carboxylate bridge), and in the electronic configuration determined for the <IT>S</IT> = 1/2 broken symmetry state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" advantage="None">Consistent trends are also seen when we compare the present results with those of our study on Mn<SP>III</SP>(μ-O)<SB>2</SB>(μ-O<SB>2</SB>CH)Mn<SP>IV</SP> and Mn<SP>III</SP>(μ-O)(μ-O<SB>2</SB>CH)<SB>2</SB>Mn<SP>IV</SP> complexes:<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit31">31</REF> in each case, the BS (<IT>S</IT> = 1/2) complex can be described as a largely valence-trapped structure consisting of high-spin Mn<SP>III</SP> antiferromagnetically coupled to Mn<SP>IV</SP>, although the Mn<SP>III</SP>(μ-O)(μ-O<SB>2</SB>CH)<SB>2</SB>Mn<SP>IV</SP> core is rather more electronically complex and displays configurational mixing from low-spin Mn<SP>III</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res32" novelty="None" advantage="None">The mixed μ-oxo/μ-carboxylato bridged complexes also invariably display markedly longer bonds for Mn<SP>III</SP>–O than for Mn<SP>IV</SP>–O (whether to oxo or carboxylato O atoms), but the elongation of the Mn<SP>III</SP>–O (carboxylato) bonds within the present <IT>S</IT> = 1/2 complex (bond lengths of 2.27 Å are 0.3 Å longer than the corresponding Mn<SP>IV</SP>–O distances) is rather greater than is seen in the earlier study,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit31">31</REF> presumably because in the present work these carboxylato O atoms lie on the Jahn–Teller axis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res33" novelty="None" advantage="None">Nevertheless, for all of the mixed μ-oxo/μ-carboxylato bridged complexes which we have studied,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit31">31</REF> the disparity between Mn<SP>III</SP>–O and Mn<SP>IV</SP>–O is more extreme in the ferromagnetically coupled <IT>S</IT> = 7/2 configuration than for <IT>S</IT> = 1/2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">This tendency for ‘milder’ Mn-ligand bond lengths in the broken-symmetry configuration than in <IT>S</IT> = 7/2 presumably indicates that the valence trapping within the BS state is less extreme than in <IT>S</IT> = 7/2, implying that pathways for overlap or mixing of Mn-based orbitals exist for <IT>S</IT> = 1/2 which are not viable (or which are less effective) for <IT>S</IT> = 7/2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ‘crossed exchange’ pathway discussed above fulfils this description, since the mixing of an occupied e<SB>g</SB>-derived high-spin-Mn<SP>III</SP>-based orbital with a vacant t<SB>2g</SB>-derived Mn<SP>IV</SP>-based orbital is possible only if the spins on Mn<SP>III</SP> and Mn<SP>IV</SP> are (antiferromagnetically) opposed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res34" novelty="None" advantage="None">Another consequence of the ‘crossed exchange’ interaction is that mixing of the occupied Mn<SP>III</SP> e<SB>g</SB>-derived orbital with a t<SB>2g</SB>-derived Mn<SP>IV</SP> orbital leads to a lessening in the Jahn–Teller distortion of the Mn<SP>III</SP> center.</annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res34" novelty="None" advantage="None">The carboxylic oxygens lie on the nominal Jahn–Teller axis in this instance, and the shorter Mn<SP>III</SP>-O<SB>carb</SB> distance of 2.27 Å seen for the <IT>S</IT> = 1/2 Mn<SP>III</SP>Mn<SP>IV</SP> dimer than that found for the <IT>S</IT> = 7/2 structure (2.32 Å) is consistent with the structural implications of the crossed-exchange mechanism.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res35" novelty="None" advantage="None">Further structural analysis—for example, of the variation in Mn–O–Mn angles as a function of the bridging combination within different modelled complexes—can be given: not surprisingly, the Mn–O–Mn angles found here, of 87.4° (BS) and 91.7° (<IT>S</IT> = 7/2), are uniformly less than those which we have previously reported for the complexes containing Mn<SP>III</SP>(μ-O)<SB>2</SB>Mn<SP>IV</SP> (97.7° (BS)), Mn<SP>III</SP>(μ-O)<SB>2</SB>(μ-O<SB>2</SB>CH)Mn<SP>IV</SP> (94.2° (BS); 93.4° (<IT>S</IT> = 7/2)), and Mn<SP>III</SP>(μ-O)(μ-O<SB>2</SB>CH)<SB>2</SB>Mn<SP>IV</SP> (130.5° (BS); 124.7° (<IT>S</IT> = 7/2)) cores , reflecting the more compact Mn–Mn distance in the present case.</annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res36" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Mn<SB>2</SB>O<SB>2</SB> core geometry may well not hold a significant direct influence over the crossed-exchange pathway, since this appears to operate through mixing of near-degenerate orbitals rather than through overlap, but the antiferromagnetic pathways <IT>J</IT><SB>xy/xy</SB> and <IT>J</IT><SB><IT>yz</IT>/<IT>yz</IT></SB> (which are, respectively, analogous to the <IT>J</IT><SB>xz/xz</SB> and <IT>J</IT><SB>yz/yz</SB> pathways explored in our study of the di-μ-oxo-bridged complexes)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30">30</REF> are dependent on the overlap of Mn-centered and O-centered orbitals and thus should be affected by the Mn–Mn and Mn–O distances and the Mn–O–Mn angles.</annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">A more detailed analysis of the structural/magnetic interplay in the Mn<SB>2</SB>(μ-O)<SB>2</SB>(μ-O<SB>2</SB>CR)<SB>2</SB> core is in preparation but is beyond the scope of the present work.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the study on [(NH<SB>3</SB>)<SB>4</SB>Mn<SP>III</SP>(μ-O)<SB>2</SB>Mn<SP>IV</SP>(NH<SB>3</SB>)<SB>4</SB>]<SP>3+</SP> in the BS (<IT>S</IT> = 1/2) state, we found that the composition of the metal-dominated, occupied valence molecular orbitals showed strong mixing between one or other Mn atom and the oxo bridges in all but the highest occupied, <IT>α</IT>-spin, a<SB>1</SB>-symmetry metal-based orbital.</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The composition of this highest occupied orbital is particularly pertinent.</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res37" novelty="None" advantage="None">Using a notation scheme similar to that employed in Table 3, our earlier study reported percentage compositions of the 17a<SB>1</SB> orbital of 31% N<SB>axial</SB> (attached to Mn<SP>A</SP>), 48% Mn<SP>A</SP> (principally d<SB><IT>z</IT><SP>2</SP></SB> character), 2% O<SB>br</SB>, 12% Mn<SP>B</SP> (principally d<SB><IT>x</IT><SP>2</SP>−<IT>y</IT><SP>2</SP></SB> character), and 0% N<SB>axial</SB> (attached to Mn<SP>B</SP>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res38" novelty="None" advantage="None">As with the HOMO 40a<SB>1</SB> in the <IT>S</IT> = 1/2 (BS) [Mn<SB>2</SB>(μ-O)<SB>2</SB>(μ-O<SB>2</SB>CH)<SB>2</SB>bpy<SB>2</SB>]<SP>+</SP> complex which forms the focus of the present study, the 17a<SB>1</SB> HOMO in the di-μ-oxo-bridged complex studied previously<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30">30</REF> is therefore a crossed exchange pathway.</annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res39" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that, due to differences in the axis assignments of the two studies (see Fig. 2 for the axis assignment used here), the occupied majority-spin e<SB>g</SB>-derived orbital on Mn<SP>III</SP> is identified, in the earlier study, as d<SB><IT>z</IT><SP>2</SP></SB> and the vacant minority-spin t<SB>2g</SB>-derived orbital on Mn<SP>IV</SP> is d<SB><IT>x</IT><SP>2</SP>−<IT>y</IT><SP>2</SP></SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None">There are also indications that the strength of the crossed exchange pathway depends upon the energy spacing between the atomic orbitals involved in this pathway.</annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res40" novelty="None" advantage="None">If we assess the ratio of ‘Mn<SP>IV</SP>’ to ‘Mn<SP>III</SP>’ character in the highest-occupied a<SB>1</SB>-symmetry orbital of di-μ-oxo-bridged complexes featuring, respectively, 0,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30">30</REF> 2 (this work), and 1<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit31">31</REF> carboxylato bridge(s), we find that this ratio consistently increases from 0.25 to 0.3 to 0.55 as the energy gap between the highest occupied and the lowest unoccupied <IT>α</IT>-spin a<SB>1</SB>-symmetry orbitals is reduced from 1.35 to 1.29 to 0.85 eV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None">While a more detailed analysis of this trend appears unwarranted since the species being compared do not possess identical terminal ligands in all cases, the results of our present study certainly strengthen the grounds for hypothesizing that the crossed exchange pathway is most efficient when the respective majority-spin e<SB>g</SB>-derived Mn<SP>III</SP> and minority-spin t<SB>2g</SB>-derived Mn<SP>IV</SP> orbitals are most nearly degenerate.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Conclusion</HEADER><P><s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our density functional theory calculations on the complex [(bpy)Mn(μ-O)<SB>2</SB>(μ-O<SB>2</SB>CH)<SB>2</SB>Mn(bpy)] show excellent structural agreement with the crystallographic results which have previously been reported for a closely analogous complex featuring bulky carboxylate substituents.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29">29</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Accordingly, we can confidently assign the experimentally observed asymmetric structure, with markedly canted carboxylate bridges, as arising from an innate electronic preference of the Mn(μ-O)<SB>2</SB>(μ-O<SB>2</SB>CR)<SB>2</SB>Mn core for a valence-trapped Mn<SP>III</SP>Mn<SP>IV</SP> configuration (with Mn<SP>III</SP> identifiably dominated by high-spin character, although an idealized low-spin structure is only 14 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> higher in energy according to our calculations) and not from steric effects originating from the bulky substituents.</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None">This valence-trapped distortion of the metal/bridge core, in turn, appears to be heavily influenced by the crossed-exchange pathway, which leads to a lessening of the Jahn–Teller distortion experienced by the nominal Mn<SP>III</SP> centre.</annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res41" novelty="None" advantage="None">The extent of configurational mixing evident between high-spin Mn<SP>III</SP> (contaminated by Mn<SP>IV</SP> character) and Mn<SP>IV</SP> (contaminated, in turn, by low-spin Mn<SP>III</SP> character) is greater than that seen in our previous calculations on complexes containing the Mn(μ-O)<SB>2</SB>Mn core, but less than in complexes featuring a Mn(μ-O)<SB>2</SB>(μ-O<SB>2</SB>CH)Mn centre.</annotationART></s> <s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is tempting to suggest that the strength of this crossed-exchange pathway is acutely sensitive to the proximity of the singly occupied and unoccupied a<SB>1</SB>-symmetry orbitals involved in this mixing, but further study is required to substantiate this notion.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
