<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b410120k" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Short and stereoselective synthesis of <IT>C</IT>-glycosylated glycine derivatives from glycals by radical addition and reduction<XREF TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" /></annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Only three steps are required for the convenient synthesis of 2-<IT>C</IT>-branched glyco-amino acids from glycals with good yields and stereoselectivities.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER /><P><s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Glycopeptides and glycoproteins are an important family of compounds, which contain a carbohydrate and a peptide domain and are of current interest in bioorganic chemistry, due to their biological functions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2">1,2</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Recent research activities were especially focused on modified glycopeptides, where the common <IT>O</IT>- or <IT>N</IT>-glycosidic bond linkages were replaced by a carbon-based unit of greater stability and resistance towards enzymatic deglycosylation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Indeed, during the last decade several syntheses of such <IT>C</IT>-glycopeptides were reported in the literature.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2 cit3">2,3</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, glycine derivatives directly linked to carbohydrates are constituents of natural products and possess remarkable antibiotic activities.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="No">However, many synthesis of <IT>C</IT>-glycosyl amino acids focused on the linkage at the anomeric position and required many reaction steps.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Only very recently, Chandrasekaran and coworkers developed an elegant entry to 2-<IT>C</IT>-branched glyco-amino acids by the ring opening of 1,2-cyclopropanated sugars.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="New" advantage="None">Herein we describe our approach for the synthesis of such <IT>C</IT>-glycosylated glycine derivatives in only three steps from commercially available glycals.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">The reaction sequence involves a radical addition and the reduction of CN double bonds, which both proceed with good yields and stereoselectivities.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">During the course of our investigations on transition-metal-mediated radical reactions, we developed a simple one-step entry to 2-<IT>C</IT>-branched carbohydrates by the addition of dimethyl malonate to various glycals in the presence of ceric(iv) ammonium nitrate (CAN).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Thus, the <IT>gluco</IT> isomer <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem2">2</XREF> was obtained in 62% yield from tri-<IT>O</IT>-acetyl-d-glucal (<XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem1a">1a</XREF>) and was chosen as the precursor for the synthesis of the desired <IT>C</IT>-glycosylated glycine derivatives.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The transformation of malonates into α-amino acids <IT>via</IT> the corresponding oximes is known since many years.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="No">However, applications in carbohydrate chemistry were hitherto unknown, due to the drastic basic conditions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="New" advantage="None">After careful optimization of the reaction, isoamyl nitrite was found as the reagent of choice for the introduction of the nitrogen functionality.</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">Thus, the oxime ester <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem3">3</XREF> was isolated in excellent yield after acetylation (Scheme 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="Old" advantage="None">NOE experiments indicated the exclusive formation of the <IT>Z</IT>-configured diastereomer, which can be rationalized in terms of steric repulsion between the <IT>N</IT>-<IT>O</IT>-acetyl group and the carbohydrate residue.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="Old" advantage="No">Unfortunately, due to the drastic reaction conditions the transformation of other malonyl-substituted saccharides <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem2">2</XREF> into the corresponding oximes failed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="New" advantage="None">To overcome this problem and to develop a general entry to 2-<IT>C</IT>-branched glyco-amino acids, we became interested in the introduction of the nitrogen functionality by the radical reaction in the first step.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="New" advantage="None">Due to its CH acidity, the nitroacetate <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem4">4</XREF> seemed to be an ideal precursor for such a transition-metal-mediated radical reaction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Indeed, the addition of nitroacetates to alkenes and arenes in the presence of Mn(OAc)<SB>3</SB> was reported in the literature,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF> but applications in carbohydrate chemistry were hitherto unknown.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">However, under the mild ceric(iv) ammonium nitrate (CAN) conditions, the addition of nitroacetate <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem4">4</XREF> to various glycals <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem1">1</XREF> proceeds smoothly, to afford the bicyclic isoxazoline <IT>N</IT>-oxides <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem5">5</XREF> in only one step in moderate yields and high diastereoselectivities (Scheme 2).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">Furthermore, compared to the synthesis <IT>via</IT> the malonate <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem2">2</XREF>, the addition of nitro acetate <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem4">4</XREF> requires only one reaction step for the introduction of the nitrogen functionality from glycals.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="New" advantage="None">From the mechanistic point of view, CAN oxidizes the intermediary formed anomeric radical to a cation, which is intramolecularly trapped by the nitro group to afford the <IT>cis</IT>-bicyclic isoxazoline <IT>N</IT>-oxides <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem5">5</XREF>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="New" advantage="None">The preferred formation of the depicted diastereomers can be rationalized by an <IT>anti</IT> attack of the radicals to the 3-<IT>O</IT>-acetyl group, in accordance with the addition of malonates.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="New" advantage="None">To obtain the desired glycine derivatives, the CN double bonds had to be reduced in the next step, with especial interest on the diastereoselectivity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The hydrogenation of simple oximes is described in the literature with several palladium catalysts.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="Old" advantage="No">However, the additional ester groups in substrates <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem3">3</XREF> and <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem5">5</XREF> diminish the reactivity towards catalytic hydrogenation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="Old" advantage="No">Furthermore, the large steric demand of the carbohydrate moiety was problematic and resulted in slow heterogeneous reactions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Thus, some catalysts were unreactive and only palladium hydroxide at 40 bar hydrogen pressure led to 81% conversion of the oxime ester <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem3">3</XREF>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">After acetylation the desired glycine derivatives <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem6">6</XREF> were isolated in good yield and diastereoselectivity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="Old" advantage="No">However, the isoxazoline <IT>N</IT>-oxides <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem5">5</XREF> did not react under such conditions (Table 1).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="New" advantage="None">To overcome this problem and to develop a general entry to 2-<IT>C</IT>-branched glyco-amino acids, we investigated the reduction of the CN double bonds by aluminium amalgam,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF> which mechanistically proceeds by an electron transfer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">Indeed, now the electron poor oxime <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem3">3</XREF> and isoxazoline <IT>N</IT>-oxides <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem5a chem5b chem5c chem5d">5a–d</XREF> did react smoothly with high conversions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">After acetylation the diastereomeric <IT>C</IT>-glycosylated amino acids <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem6">6</XREF> were separated by column chromatography and isolated in good overall yields.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Reduction of the bicyclic substrates <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem5">5</XREF> afforded α/β anomeric mixtures, due to the intermediary formed hemi-acetals, whereas oxime <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem3">3</XREF> gave exclusively the β-configured methyl glycoside (Table 1).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The catalytic hydrogenation and amalgam reductions proceed with moderate to high stereoselectivities, due to steric interactions with the carbohydrate residue.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">All main products have the same absolute configuration at the newly formed C-7 stereogenic center, which was established by comparison of the NMR spectra.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Interestingly, the <IT>gluco</IT> (<XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem3">3</XREF> and <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem5a">5a</XREF>) and <IT>xylo</IT> (<XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem5c">5c</XREF>) isomers gave similar dr (77∶23 to 85∶15), whereas the <IT>galacto</IT> isomer <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem5b">5b</XREF> reacts less selectively (70∶30) and the <IT>malto</IT> isomer <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem5d">5d</XREF> with higher selectivity (94∶6).</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">This can be rationalized by a predominant attack of the reductant from the <IT>Re</IT> side, which is hindered by the axial <IT>O</IT>-acetyl group in <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem5b">5b</XREF> and even more preferred by the equatorial carbohydrate residue in <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem5d">5d</XREF>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, the main products of all reactions should have the <IT>S</IT> configuration at C-7.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, due to the fast rotation of the C–C single bond, the determination of the configuration at the newly formed C-7 stereocenter was not possible by the coupling constants in the <SP>1</SP>H NMR spectra.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met14" novelty="New" advantage="None">Finally, the crystallization of the main isomer from the reduction of the <IT>gluco</IT>-oxime <XREF TYPE="COMPOUND" ID="chem3">3</XREF> was achieved, which was assigned unequivocally as the <IT>S</IT>-configured product by X-ray analysis (Fig. 1).<SUP TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn2" /> Interestingly, this is the opposite configuration of Chandrasekaran’s <IT>C</IT>-glycosylated amino acids,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF> which is important for future applications in glycobiology.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In conclusion, the reaction sequence, radical addition to glycals and subsequent reduction, allows the simple synthesis of various glycosylated glycine derivatives in good overall yields.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met15" novelty="New" advantage="None">The addition of nitroacetates to glycals was realized for the first time.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both steps proceed with moderate to high stereoselectivities, affording the <IT>S</IT>-configured amino acids as the main products.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">The herein described new protocol is characterized by commercially available precursors and only three reaction steps.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Studies of the scope and limitations of the reaction sequence and further applications for the synthesis of <IT>C</IT>-glycopeptides are in progress.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">This work was generously supported by the Fonds der Chemischen Industrie and the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft (Li 556/7-2).</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
