<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b410922h" hasDoc="yes" version="1184" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="None" advantage="Yes">Oxidation pathways of adenine and guanine in aqueous solution from first principles electrochemistry</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The 8-oxo-7,8-dehydropurine tautomers (8-oxoA and 8-oxoG) are mutagenic lesions found in DNA.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Two experimental pathways have been proposed for the formation of 8-oxoG: one initiated by deprotonation of the OH˙ radical adduct at the 8-position of guanine (G8OH˙) and the other initiated by a proton-coupled one-electron oxidation of G8OH˙.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">We here report standard Gibbs energies of the above processes involving proton transfer (PT), electron transfer (ET), and proton-coupled electron transfer (PT–ET) reactions calculated from first principles using DFT (B3LYP) and a continuum solvent model (IEF-PCM).</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The computed data show that the former pathway is unlikely to occur for A8OH˙ and G8OH˙ in neutral aqueous solution, because of the very low acidity of the hydrogen at the 8-position.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast, the latter route involving proton-coupled one-electron oxidations of A8OH˙ and G8OH˙ are exergonic by about 25 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> in aqueous solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Energetically, adenine and guanine behave similarly toward oxidation to yield 8-oxoA and 8-oxoG.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the calculated standard Gibbs energetics confirms that the ease of ionization of the native and oxidized forms of nucleobases B to yield the radical cations B˙<SP>+</SP> or their deprotonation products B(–H)˙ is 8-oxoG &gt; G &gt; 8-oxoA &gt; A &gt; C &gt; T in aqueous solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Consequently, 8-oxoG will most readily trap radical cations and neutral radicals in DNA, since it can reduce any nucleobase radical cation B˙<SP>+</SP> (<IT>via</IT> ET) or its deprotonation product B(–H)˙ (<IT>via</IT> PT–ET) back to the native form of the nucleobase.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="1.">Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hydroxyl radicals are formed in the normal oxygen metabolism and as a result of the radiolysis of water when living cells are exposed to ionizing radiation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">About half of the DNA damage caused by OH radicals occurs on nucleobases, where these add to the double bonds of purine bases to yield C4, C5, and C8 radical adducts in adenine (A4OH˙, A5OH˙, and A8OH˙) and guanine (G4OH˙, G5OH˙, and G8OH˙).</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Under oxidative conditions, the C8 radical adducts will react further to yield the 8-hydroxypurine derivatives (8-OHA and 8-OHG) and their 8-oxo-7,8-dehydropurine tautomers (8-oxoA and 8-oxoG).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2 cit3">1–3</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Addition of water to G˙<SP>+</SP> is an alternative and feasible pathway to yield 8-oxoG.</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">This reaction seems to be important in DNA, but experimental evidence suggests that it does not occur in solutions of nucleotides.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">8-oxoA and 8-oxoG are the major stable purine products produced by oxidation and radiolysis.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6 cit7 cit8">5–8</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Even though A and G basically form the same kind of radiation-induced derivatives, 8-oxoA is only formed in about one third the amount of 8-oxoG during aerobic radiation of both naked DNA and chromatin.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The 8-oxopurine derivatives are highly mutagenic lesions, as mispairing of 8-hydroxyguanine and 8-oxoguanine with adenine brings about G:C to T:A transversions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9 cit10 cit11">9–11</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Two pathways for oxidation have been proposed (Fig. 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The first pathway (Fig. 1, PT branch) is initiated by deprotonation of the 8-hydroxypurine radical at C8 followed by subsequent electron loss and tautomerization,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF> whereas the other (Fig. 1, PT–ET branch) is initiated by a proton-coupled one-electron oxidation of the 8-hydroxypurine radical (A8OH˙ and G8OH˙) to yield the 8-hydroxypurine derivative (8-OHA and 8-OHG) followed by tautomerizarion.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit13 cit14">4,13,14</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Based on EPR measurements at 77 K, the PT-initiated pathway has been proposed to occur by photoionization (at 248 nm) of frozen aqueous solutions of DNA.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The experiment showed selectivity for guanine, but was unable to detect the initial radical adduct G8OH˙.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The PT–ET-initiated pathway has been suggested to take place during pulse radiolysis experiments in aqueous solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">From these experiments the exact route for the formal loss of a hydrogen atom from B8OH˙ is however unclear, <IT>i.e.</IT>, whether it takes place by way of an intermediate radical anion (8-OHA˙<SP>−</SP> and 8-OHG˙<SP>−</SP>) or a neutral (8-OHA and 8-OHG) precursor.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The 8-oxopurine derivatives (8-oxoA and 8-oxoG) can be subjected to further oxidation (Fig. 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, whereas 8-OHG and 8-oxoG may undergo one-electron oxidation, tautomerization, and deprotonation, depending on the reaction conditions,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF> 8-oxoA is not as easily oxidized, as seen from the standard reduction potentials of 0.94 and 0.60 V, respectively.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3 cit16">3,16</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is claimed that 8-oxoG has a lower ionization potential than any of the nucleobases in their native state<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17 cit18">17,18</REF> and that it does not distort the structure of the duplex DNA;<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19 cit20">19,20</REF> as a result, it serves as a deep trap for a migrating electron hole.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21 cit22">21,22</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Owing to the current experimental uncertainties on the oxidation pathways of purine nucleobases, a theoretical approach may be useful in order to get insight into the redox processes for both A and G in solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">A redox reaction can be studied theoretically using two different schemes: explicitly modelling the electron transfer reaction between oxidant and reductant, or by modelling the half-reactions independently.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The first method is convenient when examining the mechanistic details of specific redox reactions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, in cases in which the general redox features of a species are inferred from the behaviour toward different agents, it is more appropriate to draw conclusions from a half-reaction model.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">In particular, the above-mentioned proposals for oxidation pathways of purine nucleobases are based on studies of reactions with different oxidants and experimental techniques that enable conclusions regarding the possible species acting as intermediates and products, as well as common features of the electron transfer processes.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">We have previously introduced and applied a first principles scheme to compute Gibbs energies of reactions in which electrons and protons participate as independent ions in solution from absolute electrochemical potentials evaluated at given temperature and pressure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In doing so, the Gibbs energies of reaction can be directly compared with the experimentally derived values.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23 cit24">23,24</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="None" advantage="Yes">The approach has proved very useful for calculating standard Gibbs energies of PT, ET, and PT–ET reactions in aqueous solution involving e−(SHE), e−(aq), H+(aq), H˙(aq).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None">This work aims at applying DFT and continuum solvation models to determine the feasibility of oxidation of the 8-hydroxypurine radicals (A8OH˙ and G8OH˙) to yield the 8-oxopurine derivatives (8-oxoA and 8-oxoG) in aqueous solution by the two experimentally proposed pathways.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="New" advantage="None">Further oxidation of the 8-oxopurine derivatives is examined in order to test their ability to trap electron holes in DNA.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj5" novelty="New" advantage="None">A comparative analysis of the oxidation pathways for purine, adenine, and guanine is presented to explain the differences that render guanine more sensitive than adenine to oxidative damage.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj6" novelty="New" advantage="None">First-principles standard Gibbs energies of electron transfer (ET), proton transfer (PT), and proton-coupled electron transfer (PT–ET) reactions involved in the oxidation pathways are reported.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.">Methods</HEADER><P><s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fully optimized geometries, harmonic vibrational frequencies, and zero-point energies of purine (Pu), adenine (A), and guanine (G) and their oxidation derivatives (Fig. 1) were computed with the B3LYP hybrid functional<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25">25</REF> and the 6-31 G(d,p) basis set.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to obtain correct geometries in the optimizations of the anions,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26 cit27 cit28">26–28</REF><IT>i.e.</IT>, puckered instead of planar anions,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24 cit28">24,28</REF> diffuse functions were added on the heavy atoms through the use of the 6-31+G(d,p) basis set.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, for the non-anionic structures no diffuse functions were included as the changes in geometries in this case are insignificant in terms of the effect on total energies and vibrational frequencies, as already noted for other compounds.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29">29</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Single point energies for all structures were obtained at the B3LYP/6-311+G(2df,p) level in the gas phase and in aqueous solution by including the polarizable continuum model (PCM)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30">30</REF> in the integral equation formalism (IEF).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit31">31</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The inclusion of diffuse functions in the calculation of Gibbs energies of solvation is a debatable point, since it is claimed that they give too low solvation energies.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit32 cit33">32,33</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, these effects are smaller than the overall accuracy of our estimates, and hence, exclusion of diffuse functions will not change the qualitative results.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have thus for consistency chosen to retain the diffuse functions in the data reported throughout the study.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">All calculations were performed with the Gaussian 94 and Gaussian 98 programs.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit34 cit35">34,35</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Gibbs energies of activation for tautomerization were calculated including a water molecule to assist the proton transfer toward ketonization.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">This catalyzing water reduced the Gibbs energies of activation by about 30 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>, without any drastic changes in the overall thermodynamics of the reactions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have therefore included the corrected water-catalyzed Gibbs energies of activation for ketonization to the Gibbs energy diagrams of oxidation of Pu, A, and G.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">According to our first principles approach to electrochemistry and ion thermochemistry,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF> the absolute standard chemical potential of species B in an ideal-dilute solution <IT>μ</IT><SP>,aq</SP>(B) is split up into the absolute standard chemical potential in the gas phase <IT>μ</IT><SP>,g</SP>(B) plus the bulk Gibbs energy of solvation Δ<SB>s</SB><IT>G</IT><SP></SP>(B):<IT>μ</IT><SP>,g</SP>(B) = <IT>μ</IT><SP>,g</SP>(B) + Δ<SB>s</SB><IT>G</IT><SP></SP>(B).</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The absolute standard chemical potential in the ideal gas phase is estimated according to quantum and statistical mechanics as the molar contribution of the translational, rotational, vibrational, electronic, and zero-point vibrational energy of a molecular species B, plus the thermal contributions of bringing the molecules together in the ideal gas phase at given temperature and pressure.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Gibbs energies of proton, electron, and proton-coupled electron transfer reactions can then be written in terms of absolute standard chemical potentials at a given temperature and pressure:</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">(i) For PT: HX<SB>(aq)</SB> = X−(aq) + H+(aq)2.303<IT>RT</IT> × p<IT>K</IT><SB>a</SB> = Δ<SB>PT</SB><IT>G</IT>0<IT>T</IT> = <IT>μ</IT>0,aq<IT>T</IT>(X<SP>−</SP>) + <IT>μ</IT>0,aq<IT>T</IT>(H<SP>+</SP>) − <IT>μ</IT>0,aq<IT>T</IT>(HX)</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">(ii) For ET: Ox<SB>(aq)</SB> + e−(<IT>β</IT>) = Red<SB>(aq)</SB>, where e−(<IT>β</IT>) = e−(vac), e−(SHE), e−(aq)Δ<SB>ET</SB><IT>G</IT><SP></SP> = <IT>μ</IT><SP>,aq</SP>(Red) − <IT>μ</IT><SP>,aq</SP>(Ox) − <IT>μ</IT><SP><IT>β</IT></SP>(e<SP>−</SP>)</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">(iii) For PT–ET: Ox<SB>(aq)</SB> + H+(aq) e−(<IT>β</IT>) = Red<SB>(aq)</SB>, where e−(<IT>β</IT>) = e−(vac), e−(SHE), e−(aq)Δ<SB>PT–ET</SB><IT>G</IT><SP></SP> = <IT>μ</IT><SP>,aq</SP>(Red) − <IT>μ</IT><SP>,aq</SP>(Ox) − <IT>μ</IT><SP>,aq</SP>(H<SP>+</SP>) − <IT>μ</IT><SP><IT>β</IT></SP>(e<SP>−</SP>)In the case of ET and PT–ET reactions, the constant <IT>μ</IT><SP><IT>β</IT></SP>(e<SP>−</SP>) defines the Gibbs energy level of a conventional reference state for electrons.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Electrons in a vacuum at infinity e−(vac) form a reference state with <IT>μ</IT><SP><IT>β</IT></SP>(e<SP>−</SP>) = <IT>μ</IT>vac0K(e<SP>−</SP>) = 0.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is thereby possible to define a reduced absolute electrode potential, <IT>E</IT>abs,r (Ox/Red).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23 cit36 cit37">23,36,37</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Electrons in a single reference electrode, <IT>e.g.</IT>, the standard hydrogen electrode SHE with e−(SHE), form a reference state with <IT>μ</IT><SP><IT>β</IT></SP>(e<SP>−</SP>) = <IT>μ</IT><SP>,SHE</SP>(e<SP>−</SP>), such that the standard electrode potential can be defined in the hydrogen scale, <IT>E</IT>SHE(Ox/Red), for cells without liquid junctions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Using Fermi–Dirac and Boltzmann statistics, experimental solvation data, and the absolute potential of the SHE, we have estimated internally consistent values for <IT>μ</IT><SP>,SHE</SP>(e<SP>−</SP>) and <IT>μ</IT><SP>,aq</SP>(H<SP>+</SP>), which are listed in Table .1<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Moreover, in order for the Gibbs energies of reaction to agree with the bond dissociation energy scale, we correct <IT>μ</IT><SP>,aq</SP>(H<SP>+</SP>) with the difference in ZPE’s of the reduced and oxidized forms for PT–ET or, in the case of PT reactions, of the conjugate base and the acid.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Gibbs energy diagrams given below contain the standard Gibbs energy of each species relative to that of the purine nucleobase and the hydroxyl radical.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In order for the Gibbs energetics to reflect that the number of particles is conserved along the reaction profile, <IT>μ</IT><SP>,SHE</SP>(e<SP>−</SP>) and <IT>μ</IT><SP>,aq</SP>(H<SP>+</SP>) are added cumulatively to the relative standard Gibbs energy of each species.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The standard Gibbs energy change associated with a given step is calculated as the difference between the listed values for the species in question.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.">Results and discussion</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.1.">Tautomerism in the 8-oxopurine derivatives</HEADER><P><s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The neutral 8-oxo-7,8-dehydropurine derivatives, 8-oxoB (B = Pu, A, G), as well as their radical cations and anions can occur in the oxidation pathways.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Albeit the derivatives have been reported to occur primarily in their keto forms, the oxidation seems to go by way of the minor enol forms in aqueous solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The standard Gibbs energy profiles of ketonization of 8-hydroxypurine (8-OHPu) and the radical ions (Figs. 2 and 3) show that the catalytic effect of water significantly lowers the activation Gibbs energy to less than 10 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> in aqueous solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The activation Gibbs energy for the water-catalyzed ketonization of neutral 8-OHPu is 1.8 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> higher than that of the radical anion and 2.2 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> lower than that of the radical cation.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">It should be noted that the explicit inclusion of a single water molecule in the model allows us to retrieve the main catalytic contribution of water to the activation Gibbs energy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is well known that water molecules from the first and second solvation sheaths reorganize so that their dipole moment distribution assists the proton transfer by electrostatic stabilization of the transition state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hence, a further lowering of the activation energy can be expected.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="No">A priori, the number of water molecules in the first, second, and third solvation shells needed to reproduce the experimental Gibbs energetics is uncertain if we use a cluster model.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The reorganization of water dipoles in the solvation shells brings about both electrostatic and entropic stabilization.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="No">The assessment of enthalpies, entropies, and Gibbs energies can be very inaccurate when using a cluster model, owing to problems in convergence of these quantities with increasing cluster size.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">However, the average electrostatic contribution can be assessed with a continuum solvent model approach, even though it cannot reproduce the local microscopic rearrangements of water molecules, which create the local electrostatic inhomogeneity that is averaged out in the macroscopic dielectric constant of the solvent.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In short, we take into account two main solvent effects, <IT>i.e.</IT>, the catalytic role of a single water molecule in the tautomerization mechanism and the average electrostatic stabilization described by a self-consistent reaction field model.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">We thus neglect the local electrostatic inhomogeneity created by the water dipoles around the tautomerization center.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The structures of the neutral 8-hydroxy- and 8-oxopurine derivatives and their radical cations are planar at the B3LYP/6-31G(d,p) level as well as 8-oxoPu˙<SP>−</SP> at the B3LYP/6-31+G(d,p) level (Fig. 3).</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, 8-OHPu˙<SP>−</SP> is puckered with the OH group in an equatorial position.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">A difference of only 0.6 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> is observed in the standard Gibbs energies of ketonization of 8-OHPu when including a water molecule or not (Fig. 2).</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of 8-OHPu˙<SP>−</SP>, however, the inclusion of a water molecule in the model lowers the standard Gibbs energy of ketonization by 4 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> because the complex reduces the ring puckering and the destabilizing strain seems larger than the explicit hydrogen-bonding stabilization in this radical anion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of 8-OHPu˙<SP>+</SP>, the standard Gibbs energy of ketonization is about 10 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> less exergonic with the inclusion of the explicit water molecule, owing to an unfavourable hydrogen-bonding pattern in the complex with the radical cation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The water molecule forms only one strong hydrogen bond with either radical cation tautomer as the bond distances shown in Fig. 3</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.2.">PT-initiated oxidation pathway in the 8-hydroxypurine radicals</HEADER><P><s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The 8-deprotonation of the C8 radical adducts B8OH˙ (Fig. 1, left branch) is endergonic by more than 25 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> in aqueous solution (Fig. 4).</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This standard Gibbs energy of deprotonation suggests that a very strong base is needed to remove the proton from the 8-position in aqueous solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The 8-deprotonation of the C8 radical adducts is therefore very unlikely in neutral or acidic medium, and in turn, the PT-initiated oxidation seem thermodynamically unfavourable.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Moreover, the standard Gibbs energies of deprotonation increase in the order Pu8OH˙ &lt; A8OH˙ &lt; G8OH˙.</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">In particular, the 8-deprotonation of G8OH˙ is far more disfavoured than that of A8OH˙.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">The radical anions, 8-OHB˙<SP>−</SP>, may follow two pathways to give the major 8-oxo-7,8-dehydropurine tautomers, 8-oxoB (Fig. 4).</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the difference in the barriers of ketonization in the radical anions (5.2 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>) and in the neutral enol forms (7.0 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>) is small, the thermodynamic effect owing to the electron loss could determine the preference for a particular pathway.</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">Inspection of the standard Gibbs energies of one-electron oxidation of the enol and keto forms indicates that, whereas the one-electron oxidation of 8-OHPu˙<SP>−</SP> and 8-OHG˙<SP>−</SP> (−55.6 and −72.5 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>, respectively) is favoured over that of 8-oxoPu˙<SP>−</SP> and 8-oxoG˙<SP>−</SP> (−47.3 and −64.6 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>, respectively) by about 8 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>, the one-electron oxidation of 8-oxoA˙<SP>−</SP> (−65.1 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>) is 3 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> more favoured than that of 8-OHA˙<SP>−</SP> (−62.1 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">As a result, it is likely that for G, one-electron oxidation of 8-OHG˙<SP>−</SP> is followed by subsequent tautomerization to yield 8-oxoG; whereas for A, one-electron oxidation and tautomerization could compete.</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Clearly, though, the oxidation reactions are thermodynamically favoured for all systems discussed above.</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The calculated standard Gibbs energies of reduction of the 8-hydroxypurine derivatives 8-OHB and their major 8-oxo-7,8-dehydropurine tautomers 8-oxoB (more than <IT>ca.</IT> 45 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> endergonic) suggest that the respective anions are powerful reductants.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.3.">PT–ET-initiated oxidation pathway in the 8-hydroxypurine radicals</HEADER><P><s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">The 8-proton-coupled one-electron oxidation of the C8 radical adducts B8OH˙ (Fig. 1, right branch) is exergonic by about 25 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> in aqueous solution–Fig. 5, Δ<IT>G</IT><SP></SP> (8-OHB) − Δ<IT>G</IT><SP></SP>(B8OH˙).</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Accordingly, a moderate to strong oxidant may be able to yield the 8-hydroxypurine derivatives, 8-OHB.</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">The standard Gibbs energy of PT–ET becomes less negative in the order Pu8OH˙ &gt; A8OH˙ &gt; G8OH˙ (−27.9, −26.8, and −25.1 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>, respectively).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">An alternative stepwise oxidation of the C8 radical adducts B8OH˙ will be driven by a strongly exergonic deprotonation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">The one-electron oxidation of the C8 radical adduct to yield the cation B8OH<SP>+</SP> is endergonic and the ease of oxidation increases in the series Pu8OH˙ &lt; A8OH˙ &lt; G8OH˙, according to the standard Gibbs energies of one-electron oxidation of the C8 radical adducts (29.2, 11.2, and 0.2 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>, respectively).</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">The subsequent deprotonation of the C8 cation adducts B8OH<SP>+</SP> is very favoured but decreases in the order Pu8OH<SP>+</SP> &gt; A8OH<SP>+</SP> &gt; G8OH<SP>+</SP> when comparing the standard Gibbs energies of deprotonation (−57.1, −38.0, and −25.3 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>, respectively).</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In short, the increasing reducing character of the C8 radical adducts B8OH˙ offsets the decreasing deprotonation tendency of the C8 cation adducts B8OH<SP>+</SP> to give 8-OHB.</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The explicit route (reduction followed by deprotonation <IT>vs.</IT> proton coupled one-electron oxidation of B8OH˙) will depend on the physiological conditions such as pH.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" advantage="None">Once 8-OHB is formed, the small barrier to ketonization (7.0 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>, Fig. 2) and the standard Gibbs energies of ketonization (−11.2, −10.0, and −12.3 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> for Pu, A, and G, respectively) readily enable a shift of the equilibrium toward the major 8-oxoB product.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.4.">Oxidation of the 8-oxopurine derivatives</HEADER><P><s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None">Unlike the radical anions 8-OHB˙<SP>−</SP> and 8-oxoB˙<SP>−</SP> (Fig. 4), the neutral keto form 8-oxoB is as easily oxidized as the neutral enol form 8-OHB (Fig. 5).</annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None">In both cases, the standard Gibbs energies of oxidation for the enol and keto forms are very close: 46.0 and 46.2 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> for Pu, 31.2 and 30.4 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> for A, and 20.1 and 21.5 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> for G, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None">For both pathways oxidation is hence endergonic and the standard Gibbs energy changes decrease in the order Pu &gt; A &gt; G. Of particular interest is that 8-oxoG is about 10 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> more easily oxidized than 8-oxoA.</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Consequently, the Gibbs energies indicate that the major 8-oxoB product can be converted into 8-oxoB˙<SP>+</SP> by reaction with a suitable oxidant.</annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The energetics also suggest that in the presence of the appropriate oxidant, the enol form 8-OHB could either be oxidized once formed or go through the keto form 8-oxoB (activation barrier 7 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>; Fig. 2), if required by the oxidation mechanism.</annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, in absence of appropriate oxidants, the equilibrium would shift toward the major keto form 8-oxoB.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res29" novelty="None" advantage="None">The calculated standard Gibbs energies of oxidation of the 8-hydroxypurine derivatives 8-OHB and their major 8-oxo-7,8-dehydropurine tautomers 8-oxoB (more than <IT>ca.</IT> 20 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> endergonic) indicate that the respective radical cations are good oxidants.</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res30" novelty="None" advantage="None">Their experimental counterparts amount to 21.7 and 13.8 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> for adenine and guanine derivatives at pH 8, respectively.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" advantage="None">It should be remarked that the calculated standard Gibbs energy of reduction for the 8-oxoG˙<SP>+</SP>/8-oxoG couple (−21.4 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>) is slightly less exergonic than that of the parent nucleobase couple G˙<SP>+</SP>/G (−25.8 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The pH-dependent absorption spectra of the one-electron oxidized 8-hydroxy-2’deoxyguanosine (8-OHdG) yields a p<IT>K</IT><SB>a</SB> of 6.6 for 8-oxodG˙<SP>+</SP>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res32" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our calculations show that the 8-oxopurine-derived radical cations 8-oxoB˙<SP>+</SP> are acidic.</annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res33" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ease of 7-deprotonation of 8-oxoB˙<SP>+</SP> into 8-oxoB(-H7)˙ is 8-oxoPu˙<SP>+</SP> &gt; 8-oxoA˙<SP>+</SP> &gt; 8-oxoG˙<SP>+</SP>, since the standard Gibbs energies of deprotonation are −15.9, −10.8, and −5.1 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res34" novelty="None" advantage="None">Accordingly, 8-oxoG˙<SP>+</SP> is a more stable radical cation than 8-oxoA˙<SP>+</SP>, inasmuch as the latter shows a greater tendency to yield 8-oxoA(–H7)˙.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res35" novelty="None" advantage="None">The same experimental data<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF> for 8-OHdG suggest that the 1-deprotonation of 8-oxoG˙<SP>+</SP> to yield 8-oxoG(–H1)˙ is as likely to occur as the 7-deprotonation to yield 8-oxoG(–H7)˙ (Fig. 6).</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res36" novelty="None" advantage="None">The computed standard Gibbs energy change favours 8-oxoG(–H7)˙ over 8-oxoG(–H1)˙ by only 3.6 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res37" novelty="None" advantage="None">Subsequent deprotonation of 8-oxoG(–H7)˙ or 8-oxoG(–H1)˙ corresponds to a experimental standard Gibbs energy change of 16.8 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF> and yields the radical anion 8-oxoG(–H1, –H7)˙<SP>−</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res38" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our calculated standard Gibbs energies of deprotonation of 8-oxoG(–H7)˙ and 8-oxoG(–H1)˙ are halfway and amount 8.3 and 4.7 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>, respectively.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res39" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both the proton-coupled one-electron oxidation of the 8-oxo-7, 8-dehydropurine tautomers (8-oxoA and 8-oxoG) and the deprotonation of their radical cations (8-oxoA˙<SP>+</SP> and 8-oxoG˙<SP>+</SP>) yield dehydrogenated nucleobase radicals (8-oxoA(–H7)˙, 8-oxoG(–H7)˙, 8-oxoG(–H1)˙) in neutral aqueous solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res40" novelty="None" advantage="None">The calculated standard Gibbs energy of reduction of 8-oxoG(–H7)˙ to 8-oxoG in aqueous solution (–16.4 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>) agrees very well with the experimental one (−17.0 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res41" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hence, also in the case of the dehydrogenated radicals (B˙<SP>+</SP> = B(−H)˙ + H<SP>+</SP>) the calculated standard Gibbs energy of reduction of the 8-oxoG(–H7)˙/8-oxoG couple is lower than that of the G(–H1)˙/G couple (−25.6 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res42" novelty="None" advantage="None">The calculated standard Gibbs energy of reduction of the 8-oxoA(–H7)˙/8-oxoA couple (−19.6 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>) is greater than that of the 8-oxoG(–H7)˙/8-oxoG couple but 8-oxoA could still reduce G(–H1)˙.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res43" novelty="None" advantage="None">As also noted for the nucleobase radical cations (A˙<SP>+</SP>, G˙<SP>+</SP>, T˙<SP>+</SP>, C˙<SP>+</SP>),<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF> the counterparts of the 8-oxo-7, 8-dehydropurine tautomers, 8-oxoB˙<SP>+</SP>, seem to be strong acids, according to the standard Gibbs energy of deprotonation for the equilibria 8-oxoB˙+(aq) = 8-oxoB(−H)˙(aq) + H+(aq).</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res44" novelty="None" advantage="None">In particular, 8-oxoA˙<SP>+</SP> (Δ<SB>PT</SB><IT>G</IT><SP></SP> = −10.7 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>) is more acidic than 8-oxoG˙<SP>+</SP> (Δ<SB>PT</SB><IT>G</IT><SP></SP> = −5.1 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>, compared to the experimental value<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF> of 9.0 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>) when yielding 8-oxoB(–H7)˙, but the H7 proton of 8-oxoG˙<SP>+</SP> is more acidic than the H1 proton (Δ<SB>PT</SB><IT>G</IT><SP></SP> = −5.1 <IT>vs.</IT> −1.5 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res45" novelty="None" advantage="None">Further deprotonation (Fig. 6) is thus more likely to occur on 8-oxoG(–H1)˙ than on 8-oxoG(–H7)˙, due to the larger Δ<SB>PT</SB><IT>G</IT><SP></SP> when forming 8-oxoG(–H1, –H7)˙<SP>−</SP>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res46" novelty="None" advantage="None">It should be noted that the IEF-PCM/B3LYP/6-311+G(2df,p)//B3LYP/6-31G(d,p) standard Gibbs energies of deprotonation are more exergonic than the few experimental values available.</annotationART></s> <s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The main source of error in the calculations comes from the insufficient solvation energies obtained by IEF-PCM on these radicals, and further studies on this aspect are thus needed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Nonetheless, the qualitative results provide the correct trends.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.">Conclusions</HEADER><P><s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The 8-oxo-7,8-dehydropurine tautomers are highly mutagenic lesions in DNA.</annotationART></s> <s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have in the present work applied a first principles electrochemical approach to explore mechanisms for their formation and explain the observed preference for 8-oxoG over 8-oxoA.</annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The PT-initiated oxidation pathway of the 8-hydroxypurine radicals (A8OH˙ and G8OH˙) followed by electron loss<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF> seems to be very unlikely in aqueous solution because of the very low acidity of the hydrogen at the 8-position.</annotationART></s> <s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Instead, the PT–ET-initiated oxidation pathway<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit13 cit14">4,13,14</REF> of A8OH˙ and G8OH˙ seems to be the favoured route in aqueous solution.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res47" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of the PT–ET-initiated oxidation, G8OH˙ is only slightly more sensitive than A8OH˙ to proton-coupled one-electron oxidation followed by tautomerization to yield 8-oxoG and 8-oxoA.</annotationART></s> <s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res48" novelty="None" advantage="None">Likewise, 8-oxoG and 8-oxoA behave similarly toward one-electron oxidation to yield the radical cations 8-oxoG˙<SP>+</SP> and 8-oxoA˙<SP>+</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The difference in reactivity does not appear to be related to the 8-hydroxylation step either, since the barriers of adenine and guanine are close to the diffusion-controlled limit and both reactions are exergonic by about 15 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the proton-coupled one-electron oxidation of 8-oxoG is preferred over that of 8-oxoA by about 5 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>, and hence, a higher yield of 8-oxoG(–H7)˙ should be expected over 8-oxoA(–H7)˙ in DNA.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res49" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our calculations furthermore show that the ease of ionization of nucleobases in their native<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF> and oxidized forms to yield B˙<SP>+</SP> (<IT>via</IT> ET) or B(–H)˙ (<IT>via</IT> PT–ET) is 8-oxoG &gt; G &gt; 8-oxoA &gt; A &gt; C &gt; T in aqueous solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res50" novelty="None" advantage="None">Accordingly, 8-oxoG can reduce any nucleobase radical cation B˙<SP>+</SP> (<IT>via</IT> ET) or their deprotonation products B(–H)˙ (<IT>via</IT> PT–ET) to the nucleobase native forms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res51" novelty="None" advantage="None">The smallest driving force thus corresponds to the repair of lesions in G (G˙<SP>+</SP> or G(–H1)˙):</annotationART></s><P><s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res51" novelty="None" advantage="None">ET:</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res51" novelty="None" advantage="None">G˙+(aq) + 8-oxoG<SB>(aq)</SB> = G<SB>(aq)</SB> + 8-oxoG˙+(aq)</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="143"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res51" novelty="None" advantage="None">Δ<SB>r</SB><IT>G</IT>0298K = −4.4 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="144"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res51" novelty="None" advantage="None">PT–ET:</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="145"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res51" novelty="None" advantage="None">G(−H1)˙(aq) + 8-oxoG<SB>(aq)</SB> = G<SB>(aq)</SB> + 8-oxoG(−H7)˙(aq)</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="146"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res51" novelty="None" advantage="None">Δ<SB>r</SB><IT>G</IT>0298K = −9.3 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> (exp1: −12.7 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>)</annotationART></s></P><s sid="147"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the driving force for the PT–ET repair is about twice as strong as that for the ET repair, the presence of 8-oxoG could also contribute to shift the equilibrium at neutral pH toward the deprotonation of the remaining G˙<SP>+</SP>, which behaves as a weak acid.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="148"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Likewise, 8-oxoG can reduce both 8-oxoA˙<SP>+</SP> (<IT>via</IT> ET) and 8-oxoA(–H7)˙ (<IT>via</IT> PT–ET).</annotationART></s> <s sid="149"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hence, albeit the conditions for damages to occur on A and G are essentially identical, 8-oxoG is more prone to reduce/repair damages on other sites (including G˙<SP>+</SP> and 8-oxoA) and to function as a sink for oxidative damage occurring in the base stack.</annotationART></s> <s sid="150"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, the detection of 8-oxo-7, 8-dehydropurine derived radicals would yield higher amounts of 8-oxoG than 8-oxoA.</annotationART></s> <s sid="151"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None">This provides an explanation as to why the observed ratio 8-oxoA:8-oxoG is 1:3 when both naked DNA and chromatin are irradiated, and could be a likely way in which 8-oxoG acts as a trap of radical cations and neutral radicals in DNA.</annotationART></s> <s sid="152"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con15" novelty="None" advantage="None">We emphasize, however, that experimental and computational studies on the addition of water to G˙<SP>+</SP> yielding 8-oxoG <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF> may provide additional insights into this problem.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
