<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b411798k" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Characterization of adsorbed xenon in Zeolite-A, X, and Y by high-pressure <SP>129</SP>Xe NMR spectroscopy</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The local structure of confined xenon in A-, X- and Y-type zeolites (molecular sieve 5A, 13X and zeolite NaY) was investigated by <IT>in situ</IT> high-pressure <SP>129</SP>Xe NMR spectroscopy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Xenon confined in dehydrated samples gives a resonance peak in the chemical shift range from 50 to 100 ppm at 0.1 MPa, and the chemical shift values increase as pressure increases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The pressure dependence of <SP>129</SP>Xe chemical shift on xenon confined in the micropores can be approximately described by the Langmuir adsorption model, resulting in the parameters being able to describe pore diameter, adsorption ability of the pore, and the local structure of the confined xenon atoms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">Using these parameters, the pore structure, the mobility and the cluster size of xenon in the micropore are discussed for A- and X-type zeolites.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None">Furthermore, the effect of pre-adsorbed water and the binder for pellet preparation on the pore structure is also examined.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the Y-zeolite, a chemical exchange of xenon between the outside and inside of the micropores was observed above 0.75 MPa.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Spectral simulation assuming a simple two-site exchange model revealed the exchange rate constant and the population ratio of xenon in the exchange between the outside and the inside the micropores.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The exchange of xenon is optimum around the supercritical point of the bulk xenon (∼6 MPa), and decreases above 6 MPa, and this originates from the cooperative phenomenon in the supercritical fluid.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="1.">Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Zeolites are crystalline porous aluminosilicates including alkali and/or alkaline earth metals, with the chemical composition of M<SB><IT>x</IT>/<IT>n</IT></SB>·[(AlO<SB>2</SB>)<SB><IT>x</IT></SB>(SiO<SB>2</SB>)<SB><IT>y</IT></SB>]·<IT>w</IT>H<SB>2</SB>O. These compounds exhibit interesting properties such as molecular sieve ability and catalysis.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">These properties can be modified by chemical treatment such as ion exchange and/or de-alumination.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Many researchers have investigated these materials at the scientific and engineering points of view,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2 cit3 cit4">2–4</REF> and it has been found that the adsorption behavior, reactivity, and molecular sieve ability of zeolites are closely related to the framework, porous structure, and intermolecular interactions between the pore wall and the adsorbed molecule, as well as between the adsorbed molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, adsorbed water present in the micropores and the formation of macro- and mesopores due to the aggregation of fine particles of zeolites, will also affect the adsorption behavior of the zeolites.</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The adsorbed water decreases the volume of the micropore to less than 0.5 nm, which is a so-called “ultra-micropore”, and screens the guest molecules from the pore wall, affecting the functional properties of zeolites such as catalysis, the molecular sieve and reactivity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, the adsorbent products consist of fine particles of synthetic zeolite with a μm diameter order, which are bound by binder agents such as clay, phosphates, and glass with a low melting point to prepare the pellets and/or beads for easy handling.</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The addition of binder agents to form pellets leads to extra pores of 1–50 nm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">These meso- and macropores increases in the amount of adsorbate at the large value of the relative pressure and play an important role in the process of the diffusion of the adsorbates such as molecular diffusion and Knudsen diffusion.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit65">65</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None"><SP>129</SP>Xe NMR is an important tool in the study of ultra-micro, micro-, meso-, and macropores.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Xenon-129 NMR spectroscopy has been developed to study the structure and topology of internal voids, adsorption sites, and intermolecular interactions in porous materials, since the potential of xenon-129 as a probe for the inner space of materials was proposed by Ito and Frassard<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF> in 1980.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Recently, this smart methodology has been widely used in the characterization of porous materials as a modern and sophisticated technique of porosimetry,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6 cit7 cit8 cit9">5–9</REF> and the local structure of materials such as zeolites,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit10 cit11 cit12 cit13 cit14 cit15">5,10–15</REF> glass,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF> fullerenes,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF> carbon nanotubes,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF> polymers,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19 cit20 cit21 cit22">19–22</REF> and clathrate compounds,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23 cit24 cit25 cit26">23–26</REF> liquid crystals,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27 cit28 cit29">27–29</REF> some organic solvents,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9 cit30">9,30</REF> and proteins in solution<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30 cit31 cit32">30–32</REF> have been investigated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In the past decade, hyperpolarized (HP) xenon NMR techniques have been developed to enhance the sensitivity of <SP>129</SP>Xe NMR.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit33 cit34">33,34</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="No">However, to obtain information from ultramicro- and/or meso- and macropores using xenon as a probe, it is necessary to confine xenon in ultra-micropores of the same size as xenon, and/or to slow down the exchange between xenon adsorbed in meso- and macropores and the bulk.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="No">It is difficult to achieve this situation under ambient conditions, and high-pressure conditions offer a solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">We recently described a conventional and newly designed <IT>in situ</IT> variable pressure NMR probe, allowing studies with pressures up to 20 MPa,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF> and it has been applied in the study of xenon–wall interactions in the free volume of polymers,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit35">35</REF> the intermolecular interaction of xenon confined in 1D-nanochannels,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit36 cit37">36,37</REF> and the supercritical phenomenon of xenon in mesoporous silica.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit38">38</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Furthermore, Brunner <IT>et al</IT>. have reported the pressure dependence of <SP>129</SP>Xe chemical shift in the supercritical state up to a pressure of about 70 MPa using a high-pressure cell made from a sapphire tube.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit39">39</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">This high pressure condition is expected to offer new insights into xenon–wall and xenon–xenon interactions for xenon confined in nanospaces, as well as the dynamic behavior of xenon in nanospaces.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">In this study, we applied the high-pressure <SP>129</SP>Xe NMR technique to some typical zeolites: molecular sieve 5A, 13X, and zeolite NaY.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Molecular sieve 5A has a type-A framework (LTA) with the chemical composition of (Ca<SB>4.8</SB>, Na<SB>2.4</SB>)[(AlO<SB>2</SB>)<SB>12</SB>(SiO<SB>2</SB>)<SB>12</SB>] ·<IT>w</IT>H<SB>2</SB>O, with the unit cell having a lattice symmetry of <IT>Pm</IT>3<IT>m</IT>, a lattice constant of <IT>a</IT><SB>0</SB> = 1.24 ± 0.001 nm, and a maximum diameter of 1.14 nm for the super cage which is linked each other by the window with a diameter of about 0.5 nm.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit40 cit41 cit42">40–42</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast, molecular sieve 13X and zeolite NaY have a faujasite X- and Y- type framework (FAU) with the chemical composition of Na<SB><IT>x</IT></SB>[(AlO<SB>2</SB>)<SB><IT>x</IT></SB>(SiO<SB>2</SB>)<SB>192-<IT>x</IT></SB>]·<IT>w</IT>H<SB>2</SB>O, respectively, with the unit cell having a lattice symmetry of <IT>Fd</IT>3<IT>m</IT>, a lattice constant of <IT>a</IT><SB>0</SB> = 2.49 ± 0.01 nm and a maximum diameter of 1.37 nm for the super cage which is linked each other by the window with a diameter of 0.74 nm.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit42 cit43">42,43</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">We have investigated the adsorption behavior of xenon on these zeolites using high-pressure <SP>129</SP>Xe NMR spectroscopy to clarify the influence of the framework, the adsorbed water and the binder agents on the adsorption behavior of xenon under high-pressure conditions.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.">Experimental</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Chemicals</HEADER><P><s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Powdered samples of molecular sieve 5A, 13X, and zeolites NaY were purchased from Aldrich Co. Ltd. Pellets of molecular sieves were purchased from Nakarai Co. Ltd. Sample dehydration was achieved by heating at 400 °C under reduced pressure (<IT>P</IT> &lt; 2 × 10<SP>−2</SP> Torr) for 3–24 h after roughly drying the specimens at ambient temperature under reduced pressure for 12 h.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">All the specimens were characterized by thermogravimetric analysis (TG), nitrogen adsorption isotherm, <SP>29</SP>Si MAS NMR spectrum, and powder X-ray diffraction (XRD) to confirm the amount of adsorbed water, the pore volume and the specific surfaces, and the ratio of SiO<SB>2</SB> to AlO<SB>2</SB> (Si/Al) in the framework.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Thermogravimetric analysis (TG)</HEADER><P><s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">TG analysis was carried out using SEIKO I SSC-5020M II TG/DTA 200-type thermal analysis equipment.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">TG diagrams were recorded at a heating rate of 10 K min<SP>−1</SP> up to 600 °C under nitrogen gas flow at a rate of 50 ml min<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">α-Alumina, α-Al<SB>2</SB>O<SB>3</SB>, was used as a reference sample.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>N<SB>2</SB> adsorption isotherm measurements</HEADER><P>Nitrogen adsorption isotherms were measured using Shimazu Gemini 2375 automatic specific surface measuring apparatus in the relative pressure range <IT>P</IT>/<IT>P</IT><SB>0</SB> from 0.001 to 0.95.</P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER><SP>29</SP>Si MAS NMR measurements</HEADER><P><SP>29</SP>Si magic-angle spinning (MAS) NMR spectra were measured using a Bruker DSX-200 spectrometer with a Larmor frequency of 39.7 MHz. <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Free-induction decay (FID) signals were recorded in a single pulse experiment using a pulse delay of 80 s, and π/2-pulse of 8 μs, under 4 kHz of MAS rate at room temperature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The chemical shift was referenced by tetramethylsilane (TMS) as an external standard.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Powder X-ray diffraction (XRD) measurements</HEADER><P><s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">XRD measurements were carried out using a Rigaku Rotaflex Rint 2000 diffractometer on HP 9000 S712/60 system from 3° to 60° in 2<IT>θ</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The scan rate was 1.00° min<SP>−1</SP>, and the increment step was 0.01°.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>High-pressure <SP>129</SP>Xe NMR measurements</HEADER><P><s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">High-pressure <SP>129</SP>Xe NMR measurements were carried out using a Bruker MSL-200 spectrometer with a Larmor frequency of 55.6 MHz, in which a home-built <IT>in situ</IT> pressure variable NMR probe<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF> was installed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The powdered or pellet samples were packed into a glass tube of 5 mm<IT>ϕ</IT>, with both ends capped with glass wool, and the tube and samples were placed in a pressure-resistant NMR cell made from ZrO<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The prepared NMR cell was then mounted onto the high-pressure NMR probe.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The FID signals were recorded in a single-pulse experiment with a pulse delay of 5 s, π/2-pulse of 3 μs and accumulation of 8-8192, depending on the signal-to-noise ratio, over a pressure range of 0.01 to 10 MPa at 298 K. <SP>129</SP>Xe chemical shift was referenced by a signal from xenon gas at zero density.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Temperature and pressure were controlled within the experimental error of ±0.5 K and 10% in MPa, respectively.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.">Results</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.1">Characterization of samples using TG, N<SB>2</SB> isotherm, and <SP>29</SP>Si MAS NMR</HEADER><P><s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thermogravimetric (TG) measurement of pre-heated samples up to 600 °C suggests that water adsorbed in the samples was removed by heating above 400 °C.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The amount of adsorbed water, defined by the ratio of the weight of water to the weight of the dehydrated zeolites, was determined from the weight loss as follows; 41% for molecular sieve 5A, 100% for molecular sieve 13X and 163% for Zeolite NaY.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">After dehydration of the samples by heating at 400 °C under reduced pressure, the N<SB>2</SB> adsorption isotherm was measured to characterize the amount of nitrogen at the maximum adsorption (<IT>W</IT><SB>sat</SB>), the specific surface area (<IT>S</IT><SB>total</SB>), the pore volume (<IT>V</IT><SB>pore</SB>), the external surface area (<IT>S</IT><SB>ex</SB>), and the internal specific surface area (<IT>S</IT><SB>in</SB>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">These samples give the typical I-type adsorption isotherm according to the IUPAC classification.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit44 cit45">44,45</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The pore volume, external and internal surface areas are given by <IT>t</IT>-plot analysis.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit46">46</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The parameters determined are listed in Table 1.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None"><SP>29</SP>Si magic angle spinning (MAS) NMR spectrum gives the atomic ratio of Si to Al, Si/Al for each sample as listed in Table .1<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit47 cit48 cit49 cit50">47–50</REF></annotationART></s> According to the results of TG and <SP>29</SP>Si MAS NMR, we can determine the chemical composition of each sample: (Ca<SB>4.8</SB>, Na<SB>2.4</SB>)[(AlO<SB>2</SB>)<SB>12</SB>(SiO<SB>2</SB>)<SB>12</SB>]·(∼39)H<SB>2</SB>O for molecular sieve 5A, Na<SB>84</SB>[(AlO<SB>2</SB>)<SB>84</SB>(SiO<SB>2</SB>)<SB>108</SB>]·(∼750)H<SB>2</SB>O for molecular sieve 13X, and Na<SB>52</SB>[(AlO<SB>2</SB>)<SB>52</SB>(SiO<SB>2</SB>)<SB>140</SB>]·(∼1200)H<SB>2</SB>O for Zeolite NaY.</P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.2"><SP>129</SP>Xe NMR spectrum for dehydrated powder samples</HEADER><P>Figs. 1(a)–(c) show the pressure dependence of the <SP>129</SP>Xe NMR spectrum in dehydrated powder samples of molecular sieve 5A, 13X and zeolite NaY, respectively. <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The pressure dependence of the chemical shift values for each resonance line is shown in Fig. 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In each sample, the spectrum at 0.1 MPa mainly consists of two dominant peaks; one near 0 ppm and other at the chemical shift range from 50 to 100 ppm.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The resonance line near 0 ppm comes from bulk free xenon gas coexisting on the powder sample.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The chemical shift of this resonance line agreed with that for pure bulk xenon gas within the experimental error, suggesting that the observed peak for bulk free xenon is not affected by the chemical exchange with xenon adsorbed in the micropores.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the other hand, the peak appearing in the lower field corresponds to xenon adsorbed in the micropore, and shifts toward the lower field side as pressure increases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The <IT>δ</IT>-value, which is extrapolated to zero pressure using the data below 0.1 MPa, gives 90 ppm for molecular sieve 5A, 65 ppm for 13X and 52 ppm for zeolite NaY, and increases rapidly as pressure increases to 1 MPa.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">For molecular sieve 5A and 13X, it reaches 260 ppm and 230 ppm at 6 MPa, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition to these two peaks, the extra peak appears at the chemical shift range 20–30 ppm higher than that of bulk-free xenon above 5 MPa.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">This peak originates from partial components of xenon contributing to the chemical exchange between the inside and outside of the micropore.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11 cit51">11,51</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast, in zeolite NaY, the resonance line shifts again toward the higher field above 1 MPa with the line broadening, and the <IT>δ</IT>-value for xenon in the micropore shows the minimum level of 110 ppm at 6 MPa.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Above 6 MPa, the resonance line shifts again to the low field with narrowing of the lines.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, under 4 MPa pressure, the resonance line at 306 K (FWHM ∼70 ppm) becomes narrower than that at 298 K (FWHM ∼100 ppm) as shown in Fig. 3.</annotationART></s> This anomalous pressure dependence is caused by the influence of the rapid chemical exchange of xenon between the inside and outside of the micropores.</P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.3"><SP>129</SP>Xe NMR spectrum for hydrated powder samples</HEADER><P>Figs. 4(a) and 4(b) show the pressure dependence on the <SP>129</SP>Xe NMR spectrum for the powder sample of molecular sieve 5A and 13X before dehydration. <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The chemical shift for xenon in the micropore entirely shifts the lower field compared to the dehydrated samples.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 5 shows the pressure dependence of the chemical shift value for each sample, in which the <IT>δ</IT>-value extrapolating to zero pressure is evaluated as 127 ppm for molecular sieve 5A, and 160 ppm for 13X.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">These values are 37 ppm and 95 ppm greater than for each dehydrated sample.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The chemical shift value increases 100 ppm for 5A and 35 ppm for 13X as pressure increases up to 6 MPa.</annotationART></s> In these samples, the extra broad peak, which appears at 20–30 ppm higher than the peak of free xenon in the dehydrated samples above 5 MPa (See Fig. 1(a) and 1(b)), was not observed.</P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.4"><SP>129</SP>Xe NMR spectrum for pellet samples</HEADER><P>Figs. 6(a)–(d) show the pressure dependence of <SP>129</SP>Xe NMR spectra of xenon adsorbed in the pellet samples of molecular sieve 5A and 13X. <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">In molecular sieve 5A, the pressure dependence of <SP>129</SP>Xe NMR spectra is similar in both the hydrated (Fig. 6(a)) and dehydrated (Fig. 6(b)) pellet samples.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The extra resonance peak, which appears above 4 MPa in the dehydrated powder sample in Fig. 1(a), was also observed in the pellet dehydrated sample.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is considered that the existence of some additional porous structure such as micro-, meso- and macropores, which is caused by binder agents, is not clear in molecular sieve 5A.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the other hand, in molecular sieve 13X, the resonance peak from xenon in the micropore is split into two peaks in the pellet sample.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is considered that there are two types of micropores in the pellet samples.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The intensity of these peaks depends on the presence of adsorbed water.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the partially hydrated sample (Fig. 6(c)), the peak in the higher field is dominant, whereas in the dehydrated sample (Fig. 6(d)), the intensity of these peaks is reversed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">This suggests that micropores corresponding to these two peaks have different affinity for water adsorption, that is, the micropore with a resonance peak in the lowest field can adsorb water easier than that with a resonance peak in the higher field.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">As pressure increases, the line width of both peaks broadens, but these peaks did not coalesce.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.">Discussion</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.1">Pressure dependence of <SP>129</SP>Xe chemical shift</HEADER><P><s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The pressure dependence of the <SP>129</SP>Xe chemical shift of xenon confined to micropores is similar to the xenon adsorption isotherm classified in type-I by IUPAC,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit44 cit45">44,45</REF> suggesting that the adsorption of xenon is accelerated in low pressure regions due to the deep potential, which is emphasized by the micropore field.</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">When the contribution of local magnetic fields in the pore to the chemical shift is quite small and there are no strong adsorption sites for xenon, the <SP>129</SP>Xe chemical shift for xenon adsorbed in the pore is described by<IT>δ</IT> = <IT>δ</IT><SB>S</SB> + <IT>δ</IT><SB>Xe</SB> + <IT>δ</IT><SB>E</SB>where <IT>δ</IT><SB>S</SB> is the interaction between xenon and the wall of the pore, and <IT>δ</IT><SB>Xe</SB> is the contribution of Xe–Xe interaction.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10 cit52">10,52</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The second term of the right hand side of eqn. (1) is assumed to be proportional to the density of xenon in the pore, and is approximated to be <IT>δ</IT><SB>Xe</SB> = <IT>δ</IT><SB>Xe–Xe</SB><IT>ρ</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, the plateau observed on the pressure dependence of <SP>129</SP>Xe chemical shift in high-pressure regions indicates that the adsorption of xenon in the micropores of molecular sieve 5A and 13X has reached saturation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The third term is contribution of local electric field caused by charge center such as Ca<SP>2+</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This term will contribute the chemical shift in molecular sieve 5A containing Ca<SP>2+</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although the adsorption amount of xenon in molecular sieve 5A and 13X in high-pressure regions up to 10 MPa enables the discussion of the density dependence of the chemical shift, the xenon adsorption isotherm in these systems is unknown.</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The appropriate assumption of the adsorption of xenon in high-pressure regions leads to the pressure dependence of xenon density in micropores.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this study, this is assumed by the Langmuir equation, because the physisorption due to micropore filling (type-I) can be qualitatively approximated by the Langmuir equation.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit53 cit54">53,54</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The surface coverage of xenon in micropores, <IT>θ</IT>, is defined by the density ratio at equilibrium pressure to the density when the adsorption is saturated, <IT>ρ</IT>(<IT>P</IT>)/<IT>ρ</IT>(∞).</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In Langmuir-type adsorption behavior, the coverage is given bywhere <IT>K</IT> is the ratio of the rate constant for adsorption to desorption.</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, the change in the chemical shift value between 0 MPa and infinite pressure is represented by Δ<IT>δ</IT><SB>Xe–Xe</SB> = <IT>δ</IT>(∞) − <IT>δ</IT><SB>S</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Using these relationships, the <SP>129</SP>Xe chemical shift at pressure, <IT>P</IT>, is represented by</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">We can discuss the adsorption behavior of xenon using the parameters, <IT>δ</IT><SB>S</SB>, Δ<IT>δ</IT><SB>Xe–Xe</SB>, and <IT>K</IT>, obtained from the pressure dependence of <SP>129</SP>Xe chemical shift value.</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In particular, parameters such as Δ<IT>δ</IT><SB>Xe–Xe</SB> and <IT>K</IT>, which relate to xenon–xenon interaction in the adsorption process of xenon, are given as high-pressure <SP>129</SP>Xe NMR measurements, in addition to <IT>δ</IT><SB>S</SB> which can be determined from conventional <SP>129</SP>Xe NMR measurements covering only the low-equilibrium pressure range.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10 cit11 cit12 cit13 cit14 cit15">10–15</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The analysis of the pressure dependence of <SP>129</SP>Xe chemical shift using eqn. (3) leads to three kinds of parameters for each sample as listed in Table 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In NaY zeolite, the analysis was carried out using chemical shift data below 0.75 MPa.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.2">Pore size from <IT>δ</IT><SB>S</SB></HEADER><P><s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None"><IT>δ</IT><SB>S</SB> reflects the interaction between xenon and pore walls.</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Fraissard <IT>et al</IT>. assumed that <IT>δ</IT><SB>S</SB> is given by the average value between the chemical shifts of xenon on the wall, <IT>δ</IT><SB>a</SB>, and in free space, <IT>δ</IT><SB>V</SB>, for de-aluminated zeolites and zeolites containing only Na<SP>+</SP> as a cation as follows:<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit55">55</REF>where <IT>δ</IT><SB>V</SB> depends on the volume of free space in the pores.</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the basis of this assumption,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit56">56</REF> there is a relation between <IT>δ</IT><SB>S</SB> and the mean free path, <IT>l</IT>, of xenon in the pore as represented byThis equation suggests a linear relation between the reciprocal value of <IT>δ</IT><SB>S</SB> and the pore size.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Assuming the shape of the pore as a sphere and cylinder, the mean free path of xenon is given by <IT>l</IT> = (<IT>D</IT><SB>S</SB> − <IT>D</IT><SB>Xe</SB>)/2 and <IT>l</IT> = (<IT>D</IT><SB>C</SB> − <IT>D</IT><SB>Xe</SB>), respectively, using the pore diameter, <IT>D</IT><SB>S</SB> and <IT>D</IT><SB>C</SB> for spherical and cylindrical pores and the van der Waals diameter of xenon, <IT>D</IT><SB>Xe</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">According to these equations, the following relations are derived between <IT>δ</IT><SB>S</SB> and <IT>D</IT><SB>C</SB> and/or <IT>D</IT><SB>S</SB>:<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit56">56</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">These equations have previously been proposed to explain the relation between the chemical shift and the free space in micropores.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although it has recently been attempted to elucidate the chemical shift of xenon in the pores using <IT>ab initio</IT> MO calculations on the basis of xenon–wall as well as xenon–xenon interactions,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit57">57</REF> it is convenient to describe the relation between <IT>δ</IT><SB>s</SB> and the pore size of zeolites.</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Using these equations, we can evaluate the pore diameter of molecular sieve 5A and 13X for hydrated and dehydrated samples, and dehydrated zeolite NaY as listed in Table 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In molecular sieve 5A, <IT>δ</IT><SB>E</SB> also contributes to <IT>δ</IT> at zero pressure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Although the effect of <IT>δ</IT><SB>E</SB> on <IT>δ</IT> will leads to overestimation of <IT>δ</IT><SB>S</SB>, <IT>δ</IT> at zero pressure, which corresponds to <IT>δ</IT><SB>S</SB> + <IT>δ</IT><SB>E</SB>, enables us to roughly estimate the pore diameter.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The pore diameter evaluated from the crystal structure is 1.14 nm for molecular sieve 5A and 1.37 nm for molecular sieve 13X and zeolite NaY.</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Comparing the pore size from <IT>δ</IT><SB>S</SB> assuming the spherical and cylindrical shape to that one, the spherical and cylindrical pore model seems to be valid for molecular sieve 5A and zeolite NaY, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">For molecular sieve 13X, the pore size from the crystal structure is the intermediate value of the spherical and cylindrical pore model.</annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">This aspect may concern the mobility of adsorbed xenon in the pore.</annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">In molecular sieve 5A, xenon is strongly adsorbed in the super cage, resulting in the long residence time of xenon in the cage.</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">Consequently, the adsorbed xenon assumes a spherical shape in the occupying space.</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">As the rate of translational motion of xenon increases in the pore, the residence time of the adsorbed xenon in the super cage decreases and xenon translating from the super cage to others assumes a cylindrical shape in the occupying space.</annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">The effective shape of the pore describing <IT>δ</IT><SB>S</SB> implies that the mobility of xenon decreases in the order; NaY &gt; 13X &gt; 5A.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.3">Influence of adsorbed water on the xenon adsorption</HEADER><P><s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">The analysis of the pressure dependence of <SP>129</SP>Xe chemical shift in the hydrated sample for molecular sieves gives the parameters, <IT>δ</IT><SB>S</SB>, Δ<IT>δ</IT><SB>Xe–Xe</SB>, and <IT>K</IT> as listed in Table 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In fact, the influence of the adsorbed water on the xenon chemical shift was already examined in NaY.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit66">66</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In NaY, both <IT>δ</IT><SB>wall</SB> and <IT>δ</IT><SB>1</SB>, which correspond to <IT>δ</IT><SB>S</SB> and <IT>δ</IT><SB>Xe</SB> in this paper, were affected by the amount of water.</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The effect of the presence of water on the xenon environments is different between the adsorption and desorption processes of water: Adsorption of water leads to inhomogeneous distribution of xenon environments, whereas desorption leads to uniform one.</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">In molecular sieve 5A and 13X, xenon environment seems to be uniform because of the single and symmetric peak for confined xenon (See Fig. 4).</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">This implies that the samples used in this study are in the partially dehydrated condition.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">The <IT>δ</IT><SB>S</SB> values in the hydrated samples are larger than the correspondence values for the dehydrated samples.</annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the reciprocal value of <IT>δ</IT><SB>S</SB> is proportional to the pore size, which depends on the pore model, this aspect suggests that the pore size felt by adsorbed xenon decreases due to water adsorption in the hydrated samples.</annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" advantage="None">In molecular sieve 5A, the decreased pore diameter for the spherical pore shape is 0.30 nm, which corresponds to a 0.5 monolayer of water with 0.27 nm cross-section based on the van der Waals diameter of O- and H-atoms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the other hand, in molecular sieve 13X, the decreased pore diameter is 0.95 nm for the spherical pore and 0.45 nm for the cylindrical pore and the average of these values is 0.70 nm, suggesting that about 1.3 molecular layers of water are formed on the wall, that is, the amount of adsorbed water in 13X is 2.6 times greater than that in 5A.</annotationART></s> <s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is consistent with the amount of water adsorbed in the pretreated samples determined by TG measurements, in which the amount of adsorbed water in 13X is 2.3 times greater than that in 5A; 41 wt.% for 5A and 100 wt.% for 13X.</annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The <IT>δ</IT><SB>wall</SB> value in NaY changes from 58 ppm for completely dehydrated sample to 158 ppm for the sample containing 85% of the saturated water content.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit66">66</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None">This change is similar to that in molecular sieve 13X.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Δ<IT>δ</IT><SB>Xe–Xe</SB> value is related to the local density of xenon in the pore when the micropore is saturated by xenon.</annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, at low density where the additivity of the <SP>129</SP>Xe chemical shift value is valid for the amount of xenon occupying the nearest neighbors, this value will approximately reflect the number of surrounding xenon atoms for a xenon atom.</annotationART></s> <s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">According to the discussion on the additivity of the <SP>129</SP>Xe chemical shift to gaseous xenon adsorbed in the α-cage of zeolite A by Jameson <IT>et al</IT>.,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit58">58</REF> the additivity is valid for the cluster sizes up to Xe<SB>6</SB> and the shift value increases to about 22 ppm on average by the addition of one xenon atom.</annotationART></s> <s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">For Xe<SB>7</SB> and Xe<SB>8</SB> clusters, the chemical shift increases by about 45 ppm and 44 ppm when a xenon atom is added to the cluster, because the increase in cluster size leads to a large contribution of the chemical shielding at a shorter interatomic distance.</annotationART></s> <s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the basis of this discussion, the Δ<IT>δ</IT><SB>Xe–Xe</SB> value for a dehydrated sample for 5A and 13X suggests the formation of a Xe<SB><IT>n</IT></SB> cluster with an average size of <IT>n</IT> = 7, whereas for the hydrated sample, the decrease in Δ<IT>δ</IT><SB>Xe–Xe</SB> value leads to the average size of cluster Xe<SB>6</SB> for 5A and of Xe<SB>3</SB> for 13X.</annotationART></s> <s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, the hydration also decreases in <IT>K</IT> value, implying that the hydrophobic interaction between xenon and the wall consisting of SiO<SB>2</SB> and/or AlO<SB>2</SB> is more efficient than the xenon–water interaction.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.4">Pore structure in pellet samples</HEADER><P><s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res29" novelty="None" advantage="None">Figs. 6(c) and 6(d) suggest that there is a space larger than the original micropore of the zeolites in molecular sieve 13X.</annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None">This may be the effect of the binder agents used in preparing the pellets, that is, relatively large micropores and/or mesopores are formed in the interspace between microcrystallites.</annotationART></s> <s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res30" novelty="None" advantage="None">This effect is clear in molecular sieve 13X.</annotationART></s> <s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Above 0.1 MPa, the extra resonance line appears at a chemical shift 15 ppm smaller than the chemical shift corresponding to xenon in the original micropore.</annotationART></s> <s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the potential well for adsorption due to the pores is inversely proportional to the pore size,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit54 cit59">54,59</REF> the larger the micropore diameter, the smaller the chemical shift value.</annotationART></s> <s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, the extra peak will correspond to xenon adsorbed in the micropores and/or mesopores formed by the process of fine particle binding.</annotationART></s> <s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res32" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, the broadening of the line width of the peak for xenon in larger sized pores than the original, indicates the exchange of xenon between these pores, but these peaks did not coalesce.</annotationART></s> <s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None">This implies that the exchange of xenon between these sites is very slow compared with the frequency separation of about 800 Hz (∼15 ppm).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None">For xenon adsorbed in the extra pores, the spectrum depends on the hydration condition of the sample.</annotationART></s> <s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the hydrated sample, the intensity of the peak from xenon in the original micropore is smaller than that in the extra-large pores.</annotationART></s> <s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast, in the dehydrated sample, the intensities of these peaks are reversed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None">This aspect suggests that the hydration water is adsorbed in the original micropore formed by the zeolite frameworks more efficiently than the extra-large pores formed in the intercrystallites.</annotationART></s> <s sid="143"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is caused by the deeper potential depth in the original micropore of 13X framework formed by the pore wall.</annotationART></s> <s sid="144"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None">For molecular sieve 5A, this effect cannot be observed.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.5">Chemical exchange of xenon in NaY zeolite</HEADER><P><s sid="145"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">In NaY, the pressure dependence of the resonance line with line broadening is related to the chemical exchange of xenon between the outside and inside of pores.</annotationART></s> <s sid="146"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res33" novelty="None" advantage="None">The change in the chemical shift at pressures above 1 MPa in Fig. 2 is quite different from those for molecular sieve 5A and 13X.</annotationART></s> <s sid="147"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res34" novelty="None" advantage="None">As an initial approximation, the pressure dependence of the chemical shift in pressure regions from 0.02 to 0.75 MPa is analyzed by the Langmuir adsorption model, because in this region, the pressure dependence is similar to those for the other two samples.</annotationART></s> <s sid="148"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res34" novelty="None" advantage="None">The analysis leads to the following parameters: <IT>δ</IT><SB>S</SB> = 52 ppm, Δ<IT>δ</IT><SB>Xe–Xe</SB> = 121 ppm, and <IT>K</IT> = 6.0 MPa<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="149"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res35" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the pressure region higher than 0.75 MPa, the Langmuir model cannot explain the pressure dependence of the chemical shift.</annotationART></s> <s sid="150"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res36" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast, part of the xenon gas co-existing with adsorbed xenon in the pore gives rise to a resonance line which coincides with the resonance for pure bulk xenon gas under the same conditions, implying that the effect of the chemical exchange of xenon is rarely affected in the observed part as free xenon gas in the spectrum.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="151"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res37" novelty="None" advantage="None">When the chemical exchange of xenon between the outside and inside of the pore occurs with the exchange rate faster than the frequency separation between two resonance peaks in relation to the exchange, a resultant resonance peak appears at a frequency given by the weighted average of these two resonance frequencies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="152"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res37" novelty="None" advantage="None">The line width of the averaged resonance line is efficiently affected by the exchange rate and the population of xenon in both sites.</annotationART></s> <s sid="153"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res37" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, the temperature dependence of the spectrum in Fig. 3 strongly suggests the existence of the chemical exchange of xenon.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="154"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Using the simple two-site exchange model,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit60">60</REF> we then analyzed the pressure dependence of the spectrum to evaluate the exchange rate for xenon between the outside and inside of the pores.</annotationART></s> <s sid="155"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Two sites for xenon, bulk-xenon gas and adsorbed xenon in the pore, are denoted by A and B, respectively, where the population of each site is <IT>p</IT><SB>A</SB> and <IT>p</IT><SB>B</SB> and the exchange rate constant from A to B site is <IT>k</IT><SB>A</SB> and that from B to A site is <IT>k</IT><SB>B</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="156"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">According to the principal of the detailed balance, <IT>p</IT><SB>A</SB><IT>k</IT><SB>A</SB> = <IT>p</IT><SB>B</SB><IT>k</IT><SB>B</SB> is satisfied.</annotationART></s> <s sid="157"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The residence time of xenon in each site is <IT>τ</IT><SB>A</SB> = <IT>k</IT><SB>A</SB><SP>−1</SP> and <IT>τ</IT><SB>B</SB> = <IT>k</IT><SB>B</SB><SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="158"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the slow exchange limit, the line width of the Lorentzian line shape function is then given as follows: Δ<IT>ν</IT><SB>A</SB> = (π<IT>T</IT><SB>2A</SB>)<SP>−1</SP> + (π<IT>τ</IT><SB>A</SB>)<SP>−1</SP> for site A and Δ<IT>ν</IT><SB>B</SB> = (π<IT>T</IT><SB>2B</SB>)<SP>−1</SP> + (π<IT>τ</IT><SB>B</SB>)<SP>−1</SP> for site B, where <IT>T</IT><SB>2A</SB> and <IT>T</IT><SB>2B</SB> are the transverse relaxation times for each original resonance peak of xenon at sites A and B, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="159"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">As the exchange rate increases, the line width also increases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="160"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">They are given by the inverse of the line width at half maximum for each resonance peak, when the chemical exchange is negligible.</annotationART></s> <s sid="161"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the fast exchange limit, the resonance line appears at a frequency given by the weighted average between the frequencies of site A and B as follows:<IT>ν</IT> = <IT>p</IT><SB>A</SB><IT>ν</IT><SB>A</SB> + <IT>p</IT><SB>B</SB><IT>ν</IT><SB>B</SB>and the line width is given by</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="162"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The eqn. (8) indicates that the resonance frequency and the line width strongly depend on the population of xenon in each site as well as the exchange rates.</annotationART></s> <s sid="163"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Spectrum analysis was carried out using the GAMMA simulation program.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit61">61</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="164"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The variables in the simulation are the ratio of the population of xenon in the pore to that for bulk xenon, and the exchange rate constant between these two sites.</annotationART></s> <s sid="165"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In simulating the spectrum, we used various assumptions for the following points: (i) The original peak position (<IT>ν</IT><SB>B</SB>) for xenon adsorbed above 0.75 MPa is assumed to be given by the curve using the Langmuir model for the chemical shift value below 0.75 MPa.</annotationART></s> <s sid="166"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="Old" advantage="None">(ii) The line width (<IT>T</IT><SB>2A</SB> and <IT>T</IT><SB>2B</SB>) for each original peak without the effect of the chemical exchange is assumed to be identical to that of the resonance peak for pure bulk xenon (<IT>ca.</IT> 50 Hz).</annotationART></s> <s sid="167"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="Old" advantage="None">(iii) For bulk xenon gas, the chemical shift values for pure bulk xenon gas are used as the original resonance peak position (<IT>ν</IT><SB>A</SB>) at the corresponding pressure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="168"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res38" novelty="None" advantage="None">The observed and simulated spectra are shown in Fig. 7(a) and 7(b), which focus on the chemical shift range from 40 to 200 ppm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="169"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res39" novelty="None" advantage="None">The simulated spectrum on each pressure well reproduces the observed spectrum.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="170"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res40" novelty="None" advantage="None">The result of the simulation and the resultant parameters such as <IT>p</IT><SB>A</SB>/<IT>p</IT><SB>B</SB> and the exchange rate constant from the inside of the pore to outside are shown in Fig. 8(a) and 8(b), respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="171"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res41" novelty="None" advantage="None">The <IT>p</IT><SB>A</SB>/<IT>p</IT><SB>B</SB> value and the exchange rate constant increase linearly as pressure increases from 0.75 MPa to 6 MPa, indicating that the exchange of xenon is dominated by the density of xenon for bulk xenon more efficiency than that for adsorbed xenon.</annotationART></s> <s sid="172"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res42" novelty="None" advantage="None">Above 0.75 MPa, the pressure dependence of the chemical shift for adsorbed xenon seems to be saturated, and then the chemical exchange of xenon between the outside and the inside of the pores is accelerated by the increase in xenon density outside of the pores.</annotationART></s> <s sid="173"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res43" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast, <IT>p</IT><SB>A</SB>/<IT>p</IT><SB>B</SB> seems to slightly increase above 6 MPa and the exchange rate constant decreases as pressure increases after the maximum at 6 MPa, where xenon outside the pores becomes supercritical fluid (<IT>T</IT><SB>c</SB> = 289.8 K and <IT>P</IT><SB>c</SB> = 5.8 MPa).</annotationART></s> <s sid="174"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None">This implies that under the supercritical fluid, a constant amount of xenon outside of the pores is concerned with the exchange of xenon inside of the pores.</annotationART></s> <s sid="175"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The origin of this behavior can not be clearly identified, but it may be concerned with the co-operative phenomenon in supercritical fluid such as the large fluctuation of xenon density and the large correlation length between xenon atoms.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit62">62</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="176"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The intermolecular coherence among xenon atoms in supercritical fluid may promote the co-operative aggregation of xenon atoms such as the cluster formation.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit63">63</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="177"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None">This structure formation may contribute to decrease the efficiency of xenon exchange between the outside and inside of the pores.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit64">64</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="178"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Finally, it is very interesting to show the different behavior of NaY on the chemical exchange from that of molecular sieve 13X, althought both zeolites have a same crystal structure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="179"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con15" novelty="None" advantage="None">This different behavior on the chemical exchange will come from the difference in Si/Al values between X and Y type and/or the position of cations in the unit cell.</annotationART></s> <s sid="180"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con16" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the present study, we can not examine what effect is dominant for the chemical exchange between the inside and the outside of the pore.</annotationART></s> <s sid="181"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The further study is now in progress.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="5.">Conclusion</HEADER><P><s sid="182"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con17" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this study, high pressure <SP>129</SP>Xe NMR measurements were carried out to examine the local structure of confined xenon in the original micropores of the framework, as well as the effect of adsorbed water and the binding of polycrystalline on the xenon environments in molecular sieve 5A, 13X and zeolite NaY.</annotationART></s> <s sid="183"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The observations made were as follows:</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="184"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con18" novelty="None" advantage="None">1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="185"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The pressure dependence of the <SP>129</SP>Xe chemical shift value of xenon confined in the micropores of molecular sieve 5A, 13X and zeolite NaY are analyzed by the Langmuir adsorption model, leading to information about the pore size, the amount of xenon at saturated pressure, and the ratio of the apparent rate constant between the adsorption and desorption of xenon in the pores.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="186"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con19" novelty="None" advantage="None">2. <SP>129</SP>Xe NMR spectrum and their pressure dependence enable us to detect decreases in the pore diameter due to the adsorption of water and the formation of additional micropores due to the binding of polycrystalline for pellet production.</annotationART></s> <s sid="187"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res44" novelty="None" advantage="None">The super cage in molecular sieve 13X (FAU type framework) can accommodate water more efficiently than that in molecular sieve 5A (LTA type framework).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="188"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res45" novelty="None" advantage="None">3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="189"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res45" novelty="None" advantage="None">The analysis of the pore diameter assuming a spherical and the cylinder shaped pore suggests that the mobility of xenon adsorbed in the micropore of the framework increases in the order NaY &gt; 13X &gt; 5A.</annotationART></s> <s sid="190"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res46" novelty="None" advantage="None">In zeolite NaY, the chemical exchange of xenon between the inside and outside of the micropore can be observed at high-pressure regions above 1 MPa.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="191"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res47" novelty="None" advantage="None">4.</annotationART></s> <s sid="192"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res47" novelty="None" advantage="None">The exchange rate constant and the population of xenon contributing to the exchange seem to be affected by the supercritical phenomena of bulk xenon gas co-existing with adsorbed xenon in the micropore.</annotationART></s> <s sid="193"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs19" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the supercritical state, the exchange rate decreases, although the population of xenon in the micropores and the bulk gas is almost constant.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="194"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con20" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, the high-pressure <SP>129</SP>Xe NMR technique offers new microscopic aspects on the pore structure, the intermolecular interaction of xenon confined in the pore, and the dynamical behavior of adsorbed xenon.</annotationART></s> <s sid="195"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con21" novelty="None" advantage="None">This method will be a useful and powerful tool to investigate the porosity of materials from a microscopic point of view, and will be developed as a compensative method of the adsorption isotherm in the characterization of pore structure.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
