<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b310825b" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None"><IT>Ab initio</IT> QM/MM molecular dynamics simulation of preferential K<SP>+</SP> solvation in aqueous ammonia solution</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">A combined <IT>ab initio</IT> quantum mechanical/molecular mechanical (QM/MM) molecular dynamics simulation has been performed to investigate the solvation structure of K<SP>+</SP> in 18.4% aqueous ammonia solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The chemically most relevant region, the first solvation sphere of K<SP>+</SP>, was treated by Born–Oppenheimer <IT>ab initio</IT> quantum mechanics using LANL2DZ basis sets, while the rest of the system was described by classical pair potentials.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Within the first solvation shell of K<SP>+</SP>, the QM/MM simulation reveals a polyhedral structure with an average coordination number of 7.6, consisting of 6.7 water and 0.9 ammonia molecules, compared to the corresponding value of 8.7 composed of 5.3 water and 3.4 ammonia molecules obtained by classical pair potential simulation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The QM/MM results, in contrast to the classical simulation, clearly indicate a preference for water ligands and a higher flexibility of ligand arrangements in the first solvation shell of the ion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The preference for ligands is discussed on the basis of detailed simulation results.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, a “structure-breaking” behavior of the ion is well recognized by the detailed analysis on ligand exchange processes and the mean residence times of the ligands surrounding the ion.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="1.">Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since ion solvation processes are of great importance in a wide variety of systems, hydrated ions have become an increasingly important subject of both experimental and theoretical studies.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2 cit3 cit4 cit5 cit6 cit7 cit8 cit9">1–9</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In general, comparison between experiments and theories is not always straightforward because most of the experimental methods for structural analysis have to be performed with solutions of relatively high concentrations, while the theoretical approaches mostly refer to very dilute solutions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Theoretical methods, in particular Monte Carlo (MC) and molecular dynamics (MD) simulations, can provide valuable complementary information not accessible to experimental approaches both in the characterization of ion–solvent complexes and in the specific mechanism of the involved interactions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">During the past decades, numerous MC and MD simulations have been carried out to evaluate hydration structures, hydration energies, mobilities, librational and vibrational spectra and other properties.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, most of the simulation works had relied on classical molecular mechanical potentials, and hence, deviation of the results from experiments was often found, strongly depending on the type and quality of the potential models employed in the simulations.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10 cit11">10,11</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">To provide a realistic view of the solvated ion properties, it has been shown that the model interaction potential must include polarizability and many-body nonadditive contributions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">With regard to this point, various schemes have been proposed, for example, the polarizable continuum model (PCM),<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF> which incorporates the many-body interactions in an average way, or a direct approach by calculating the energy hypersurface of many-body interactions and then fitting them to an analytical function.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14 cit15">14,15</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="No">Both exemplary models can provide significant improvement of the results, however, for the PCM model, a major weakness is that it can not reproduce specific interaction with the surrounding solvent, such as hydrogen bonds.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the second model, construction of many-body potentials is rather difficult, and is hardly feasible for large molecular systems because of their complicated orientation dependence.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15 cit17">15,17</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">To describe molecular interactions correctly, more sophisticated simulation technique incorporating quantum mechanical algorithms, namely the combined quantum mechanical and molecular mechanical (QM/MM) method has been introduced.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18 cit19 cit20">18–20</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Several hybrid QM/MM models combine either semiempirical,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18 cit20 cit21 cit22">18,20–22</REF> density functional,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF> valence bond,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24 cit25">24,25</REF> or even <IT>ab initio</IT> Hartree–Fock<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19 cit26">19,26</REF> methodology with commonly used force fields.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In recent years, a “Born–Oppenheimer <IT>ab initio</IT> QM/MM dynamics” has been proposed and successfully applied for elucidating structural and dynamical properties of various ions in solutions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27 cit28 cit29 cit30 cit31 cit32 cit33 cit34 cit35 cit36 cit37 cit38 cit39 cit40 cit41">27–41</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">This technique treats the active-site region, <IT>i.e.</IT> the solvation shell around the ion, quantum mechanically, while the environment consisting of further solvent molecules is described by classical molecular mechanical potentials.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">By this approach, the complicated many-body contributions as well as the polarization effects within the solvation sphere of the ion can be reliably included.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The QM/MM results have clearly shown the important role of non-additive contributions and that inclusion of higher-order interaction terms is essential for the correct description of the solvated ions, even for monovalent ions in which many-body interactions could be expected to be weaker than in the case of di- and trivalent ions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29 cit30 cit32 cit33 cit38">29,30,32,33,38</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">For ion solvation in mixed solvent systems, Born–Oppenheimer <IT>ab initio</IT> QM/MM molecular dynamics simulations have been successfully applied to Li<SP>+</SP>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit32">32</REF> Na<SP>+</SP>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit33">33</REF> Mg<SP>2+</SP><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit34">34</REF> and Ca<SP>2+</SP><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit35">35</REF> in aqueous ammonia solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">The results from QM/MM simulations have provided more reliable geometrical arrangements of the solvated ion structures as well as ligand preferences in good agreement with the qualitative expectation according to Lewis acid–base interactions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit42 cit43 cit44">42–44</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In comparison to the results obtained by classical pair potential simulations, the QM/MM simulations have indicated that the pairwise additive potentials, which lack suitable parameterization, are obviously insufficient for the description of the structural properties of solvated ions in such a solvent mixture.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">In the present work, a Born–Oppenheimer <IT>ab initio</IT> QM/MM dynamics simulation was performed to characterize the preferential solvation of K<SP>+</SP> in aqueous ammonia solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The biological importance of K<SP>+</SP> is well known, <IT>e.g.</IT> in neuron signaling and osmotic stability of cells.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit45 cit46">45,46</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In ion channels of the nervous system, the binding of potassium to ligands is an essential part of the mechanism for message transport.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit47">47</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to understand such biological processes, detailed knowledge of ion structures in solution is required.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The solvation structure of K<SP>+</SP> in water and in ammonia has been studied by X-ray and neutron diffraction experiments<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit48 cit49 cit50 cit51 cit52">4,48–52</REF> as well as by theoretical investigations.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit9 cit30 cit53 cit54 cit55">8,9,30,53–55</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Experiments reported hydration numbers of K<SP>+</SP> in the range 4–7,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit48 cit49 cit50 cit51">48–51</REF> while a coordination number of 6 was found in ammonia.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit52">52</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, the experiments have shown that K<SP>+</SP> acts as “structure-breaking” ion, <IT>i.e.</IT>, the presence of this ion in the solvent can be regarded rather as a perturbation of the solvent network structures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In theoretical investigations, classical and QM/MM simulations predicted hydration numbers of K<SP>+</SP> in the range of 5–10<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit9 cit53 cit54 cit55">8,9,53–55</REF> and 8.3,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30">30</REF> respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our previous QM/MM simulation<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30">30</REF> has shown that the structure-breaking behavior of this ion is only reproduced, if the first hydration shell is treated quantum mechanically.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">For the coordination number of K<SP>+</SP> in ammonia, a classical MD simulation reported an average value of 8..7<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit56">56</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since no structural data for K<SP>+</SP> in aqueous ammonia solution have been reported so far, structural information for this particular ion solvation by means of <IT>ab initio</IT> QM/MM dynamics could be expected to provide useful information regarding the functionality of this metal ion in biological systems with different coordination sites.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.">Methods</HEADER><P><s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="New" advantage="None">Based on Born–Oppenheimer <IT>ab initio</IT> dynamics, the system is partitioned into a part described by quantum mechanics (QM) and another part treated by means of molecular mechanical potentials (MM).</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The total interaction energy of the system can be defined as <IT>E</IT><SB>total</SB> = 〈Ψ<SB>QM</SB>|<IT>Ĥ</IT>|Ψ<SB>QM</SB>〉 + <IT>E</IT><SB>MM</SB> + <IT>E</IT><SB>QM–MM</SB>, where 〈Ψ<SB>QM</SB>|<IT>Ĥ</IT>|Ψ<SB>QM</SB>〉 refers to interactions within the solvation sphere of K<SP>+</SP>, treated by Born–Oppenheimer <IT>ab initio</IT> Hartree–Fock quantum mechanical calculations, while <IT>E</IT><SB>MM</SB> and <IT>E</IT><SB>QM–MM</SB> represent interactions within the MM region and between QM and MM regions, respectively, and are described by classical pair potentials.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Within the QM region, the accurate description of molecular interactions at Hartee–Fock level obviously depends only on the basis set quality.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The LANL2DZ basis sets<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit57 cit58">57,58</REF> were selected as a reasonable choice compromising between the quality of simulation results and the requirement of CPU time.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28 cit29 cit30 cit32 cit33 cit34 cit35">28–30,32–35</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Effects of electron correlation may play some role in the interaction between the ion and solvent especially when the number of solvent molecules in the QM region increases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, treatment at the correlated level is very time-consuming, and thus beyond the current computational feasibility.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">In our previous QM/MM simulation,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit38">38</REF> these effects were found to be rather marginal even for anion–water interactions, when the stabilization energies obtained by HF single point calculations of the anions plus their first hydration shells for several selected configurations were compared to those of MP2 calculations.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="New" advantage="None">In the QM/MM procedure, an <IT>ab initio</IT> calculation was performed in each simulation step, providing quantum mechanical forces to be incorporated into the total force of the system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the exchange of solvent molecules between the QM and MM regions can occur frequently during the simulation, the forces acting on each particle in the system are switched according to the defined region upon entering or leaving of the ligand and can be defined as: <IT>F</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB> = <IT>S</IT><SB>m</SB>(<IT>r</IT>)<IT>F</IT><SB>QM</SB> + (1 – <IT>S</IT><SB>m</SB>(<IT>r</IT>))<IT>F</IT><SB>MM</SB>, where <IT>F</IT><SB>QM</SB> and <IT>F</IT><SB>MM</SB> are quantum mechanical and molecular mechanical forces, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None"><IT>S</IT><SB>m</SB>(<IT>r</IT>) is a smoothing function,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit59">59</REF> where <IT>r</IT><SB>1</SB> and <IT>r</IT><SB>0</SB> are the distances characterizing the beginning and the end of the QM region.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None"><IT>S</IT><SB>m</SB>(<IT>r</IT>) ensures a continuous change of forces in the transition between QM and MM regions.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="New" advantage="None">For interactions inside the MM and between QM and MM regions, flexible models, which describe inter- and intramolecular interactions, were employed for water<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit60 cit61">60,61</REF> and ammonia.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit62">62</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="New" advantage="None">The use of flexible models is to be favored over any of the popular rigid water and ammonia models, in order to ensure compatibility and a smooth transition, when solvent molecules move from the QM region with their full flexibility of ligand molecules to the MM region.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The pair potential function for water–ammonia interactions was adopted from Tanabe and Rode.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit63">63</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The pair potential function for K<SP>+</SP>–H<SB>2</SB>O interactions was obtained from our previous work,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30">30</REF> and the pair potential function for K<SP>+</SP>–NH<SB>3</SB> interactions was newly constructed in the present work using DZV+(d,p) basis set for NH<SB>3</SB><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit57">57</REF> and Los Alamos ECP plus DZ basis set for K<SP>+</SP>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit58">58</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">These basis sets are consistent with the ones used in the construction of the K<SP>+</SP>–H<SB>2</SB>O potential.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="New" advantage="None">The 1500 Hartree–Fock interaction energy points for various K<SP>+</SP>–NH<SB>3</SB> configurations, obtained from Gaussian98<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit64">64</REF> calculations, were fitted to the analytical form of where <IT>A</IT>, <IT>B</IT>, <IT>C</IT> and <IT>D</IT> are the fitting parameters (see Table 1), <IT>r</IT><SB><IT>ic</IT></SB> denotes the distances between K<SP>+</SP> and the <IT>i</IT>-th atom of ammonia and <IT>q</IT> are the atomic net charges.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The charges on K<SP>+</SP>, N and H of ammonia were set to 1.0, –0.8022 and 0.2674, respectively.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="New" advantage="None">A classical molecular dynamics simulation using pair potentials was performed first, then a combined QM/MM molecular dynamics simulation starting from the equilibrium configuration obtained by the classical simulation was carried out.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="New" advantage="No">For the QM/MM simulation, undoubtedly, the QM region is the most expensive computational part and hence the size of it has to be a compromise between the reliability of results and the available computational resources.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="New" advantage="None">In general, the suitable QM size is the sphere including all ligands within the complete first solvation sphere of the ions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="New" advantage="No">A too small size of the QM region can lead to artifacts, which, however, disappear, if the choice of the diameter guarantees that all molecules of the first solvation shell plus eventually exchanging ligands are included in this region.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27 cit67">27,67</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">This is always achieved, when the QM limit is set to the beginning or even slightly inside the second solvation shell.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this case, also an increase of width of the transition region does not make any difference for the results.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">As can be seen from the K–(N + O) radial distribution function (RDF) obtained by the classical simulation (Fig. 1), the first minimum of the RDF peak is located around 3.8 Å.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="New" advantage="None">Within this region, there are about 6–8 water and 3–4 ammonia molecules, which seem rather convenient to perform the QM/MM simulation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="Old" advantage="None">However, as our previous QM/MM simulation for K<SP>+</SP> in water<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30">30</REF> had predicted a somewhat larger hydration shell compared to the one obtained by classical pair potential simulation, a larger QM region with diameter of 8.4 Å was employed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="New" advantage="None">This QM size was assumed to be large enough to ensure a smooth convergence of the quantum mechanical forces to the pair potential forces beyond the QM region.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="New" advantage="None">There are about 8–10 water and 3–4 ammonia molecules located within this region, leading to 8–12 min for computing the forces in each QM/MM step on a DEC Alpha XP1000 workstation.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The classical and combined QM/MM simulations were performed in a canonical ensemble at 293 K. This canonical ensemble has been realized by coupling to an external temperature bath.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The time step was set to 0.2 fs, which allows for explicit movement of hydrogen atoms of water and ammonia.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The basic cube, with a length of 18.56 Å, contained one K<SP>+</SP>, 37 ammonia and 163 water molecules, assuming the experimental density of 18.4% aqueous ammonia solution at the given temperature (0.9398 g cm<SP>–3</SP>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="New" advantage="None">The reaction-field method was employed for the treatment of long-range interactions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit65">65</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">This method also implies a compensation of the electrical non-neutrality of the basic box.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met14" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The classical pair potential simulation started from an equilibrium configuration obtained from our previous QM/MM simulation for Ca<SP>2+</SP> in aqueous ammonia solution.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit35">35</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="New" advantage="None">The system was equilibrated for 80 000 steps, and the simulation was continued for another 100 000 steps for collecting configurations every 10th step.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">As the equilibrium configuration of a QM/MM simulation is usually not much different from that of the classically treated system, and differences refer mostly to the small subsystem of the ion and its environment, a time-span of 2–3 ps is sufficient to achieve re-equilibration, even for systems with stronger ion–solvent interactions than the one investigated here, as can be seen from the behavior of velocities and RDFs after that period.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit34 cit37 cit41">34,37,41</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="New" advantage="None">The QM/MM simulation started with a re-equilibration for 20 000 simulation steps, followed by another 30 000 steps to collect configurations every 5th step.</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="New" advantage="None">The 6 ps interval of our QM/MM simulation can be considered long enough for structural analysis since it has been shown that even a 2 ps simulation can deliver most of the structural and dynamical properties of similar solutions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28 cit29 cit30">28–30</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The switching function of eqn. (2) was applied within an interval of 0.2 Å (<IT>i.e.</IT>, in eqn. (3), <IT>r</IT><SB>1</SB> = 4.0 and <IT>r</IT><SB>0</SB> = 4.2 Å).</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.">Results and discussion</HEADER><P><s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 1 displays and compares the over-all K–(N + O) and K–H (from both water and ammonia molecules) RDFs and their corresponding integration numbers obtained from both classical and combined QM/MM simulations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The classical simulation gives a pronounced first K–(N + O) peak at 2.93 Å, corresponding to an average coordination number of 8.7.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The first solvation shell is not clearly separated from the bulk, indicating an interchange of ligand molecules between the first solvation shell of K<SP>+</SP> and bulk.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the QM/MM simulation, a less pronounced unsymmetrical first K–(N + O) peak, with a maximum at shorter distance of 2.79 Å, is observed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The shape of the K–(N + O) peak indicates an asymmetry of the K<SP>+</SP> solvation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The first solvation shell of K<SP>+</SP> is also not distinctly separated from the bulk, showing even more frequent ligand interchange at the boundary between the solvation shell and bulk.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">An integration, calculated up to the first K–(N + O) minimum, yields an average coordination number of 7.6.</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In both pair potential and QM/MM simulations, a second solvation shell of K<SP>+</SP> is not found, as can be seen from further curves of K–(N + O) RDFs.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met15" novelty="New" advantage="None">The ligand compositions of the solvation shell of K<SP>+</SP> can be analyzed by plotting the K<SP>+</SP>–H<SB>2</SB>O and K<SP>+</SP>–NH<SB>3</SB> RDFs and their corresponding integration numbers separately, as shown in Figs. 2 and 3, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the K<SP>+</SP>–H<SB>2</SB>O RDFs (Fig. 2), the QM/MM simulation reveals a broader unsymmetrical first K–O peak with maximum at 2.81 Å, compared to the corresponding peak at 2.75 Å of the pair potential simulation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The unsymmetrical K–O peak observed in the QM/MM simulation corresponds to weak K<SP>+</SP>–water interactions and a high mobility of water molecules in the solvation shell of K<SP>+</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition to the broader K–O peak, a larger and broader K–H(W) peak obtained from the QM/MM simulation (Fig. 2b) supports well a high flexibility and rather freely-oriented arrangements of the water molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The average numbers of water molecules in the solvation shell of K<SP>+</SP> are about 5.3 ± 0.2 and 6.7 ± 0.1 for pair potential and QM/MM simulation, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the K<SP>+</SP>–NH<SB>3</SB> RDFs (Fig. 3), the pair potential simulation produces a sharp first K–N peak with maximum at 2.96 Å, giving an average coordination number of 3.4 ± 0.2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the QM/MM simulation, a less pronounced unsymmetrical first K–N peak is exhibited at a much shorter K–N distance of 2.77 Å, corresponding to approximately 0.9 ammonia molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">As in the case of K–O peak, the asymmetrical K–N peak in the QM/MM simulation also indicates a high ammonia mobility, associated with an over-all distorted structure of the solvation shell.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 4 shows the probability distributions of the solvation numbers of K<SP>+</SP>, calculated up to the first minimum of the K–(N + O) RDFs.</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the pair potential simulation, the first solvation shell of K<SP>+</SP> prefers a coordination number of 8 (followed by 9 and 7 in decreasing amounts), consisting of 5 (and 6 in decreasing amount) water and 3 (followed by 4 in smaller amount) ammonia molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the QM/MM simulation, the first solvation shell favors a coordination number of 7 (in addition to 8 and 6 in smaller amounts), consisting of 6 (followed by 7, 8 and 5 in smaller amounts) water and one ammonia molecule.</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">As can be seen from Fig. 4, the 8-, 9- and 7-coordinated complexes are mostly dominant in the pair potential simulation, while numerous possible species, varying from 5- to 10-fold coordinated complexes, exist in the QM/MM simulation.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">In comparison to the statistical average distribution of ligands in the solution of approximately 4.4∶1 for water and ammonia molecules, respectively, the QM/MM simulation obviously indicates a preference for H<SB>2</SB>O with a water-to-ammonia ratio of 7.4∶1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast to the QM/MM results, the corresponding ratio of 1.6∶1 is observed in the pair potential simulation, which reflects a preference for NH<SB>3</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">In our previous works, we have shown that the assumption of pairwise additive approximations for the K<SP>+</SP>(H<SB>2</SB>O)<SB><IT>n</IT></SB><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30">30</REF> and K<SP>+</SP>(NH<SB>3</SB>)<SB><IT>n</IT></SB><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit56">56</REF> complexes had led to energetic errors of approximately 17% and 13%, respectively, for <IT>n</IT> = 6, and these errors increased rapidly to 32% and 20% for <IT>n</IT> = 8.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Undoubtedly, the many-body contributions can play a significant role for the preferential solvation of the K<SP>+</SP>, and thus the results predicted by classical pairwise additivity are by no means sufficient for a correct description of this ion's solvation in such binary solvent systems.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 5 displays the O–K–O, N–K–N and O–K–N angular distributions, calculated up to the first minimum of the K–(N + O) RDFs.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">In both classical and combined QM/MM simulations, the solvation shell structure of K<SP>+</SP> is predicted to be approximately polyhedral.</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rather broad angular distributions indicate the extreme lability and irregular structure of the K<SP>+</SP> solvation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met16" novelty="New" advantage="None">In order to describe the geometrical arrangement of the K<SP>+</SP> solvation, the angle <IT>θ</IT>, defined by the K⋯O and K⋯N axes and the dipole vectors of ligands, has been used to investigate the preferential orientations of solvated ligands.</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The dipole-oriented arrangements of water and ammonia molecules within the solvation shell of the ion are given in Figs. 6.</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both classical and combined QM/MM simulations point out that ammonia ligands stick more rigidly to the dipole-oriented arrangement than water molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the QM/MM simulation, a more flexible arrangement is observed, in particular for water molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">As can be seen from Fig. 6a, the QM/MM simulation clearly indicates a higher flexibility of the solvated water's orientation, proving the weak structure-forming ability of K<SP>+</SP> even for its nearest water molecules.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The higher mobility of the solvated ligands, as observed in the QM/MM simulation, would increase the number and rate of ligand exchange processes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Several ligand exchange processes can be seen when the K–O and K–N distances were separately plotted during the QM/MM simulation, as shown in Figs. 7 and 8, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Within the simulation time of 6 ps, 13 water and 3 ammonia molecules were involved in the exchange processes, indicating the extremely fast dynamics of the K<SP>+</SP> solvation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the exchange of water molecules, both associative and dissociative interchange (defined as <IT>I</IT><SB>a</SB> and <IT>I</IT><SB>d</SB>) mechanisms are observed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of ammonia molecules, the first exchange, which took place around 2 ps, shows the <IT>I</IT><SB>d</SB> mechanism, while the second exchange, which occurred beyond 5 ps, seemingly represents the <IT>I</IT><SB>a</SB> type.</annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to estimate the rate of ligand exchange processes at K<SP>+</SP>, the mean residence times (MRT) of the ligands were evaluated within the restrictions set by the available period of the QM/MM simulation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">Based on a direct accounting<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit66">66</REF> and setting the minimum time a ligand has to remain inside/outside a shell upon a migration process as <IT>t</IT>*, the MRT values of 2.1 and 1.9 ps for <IT>t</IT>* = 0.5 and of 15.3 and 5.9 ps for <IT>t</IT>* = 2.0 are obtained for water and ammonia molecules, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The corresponding values for water ligands of hydrated Cs<SP>+</SP> and for pure water<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit66 cit67">66,67</REF> are 1.7 and 1.8 ps for <IT>t</IT>* = 0.5, and 10.6 and 13.7 ps for <IT>t</IT>* = 2.0.</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">These data show the particular lability of NH<SB>3</SB> ligands in the first shell of K<SP>+</SP>, but also that the water ligands in this shell have a similar mobility as in pure water.</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Overall, this represents a well-recognizable structure-breaking effect, although not as pronounced as in the case of Cs<SP>+</SP>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The great lability of NH<SB>3</SB> ligands in the neighborhood of K<SP>+</SP> gives some valuable hints at the binding properties of this ion in biological systems involving N-binding sites.</annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">In a previous paper,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30">30</REF> it has been shown that the main reason of K-specific ion channels to transport this ion preferentially to Na<SP>+</SP> is the easy removal of the ion's hydration shell.</annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results presented here indicate in addition that O-binding sites should be considerably more competitive in K<SP>+</SP> binding than N sites.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.">Conclusion</HEADER><P><s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None">The combined <IT>ab initio</IT> QM/MM molecular dynamics simulation has provided more detailed information on the solvation shell structure of K<SP>+</SP> in 18.4% aqueous ammonia solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">The QM/MM simulation has revealed a flexible polyhedral structure with an average coordination number of 7.6.</annotationART></s> <s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">The solvation shell contains approximately 6.7 water and 0.9 ammonia molecules, which reflects a clear preference for water molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, the simulation has supplied information on the stability of the K<SP>+</SP> solvate, in particular the “structure-breaking” behavior of the ion and its preference for O-binding sites.</annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The classical simulation based on pairwise additive approximations is apparently not adequate to reproduce well enough the flexible structure and a realistic solvation shell and, therefore, the relevance of n-body and polarization effects, even for weakly interacting ions as K<SP>+</SP>, could be demonstrated once more.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
