<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b312562a" hasDoc="yes" version="1168" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Measurements of molecular fragment alignment and orientation in the UV photodissociation of NO<SB>2</SB> and O<SB>3</SB></annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">REMPI-TOF studies of the UV photodissociation of NO<SB>2</SB> and O<SB>3</SB> at 320 nm and 270 nm respectively have allowed both the orientation and alignment parameters of the molecular photofragments to be determined.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The orientation parameter, <IT>β</IT>20(21), for the NO(X<SP>2</SP>Π, <IT>v</IT> = 0) fragment is found to be essentially the same for the three quantum states, <IT>N</IT> = 29, 30 and 40 with a value of 0.24 ± 0.04 (2σ), as probed <IT>via</IT> (1 + 1′) REMPI, on the A<SP>2</SP>Σ<SP>+</SP> (<IT>v</IT> = 0) ← X<SP>2</SP>Π<SB>Ω</SB> (<IT>v</IT> = 0) transition.The O<SB>2</SB> (a <SP>1</SP>Δ<SB>g</SB><IT>v</IT> = 0 <IT>J</IT> = 20) fragment shows a markedly larger orientation parameter, for example <IT>β</IT>20(21) = 0.55 ± 0.04, measured on the S(20) transition.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">These orientation parameters and the accompanying alignment parameters which describe the fragments' angular momentum polarisation have been used to confirm spectral assignments within the highly perturbed (2 + 1) d <SP>1</SP>Π<SB>g</SB>(<IT>v</IT> = 2) ←← a <SP>1</SP>Δ<SB>g</SB> (<IT>v</IT> = 0) REMPI spectrum of O<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="1.">Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Angular momentum polarisation of both atomic and molecular photofragments is a direct consequence of the nature of the potential energy surface upon which the bond cleavage occurs, and experimental studies of photodissociation have increasingly focused on measuring the distributions of photofragment angular momentum vectors <B><IT>J</IT></B> relative to other vector quantities such as the fragment relative velocity and the parent transition moment.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2 cit3 cit4 cit5">1–5</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">These distributions of angular momentum are characterised by a set of moments, <IT>β</IT><IT>K</IT><IT>Q</IT>(<IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB><IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB>), averaged over the photofragment ensemble,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF> and can be divided into two classes, namely those corresponding to the <IT>alignment</IT> and to the <IT>orientation</IT> of <B><IT>J</IT></B> (those of even and odd rank <IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB> respectively).</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The former can be probed with linearly polarised light, and have been the subject of many investigations into the alignment of product angular momentum with respect to a reference axis.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2 cit3 cit4 cit5">1–5</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">An example is in the moment <IT>β</IT>00(22) which relates the products' velocity <B><IT>v</IT></B> and angular momentum <B><IT>J</IT></B> and is equal to the expectation value of the second order Legendre polynomial, 〈<IT>P</IT><SB>2</SB>(cos<IT>α</IT>)〉, where <IT>α</IT> is the angle between the vectors.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="No">However, such measurements give us no insight into the sense of this angular momentum.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">For example, they may inform us that a molecular photofragment is rotating in the <IT>xz</IT>-plane with its velocity related to that plane, say in the positive <IT>x</IT> direction, but we cannot tell if the angular momentum vector is pointing in the positive or negative <IT>y</IT> direction: we can measure alignment but not orientation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The use of circularly polarised light overcomes this difficulty and allows orientation parameters to be measured.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Such experiments on the orientation of molecular fragments<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7 cit8 cit9 cit10 cit11 cit12">7–12</REF> are far less numerous than their alignment counterparts, yet the information they yield is essential for a full understanding of the state or states involved in the photodissociation.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">In the work presented here we first employ both linearly and circularly polarised light to probe, <IT>via</IT> (1 + 1′) resonance enhanced multiphoton ionisation (REMPI), the NO photofragment from NO<SB>2</SB> photolysis at 320 nm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">We demonstrate the applicability of time of flight (TOF) spectrometry to extract alignment and orientation parameters on this test system, and compare our orientation results with those previously obtained by Brouard <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF>. using laser induced fluorescence (LIF), and Nesterov and Cline<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF> using ion imaging.</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Secondly, we apply the same method to measure alignment and orientation parameters for the O<SB>2</SB>(a <SP>1</SP>Δ<SB>g</SB><IT>v</IT> = 0 <IT>J</IT> = 20) fragment from the 270 nm photolysis of ozone.</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">We use several (2 + 1) REMPI transitions which involve excitation of the two photon d <SP>1</SP>Π<SB>g</SB>(<IT>v</IT> = 2) ←← a <SP>1</SP>Δ<SB>g</SB> (<IT>v</IT> = 0) transition,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF> and show that by measurement of both alignment and orientation we can confirm the assignments in the highly perturbed rotationally resolved spectrum: spectroscopy through dynamics.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.">Experimental</HEADER><P><s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the photolysis of NO<SB>2</SB>, pulsed radiation at 320 nm was provided by the frequency doubled output of a Nd:YAG pumped tuneable dye laser [Spectra Physics GCR-200 + LAS LDL 2051], while the counter-propagating pulsed probe radiation around 225 nm was from the frequency doubled output of a XeCl excimer pumped dye laser [Lambda Physik EMG 101 MSC + Lambda Physik FL2002], exciting individual rotational lines of the NO A <SP>2</SP>Σ<SP>+</SP> (<IT>v</IT> = 0) ← X<SP>2</SP>Π<SB>Ω</SB> (<IT>v</IT> = 0) band.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The beams were focussed to overlap in the source region of a modified Wiley McLaren TOF mass-spectrometer, into which a room temperature sample of NO<SB>2</SB>, at a backing pressure of around 120 Torr, was injected <IT>via</IT> a pulsed valve.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rotational temperature of the molecular beam was measured to be 150 ± 10 K from the REMPI spectrum of NO expanded through the nozzle under the same conditions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The laser pulses were overlapped temporally as well as spatially to allow a (1 + 1′) REMPI detection scheme whereby both the photolysis and ionising radiation were provided by the 320 nm wavelength light.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The probe light at 226 nm was kept at low intensities to avoid saturation of the strong one-photon resonant transition,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14 cit15">14,15</REF> and the absence of saturation was confirmed by the invariance of the TOF profiles with laser intensity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the studies on ozone the excimer pumped system was used as the 270 nm photolysis laser, with the YAG pumped system providing the photons near 320 nm for the (2 + 1) REMPI of the O<SB>2</SB> a <SP>1</SP>Δ<SB>g</SB> (<IT>v</IT> = 0) product.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Ozone was introduced through the pulsed valve into the mass spectrometer from a room temperature bulb containing approximately 100 Torr of a 1∶1 mixture of ozone and O<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The space-focussed ions were detected by the TOF system following the REMPI pulse as previously described.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The alignment moments were extracted using linearly polarised pump and probe sources.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The polarisation of one laser was fixed with its electric vector at a predetermined angle to the TOF axis, using a polarizing crystal.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The counter-propagating second laser beam was switched between two values of this angle, <IT>θ</IT>, normally 0 and 90° using a photoelastic modulator [Hinds Instruments Inc. PEM-90].</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The extraction of the orientation parameters required a circularly polarised probe beam, which was again provided by the photoelastic modulator.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Here the helicity of the probe beam was switched, with the electric vector of the photolysis beam held at 45° to the TOF axis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Weak single-laser signals were subtracted from the two-laser signal, and all profiles were power normalised by monitoring the intensity of back reflections of the uv light.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">For extraction of the alignment moments, the average of around 1000 time of flight profiles per geometry was found to give a sufficient signal-to-noise ratio.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the photolysis of NO<SB>2</SB> the comparatively small differences between the profiles generated with switched left and right circularly polarised light meant that averages of around 15 000 profiles were required for experiments to determine the orientation moment.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The greater effect on the time of flight profile of the orientation parameter in a (2 + 1) REMPI process compared to that for a (1 + 1′) scheme meant that it was unnecessary to average more than 2000 profiles to extract moments in the ozone experiments.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.">Theory</HEADER><P><s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The intensity and shape of the time of flight profile depends upon both geometric parameters (such as the photolysis and probe lasers' polarisations relative to the time of flight axis and the spectroscopic transition being used) and dynamical parameters (the distributions of the vectors <B><IT>μ</IT></B>, the parent molecule transition moment, <B><IT>v</IT></B>, the fragments' relative velocity and <B><IT>J</IT></B>, the diatomic angular momentum).</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The profile may be described by the expression: where <IT>g</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB> are functions of geometric parameters (relative directions of the laser beams and TOF axis), line strength factors (we refer to the latter as <IT>q</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB>) and moments, <IT>β</IT><IT>K</IT><IT>Q</IT>(<IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB><IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB>), <IT>P</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB>(<IT>x</IT>) are <IT>i</IT><SP><IT>th</IT></SP> order Legendre polynomials, and the variable <IT>x</IT> = <IT>v</IT><SB><IT>z</IT></SB>/<IT>v</IT><SB>0</SB>, where <IT>v</IT><SB><IT>z</IT></SB> is the projection of the fragment velocity along the TOF axis, and <IT>v</IT><SB>0</SB> its speed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The index <IT>i</IT> takes values that are determined by the polarisations of the pump and probe lasers and the number of photons used in the REMPI process.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The line strength factors, <IT>q</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB>, are calculated using the formalism derived by Kummel, Sitz and Zare (KSZ).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The values that we seek are <IT>β</IT><IT>K</IT><IT>Q</IT>(<IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB><IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB>), the moments of the distribution, ie the ensemble averaged values of the distributions of the vector quantities.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The most important of the bipolar moments of even rank are <IT>β</IT>00(22), <IT>β</IT>20(20) and <IT>β</IT>20(02), describing the <B><IT>v</IT></B>–<B><IT>J</IT></B>, <B><IT>μ</IT></B>–<B><IT>v</IT></B> and <B><IT>μ</IT></B>–<B><IT>J</IT></B> pair correlations respectively, and these can be found by analysing the TOF lineshapes taken with judicious choices of angles of the electric vectors of the linearly polarised photolysis and REMPI lasers relative to the TOF axis.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18 cit19 cit20">18–20</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">There are also higher order moments which affect the shape of the time of flight profile, such as <IT>β</IT>20(22) which represents the triple vector correlation between <B><IT>μ</IT></B>, <B><IT>v</IT></B> and <B><IT>J</IT></B>, and their extraction and significance is discussed later.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Maximum sensitivity to the orientation moment is obtained by photolysing with linearly polarised light at an angle of 45° to the TOF axis and taking the difference between TOF profiles with left and right circularly polarised probe radiation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">We give explicitly our expression for Δ<IT>g</IT>(<IT>x</IT>), the difference between left and right circularly polarised signals as a function of the parameter <IT>x</IT>:Δ<IT>g</IT>(<IT>x</IT>) can be quantitatively related to the distribution of ion arrival times, our experimental observations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">We note that Δ<IT>g</IT>(<IT>x</IT>) is for the difference of <IT>normalised</IT> arrival times: in practice we find that the time integrated left and right circularly polarised signals are equal to within experimental error (4%), giving confidence in the successful operation of the photoelastic modulator.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our expression for Δ<IT>g</IT>(<IT>x</IT>) derived from the KSZ formalism<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF> is identical to that derived by Cline <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19">19</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In particular we are able to obtain the orientation moment <IT>β</IT>20(21), which describes the preferred sense of rotation of the diatomic fragment and is defined as <IT>β</IT>20(21) = −2〈sin <IT>θ</IT><SB><IT>t</IT></SB> cos <IT>θ</IT><SB><IT>t</IT></SB> sin <IT>θ</IT><SB><IT>r</IT></SB> sin <IT>ϕ</IT><SB><IT>r</IT></SB>〉 where (<IT>θ</IT><SB><IT>t</IT></SB>,<IT>ϕ</IT><SB><IT>t</IT></SB>) and (<IT>θ</IT><SB><IT>r</IT></SB>,<IT>ϕ</IT><SB><IT>r</IT></SB>) are the polar angles which define the photofragment velocity and angular momentum vectors respectively in the body fixed frame.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6 cit8 cit9">6,8,9</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this frame the fragment recoil velocity lies in the <IT>xz</IT> plane and the <IT>z</IT> axis is parallel to the transition dipole moment <B><IT>μ</IT></B>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, in the case where <IT>θ</IT><SB><IT>t</IT></SB> and <IT>θ</IT><SB><IT>r</IT></SB> are less than 90°, a positive value for <IT>β</IT>20(21) indicates that fragments' angular momentum is oriented preferentially along the −<IT>y</IT> direction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Again higher order odd rank moments appear in eqn. (2), and we discuss their influence later.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.">Results and discussion</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.1">Photodissociation of NO<SB>2</SB> at 320 nm</HEADER><P><s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="New" advantage="None">First, we present data on the nascent NO fragment from the photodissociation of NO<SB>2</SB> at 320 nm recorded using (1 + 1′) REMPI <IT>via</IT> the A state of NO.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="New" advantage="None">Although our emphasis is on the orientation of the NO fragment we discuss first the alignment parameters obtained for photolysis at 320 nm with the linearly polarised probe beam tuned to the P<SB>22</SB> + Q<SB>12</SB>(<IT>N</IT> = 40) transition in the A <SP>2</SP>Σ<SP>+</SP> (<IT>v</IT> = 0) ← X <SP>2</SP>Π<SB>3/2</SB> (<IT>v</IT> = 0) band.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Table 1 shows the results.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">For prompt dissociation of a non-rotating and non-vibrating NO<SB>2</SB> molecule, where the transition moment <B><IT>μ</IT></B> for the <SP>2</SP>B<SB>2</SB>–<SP>2</SP>A<SB>1</SB> band lies in the molecular plane parallel to the line joining the two oxygen atoms, we would expect <B><IT>J</IT></B> to be perpendicular to both <B><IT>μ</IT></B> and <B><IT>v</IT></B>, <IT>i.e.</IT> the correlations with <B><IT>J</IT></B> to be close to their perpendicular limits, and this is seen to be the case in Table 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">If the ground state geometry of NO<SB>2</SB> is preserved in the promptly dissociating excited state we expect the <B><IT>μ</IT></B>–<B><IT>v</IT></B> correlation <IT>β</IT>20(20) = 0.88.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Many previous studies have measured <IT>β</IT>20(20), and have shown that its value is reduced from this limit for the rotating molecule, and depends upon fragment speed (and thus dissociation wavelength).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In LIF experiments probing NO (<IT>v</IT> = 0, <IT>N</IT> = 29) from a thermal sample of NO<SB>2</SB> Brouard <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF>. found <IT>β</IT>20(20) = 0.61 ± 0.02 at a photolysis wavelength of 308 nm, whilst earlier experiments by Baker <IT>et al.</IT> in this group reported <IT>β</IT>20(20) = 0.26 ± 0.14 for photolysis at 355 nm, where the fragment speed is approximately halved.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Baker <IT>et al.</IT> also measured the NO (<IT>v</IT> = 0, <IT>N</IT> = 15) fragment and found that <IT>β</IT>20(20) increased to 0.41 ± 0.06, reflecting the greater energy available for product translation.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">When the same <IT>N</IT> = 15 line was probed in photolysis of a jet cooled (10 K) NO<SB>2</SB> sample, <IT>β</IT>20(20) increased to 0.61 ± 0.15,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF> the same value as that reported by Hradil <IT>et al.</IT> in ion imaging experiments carried out on a 15 K sample.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">These authors noted that their result, the average over several rotational states, was substantially larger than values previously measured<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23 cit24 cit25"><SP>23–25</SP></REF> for samples close to room temperature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The present value of 0.64 ± 0.03 for <IT>N</IT> = 40 at a photolysis wavelength of 320 nm and a sample temperature of 150 K is consistent with previous observations.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">There are fewer previous measurements of other pair correlations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our value of <IT>β</IT>00(22) = −0.42 ± 0.06 is in keeping with previously published results which show <B><IT>v</IT></B> and <B><IT>J</IT></B> to be dominantly perpendicular<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit21 cit25">8,21,25</REF> The value of <IT>β</IT>20(02) = −0.30 ± 0.05 is within experimental error the same as that of Brouard <IT>et al.</IT> (−0.23 ± 0.02) for the same line at 308 nm,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF> but as we would again expect the <B><IT>μ</IT></B>–<B><IT>J</IT></B> correlation to be dependent upon fragment translational energy and parent internal energy, the agreement may be fortuitously dependent upon the cancelling of these two effects in the two studies (room temperature sample, 308 nm photolysis and probing <IT>N</IT> = 29 at room temperature<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF> compared with 320 nm photolysis and probing <IT>N</IT> = 40 at 150 K for the present data).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">We finally note the higher moments in Table 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None"><IT>β</IT>20(22), the triple vector correlation, was found simultaneously with <IT>β</IT>00(22)from the sum and difference of profiles taken with magic angle photolysis and switching the 226 nm beam between <IT>θ</IT> = 0 and 90°.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the <IT>β</IT>20(42) term (which describes a higher order correlation between <B><IT>μ</IT></B>, <B><IT>v</IT></B> and <B><IT>J</IT></B>), profiles were analysed with the photolysis laser polarised parallel to the TOF axis and with <IT>θ</IT> = 0 and 90°: these show an increased sensitivity to this moment.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results are consistent with the pair correlation values of Table 1 and these, together with the pair correlations discussed above serve to give confidence in the analysis procedures employed in these TOF studies.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj5" novelty="New" advantage="None">We now describe the results of experiments with circularly polarised probe radiation to determine the orientation moment <IT>β</IT>20(21).</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj5" novelty="New" advantage="None">Three lines were chosen for study, namely the P<SB>22</SB> + Q<SB>12</SB>(<IT>N</IT> = 40) line discussed above, together with the R<SB>11</SB> + Q<SB>21</SB> (<IT>N</IT> = 30) and P<SB>11</SB> (<IT>N</IT> = 29) features.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">In Figs 1a and 1b we show the sum and difference profiles for left and right circularly polarised 226 nm probe radiation for the R<SB>11</SB> + Q<SB>21</SB> (<IT>N</IT> = 30) and P<SB>11</SB> (<IT>N</IT> = 29) lines, with the 320 nm photolysis laser polarisation at 45° to the TOF axis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Sums and differences are shown to give an idea of the magnitude of the difference between the signals with the two circular polarisations, of the order of 5% at the line centres.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The best fits to the difference profiles are shown, and yield <IT>β</IT>20(21) = 0.26 ± 0.04 and 0.22 ± 0.04 for <IT>N</IT> = 30 and 29 respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the P<SB>22</SB> + Q<SB>12</SB>(<IT>N</IT> = 40) transition we find <IT>β</IT>20(21) = 0.25 ± 0.04.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">We note that in this (1 + 1′) REMPI process the difference profiles are expected to be equal in magnitude but opposite in sign for R and P branches, and this is observed in Fig. 1a and 1b.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Q branches are insensitive to the fragment helicity at these high values of <IT>N</IT>, and hence the contribution of the Q<SB>21</SB> and Q<SB>12</SB> sub-bands to the <IT>N</IT> = 30 and <IT>N</IT> = 40 lines does not affect the difference profiles providing the R or P branch contribution is appropriately normalised.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9 cit19">9,19</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The difference profiles should be zero for the geometries where the photolysis beam electric vector is at 0° or 90° to the TOF axis,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9 cit26">9,26</REF> and an example confirming this is shown in Fig. 1c for the P<SB>22</SB> + Q<SB>12</SB> (<IT>N</IT> = 40) transition and <IT>θ</IT> = 90°.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The contributions of the higher order <IT>β</IT>20(23) and <IT>β</IT>20(43)terms to the difference profile were neglected in our analysis, as the value of <IT>q</IT><SB>3</SB> in eqn. (2) is zero for a (1 + 1′) REMPI process when the ionisation efficiency is assumed to be independent of fragment alignment.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">We find the <IT>β</IT>20(21) moment to be insensitive to the three quantum states probed, with a state averaged value of 0.24 ± 0.04.</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is in excellent agreement with the results of ion imaging studies by Nesterov <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF>. at 355 nm in which the NO<SB>2</SB> sample was cooled in a molecular beam, (<IT>β</IT>20(21) = 0.2 for levels probed with the P<SB>11</SB> (<IT>N</IT> = 36) and R<SB>21</SB> (<IT>N</IT> = 21) lines) and with the LIF studies by Brouard <IT>et al.</IT> at 308 nm<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF> which employed a room temperature sample and measured <IT>β</IT>20(21) = 0.22 ± 0.04 for the same P<SB>11</SB> (<IT>N</IT> = 29) transition as measured here.</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">It appears that the orientation is little affected by parent angular momentum, as the three studies used markedly different NO<SB>2</SB> rotational temperatures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">We note that in the work by Cline the A state of NO was ionised using a third colour whereas in this work, we use the photolysis laser to ionise NO from the intermediate A state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Saturation of the first excitation step would lead to an apparently reduced magnitude of the moments measured, but the good agreement between our values of <IT>β</IT>20(21) and the alignment moments compared with those of previous work again suggests that we avoid saturation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results are qualitatively in accord with the expectation that the impulse given by the departing O atom acts on the N end of NO, causing rotation with <B><IT>J</IT></B> pointing in the <IT>−y</IT> direction<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit9">8,9</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.2">Photodissociation of O<SB>3</SB> at 270 nm</HEADER><P><s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj6" novelty="New" advantage="None">Having established the consistency of the results obtained from our experimental method with those measured previously, we now turn to the photolysis of ozone.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">At a photolysis wavelength of 270 nm the dominant dissociation channel produces O<SB>2</SB> in the low lying first excited state, a <SP>1</SP>Δ<SB>g</SB>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27 cit28">27,28</REF> and Fig. 2 shows a section of the (2 + 1) d <SP>1</SP>Π<SB>g</SB>(<IT>v</IT> = 2) ←← a <SP>1</SP>Δ<SB>g</SB> (<IT>v</IT> = 0) REMPI spectrum of nascent O<SB>2</SB> around 320 nm, with assignments from the recent analysis of Morrill <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The d <SP>1</SP>Π<SB>g</SB>(<IT>v</IT> = 2) upper level is perturbed by curve crossings with the nearby II <SP>1</SP>Π<SB>g</SB> valence state,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF> and this results in a highly irregular band structure, with branches split into a number of spectrally distinct sections.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The S and R branches shown in Fig. 2 however have <IT>J</IT> values around 20 which are highly populated in the photolysis of ozone at 270 nm,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29">29</REF> and the lines in the nascent spectrum are not markedly overlapped by other transitions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Photodissociation at 270 nm in the Hartley band proceeds by two spin allowed routes forming O<SB>2</SB>(a <SP>1</SP>Δ<SB>g</SB>) + O(<SP>1</SP>D) and O<SB>2</SB>(X <SP>3</SP>Σ<SB>g</SB><SP>−</SP>) + O(<SP>3</SP>P) in the ratio 0.9∶0.1 respectively.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27 cit28 cit29">27–29</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The curve crossing on the excited state potential that leads to formation of the X <SP>3</SP>Σ<SB>g</SB><SP>−</SP> state of O<SB>2</SB> is allowed only for odd J states.</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">This results in a selective depletion of species with odd J in the rotational distribution of the O<SB>2</SB>(a <SP>1</SP>Δ<SB>g</SB>) product, a result first demonstrated in the CARS experiments of Valentini and co-workers.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29 cit30">29,30</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although populations are difficult to extract from the highly perturbed REMPI spectra, the data of Fig. 2 do show an intensity alternation, with depletion of the intensities of lines with odd J. For example, in Fig. 2 the intensity of the S(19) line is considerably below that of the neighbouring S(20) and S(18) lines, whereas for a REMPI spectrum taken under conditions where the population alternation is absent (for example, Fig. 6 of <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">ref. 13</REF>) the S(19) intensity is higher than those of its neighbours.</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">A similar effect is seen in the R and in the (more congested) O branch of Fig. 2.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">We focus first on the two (2 + 1) REMPI transitions shown in Fig. 2 at the probe laser wavelengths of 320.499 nm and 320.821 nm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our wavelength scale for the transitions is in accord with the energies given by Morrill <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF>. to within the precision of our laser wavelength step size (0.002 nm).</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The lines have been assigned as S(20) and R(20) transitions respectively<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF> and we again show first the results of experiments with linearly polarised photolysis and probe beams.</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Table 2 collects data for the two transitions taken (as for NO<SB>2</SB>) with appropriate combinations of photolysis and probe polarisations, and shows good agreement amongst the values of the alignment moments for the two probe transitions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The constancy of such data confirms the assignments of Morrill <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF>. for these two lines, and we illustrate this confirmation in the analysis of data in Figs. 3a and 3b.</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj7" novelty="New" advantage="None">Here we see the effect of switching the polarisation of the REMPI laser from <IT>θ</IT> = 0 to 90°, whilst holding the photolysis laser at the magic angle of 54.7° to the TOF flight axis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj7" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">This experimental geometry is sensitive mainly to the bipolar moment <IT>β</IT>00(22), <IT>i.e.</IT> the <B><IT>v</IT></B>–<B><IT>J</IT></B> correlation.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">We see that the difference profiles are of opposite sign in the two cases, exactly as expected for S and R branch transitions, with a smaller difference for the R branch as expected from the relative values of the line strength factors <IT>q</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Probing on an S branch transition will therefore yield a higher sensitivity to the <B><IT>v</IT></B>–<B><IT>J</IT></B> correlation moment <IT>β</IT>00(22), as seen in the slightly lower error limit of Table 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fits to the data with the assumption that the lines are identified as S(20) and R(20) respectively return a common and physically reasonable value of <IT>ca.</IT> −0.26 for the <IT>β</IT>00(22) bipolar moment, indicating the velocity and angular momentum of the diatomic photofragment are dominantly perpendicular (although not as marked as in the case of NO<SB>2</SB>).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The higher order terms listed in Table 2 were obtained in a similar way to that described for NO<SB>2</SB> photolysis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition however it was necessary to involve moments <IT>β</IT><IT>K</IT><IT>Q</IT>(<IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB><IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB>) with the index <IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB> = 4.</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">These moments have a particularly marked effect on the R branch transition of a (2 + 1) REMPI process, as reflected in the flatter profile near <IT>x</IT> = 0 in Fig. 3b compared with the shape of the S branch in Fig. 3a, and their values were consistent with the lower order moments shown in Table 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">If we neglect the moments with <IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB> = 4, we find for example values of <IT>β</IT>00(22) = −0.16 ± 0.2 and −0.21 ± 0.08 for the R(20) and S(20) lines respectively, and a comparison of these values with the data of Table 2 indicates the large effect for the R branch, together with a change in the error limits for the less affected S branch.</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None">We also note that the widths of the profiles are consistent with these assignments: the width depends upon the translational energy release in the photolysis, and its value gives an estimate of the O<SB>2</SB> internal energy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The resultant energy resolution for these data at <IT>J</IT> = 20 can be estimated as corresponding to Δ<IT>J</IT> = ±3, by no means of high spectroscopic quality, but useful again for confirmation of the assignment.</annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The other alignment moments in Table 2 for <IT>J</IT> = 20 are consistent with a parallel transition followed by prompt dissociation, as for NO<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our reported values for the <B><IT>μ</IT></B>–<B><IT>v</IT></B> correlation, <IT>β</IT>20(20), are in broad agreement with previously published data on the molecular fragment from photofragment translational spectroscopy (0.8 ± 0.1, 275 − 295 nm)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit31">31</REF> and time-of-flight studies within this group<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit32">32</REF> (0.65 ± 0.07 at 290 nm) and on the atomic fragment <IT>via</IT> photofragment spectroscopy (0.50 ± 0.05, 274 nm),<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27">27</REF> VUV LIF (0.56 ± 0.06, 266 nm)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit33">33</REF> and ion imaging (0.75 ± 0.08, 265 nm; 0.80 ± 0.08, 275 nm).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit34">34</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The variation in magnitude of <IT>β</IT>20(20) within these studies can again be attributed to varying rotational temperatures of the parent O<SB>3</SB> molecule.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22 cit33">22,33</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Qualitative indications of perpendicular alignment of <B><IT>v</IT></B> and <B><IT>J</IT></B> vectors in the Hartley band dissociation of ozone have been reported in our previous TOF measurements,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit32">32</REF> and in the ion imaging experiments by Suits <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit35">35</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" advantage="None">In Table 2 we also include measurements on the O(24) line at 321.810 nm, which also appears to be isolated in Fig. 2 (we are unable to study O(20) because of spectral congestion).</annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Once again the analysis as an O branch line yields similar alignment parameters to those for the S and R branch lines.</annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Measurements of these vector correlations at different wavelengths in the Hartley band, as a function of <IT>J</IT>, and on transitions in the (1,0) as well as the (2,0) d <SP>1</SP>Π<SB>g</SB> ←← a <SP>1</SP>Δ<SB>g</SB> band will be described elsewhere:<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit36">36</REF> in this work we concentrate only on even values of <IT>J</IT> for photolysis at 270 nm.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">We now turn our attention to the orientation parameter <IT>β</IT>20(21).</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 4 shows measurements on the S(20) and R(20) features of Fig. 2, again with the electric vector of the photolysis laser at 45° to the TOF axis and with circularly polarised probe radiation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Differences between profiles taken with left and right circularly polarised light should now show the same sign for S and R branches (the dominant <IT>q</IT><SB>1</SB> term in eqn. (2) is the same sign for the two branches), as experimentally observed, and in contrast to the linearly polarised example shown in Fig. 3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs20" novelty="None" advantage="None">We also note the magnitude of the difference is considerably larger than for the NO case of Fig. 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although part of this is because of a larger value of <IT>β</IT>20(21) (see below), we note that the orientation effect is much more easily observed using a (2 + 1) REMPI scheme, as the geometric factors, <IT>q</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB>, for probing the orientation moment <IT>β</IT>20(21) are considerably greater than for (1 + 1′) REMPI.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs21" novelty="None" advantage="None">Lineshapes observed with linearly polarised light allows straightforward differentiation between branches with different values of |Δ<IT>J</IT>|, <IT>i.e.</IT> the S and R branches shown in Fig. 3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs22" novelty="None" advantage="None">With linearly polarised light however it is not straightforward to distinguish between O and S branch transitions as the sensitivity to branches with |Δ<IT>J</IT>| = 2 is the same.</annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs22" novelty="None" advantage="None">They may be differentiated when circular polarisation is employed, as shown in Fig. 4c.</annotationART></s> <s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Here we measure correlations on the O(24) transition at 321.810 nm and observe a change in sign of the difference profiles compared with the S branch, confirming the assignment of Morrill <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although the present measurements are on lines where the assignments are robust, we suggest that the use of this “spectroscopy through dynamics” method of determining the magnitude and sign of Δ<IT>J</IT> and also the magnitude of <IT>J</IT> (within rather wide error bars) will be useful in the assignment of the more perturbed and overlapped regions of the spectrum.</annotationART></s> <s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">For example, on the strong feature at 321.451 nm in Fig. 2, noted as a P branch head, we measure a value of <IT>β</IT>00(22) = −0.07 ± 0.07 when it is analysed as a pure P branch transition, a result which is incompatible with the values of <IT>ca.</IT> −0.27 obtained earlier.</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Part of this discrepancy may be explained by overlap with O branch features at this wavelength,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF> as the two branches in linear polarisation will have difference spectra which have opposite signs.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj8" novelty="New" advantage="None">We now consider the values of the <IT>β</IT>20(21) bipolar moment, and turn first to the S(20) transition.</annotationART></s> <s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ratio <IT>q</IT><SB>1</SB>/<IT>q</IT><SB>3</SB> in eqn. (2) is 4.5, which in combination with the premultiplier factors means that the effect of the higher moment terms is negligible (for example, the coefficient of <IT>β</IT>20(23) is only 6% of that for <IT>β</IT>20(21)).</annotationART></s> <s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">Extraction of <IT>β</IT>20(21) for this and similarly for the O(24) line is therefore straightforward and yields values of 0.55 ± 0.04 and 0.60 ± 0.04 respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the R(20) line the magnitude of the coefficient of <IT>β</IT>20(23) is now 30% of that for <IT>β</IT>20(21), and we should not neglect higher terms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs23" novelty="None" advantage="None">However we find that our returned values of <IT>β</IT>20(21) are relatively insensitive to the absolute magnitudes the two higher terms in eqn. (2), because their coefficients are of opposite sign and their effects tend to cancel.</annotationART></s> <s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">For example, if we set <IT>β</IT>20(21) equal to 0.57, the average value found from the S and O branch measurements, and vary both <IT>β</IT>20(23) and <IT>β</IT>20(43) in fitting the sum and difference profiles of the R branch line we find values of −0.32 and +0.80 respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">If we neglect the higher moments we obtain a value of <IT>β</IT>20(21) = 0.65 ± 0.02, close to our value when higher moments are taken into account, and illustrating the cancelling effect.</annotationART></s> <s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None">We should note however that although we are insensitive to the absolute values of these higher moments, we are sensitive to their ratio.</annotationART></s> <s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the limiting case when <B><IT>μ</IT></B> and <B><IT>v</IT></B> are perpendicular to <B><IT>J</IT></B>, then we can express<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF><IT>β</IT>20(23)/<IT>β</IT>20(43) = −√15/8 = −0.48, and this is close to our observed ratio of −0.40.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs24" novelty="None" advantage="None">We see good agreement with the values of the orientation moment <IT>β</IT>20(21) for the three branches.</annotationART></s> <s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our value for the S(20) line, 0.55, is approximately twice those observed from the photolysis of NO<SB>2</SB> but of the same sign, indicating again the dominance of the recoil effect on the central atom in determining the sense of the product rotation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None">The magnitude of the impulse delivered by the departing O atom is approximately the same for the photolysis of both parent molecules, with the departing NO and O<SB>2</SB> fragments both having speeds of approximately 1000 ms<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The difference in <IT>β</IT>20(21) values remains to be explained in terms of the appropriate angles described in eqn. 3 and we hope that measurements such as these will stimulate trajectory calculations on the latest <IT>ab initio</IT> surfaces<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit37">37</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="5.">Conclusions</HEADER><P><s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res29" novelty="None" advantage="None">Photolysis of a thermal sample of NO<SB>2</SB> at 320 nm produces NO(X <SP>2</SP>Π) fragments whose average orientation parameter, <IT>β</IT>20(21), is 0.24 ± 0.04.</annotationART></s> <s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res30" novelty="None" advantage="None">The orientation parameter is found to be essentially independent of the quantum state probed and our results are in excellent agreement with complementary investigations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" advantage="None">Studies on the O<SB>2</SB> (a <SP>1</SP>Δ<SB>g</SB>) fragment produced from photolysis of O<SB>3</SB> at 270 nm show that this fragment is also oriented but now the orientation is markedly larger with <IT>β</IT>20(21) ≈ 0.6.</annotationART></s> <s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have been able to make use of angular momentum polarisation to confirm spectral assignments of the highly perturbed O<SB>2</SB> d <SP>1</SP>Π<SB>g</SB>(<IT>v</IT> = 2) ←← a <SP>1</SP>Δ<SB>g</SB> (<IT>v</IT> = 0) REMPI spectrum.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
