<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b312859h" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Possible induced enhancement of dispersion forces by cellular phones<XREF TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" /></annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">We derive the dispersion forces between objects in the presence of a non-thermal radiation field.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">We apply the formalism to a model system representing two human blood cells in blood.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">By focusing the same radiation density, as in room-temperature thermal radiation, in the microwave region we find a huge enhancement of the attractive force.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Related effects are predicted to occur also in other types of biological tissue.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The quantitative results should not be taken at face value, since the model is crude.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The effects are so large though, that further investigation is motivated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The origin of the effects lies in the variation of water and/or ion content.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the microwave region of the spectrum both the dipolar contributions from the water-molecules, and the mobile-ion contributions are important parts of the dielectric function, and cause the enhancement.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="I.">Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The dispersion forces between two objects can be expressed in terms of the electromagnetic normal modes of the system.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">These forces are van der Waals forces<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">2</REF> at intermediate separation and Casimir forces<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3 cit4">3,4</REF> at large separations.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">We know how the forces behave at zero and finite temperatures but we do not fully understand the behavior in non-equilibrium situations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is a well-known fact that gradients of optical fields can produce forces on microscopic dielectric objects.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">This effect is utilized in so-called optical tweezers.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Optical binding between two dielectric objects in the presence of a strong optical field was discussed and demonstrated by Burns <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Other related studies have been performed investigating the van der Waals force involving excited state atoms.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit9 cit10">8–10</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The work by Burns <IT>et al.</IT> is an example of virtual excitations of the normal modes; the other studies involve real electronic excitations within one of the two interacting objects, not excitations of the normal modes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">In the present work<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF> we study the effects of real excitations of the normal modes of the system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus the present work complements the previous studies.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The outline of the article is the following.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="New" advantage="None">In section II we derive the force between two objects at zero temperature in terms of the electromagnetic normal modes; in this case the modes are not occupied.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">In section III we extend the derivation to finite temperatures where the modes are in equilibrium with the thermal radiation field; in this case the modes are occupied according to the distribution function for mass-less bosons at the given temperature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In section IV we use a Lorentzian distribution function.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="New" advantage="None">In section V we concentrate on spherical objects.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In section VI we let the Lorentzian distribution function be peaked in the microwave region and apply the theory to the force between two water drops, between two air bubbles in water and finally between two human blood cells in blood.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Section VII is a summary and conclusion section.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="II.">Forces at zero temperature</HEADER><P><s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">At zero temperature the force, fo(<IT>r</IT>), between two objects as a function of separation, <IT>r</IT>, is given by the derivative of the energy, <IT>E</IT>: where the energy is the sum of the zero-point energies of the modes, </annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The modes are of two types: one type is localized to the surfaces of the objects and gives rise to the van der Waals interaction; one type extends between the objects and gives rise to the Casimir interaction (see <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">ref. 1</REF>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In a simple system with a small number of well-defined modes this summation can be performed directly.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the general case this is not so.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Then we can rely on an extension of the so-called argument principle to find the results.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Let us study a region in the complex frequency plane.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have two functions defined in this region; one, <IT>φ</IT>(<IT>z</IT>), is analytic in the whole region; one, <IT>f</IT>(<IT>z</IT>), has poles and zeros inside the region.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The following relation holds for an integration path around the region: where <IT>z</IT><SB>0</SB> and <IT>z</IT><SB>∞</SB> are the zeros and poles, respectively, of function <IT>f</IT>(<IT>z</IT>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the argument principle the function <IT>φ</IT> is replaced by unity and the right hand side then equals the number of zeros minus the number of poles for function <IT>f</IT>(<IT>z</IT>) inside the integration path.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">If we choose the function <IT>f</IT>(<IT>z</IT>) to be the function in the defining equation for the normal modes of the system,<IT>f</IT>(<IT>ω</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB>) = 0,the function <IT>φ</IT> (<IT>z</IT>) to beand let the contour enclose all the zeros of the function <IT>f</IT>(<IT>z</IT>), eqn. (3) produces the energy of eqn. (2).</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Using this theorem we end up integrating along a closed contour in the complex frequency plane.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In most cases it is fruitful to choose the contour shown in Fig. 1.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have the freedom to multiply the function <IT>f</IT> (<IT>z</IT>) by an arbitrary constant without changing the result on the right hand side of eqn. (3).</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">If we choose it carefully we can make the contribution from the curved part of the contour vanish and we are only left with an integration along the imaginary frequency axis: where the last line was obtained from an integration by parts.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">This needs some clarification.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The function <IT>f</IT>(<IT>z</IT>) contains polarizabilities or other time-correlation functions representing the response of the system one is treating.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">These functions approach zero as the argument goes towards infinity since there is an upper limit for the frequency the system can respond to.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Consequently <IT>f</IT>(<IT>z</IT>) approaches a constant and after we have rescaled the function it approaches unity and the value of the logarithm approaches zero.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">One further property of <IT>f</IT>(<IT>z</IT>) we should mention is that on the imaginary axis it is an even function of its argument; this is a general property of the time-correlation functions contained in <IT>f</IT>(<IT>z</IT>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">We will refer to this property below.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="III.">Forces at thermal equilibrium</HEADER><P><s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The contribution to the internal energy from the interaction between two objects separated by the distance <IT>r</IT> can in general be written as:where the index <IT>i</IT> runs over all electromagnetic modes of the system and <IT>n</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB> and <IT>ε</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB> are the occupation number and energy, respectively, of the mode number <IT>i</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Let us now concentrate on one of the modes and omit the indexNote that the occupation number <IT>n</IT>(<IT>r</IT>) is a function of energy or frequency and becomes a function of <IT>r</IT> because the mode energy depends on <IT>r</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">An infinitesimal change in <IT>r</IT> modifies <IT>E</IT> both because of the change in mode energy and because of the change in occupation number The first term is due to mechanical work and the second to heat exchange with the surroundings.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The free energy <IT>Θ</IT> = <IT>E</IT> − <IT>Φ</IT> is the quantity that determines the force.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Let us now determine <IT>Φ</IT> and <IT>Θ</IT> where on the last line we have omitted the constant.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The energy functions are relative to some arbitrary reference level.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">We usually choose this to be the value at infinite separation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus the free energy is where on the last line we have identified the result as the Helmholtz free energy.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The force is </annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">This was the contribution from one of the modes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The total contribution to the Helmholtz free energy is We make the observation that we may use the argument principle but now with ln[2sinh(<IT>βħz</IT>/2)]/<IT>β</IT> instead of <IT>ħz</IT>/2 for <IT>φ</IT>(<IT>z</IT>) in the integrand.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">There is however one complication.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">This new function has poles of its own in the complex frequency plane.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have to choose our contour so that it includes all poles and zeros of the function <IT>f</IT>(<IT>z</IT>) but excludes those of <IT>φ</IT>(<IT>z</IT>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The poles of function <IT>φ</IT>(<IT>z</IT>) all are on the imaginary frequency axis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">We use the same contour as in Fig. 1., but now let the straight part of the contour lie just to the right of, and infinitesimally close to, the imaginary axis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have The coth function has poles on the imaginary <IT>z</IT>-axis and they should not be inside the contour.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The poles are at and all residues are the same, equal to 2/<IT>ħβ</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">We integrate along the imaginary axis and deform the path along small semicircles around each pole.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The integration path is illustrated in Fig. 2.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The integration along the axis results in zero since the integrand is odd with respect to <IT>ω</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The only surviving contributions are the ones from the small semicircles.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The result is Since the summand is even in <IT>n</IT> (see comment at the end of Section II) we can write this as where the prime on the summation sign indicates that the <IT>n</IT> = 0 term should be multiplied by a factor of one half.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">This factor of one half is because there is only one term with |<IT>n</IT>| = 0 in the original summation but two for all other integers.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">When the temperature goes to zero the spacing between the discrete frequencies goes to zero and the summation may be replaced by an integration: and we regain the contribution to the internal energy from the interactions, the change in zero-point energy of the modes, as given in eqn. (6).</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="IV.">Forces at non-thermal equilibrium</HEADER><P><s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the absence of thermal equilibrium the occupation numbers are different from the Bose–Einstein ones for mass-less bosons and the summation along the imaginary frequency axis will no longer be the same.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The summation points came from the poles of the distribution function.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">We want a narrow distribution function that is peaked in the microwave region of the spectrum where the cellular phones operate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">We want a distribution function that is peaked in a narrow energy range and has poles that give rise to feasible calculations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">A Gaussian distribution function would seem like a good candidate but it does not fulfil these criteria; it has an infinite number of poles on the imaginary axis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">We instead choose a Lorentzian distribution function.</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Let us now specify our choice of <IT>n</IT>(<IT>ω</IT>): <IT>n</IT>(<IT>ω</IT>) = i<IT>A</IT>[(<IT>ω</IT> − <IT>ω</IT><SB>0</SB> + i<IT>B</IT>)<SP>−1</SP> − (<IT>ω</IT> − <IT>ω</IT><SB>0</SB> − i<IT>B</IT>)<SP>−1</SP> + (<IT>ω</IT> + <IT>ω</IT><SB>0</SB> + i<IT>B</IT>)<SP>−1</SP> − (<IT>ω</IT> + <IT>ω</IT><SB>0</SB> − i<IT>B</IT>)<SP>−1</SP>]This function is real-valued on the real frequency axis and is a sum of two Lorentzian functions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">This function has the proper analytic properties and symmetries of a distribution function.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The energy or frequency where the distribution is focused is given by <IT>ω</IT><SB>0</SB> and the width of the distribution by <IT>B</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The function has two poles in the right half plane; it is an even analytic function on the imaginary frequency axis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our integration contour will now consist of the contour in Fig. 1., and two small circles clockwise around the two poles of the distribution function.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="New" advantage="None">The integrand will be derived next.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Using eqns. (7), (10) and (11) gives </annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">We first assume that we have an explicit expression for the second term of the free energy: </annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Then we may write: and we may use the argument principle again and get one contribution from the integration along the contour of Fig. 1. and one from the contribution of the small circles around the poles of the distribution function: <IT>Θ</IT>(<IT>r</IT>) = <IT>Θ</IT><SB>1</SB>(<IT>r</IT>) + <IT>Θ</IT><SB>2</SB>(<IT>r</IT>), and <IT>Θ</IT><SB>2</SB>(<IT>r</IT>) = i<IT>ħA</IT>[ln <IT>f</IT>(<IT>ω</IT><SB>0</SB> − i<IT>B</IT>) − ln <IT>f</IT>(<IT>ω</IT><SB>0</SB> + i<IT>B</IT>)]Thus in eqn. (24) we have a similar expression to that for the equilibrium case for <IT>T</IT> = 0 in eqn. (6), but now with a factor <IT>n</IT> + 1/2 instead of just 1/2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that the occupation number is evaluated on the imaginary frequency axis.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="V.">Forces between spherical objects</HEADER><P><s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj5" novelty="New" advantage="None">We will now limit the treatment to the interaction between two spherical objects at large and intermediate separations where the dipole-dipole interaction is dominant.</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">We limit the treatment to the van der Waals region.</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Then the mode defining function is (see <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">ref. 1</REF>)<IT>f</IT>(<IT>z</IT>) = [1 − <IT>α</IT><SB>1</SB>(<IT>z</IT>)<IT>α</IT><SB>2</SB>(<IT>z</IT>)/<IT>r</IT><SP>6</SP>]<SP>2</SP>[1 − 4<IT>α</IT><SB>1</SB>(<IT>z</IT>)<IT>α</IT><SB>2</SB>(<IT>z</IT>)/<IT>r</IT><SP>6</SP>]and the free energy is</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod11" novelty="None" advantage="None">In eqns. (27) and (28) we have expanded the logarithm for small arguments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Now the polarizability for the spherical object <IT>i</IT> in some ambient medium, a, is where <IT>R</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB> is the radius of the object and <IT>ε</IT><SB>a</SB>(<IT>ω</IT>) the dielectric function of the ambient medium.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="VI.">Numerical results</HEADER><P><s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj6" novelty="New" advantage="None">We now apply the theory to some systems where the objects have a water content differing from that of the ambient medium.</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Water is strongly active in the microwave region due to the permanent dipole moments of the water molecule.</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">This property is the basis of the microwave oven.</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The field induces rotations of the molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rotational energy is transformed into heat, due to the internal friction of water.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj7" novelty="New" advantage="None">We study two water drops, two air bubbles in water, and two blood cells in blood.</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The dielectric properties of water have been studied extensively and are available in the literature.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">We need these data both on the imaginary frequency axis for eqn. (27) and at general points of the complex frequency plane for eqn. (28).</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The measured values are of course on the real frequency axis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The values on the imaginary axis can be obtained from the knowledge of the imaginary part, <IT>ε</IT><SB>2</SB>(<IT>ω</IT>) on the real frequency axis from a generalization of the Kramers–Kronig dispersion relations, derived from general properties of analytical functions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The relation is For a general point, <IT>ω</IT> = <IT>a</IT> + i<IT>b</IT>, in the complex frequency plane the relations for the real part <IT>ε</IT><SB>1</SB> (<IT>ω</IT>) and imaginary part, <IT>ε</IT><SB>2</SB>(<IT>ω</IT>), are </annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod13" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of water drops the dielectric function for the ambient medium in eqn. (29) is unity and <IT>ε</IT><SB>i</SB>(<IT>ω</IT>) is the dielectric function of water.</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that the index <IT>i</IT> here runs over the two drops and does not represent real and imaginary parts.</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod14" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of air bubbles in water the ambient dielectric function is that of water and <IT>ε</IT><SB>i</SB>(<IT>ω</IT>) is unity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results for two water drops are shown in Fig. 3 and the corresponding results for two bubbles in water are shown in Fig. 4.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this work the main objective is the force between two human red blood cells in blood.</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">To be able to perform a reliable, quantitative, calculation of the effects on the force between objects one needs to know the dielectric function in the full spectral range, both for the objects and for the ambient medium.</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the information we have is limited we are restricted to rather crude model calculations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The dielectric properties of blood in the range of 10 Hz to 100 GHz are known.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The data for red blood cells<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF> are sparser, though.</annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod15" novelty="None" advantage="None">We model the cell as a spherical object of radius <IT>R</IT> enclosed by a membrane; the radius of a human red blood cell is 4.5 μm and the thickness of the cell membrane is 8 nm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod15" novelty="None" advantage="None">We assume that the membrane has the same dielectric parameters as the cell membrane of a white blood cell of B-type.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The interior is treated as homogeneous and we adjust the water and ion content of the cytoplasm so that the real and imaginary parts of the dielectric function for the cell agree with the few available, measured values;<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF> we end up with a water content of 75% and obtain the value 0.525 S m<SP>−1</SP> for the conductivity from the ions; these values seem reasonable.</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">We should be more specific with the dielectric functions used for the blood and blood cells.</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="Old" advantage="None">For the blood we use the expression in eqn. (4) of .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">ref. 13</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod16" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is valid for frequencies up to 100 GHz and consists of four terms; the first is the high-frequency asymptote; the second is the rotational contribution from water molecules; the third is the rotational contribution from larger entities; the fourth is the contribution from all mobile ions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac20" novelty="None" advantage="None">The authors of <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">ref. 13</REF> adjusted the eight parameters to give a good fit to the experimental data.</annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac21" novelty="None" advantage="None">The red blood cell consists of a membrane enclosing the cytoplasm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac21" novelty="None" advantage="None">We thus need the dielectric properties of these two materials.</annotationART></s> <s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Here we use just two of the terms discussed above, the first and the fourth, just as in eqn. (3) of <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">ref. 15</REF> with parameter values given in that reference.</annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod17" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the cytoplasm we keep in principle the first, second and fourth terms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The two first terms we replace by 1 + <IT>F</IT>[<IT>ε</IT><SB><IT>w</IT></SB>(<IT>ω</IT>) − 1], where <IT>F</IT> is the fraction of water and <IT>ε</IT><SB>w</SB>(<IT>ω</IT>) is the dielectric function of water.</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod17" novelty="None" advantage="None">This gives us two parameters to vary, <IT>viz.</IT>, <IT>F</IT> and the parameter of the fourth term of the dielectric function, the static conductivity of the mobile ions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The effective dielectric function of the blood cell we determine along the lines of eqns. (4)–(6) of <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">ref. 15</REF>, where we remove the effects from the nucleus.</annotationART></s> <s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac22" novelty="None" advantage="None">The red blood cells have no nucleus.</annotationART></s> <s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod18" novelty="None" advantage="None">We then vary the two parameters, to get a good fit to the experimental imaginary and real parts of the dielectric function of a red blood cell.</annotationART></s> <s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fit is seen in Fig. 5.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have probably got good enough estimates of the dielectric properties of blood and cells for the spectral range up to 100 GHz, but we need the properties also for higher frequencies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">We lack this information.</annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac23" novelty="None" advantage="None">We know the dielectric function of water<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF> in the whole spectral range.</annotationART></s> <s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac23" novelty="None" advantage="None">The most characteristic feature of this dielectric function is the large contribution from Debye<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit17">1,17</REF> rotational relaxation in the microwave region.</annotationART></s> <s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="New" advantage="None">We model the dielectric function of the cell and of blood by letting them be equal to the function for water for high frequencies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The functions used are displayed in Fig. 5.</annotationART></s> <s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The solid, dashed and dotted curves are the imaginary parts of the dielectric function for the cell, for blood and for water, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac24" novelty="None" advantage="None">The circles are the experimental values for the cell from .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">ref. 14</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The short piece of solid curve is our real part of the dielectric function for the cell compared to the experimental values from <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">ref. 14</REF>, indicated by the squares.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The energy density at the surface of a black-body radiator at 300 K is approximately 6 × 10<SP>−6</SP> J m<SP>−3</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The corresponding radiative power is 46 mW cm<SP>−2</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="New" advantage="None">We choose a Lorentzian function peaked at the photon energy 3.5 × 10<SP>−6</SP> eV and with a FWHM of 5% of the peak energy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results are found to be insensitive to the peak width.</annotationART></s> <s sid="143"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="New" advantage="None">We have let the strength of the distribution be such that the energy density in the radiation field is 1 × 10<SP>−6</SP> J m<SP>−3</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="144"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The corresponding radiative power is 7.5 mW cm<SP>−2</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="145"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac25" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus we have chosen a slightly weaker radiation than that of the black-body radiator.</annotationART></s> <s sid="146"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The numerical values used for <IT>ω</IT><SB>0</SB>, <IT>B</IT> and <IT>A</IT> are 5.32 × 10<SP>9</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>, 1.33 × 10<SP>8</SP> s<SP>−1</SP> and 2.95 × 10<SP>24</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>, respectively.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="147"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">In Fig. 6 we show the result, the upper solid curve, for the interaction potential in the microwave field.</annotationART></s> <s sid="148"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">For comparison we have included the room temperature result, middle curve, and one in the absence of radiation, lower curve.</annotationART></s> <s sid="149"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">To give the reader a feeling for the strength of the potential we have added two reference potentials: The first is the dash-dotted curve.</annotationART></s> <s sid="150"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is the unscreened potential between two unit charges; in a colloid the particles become charged and typically attain a charge of the order of 100 unit charges, but the resulting repulsive potential between the particles becomes screened by the counterions in the solution and the net potential is strongly reduced and also short range.</annotationART></s> <s sid="151"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, a comparison between the repulsive Coulomb potential and the attractive dispersion potential, induced by the microwave field, should be made towards the left in the figure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="152"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The second reference potential is the short horizontal line in the figure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="153"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">It represents the energy 6<IT>k</IT><SB>B</SB><IT>T</IT> for room temperature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="154"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">This number is an estimate used to determine if a potential barrier is large enough to prevent the particles from overcoming it through the Brownian motion.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="155"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met14" novelty="New" advantage="None">The force between the cells is obtained by taking the derivative of the potential with respect to separation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="156"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Doing this we find that the force ranges from 0.15 μN at the small-separation end of the figure to 1.5 zN<SUP TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn2" /> at the large-separation end.</annotationART></s> <s sid="157"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The potential and force resulting from the microwave radiation can not be considered negligible in comparison with other forces experienced by the blood cells.</annotationART></s> <s sid="158"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The lowest curve in the figure is the result without radiation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="159"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">This potential comes entirely from the zero-point energy of the normal modes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="160"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac26" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is only of academic interest since it corresponds to absolute zero temperature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="161"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac26" novelty="None" advantage="None">The thermal radiation enhances the interaction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="162"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">At room temperature the radiation causes an enhancement of the potential and force at intermediate separations of several orders of magnitude.</annotationART></s> <s sid="163"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The enhancement at microwave radiation is much more impressive.</annotationART></s> <s sid="164"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">It gives an additional enhancement of ten orders of magnitude.</annotationART></s> <s sid="165"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The photon energy where the microwave radiation is concentrated is indicated by a bar at the bottom of Fig. 5.</annotationART></s> <s sid="166"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">We see that the energy or frequency is here low enough for the mobile ions to contribute to the screening.</annotationART></s> <s sid="167"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ion contribution is of the Drude-tail type and varies as <IT>ω</IT><SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="168"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The enhancement of the force in the microwave region is probably due to both ion contributions and contributions from rotations of the water molecules.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="169"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the calculations for water drops and for bubbles in water we found strong enhancement of the force but not as strong as the result in Fig. 6.</annotationART></s> <s sid="170"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">In these two cases the ion contributions are absent but the rotational contributions are stronger and there are contributions from the whole spectral range including the infrared and ultraviolet regions.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="VII.">Summary and conclusions</HEADER><P><s sid="171"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj8" novelty="New" advantage="None">To summarize, we have gone beyond the approximation of treating cellular phones as black-body radiators, which is usually done in setting the radiation standards.</annotationART></s> <s sid="172"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met15" novelty="New" advantage="None">We have focused the radiation power to a peak in the microwave region.</annotationART></s> <s sid="173"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj9" novelty="New" advantage="None">We have studied the effect of this radiation on the attractive part of the force between two blood cells in blood using a simplified model for the dielectric properties of the system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="174"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">We found an enhancement of the force by ten orders of magnitude when changing the radiation spectrum from thermal to one that is peaked in the microwave region.</annotationART></s> <s sid="175"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the results depend on the water and ion content in the blood and blood cells and since these vary between individuals and also depend on the person's health status the effects can vary from person to person.</annotationART></s> <s sid="176"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Another possible result from the radiation could be that thin blood vessels contract and thereby limit the flow of blood through them; the surface energy of the blood vessel might increase drastically making a contraction energetically favorable.</annotationART></s> <s sid="177"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Still other unwanted effects could be growth of precipitates in tissue and organs, in the eye for example.</annotationART></s> <s sid="178"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">At this stage it is only speculation.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="179"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac27" novelty="None" advantage="None">A word of caution: The present work should not be considered as a proof of that cellular phones are harmful.</annotationART></s> <s sid="180"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac27" novelty="None" advantage="None">It shows that there may be effects not considered before.</annotationART></s> <s sid="181"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">The weakness of the model calculations lies in the incomplete input data for the dielectric properties of biological tissue and in the description of the radiation field.</annotationART></s> <s sid="182"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac28" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have not taken into account that the field may be polarized; in a polarized field the forces between the two cells also depend on their relative orientation with respect to the polarization direction; the force may be repulsive for some orientations and even more strongly attractive for others.</annotationART></s> <s sid="183"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac29" novelty="None" advantage="None">In general, the force induced by a radiation field has attractive and repulsive contributions from different parts of the spectral range.</annotationART></s> <s sid="184"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">The origin of the enhancement, we have found, for the interaction between the cells is that the energy density in the radiation field has been concentrated in a spectral range where the contributions are attractive.</annotationART></s> <s sid="185"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">The result is not sensitive to the particular choice of distribution as long as it is peaked at the same spectral position.</annotationART></s> <s sid="186"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met16" novelty="Old" advantage="None">We have used a Lorentzian distribution function because it has only two poles in the right half of the complex frequency plane, giving rise to the two terms in eqn. (28).</annotationART></s> <s sid="187"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met17" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The Bose–Einstein distribution function for thermal radiation has an infinite number of poles giving rise to the infinite number of terms in eqn. (17).</annotationART></s> <s sid="188"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac30" novelty="None" advantage="None">Had we used a Gaussian distribution function we would also have ended up with an infinite number of terms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="189"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac30" novelty="None" advantage="None">The final result would have been similar but the mathematics more cumbersome and the treatment less transparent.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="190"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hopefully this study will stimulate efforts to measure the dielectric properties of all components in biological tissue over the full spectral range, making more realistic studies feasible.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
