<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b315071b" hasDoc="yes" version="1184" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Environmental effects on a conical intersection: A model study</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Excited-state processes at conical intersections (CIs) involving charge transfer phenomena can depend sensitively on the influence of a polar and polarizable environment.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="None" advantage="None">We propose here a formulation to describe the chromophore–environment interaction for such situations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In a model study, we focus on an extension of the two-electron two-orbital model by V. Bonačić-Koutecký, J. Koutecký, and J. Michl [<IT>Angew. Chem., Int. Ed. Engl.</IT>, 1987, <B>26</B>, 170], which yields a diabatic model for the S<SB>1</SB>–S<SB>0</SB> CI in protonated Schiff bases and related systems, and describes the charge properties and charge translocation phenomena associated with this CI.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The electrostatic effects of the environment, which are expected to strongly affect the CI topology, are accounted for by a dielectric continuum model.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This translates to the image of free energy surfaces for the coupled chromophore–environment system represented by molecular coordinates plus a solvent coordinate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">The environment's impact on the location and character of the CI is investigated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The limiting situations of “frozen” and equilibrium solvation effects are examined.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="1.">Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Conical intersections (CIs), <IT>i.e.</IT>, multidimensional, cone-like topological structures at degeneracies between Born–Oppenheimer surfaces, are known to play a key role in the ultrafast dynamics of photoexcited molecular systems.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2 cit3 cit4">1–4</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Their great relevance for biochemical and biological systems has been confirmed over the past decades.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6">5,6</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">By their particular topology, CIs act as “photochemical funnels” which effectively and selectively induce transitions between electronic states.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">While such processes have been extensively studied in gas phase species, the influence of an environment on conical intersections has not yet been systematically investigated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">For example, the recent study involving two of us in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7 cit8 cit9">refs. 7–9</REF> is the first explicit investigation of solvent effects on the ground state reaction path near a CI, and the QM/MM type calculational approaches of <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10 cit11">refs. 10, 11</REF> provide an avenue to the microscopic description of both ground and excited states in an environment.</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">In the present contribution, we discuss a new approach to modeling the environment's influence on the excited-state processes at a conical intersection.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The importance of understanding environmental effects on the processes at and near CIs is highlighted by a number of recent studies of biologically relevant systems, notably the chromophores of the rhodopsin family<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12 cit13 cit14">12–14</REF> and other photoactive proteins,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15 cit16 cit17 cit18 cit19 cit20">15–20</REF> porphyrin-quinone complexes,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF> as well as the building blocks of DNA.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22 cit23">22,23</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">These studies reveal the crucial role of CIs and suggest that a solvent or protein environment has a pronounced impact on the electronic structure and CI topology.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Due to the environment, CIs can indeed be substantially displaced, or may even disappear.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Given the complexity of these systems, a key step in the theoretical analysis is to select the relevant features which determine the energetics and dynamics of the chromophore–environment supermolecular system.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None">In the present work, we focus on situations where the CI involves a charge transfer process and therefore couples strongly to the environment's electrostatic properties.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is of relevance, in particular, for the S<SB>1</SB>–S<SB>0</SB> CI in protonated Schiff bases (PSBs) like retinal, which plays a key role in the chromophore's <IT>cis</IT>–<IT>trans</IT> isomerization and can be associated with the translocation of a positive charge.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Charge transfer has also been shown to characterize the earliest events in the photoactive yellow protein, PYP, photocycle.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">The theoretical model developed within is designed to capture the electrostatic aspects of the chromophore–environment interaction and is thus specifically adapted to such situations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">At the level of description adopted here (which allows for considerable generalization), the model involves (i) a description of the environment as a dielectric continuum (Section 2) which translates to a solvent coordinate picture, previously exploited in models for charge transfer reactions strongly coupled to large amplitude nuclear motion, see <IT>e.g.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7 cit25 cit26 cit27 cit28 cit29">refs. 7, 25–29</REF>, in conjunction with (ii) a representation of the chromophore's electronic structure in a diabatic basis of states which are constructed such as to preserve their charge character in the nonadiabatic coupling region.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This type of basis is best adapted to formulate the interaction with a polar and polarizable environment.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">(The term diabatic is here meant in a loose sense, to describe a basis which has “smooth” properties and approximately diagonalizes the nuclear kinetic energy operator.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2">1,2</REF>)</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this first effort, we focus on a simple realization of such a basis in terms of valence bond (VB) type states suitable for the description of PSBs, as an extension of the two-electron two-orbital model by Bonačić-Koutecký, Koutecký, and Michl<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6 cit24 cit30">5,6,24,30</REF> (Section 3).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The description of the environment as a dielectric continuum leads to an augmented electronic structure problem yielding free energies; the latter carry a parametric dependence on the chromophore's internal degrees of freedom plus a solvent coordinate representing the environmental polarization field.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The solvent coordinate thus appears as an additional degree of freedom which, for the coupled free energy surfaces at the CI, plays a substantial role in determining the CI topology and the concerted chromophore–environment dynamical path.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="New" advantage="None">In the present context, we examine the two extreme cases of a “frozen” solvent <IT>vs.</IT> equilibrium solvation situation (Section 4).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">While the present work focusses on the case of a small chromophore in solution phase, the theoretical framework we are developing is generalizable to take into account the specific nature of the environment, by referring to microscopic solvent coordinate concepts,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit31 cit32 cit33 cit34">31–34</REF> with emphasis on the environment's heterogeneous character.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">This opens up an avenue to treat very general types of system–environment situations, in particular (i) complex molecular systems, even gas phase species, characterized by a local site which interacts with an intramolecular “bath” involving charged and polarizable groups, and (ii) large molecules in a solvent environment, where the local site of interest interacts with an effective environment comprising intramolecular and solvent components.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">For a chromophore embedded in a protein <IT>via</IT> electrostatic, hydrogen bonding and covalent interactions, the local environment bears features of both cases (i) and (ii).</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The present work maps out the very first steps towards such complex environments.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The paper is organized as follows.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Section 2 addresses the general theoretical formulation leading to a free energy surface description of the combined chromophore–environment system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Section 3 introduces the extended two-electron two-orbital model we use to describe the coupled S<SB>1</SB>–S<SB>0</SB> states in protonated Schiff bases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">In Section 4, we address the charge properties, free energy surfaces, and solvent effects for the CI model.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Section 5 summarizes some future perspectives and concludes.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.">Free energy formulation for the combined chromophore–environment system</HEADER><P><s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">We adopt a description of the environment <IT>via</IT> a dielectric continuum model, <IT>i.e.</IT>, the environment is described in terms of a polarization field interacting with the electric field created by the solute.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The polarization field can be represented as the sum of two components, <B><IT>P</IT></B>(<B><IT>x</IT></B>) = <B><IT>P</IT></B><SB>el</SB>(<B><IT>x</IT></B>) + <B><IT>P</IT></B><SB>or</SB>(<B><IT>x</IT></B>) where <B><IT>x</IT></B> denotes a field point in the solvent, and the sum refers to an electronic (“fast”) component <B><IT>P</IT></B><SB>el</SB> associated with the electronic solvent degrees of freedom and an orientational (“slow”) component <B><IT>P</IT></B><SB>or</SB> associated with the solvent dipoles' reorientation in response to the solute field.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">This latter component determines the <IT>non-equilibrium</IT> effects in the solvation dynamics: There is no requirement in general that the orientational polarization be in equilibrium with the molecular solute's charge distribution in its dynamical evolution.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">As detailed in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit35 cit36">refs. 35 and 36</REF>, the interacting solute–solvent system can be characterized <IT>via</IT> a free-energy functional <IT>G</IT>[<IT>ψ</IT><SB>el</SB>, <B><IT>P</IT></B><SB>el</SB>, <B><IT>P</IT></B><SB>or</SB>].</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Here, the interaction with the environmental polarization fields is added to the molecular electronic Hamiltonian, thus defining an augmented electronic structure problem.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Minimization of <IT>G</IT> yields solutions which depend parametrically on two types of “slow” variables: the internal nuclear coordinates of the chromophore <B><IT>R</IT></B>, and the slow polarization component <B><IT>P</IT></B><SB>or</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">These solutions <IT>G</IT>(<B><IT>R</IT></B>,<B><IT>P</IT></B><SB>or</SB>) are adiabatic free energies, by analogy with the adiabatic energies of the conventional wavefunction description.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Importantly, a nonequilibrium process can be described in terms of the dynamics on such free energy surfaces <IT>G</IT>(<B><IT>R</IT></B>,<B><IT>P</IT></B><SB>or</SB>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">This necessitates the introduction of a kinetic energy for <B><IT>P</IT></B><SB>or</SB>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25 cit26 cit37 cit38 cit39 cit40 cit41">25,26,37–41</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Time scales of nonequilibrium solvation are generally similar to the internal molecular degrees of freedom dynamics: picoseconds to femtoseconds.</annotationART></s></P><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.1.">Free energies in the Born–Oppenheimer limit for the electronic polarization</HEADER><P><s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">While the solution to the combined solute–solvent electronic structure problem is non-trivial, and in general necessitates a quantum treatment of the electronic polarization field<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit35">35</REF>, we focus here on a particular limiting situation: The solvent electronic polarization adjusts rapidly to the solute's electronic configuration and can therefore be adiabatically eliminated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">In electron transfer language, the electronic polarization is fast compared to the transferring electron.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">This limit is characterized by the condition 2<IT>β</IT>/ℏ<IT>ω</IT><SB>el</SB> ≪ 1 in terms of the electronic coupling <IT>β</IT>, which sets the electron transfer time scale, and the characteristic solvent electronic polarization energy ℏ<IT>ω</IT><SB>el</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">This condition is applicable to an important class of charge transfer reactions in various solvents.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">This Born–Oppenheimer (BO) limit<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit35 cit42">35,42</REF> leads to the following, simplified, form of the free energy functional<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit35">35</REF><IT>G</IT><SB>BO</SB>[<IT>ψ</IT><SB>el</SB>, <B><IT>P</IT></B><SB>or</SB>] = <IT>H</IT><SB>mol</SB>[<IT>ψ</IT><SB>el</SB>,<B><IT>P</IT></B><SB>or</SB>] + <IT>G</IT><SB>int</SB>[<IT>ψ</IT><SB>el</SB>,<B><IT>P</IT></B><SB>or</SB>] + <IT>G</IT><SB>el</SB>[<IT>ψ</IT><SB>el</SB>] + <IT>G</IT><SB>or</SB>[<B><IT>P</IT></B><SB>or</SB>]with the following contributions:</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">(i) the expectation value of the electronic Hamiltonian <IT>H</IT><SB>0</SB> of the isolated molecular system, <IT>H</IT><SB>mol</SB>[<IT>ψ</IT><SB>el</SB>,<B><IT>P</IT></B><SB>or</SB>] = 〈<IT>ψ</IT><SB>el</SB>|<IT>H</IT><SB>0</SB>|<IT>ψ</IT><SB>el</SB>〉for the solution phase solute electronic wavefunction <IT>ψ</IT><SB>el</SB>(<B><IT>x</IT></B><SB>el</SB>;<B><IT>R</IT></B>,<B><IT>P</IT></B><SB>or</SB>) which has a parametric dependence on the nuclear degrees of freedom <B><IT>R</IT></B> and on the orientational polarization field <B><IT>P</IT></B><SB>or</SB>;</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">(ii) the solute–solvent interaction <IT>G</IT><SB>int</SB>, <IT>i.e.</IT>, interaction between the polarization <B><IT>P</IT></B><SB>or</SB> and the solute electric field <SB><IT>ψ</IT></SB>, <IT>G</IT><SB>int</SB>[<IT>ψ</IT><SB>el</SB>,<B><IT>P</IT></B><SB>or</SB>] = –(1 – 4π<IT>C</IT>–1el)∫ d<B><IT>x</IT></B> <SB><IT>ψ</IT></SB>·<B><IT>P</IT></B><SB>or</SB>where <IT>C</IT><SB>el</SB> = 4π<IT>ε</IT><SB>∞</SB>/(<IT>ε</IT><SB>∞</SB> – 1), with <IT>ε</IT><SB>∞</SB> the optical dielectric constant;</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">(iii) the electronic polarization contribution <IT>G</IT><SB>el</SB>, for an electronic polarization <B><IT>P</IT></B><SB>el</SB> field which instantaneously equilibrates to the solute electric field <SB><IT>ψ</IT></SB>, </annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">(iv) the orientational self-free energy contribution <IT>G</IT><SB>or</SB>, with <IT>C</IT><SB>or</SB> = 4π(1 + <IT>ε</IT><SB>0</SB> – <IT>ε</IT><SB>∞</SB>)/(<IT>ε</IT><SB>0</SB> – <IT>ε</IT><SB>∞</SB>) where <IT>ε</IT><SB>0</SB> is the static dielectric constant.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">We note that the free energies resulting from minimizing the functional eqn. (2) can be formulated as the eigenvalues of an effective Hamiltonian.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit35">35</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the above expressions, the electric field <SB><IT>ψ</IT></SB> generated by the solute is<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit35 cit36">35,36</REF> <SB><IT>ψ</IT></SB>(<B><IT>x</IT></B>; <B><IT>R</IT></B>) = –∇<IT>φ</IT>(<B><IT>x</IT></B>; <B><IT>R</IT></B>) with the potential produced at point <B><IT>x</IT></B> in the solvent by the solute electronic density <IT>ρ</IT>(<B><IT>x</IT></B>′;<B><IT>R</IT></B>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The latter is the single-particle density derived from the electronic wavefunction, <IT>ρ</IT>(<B><IT>x</IT></B><SB>1</SB>; <B><IT>R</IT></B>) = <IT>N</IT>∫ d<B><IT>x</IT></B><SB>2</SB>…d<B><IT>x</IT></B><SB><IT>N</IT></SB> <IT>ψ</IT><SB>el</SB>(<B><IT>x</IT></B><SB>1</SB>,…,<B><IT>x</IT></B><SB><IT>N</IT></SB>;<B><IT>R</IT></B>)<IT>ψ</IT><SB>el</SB>*(<B><IT>x</IT></B><SB>1</SB>,…,<B><IT>x</IT></B><SB><IT>N</IT></SB>; <B><IT>R</IT></B>)</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">We will focus within on the case where the wavefunction is expressed in a basis of states {<IT>ϕ</IT><SB><IT>j</IT></SB>(<B><IT>x</IT></B><SB>el</SB>;<B><IT>R</IT></B>)}, each of which corresponds to a fixed charge distribution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">These states are what we term valence bond (VB) states and constitute an appropriate basis for including the interaction with the external polarization fields.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The solute charge distribution can thus be written<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28 cit35 cit36">28,35,36</REF> with component densities <IT>ρ</IT><SB><IT>ij</IT></SB>(<B><IT>x</IT></B><SB>1</SB>,<B><IT>R</IT></B>) = <IT>N</IT>∫ d<B><IT>x</IT></B><SB>2</SB>…d<B><IT>x</IT></B><SB><IT>N</IT></SB><IT>ϕ</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB>(<B><IT>x</IT></B><SB>1</SB>,…<B><IT>x</IT></B><SB><IT>N</IT></SB>;<B><IT>R</IT></B>) × <IT>ϕ</IT>*<SB><IT>j</IT></SB>(<B><IT>x</IT></B><SB>1</SB>,…,<B><IT>x</IT></B><SB><IT>N</IT></SB>;<B><IT>R</IT></B>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">This partitioning carries over to the potential <IT>φ</IT> = ∑<SB><IT>ij</IT></SB> <IT>φ</IT><SB><IT>ij</IT></SB> and to the electric field, <SB><IT>ij</IT></SB> = –∇<IT>φ</IT><SB><IT>ij</IT></SB>, such that the solute–solvent interaction takes the form.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, components of the interaction free energy can be associated with the field generated by the component solute charge distributions <IT>ρ</IT><SB><IT>ij</IT></SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The orientational polarization also couples to the off-diagonal components <IT>i</IT> ≠ <IT>j</IT>, corresponding to the “exchange” field components,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit35">35</REF> giving rise to off-diagonal terms in the diabatic representation for the free energy and leading to a diabatic coupling renormalization<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit35 cit36 cit43 cit44">35,36,43,44</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.2.">Solvent coordinate formulation</HEADER><P><s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The interaction free energy partitioning eqn. (10) is taken as a basis to define solvent coordinates associated with each component.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit35 cit36">35,36</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">To calculate the individual contributions, knowledge of the nonequilibrium polarization field <B><IT>P</IT></B><SB>or</SB> is required, and necessitates approximations in the absence of a complete representation of the field.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">One useful approach is the representation of <B><IT>P</IT></B><SB>or</SB> in terms of <IT>linear combinations of equilibrium contributions</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In particular, the nonequilibrium polarization can be expressed, in a chemical reaction context, in terms of a single solvent coordinate <IT>z</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit37 cit41">37,41</REF> which weights the equilibrium contributions in the reactant (<IT>R</IT>) and product (<IT>P</IT>) states, <B><IT>P</IT></B><SB>or</SB>(<B><IT>x</IT></B>;<B><IT>R</IT></B>) = (1 – <IT>z</IT>)<B><IT>P</IT></B>eqor,<IT>R</IT>(<B><IT>x</IT></B>;<B><IT>R</IT></B>) + <IT>z</IT><B><IT>P</IT></B>eqor,<IT>P</IT>(<B><IT>x</IT></B>;<B><IT>R</IT></B>) Here, the off-diagonal components <IT>i</IT> ≠ <IT>j</IT> of eqn. (10) have been neglected.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit35">35</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">(We will later identify <IT>R</IT> and <IT>P</IT> in the CI context).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">With eqn. (11) for the polarization field, the “Marcus-like” free energy parabolas are obtained, displaced along the solvent coordinate <IT>z</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The free energies of eqn. (12), denoted by a subscript <IT>s</IT>, comprise components in the interaction free energy <IT>G</IT><SB>int</SB> of eqn. (4), the electronic solvent free energy <IT>G</IT><SB>el</SB> of eqn. (5), and the orientational self free energy <IT>G</IT><SB>or</SB> of eqn. (6).</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The <IT>G</IT><IT>R</IT>,<IT>P</IT>eq(<B><IT>R</IT></B>) are the equilibrium free energies for the <IT>R</IT> and <IT>P</IT> states, <IT>i.e.</IT>, the free energies with <B><IT>P</IT></B><SB>or</SB> equilibrated to the charge distributions in <IT>R</IT> and <IT>P</IT>, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The “solvent force constant” is <IT>k</IT><SB>s</SB>(<B><IT>R</IT></B>) = <IT>k</IT>0<IT>s</IT>∫<IT>d</IT><B><IT>x</IT></B>[<B><IT>P</IT></B>eqor(<B><IT>x</IT></B>, <B><IT>R</IT></B>) – <B><IT>P</IT></B>eqor, <IT>P</IT>(<B><IT>x</IT></B>, <B><IT>R</IT></B>)]<SP>2</SP>, with <IT>k</IT>0<IT>s</IT> = 4π/(1 – <IT>ε</IT><SB>∞</SB>/<IT>ε</IT>), and is directly related to the reorganization energy <IT>λ</IT>(<B><IT>R</IT></B>) = <IT>k</IT><SB>s</SB>(<B><IT>R</IT></B>)/.2<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit37 cit41">37,41</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that all relevant quantities – in particular, the equilibrium polarization fields, the solvent force constant, and the reorganization energy – carry a dependence on the internal molecular coordinates <B><IT>R</IT></B>, due to the solute electric field <SB><IT>ψ</IT></SB> dependence on <B><IT>R</IT></B>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.">A model for the S<SB>1</SB>–S<SB>0</SB> conical intersection in protonated Schiff bases</HEADER><P><s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Conical intersections of charge transfer type, <IT>i.e.</IT>, involving a transition between an ionic and a covalent state, constitute a generic class of conical intersections in polar double bond systems.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit45">45</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Among these, as anticipated in the Introduction, protonated Schiff bases (PSBs) may be considered a paradigm example, for which S<SB>1</SB>–S<SB>0</SB> isomerization can proceed <IT>via</IT> a CI, for both the CC and CN bonds.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6 cit24 cit30 cit46">5,6,24,30,46</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">While the chromophores in question in fact exhibit a complicated electronic structure, with various CIs of different types, notably of one-bond flip (OBF) and hula-twist (HT) type,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit45">45</REF> we focus here exclusively on an OBF mechanism which only involves a twist around the CC double bond, rather than a concerted twist/flip process for several neighboring bonds.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The CIs in question occur at a twisted geometry of the double bond – often close to 90°<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30 cit47 cit48 cit49 cit50">30,47–50</REF> or, according to our model, at exactly 90°<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24 cit30">24,30</REF> – and thus correspond to a biradicaloid structure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The two-electron two-orbital model developed by Bonačić-Koutecký and Michl<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24 cit30">24,30</REF> in the late 80s explains the occurrence of such CIs by a degeneracy, at a biradicaloid geometry, of a covalent (“dot–dot”) and ionic (“hole-pair”) type configuration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">A key observation of the model is that the electronegativity difference across the double bond, measured by a parameter <IT>δ</IT>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24 cit30">24,30</REF> determines whether a CI can actually be found: With increasing values of <IT>δ</IT>, the S<SB>1</SB> state is stabilized until an S<SB>1</SB>/S<SB>0</SB> degeneracy is met at a threshold value.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The model thus explains that, while no CI is found for twisted ethylene (<IT>δ</IT> = 0), in the absence of asymmetric perturbations as induced, <IT>e.g.</IT>, by pyramidalization, CIs do occur for PSBs.</annotationART></s></P><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.1.">Two-state model including solvent</HEADER><P><s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The relevant PSB electronic configurations can be represented in an approximate fashion in a basis of localized p orbitals, which are best adapted to the biradicaloid structure at the twisted geometry.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">A minimal model for the S<SB>1</SB>–S<SB>0</SB> conical intersection can be formulated in terms of the two singlet states<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24 cit30">24,30</REF> with the notation A ≡ p<SB>A</SB> and B ≡ p<SB>B</SB> for two p orbitals on neighboring carbon centers, and |Σ〉 = (1/√2)(α<SB>1</SB>β<SB>2</SB> – β<SB>1</SB>α<SB>2</SB>) the singlet spin configuration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The |AB〉 state corresponds to the dot–dot configuration mentioned above while the |B<SP>2</SP>〉 state is one of two hole-pair configurations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">(The complementary |A<SP>2</SP>〉 configuration is assumed to be shifted to high energies, due to the effect of the asymmetry parameter <IT>δ.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24 cit30">24,30</REF>)</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">A detailed description of the model is given in .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit51">ref. 51</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The two configurations eqn. (13) have different locations of the positive excess charge carried by the PSBs.</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">If one thinks of the following partitioning in terms of the left and right hand PSB moieties (see also <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit49 cit47">refs. 49, 47</REF>), where the vertical bar indicates a cut through the CC double bond, the charge characteristics of the basis states may be described in a short-hand notation,<IT>i.e.</IT>, the positive charge is localized on the nitrogen end for the |AB〉 state and on the hydrocarbon end for the |B<SP>2</SP>〉 state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">A charge <IT>translocation</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF> therefore takes place upon the transition between these two states.</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The {|AB〉,|B<SP>2</SP>〉} states represent a charge-localized, valence bond (VB) type basis, and provide a simple realization of a more general type of diabatic representation which preserves the basis states' charge character in the nonadiabatic coupling region.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">At the 90° twisted geometry, the |AB〉 and |B<SP>2</SP>〉 states are uncoupled due to symmetry reasons<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit51">51</REF> and describe biradicaloid configurations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Twisting away from <IT>θ</IT> = 90° induces a non-zero overlap and, hence, π-binding effects between the p orbitals on neighboring centers, such that the |AB〉 and |B<SP>2</SP>〉 states are mixed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The twisting coordinate <IT>θ</IT> therefore acts as a <IT>coupling</IT>, or <IT>symmetry-breaking</IT>, coordinate.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24 cit30 cit51">24,30,51</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The solution phase diabatic free energy model we adopt takes the following form, where the coordinate <IT>r</IT> (associated with CC stretch motion) plays the role of a <IT>tuning</IT> coordinate,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF> which only contributes to the diagonal terms and thus modulates the energy gap between the two diabatic states.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The solvent coordinate <IT>z</IT> also acts as a tuning coordinate <IT>via</IT> the diagonal terms in eqn. (16).</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Generally, the electronic coupling <IT>γ</IT>(<IT>θ</IT>) is not identical to the coupling in the isolated chromophore; it also includes the interaction with the orientational polarization field eqn. (10), <IT>γ</IT>(<IT>θ</IT>) = <IT>γ</IT><SB>0</SB>(<IT>θ</IT>) – (1 – 4π<IT>C</IT>–1el)∫d<B><IT>x</IT></B> <SB>ex</SB>·<B><IT>P</IT></B><SB>or</SB><IT>via</IT> the “exchange” field component <SB>ex</SB> related to the off-diagonal component density <IT>ρ</IT><SB><IT>ij</IT></SB> with <IT>i</IT> = |AB〉 and <IT>j</IT> = |B<SP>2</SP>〉.</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">(We have suppressed the explicit dependence of <IT>γ</IT> on <B><IT>P</IT></B><SB>or</SB>(<B><IT>x</IT></B>;<IT>r</IT>,<IT>θ</IT>) in the notation).</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The solvent-induced component thus leads to a renormalization<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit35">35</REF> of the coupling.</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac20" novelty="None" advantage="None">Further, at a CI, the solvent-induced coupling can have a symmetry-breaking effect: <IT>i.e.</IT>, a coupling can be induced by the solvent for <IT>θ</IT> = 90° while <IT>γ</IT><SB>0</SB>(<IT>θ</IT> = 90°) = 0 by symmetry for the isolated chromophore.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac20" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this case, the CI is shifted away from <IT>θ</IT> = 90°.</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac21" novelty="None" advantage="None">We consider this type of effect no further here.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The model eqn. (16) should be taken to correspond to the simplest scenario which gives a qualitatively correct picture for the S<SB>1</SB>–S<SB>0</SB> intersection in PSBs.</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac22" novelty="None" advantage="None">Different interpretations are currently given as to whether an effective two-mode model is in fact viable to describe the dynamics in various retinal analogs and other PSBs.</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac22" novelty="None" advantage="None">While Robb, Olivucci and co-workers indeed supported a two-state-two-mode model in their recent work,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit49">49</REF> Martínez and co-workers<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit47">47</REF> provided evidence that, besides the torsion and the CC stretching mode (or a concerted stretching motion across the PSB carbon skeleton), the C–N stretch plays an important role in the branching space of the S<SB>1</SB>–S<SB>0</SB> conical intersection.</annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our model could be extended in view of these findings.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.2.">Parameterization of the model</HEADER><P><s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The model eqn. (16) is parameterized in an approximate fashion for the internal modes (<IT>r</IT>, <IT>θ</IT>) and solvent coordinate <IT>z</IT>; Table 1 lists the relevant parameter values.</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac23" novelty="None" advantage="None">While we do not explicitly make contact with the electronic structure side in the present study, we suggest as a future strategy to fit <IT>ab initio</IT> data to the model under consideration.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The diagonal contributions <IT>V</IT><SB>AB</SB>(<IT>r</IT>,<IT>θ</IT>) and <IT>V</IT><SB>B<SP>2</SP></SB>(<IT>r</IT>,<IT>θ</IT>) in eqn. (16) include (i) a Morse form in the stretch coordinate <IT>r</IT>, (ii) a <IT>θ</IT>-dependent shift term which displaces the minimum of the Morse potential for increasing <IT>θ</IT>, and (iii) a diagonal angle-dependent term chosen according to the study by Tennyson and Murrell for ethylene.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit52">52</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hence, <IT>V</IT><SB>AB</SB>(<IT>r</IT>,<IT>θ</IT>) = <IT>V</IT>ABmorse(<IT>r</IT>) + <IT>V</IT>ABshift(<IT>r</IT>,<IT>θ</IT>) + <IT>V</IT>AB<IT>θ</IT>(<IT>θ</IT>)with the individual terms<IT>V</IT>ABmorse(<IT>r</IT>) = <IT>D</IT><SB>AB</SB>(1 – exp[–<IT>α</IT><SB>AB</SB> (<IT>r</IT> – <IT>r</IT><SB>0,AB</SB>)])<SP>2</SP>where <IT>r</IT><SB>0,AB</SB> is the CC equilibrium distance at the planar geometry, and an angle dependent shift potential<IT>V</IT>ABshift(<IT>r</IT>,<IT>θ</IT>) = <IT>ξ</IT><SB>AB</SB>(<IT>r</IT>)sin<SP>2</SP><IT>θ</IT>which is adjusted to shift the minimum of the Morse curve to its appropriate value at <IT>θ</IT> = 90°.</annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Here, <IT>ξ</IT><SB>AB</SB>(<IT>r</IT>) = <IT>c</IT>ABshift (<IT>r</IT> – <IT>r</IT><SB>0,AB</SB>)exp(–|<IT>r</IT> – <IT>r</IT><SB>0,AB</SB>|/<IT>σ</IT><SB><IT>r</IT></SB>) with <IT>c</IT>ABshift = –2<IT>D</IT><SB>AB</SB><IT>α</IT>2ABΔ<IT>r</IT><SB>AB</SB>, for a shift Δ<IT>r</IT><SB>AB</SB> in the minimum geometry.</annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note the exponential which is added to attenuate the effect of the linear term for increasing distance from the minimum geometry.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Further, the diagonal contribution in the torsion is given as<IT>V</IT>AB<IT>θ</IT>(<IT>θ</IT>) = <IT>c</IT>AB<IT>θ</IT>cos<SP>2</SP><IT>θ</IT>with <IT>c</IT>AB<IT>θ</IT> &lt; 0 such that the diabatic ground-state potential is bonding for <IT>θ</IT> = 0°, see .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit52">ref. 52</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Similarly, the diagonal potential for the hole-pair state |B<SP>2</SP>〉 reads , with definitions analogous to eqns. (19), (20) and (21), in addition to an energy shift Δ<IT>E</IT><SB>B<SP>2</SP></SB> with respect to the |AB〉 state.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The coupling between the |AB〉 and |B<SP>2</SP>〉 states is given as <IT>γ</IT>(<IT>θ</IT>) = <IT>c</IT>(1)<IT>γ</IT>cos <IT>θ</IT> + <IT>c</IT>(3)<IT>γ</IT>cos<SP>3</SP><IT>θ</IT>in accordance with the models developed for ethylene by Domcke, Manthe and co-workers<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit53">53</REF> and, for the contribution in cos <IT>θ</IT>, by Tennyson and Murrell.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit52">52</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac24" novelty="None" advantage="None">The physical origin of the term in cos <IT>θ</IT> is a resonance integral, proportional to the overlap between the p orbitals on the neighboring centers;<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24 cit54">24,54</REF> the third-order term should be understood as a higher-order correction conforming to the required symmetry.</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj5" novelty="New" advantage="None">We restrict the present analysis to the term in cos <IT>θ</IT>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Finally, the solvent free energies <IT>G</IT>ABs and correspond to two displaced parabolas in accordance with eqn. (12), with the <IT>same</IT> equilibrium free energies and force constants <IT>k</IT><SB>s</SB>, The free energies eqn. (23) are analogous to, <IT>e.g.</IT>, the model developed in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit55 cit56">refs. 55, 56</REF> for charged polyenes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">An estimate for the solvent force constant <IT>k</IT><SB>s</SB> = 2<IT>λ</IT><SB>s</SB> (here assumed to be independent of the internal coordinates), with <IT>λ</IT><SB>s</SB> the solvent reorganization energy, can be obtained from the Marcus–Born model<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit37 cit41">37,41</REF> where the solute charge distribution is surrounded by a cavity in the dielectric continuum.</annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reorganization energy <IT>λ</IT><SB>s</SB> is then related to the work required to transfer charges from the reactant to the product cavity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Here, a value of <IT>k</IT><SB>s</SB> = 2.5 eV is used, which has been derived for acetonitrile<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF> but is also applicable in an approximate fashion to other solvents.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.">Two-state model for the coupled S<SB>0</SB>/S<SB>1</SB> states in PSBs</HEADER><P><s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The following analysis is based on the two-state, three-mode model of eqn. (16), with the twisting coordinate <IT>θ</IT> as a coupling mode, the CC stretch coordinate <IT>r</IT> as a tuning mode, and the solvent coordinate <IT>z</IT> as an additional tuning mode.</annotationART></s> <s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj6" novelty="New" advantage="None">We will successively address the resulting potential surfaces and their topology for the isolated chromophore (Section 4.1), the associated charge distributions resulting from the mixing of the {|AB〉,|B<SP>2</SP>〉} states and their decoupling at the 90° twisted geometry (Section 4.2), and the inclusion of the solvent (Section 4.3).</annotationART></s></P><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.1.">Potentials</HEADER><P><s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 1 shows the coupled S<SB>1</SB> and S<SB>0</SB> surfaces for the isolated chromophore, obtained by diagonalizing the matrix eqn. (16) excluding the solvent contribution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The surfaces feature a CI at <IT>θ</IT> = 90°, which coincides with the minimum of the upper adiabatic surface.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 2a shows a cut of the potential surface along the torsional coordinate, at a value of the CC stretch coordinate corresponding to the intersection point, <IT>r</IT> = <IT>r</IT>0CI.</annotationART></s> <s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The cut illustrates that while the coupling vanishes for <IT>θ</IT> = 90°, the diabatic <IT>vs.</IT> adiabatic surfaces increasingly diverge when moving towards the planar geometry.</annotationART></s> <s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 2b shows a complementary cut for the CC stretch potential at the 90° twisted geometry.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac25" novelty="None" advantage="None">We pause to note that while our analysis focuses on the conical intersection region, the work by Robb, Olivucci and co-workers<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit48 cit49">48,49</REF> shows that the earliest dynamical events in the isomerization of short-chain retinal analogs (subsequent to the Franck–Condon (FC) excitation to S<SB>1</SB> at planar geometry) involve a pronounced displacement in the skeletal stretching modes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac26" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our perspective relates to the second phase of the dynamical process which predominantly involves a displacement in the torsional coordinate, towards the conical intersection point.</annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this context, we note that the upper adiabatic surface of our model does not give an accurate representation of the Franck–Condon region: for the retinal analogs studied in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit48 cit49">refs. 48 and 49</REF>, the S<SB>1</SB> surface is bound in the torsional angle for the initial planar geometry.</annotationART></s> <s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot3" novelty="None" advantage="None">For a complete analysis of the reaction path, crucial for the understanding of the femtosecond to picosecond events, the model Hamiltonian has to be modified to account for this feature.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.2.">Evolution of charge distributions at the CI</HEADER><P><s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac27" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the basis functions |AB〉 and |B<SP>2</SP>〉 are associated with fixed charge distributions, the charge properties of the adiabatic states S<SB>0</SB> and S<SB>1</SB> as a function of geometry can be derived from an eigenvector decomposition in terms of the VB type components.</annotationART></s> <s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac27" novelty="None" advantage="None">While the {|AB〉,|B<SP>2</SP>〉} states mix substantially for geometries away from <IT>θ</IT> = 90°, they decouple at the conical intersection.</annotationART></s> <s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac27" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hence, a pronounced polarization effect is expected when moving towards the conical intersection.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">This effect is illustrated in Fig. 3, for the isolated chromophore adiabatic surfaces as depicted in Fig. 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The figure shows the decomposition of the eigenvector corresponding to the S<SB>1</SB> state in terms of its {|AB〉,|B<SP>2</SP>〉} components, as a function of the twist angle <IT>θ</IT> and the tuning coordinate <IT>r</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">A step function-like feature is observed for <IT>θ</IT> = 90° along <IT>r</IT>, reflecting that the adiabatic states correspond to different diabatic branches to the left and right of the conical intersection point (see also Fig. 2b).</annotationART></s> <s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, while the S<SB>1</SB> surface is predominantly of |B<SP>2</SP>〉 character close to the planar geometry, and is entirely |B<SP>2</SP>〉 along the line <IT>θ</IT> = 90°, for <IT>r</IT> &lt; <IT>r</IT>0CI, the same surface is of |AB〉 character at and near <IT>θ</IT> = 90°, for <IT>r</IT> &gt; <IT>r</IT>0CI.</annotationART></s> <s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">As can be inferred from Fig. 3, the discontinuity is smoothed out away from <IT>θ</IT> = 90°.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">An entirely complementary picture holds for S<SB>0</SB>, with the roles of the diabatic |AB〉 and |B<SP>2</SP>〉 states exchanged.</annotationART></s> <s sid="143"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The S<SB>0</SB> surface is thus predominantly of |AB〉 character, apart from the charge reversal near <IT>θ</IT> = 90° for <IT>r</IT> &gt; <IT>r</IT>0CI.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="144"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The prominent features of the charge distributions of the adiabatic states S<SB>0</SB> and S<SB>1</SB> can be summarized as follows: (i) a “polarization” effect when moving towards <IT>θ</IT> = 90° at a given <IT>r</IT>, as a signature of the |AB〉 and |B<SP>2</SP>〉 state decoupling, and (ii) a sudden charge character change when traversing the CI region along <IT>r</IT>, for values of <IT>θ</IT> near <IT>θ</IT> = 90°.</annotationART></s> <s sid="145"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">This change is step function-like at <IT>θ</IT> = 90°.</annotationART></s> <s sid="146"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac28" novelty="None" advantage="None">The above observations in part agree with the picture described by Robb, Olivucci and co-workers<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit48 cit49 cit57 cit58">48,49,57,58</REF> and the results obtained by Martínez and co-workers<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit47">47</REF> for different retinal analogs.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.3.">Solvent effects</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.3.1.">Properties and topology of the free energy surfaces</HEADER><P><s sid="147"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The S<SB>0</SB> and S<SB>1</SB> free energy surfaces derived by diagonalizing the matrix potential eqn. (16) depend on the two tuning modes <IT>r</IT> and <IT>z</IT>, in addition to the coupling mode <IT>θ</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="148"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hence, a <IT>seam</IT> of conical intersections results, <IT>i.e.</IT>, a line in the (<IT>r</IT>,<IT>z</IT>) space for <IT>θ</IT> = 90°, depicted in Fig. 4.</annotationART></s> <s sid="149"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The minimum energy CI (MECI) is located at (<IT>r</IT> = 1.54 Å,<IT>z</IT> = 0.55); the slight departure from the midpoint <IT>z</IT> = 0.5 can be shown to follow from an analytic analysis.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit51">51</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="150"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac29" novelty="None" advantage="None">(Note also the discussion in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">ref. 1</REF> regarding the general tendency towards lowering of the MECI energy upon adding further tuning modes).</annotationART></s> <s sid="151"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the present system, the MECI point in fact represents the global minimum of the S<SB>1</SB> surface.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit51">51</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="152"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">As can further be inferred from Fig. 4, no CI exists for values of <IT>z</IT> below a certain limiting value, here <IT>z</IT> &lt; 0.21.</annotationART></s> <s sid="153"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">As <IT>z</IT> increases, the intersection point is shifted to smaller <IT>r</IT> values.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="154"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The locations (<IT>r</IT>,<IT>z</IT>) along the CI seam are determined by the condition Δ<IT>V</IT>(<IT>r</IT>, <IT>θ</IT> = 90°) = –Δ<IT>G</IT><SB>s</SB>(<IT>z</IT>) for a degeneracy of the two adiabatic states, given a vanishing coupling (<IT>θ</IT> = 90°), with Δ<IT>V</IT>(<IT>r</IT>, <IT>θ</IT>) = <IT>V</IT><SB>B<SP>2</SP></SB>(<IT>r</IT>,<IT>θ</IT>) – <IT>V</IT><SB>AB</SB>(<IT>r</IT>,<IT>θ</IT>) and the solvent-induced free-energy gap The required degeneracy at the CI seam is thus achieved by matching the respective energy gaps induced by the two tuning coordinates <IT>r</IT> and <IT>z</IT>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="155"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod11" novelty="None" advantage="None">According to eqn. (25), the solvent-induced free energy gap Δ<IT>G</IT><SB>s</SB>(<IT>z</IT>) is a linear function of <IT>z</IT> and vanishes for <IT>z</IT> = 1/2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="156"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The maximum value of Δ<IT>G</IT><SB>s</SB>(<IT>z</IT>) which allows for a CI to occur corresponds to <IT>z</IT> = 1, for a solvent equilibrated to the |B<SP>2</SP>〉 state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="157"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">This point, at (<IT>r</IT> = 1.33 Å,<IT>z</IT> = 1,<IT>θ</IT> = 90°), coincides with the unique equilibrium point (EQCI) along the CI seam, see the discussion below.</annotationART></s> <s sid="158"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Importantly, the equilibrium CI point does <IT>not</IT> minimize the S<SB>1</SB> free energy, <IT>i.e.</IT>, the EQCI and MECI points do not coincide.</annotationART></s> <s sid="159"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">This reflects the particular character of the CI topology, as further detailed below (Section 4.3.3). in connection with an equilibrium solvation perspective.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="160"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac30" novelty="None" advantage="None">The CI seam plays a key role for the S<SB>1</SB> topology and, hence, the excited-state dynamics.</annotationART></s> <s sid="161"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac30" novelty="None" advantage="None">The combined dynamical evolution in the internal coordinates and solvent coordinate <IT>z</IT> will ultimately tend towards the CI seam and the MECI point.</annotationART></s> <s sid="162"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac30" novelty="None" advantage="None">In a manner depending on the nonadiabatic dynamics details, this will be followed by a path involving the solvent coordinate on the adiabatic ground state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="163"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac30" novelty="None" advantage="None">In general, motion in the solvent coordinate <IT>z</IT> will be of a <IT>non</IT>-equilibrium character, <IT>i.e.</IT>, the orientational polarization will not be that appropriate to the actual charge distribution in the chromophore as the latter evolves in <IT>r</IT> and <IT>θ</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="164"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot4" novelty="None" advantage="None">This necessitates consideration of the full three-dimensional surfaces <B><IT>G</IT></B>(<IT>r</IT>,<IT>θ</IT>,<IT>z</IT>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="165"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac31" novelty="None" advantage="None">An approximate dynamical scenario for the nonequilibrium case is addressed in .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit51">ref. 51</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="166"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj7" novelty="New" advantage="None">In the remainder of this section, we focus on the solvent's effect on the chromophore for two limiting situations: (i) a “frozen” solvent polarization (Section 4.3.2). where the solvent coordinate is fixed throughout, imposing a pronounced nonequilibrium solvation situation, and (ii) the case of equilibrium solvation (Section 4.3.3). which implies extremely rapid solvent motion, adiabatically adjusting to the solute charge distribution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="167"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac32" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both cases allow for a reduction from the three-dimensional (<IT>r</IT>,<IT>θ</IT>,<IT>z</IT>) space to effective free energy surfaces <B><IT>G</IT></B><SB>eff</SB>(<IT>r</IT>, <IT>θ</IT>) in <IT>two</IT> dimensions.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.3.2.">Frozen solvent perspective</HEADER><P><s sid="168"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj8" novelty="New" advantage="None">For a frozen solvent polarization, determined by a particular value <IT>z</IT>, a single point on the CI seam is selected.</annotationART></s> <s sid="169"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac33" novelty="None" advantage="None">Due to the correlation between the two tuning coordinates <IT>r</IT> and <IT>z</IT> along the seam, the value of <IT>z</IT> determines the location of the CI in <IT>r</IT>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="170"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 5 illustrates the adiabatic S<SB>0</SB> and S<SB>1</SB> surfaces as a function of <IT>r</IT> and <IT>θ</IT>, for two cases which represent equilibrium situations for the uncoupled |AB〉 and |B<SP>2</SP>〉 states at <IT>θ</IT> = 90°: (i) a solvent equilibrated to the |AB〉 charge distribution, <IT>z</IT>ABeq = 0 and (ii) a solvent equilibrated to the |B<SP>2</SP>〉 charge distribution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="171"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod12" novelty="None" advantage="None">For each fixed <IT>z</IT> value, a <IT>non</IT>equilibrium solvation situation applies for all geometries away from <IT>θ</IT> = 90°, since the solvent polarization is not allowed to adjust to the actual solute charge distribution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="172"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">With either condition eqn. (26) or eqn. (27), the solvent-induced free energy gap eqn. (25) takes a fixed value, of Δ<IT>G</IT><SB>s</SB>(<IT>z</IT>ABeq) = <IT>k</IT><SB>s</SB>/2 and , respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="173"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The former does not allow for a degeneracy according to eqn. (24), such that the CI is actually <IT>lost</IT> for <IT>z</IT> = <IT>z</IT>ABeq = 0.</annotationART></s> <s sid="174"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">For , a CI does exist, at a value of <IT>r</IT> = 1.33 Å determined from eqn. (24).</annotationART></s> <s sid="175"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac34" novelty="None" advantage="None">This point is in fact the EQCI point referred to above.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="176"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">For <IT>z</IT> = 1, the shift in location of the CI point leads to a change in CI topology from “peaked” for the isolated chromophore to “sloped”,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit59">59</REF> further illustrated by the one-dimensional cut in Fig. 6.</annotationART></s> <s sid="177"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this case, the minimum of the upper adiabatic (S<SB>1</SB>) surface along <IT>r</IT> no longer coincides with the CI; see also the discussion on the role of CI topology in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit60 cit61">refs. 60, 61</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.3.3.">Equilibrium solvation perspective</HEADER><P><s sid="178"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The condition of equilibrium solvation identifies the particular points on the free energy surfaces which correspond to a solvent orientational polarization field which is always in equilibrium with the chromophore's charge distribution at each given geometry (<IT>r</IT>, <IT>θ</IT>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="179"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod13" novelty="None" advantage="None">These equilibrium points <IT>z</IT> = <IT>z</IT><SB>eq</SB>(<IT>r</IT>, <IT>θ</IT>) are derived from the free energy condition ∂<IT>G</IT><SB><IT>n</IT></SB>(<IT>r</IT>, <IT>θ</IT>, <IT>z</IT>)/∂<IT>z</IT> = 0 where the index <IT>n</IT> corresponds to the adiabatic state in question.</annotationART></s> <s sid="180"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj9" novelty="New" advantage="None">We focus in the following on the situation where the solvent is equilibrated to the upper adiabatic surface S<SB>1</SB>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="181"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod13" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the matrix potential eqn. (16), analytical diagonalization yields an explicit form for the adiabatic surfaces <IT>G</IT><SB>S<SB>0</SB></SB>(<IT>r</IT>, <IT>θ</IT>, <IT>z</IT>) and <IT>G</IT><SB>S<SB>1</SB></SB>(<IT>r</IT>, <IT>θ</IT>, <IT>z</IT>) and the corresponding eigenvectors.</annotationART></s> <s sid="182"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod13" novelty="None" advantage="None">From this follows for the free energy derivative with respect to <IT>z</IT>, for S<SB>1</SB>, with <IT>c</IT><SB>|B<SP>2</SP>〉</SB>(<IT>r</IT>, <IT>θ</IT>, <IT>z</IT>) the |B<SP>2</SP>〉 component of the S<SB>1</SB> eigenvector.</annotationART></s> <s sid="183"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod13" novelty="None" advantage="None">From the minimum free energy condition and eqn. (28), the geometry dependent equilibrium values are thus found as a solution to </annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="184"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The case <IT>θ</IT> = 90°, with a vanishing diabatic coupling, represents a particular instance of eqns. (28) and (29).</annotationART></s> <s sid="185"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod13" novelty="None" advantage="None">For this angle, eqn. (29) is the equilibrium condition for the diabatic states, (i) for the S<SB>1</SB> branch corresponding to |B<SP>2</SP>〉, for <IT>r</IT> ≤ <IT>r</IT><SB>EQCI</SB>, and (ii) <IT>z</IT>ABeq = 0 for the S<SB>1</SB> branch corresponding to |AB〉, for <IT>r</IT> &gt; <IT>r</IT><SB>EQCI</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="186"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that the EQCI point at (<IT>r</IT><SB>EQCI</SB> = 1.33 Å, <IT>z</IT><SB>EQCI</SB> = 1) is the unique equilibrium point lying on the CI seam.</annotationART></s> <s sid="187"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod13" novelty="None" advantage="None">(In general, all points fulfilling the degeneracy condition eqn. (24) for or <IT>z</IT> = <IT>z</IT>ABeq represent EQCI points; the latter case is excluded in the present system as discussed in Section 4.3.2)..</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="188"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 7a shows the (<IT>r</IT>, <IT>θ</IT>) dependent solutions of eqn. (29) and illustrates the step function-like behavior <IT>versus</IT><IT>r</IT>, at <IT>θ</IT> = 90°, at the EQCI point.</annotationART></s> <s sid="189"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The picture is the analog, for S<SB>1</SB> equilibrium solvation, of Fig. 3a for the isolated chromophore.</annotationART></s> <s sid="190"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Detailed comparison of the two figures reveals that the equilibrium solvation case further exhibits a discontinuity in <IT>θ</IT>, at <IT>θ</IT> = 90°, along the whole |AB〉 branch of S<SB>1</SB>(<IT>r</IT> &gt; <IT>r</IT><SB>EQCI</SB>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="191"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac35" novelty="None" advantage="None">This requires further explanation, now given.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="192"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa3" novelty="None" advantage="None">To understand the origin of the discontinuity, we consider in Fig. 8 a projection of the three-dimensional <B><IT>G</IT></B>(<IT>r</IT>, <IT>θ</IT>, <IT>z</IT>) surfaces along <IT>z</IT>, at fixed <IT>r</IT> = <IT>r</IT>0CI = 1.59 Å and <IT>θ</IT> = 90° (panel a) <IT>vs.</IT><IT>θ</IT> = 90° + <IT>ε</IT> (panel b).</annotationART></s> <s sid="193"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">While the free energy minimum for the uncoupled case (a) corresponds to the diabatic minimum at <IT>z</IT>ABeq = 0, the adiabatic S<SB>1</SB> minimum in (b) is located at .</annotationART></s> <s sid="194"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The limiting value as <IT>θ</IT> approaches 90° is defined by the crossing of the diabatic states, and hence, the point (<IT>r</IT> = <IT>r</IT>0CI, <IT>z</IT> = 0.5) along the CI seam, <IT>i.e.</IT>, .</annotationART></s> <s sid="195"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since this limiting value does <IT>not</IT> coincide with the equilibrium point <IT>z</IT>ABeq = 0 at <IT>θ</IT> = 90°, a discontinuity arises.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="196"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">A similar observation holds for all <IT>r</IT> values (within the range of existence of a conical intersection) such that the equilibrium points on the upper adiabatic surface tend towards the <IT>z</IT> values <IT>along the CI seam</IT>, Only at the EQCI point does the <IT>z</IT><SB>seam</SB> value coincide with the true equilibrium value, <IT>z</IT><SB>EQCI</SB> = <IT>z</IT><SB>seam</SB>(<IT>r</IT> = 1.33 Å) = 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="197"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 7b illustrates the limiting behavior eqn. (30).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="198"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">While the overall seam does <IT>not</IT> conform to an equilibrium condition, its role as a limiting value according to eqn. (30) nonetheless turns out to be crucial for the topology of the free energy surfaces.</annotationART></s> <s sid="199"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is illustrated in Fig. 9 for the equilibrium solvation free energies .</annotationART></s> <s sid="200"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">At <IT>θ</IT> = 90°, the free energies of both states approach the degeneracy at the CI seam, as a result of converging to <IT>z</IT><SB>seam</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="201"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the S<SB>1</SB> and S<SB>0</SB> surfaces thus tend towards a <IT>line</IT> of degeneracies, the topology is markedly different from the surfaces of Fig. 1 and Fig. 5 which exhibit a single CI <IT>point</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="202"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Conditions of equilibrium solvation with respect to S<SB>1</SB> are therefore expected to induce enhanced nonadiabatic transition probabilities to the S<SB>0</SB> ground state as compared with either the isolated chromophore or frozen solvent conditions.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="5.">Conclusions and outlook</HEADER><P><s sid="203"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="New" advantage="None">We have introduced a theoretical formulation to describe the environment's impact on a conical intersection (CI), which in this first effort has focussed on the environment's influence on the existence, location and character of the CI.</annotationART></s> <s sid="204"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">This formulation describes the interacting chromophore–environment system in situations where electrostatic interactions are dominant such that the environment's orientational polarization field interacts strongly with the chromophore.</annotationART></s> <s sid="205"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The combined chromophore–environment system is characterized by free energy surfaces in the space of internal molecular coordinates plus one or several solvent coordinate(s).</annotationART></s> <s sid="206"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac36" novelty="None" advantage="None">A first sketch is given of applying this formulation to the coupled S<SB>1</SB>/S<SB>0</SB> states in protonated Schiff bases.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="207"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The perspective we have developed is based on a free energy model including the solvent as an additional “tuning” mode which modulates the energy gap and displaces the CI.</annotationART></s> <s sid="208"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The impact of a solvent can be substantial: For example, if the solvent is equilibrated to a solute state characterized by the charge distribution pertaining to one or the other diabatic state and then frozen, the conical intersection can be entirely lost, or its topology may be altered (here, from “peaked” to “sloped”).</annotationART></s> <s sid="209"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the opposite limit of extremely rapid solvent motion, equilibrium solvation free energies can be defined whose topology is determined by the CI seam: <IT>i.e.</IT>, a <IT>line</IT> of intersections, rather than a single point in (<IT>r</IT>,<IT>θ</IT>) space.</annotationART></s> <s sid="210"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Pronounced implications for the dynamics are thus expected for the different solvation limits.</annotationART></s> <s sid="211"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition to these effects, the solvent can also have off-diagonal contributions, solvent-induced couplings, which have a symmetry-breaking effect at the geometries where the coupling intrinsic to the chromophore vanishes.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="212"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac37" novelty="None" advantage="None">A detailed discussion of the PSBs and related systems in the context of the present model will require an <IT>ab initio</IT> based parameterization including all relevant modes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="213"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac38" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, the model should be further developed in view of the following aspects: (i) Extension of the free energy picture to molecular level interactions, beyond the dielectric continuum description (This leads to the definition of generalized, microscopic solvent coordinates<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit31 cit32 cit33 cit34">31–34</REF> and paves the way for the application of the present approach to complex environments), (ii) the development of general strategies to define an appropriate diabatic basis representation, chosen such as to exhibit a well-defined charge character, and (iii) a dynamical description including the solvent, leading to the image of a combined dynamical path for the chromophore–environment supermolecular system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="214"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac38" novelty="None" advantage="None">This necessitates the combination of the nonequilibrium dynamics in the solvent coordinate with the quantum dynamics of the chromophore.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="215"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac38" novelty="None" advantage="None">Given the above elements, the present approach should contribute to clarifying various aspects of the environment's impact on the subpicosecond and picosecond dynamics in the PSBs.</annotationART></s> <s sid="216"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac38" novelty="None" advantage="None">This relates, in particular, to the pronounced differences in the dynamics observed in solution phase as compared with the native protein environment: For the retinal chromophores of rhodopsin and bacteriorhodopsin, and similarly for the chromophore of the photoactive yellow protein, the decay observed in solution is much slower (of the order of 10 ps)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18 cit63 cit62">18,63,62</REF> than the decay observed for the native protein (of the order of 200–500 fs).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12 cit13 cit14 cit15 cit17">12–15,17</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="217"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac39" novelty="None" advantage="None">For both the solution phase and protein environments, an interesting comparison will arise from the comparison with QM/MM type approaches as developed, <IT>e.g.</IT>, in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">ref. 10</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
