<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b315520j" hasDoc="yes" version="1184" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">The shape of neurotransmitters in the gas phase: A theoretical study of adrenaline, pseudoadrenaline, and hydrated adrenaline<XREF TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" /></annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">The conformational landscapes of adrenaline and pseudoadrenaline have been explored by electronic structure computation at the B3LYP/6-31+G*, MP2/6-31+G* and MP2/aug-cc-pVDZ levels of theory.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Based on the relative energies of the different conformers, we conclude that the extended AG1a and folded GG1a conformers are the most likely candidates for detection in spectroscopy experiments using a supersonic expansion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Predictions for the infrared spectra of the AG1a and GG1a conformers and their 1∶1 hydrates are presented.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="New" advantage="None">We explored the suitability of a rigid-body DMA-based model potential to locate the most stable 1∶1 and 1∶2 adrenaline-water clusters.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The model potential was able to locate all relevant 1∶1 clusters, but failed to find the most stable 1∶2 cluster.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This paper is part of a combined theoretical/experimental study of the catecholamine neurotransmitters.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Previous work in this series include the investigation of the conformational landscapes of noradrenaline (NA),<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF> the simplest catecholamine neurotransmitter, and of singly hydrated NA.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">2</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The current work focuses on the adrenaline (A)/pseudoadrenaline (PA) pair.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Noradrenaline has one chiral centre (the C<SB>β</SB> atom, see Fig. 1 for the labelling of the atoms), and thus occurs in two spectroscopically identical chiral forms (<IT>R</IT> and <IT>S</IT>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Adrenaline/pseudoadrenaline is formed by the replacement of one of the hydrogens of the terminal NH<SB>2</SB> group by a methyl group.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This makes the N atom chiral as well, which leads to the existence of two diastereoisomers: adrenaline (1<IT>R</IT>2<IT>S</IT>/1<IT>S</IT>2<IT>R</IT>) and pseudoadrenaline (1<IT>S</IT>2<IT>S</IT>/1<IT>R</IT>2<IT>R</IT>).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">A biomolecule's molecular shape plays a crucial role in its transport properties, its selectivity and function, and its receptor binding properties.</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Its shape and conformation result from a delicate balance of intramolecular and environmental influences.</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The study of gas-phase biomolecules is essential in order to differentiate the relative importance of the intrinsic and environmental influences on the biomolecule's conformation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">In this article we provide a full theoretical characterisation of the neutral conformers of adrenaline and pseudoadrenaline in the gas phase, and provide a first investigation of the 1∶1 and 1∶2 hydrates of adrenaline.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The functional groups of the catecholamine neurotransmitters (the catecholic hydroxyls, the chain OH and NH groups, and the π electron cloud) provide many possible water-binding sites.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the most stable NA conformer (AG1a), we located as many as eleven different AG1a–H<SB>2</SB>O structures.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">2</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">To find the most stable hydrates, one should not only investigate clusters involving the most stable conformer, but one has to consider several of the low-lying conformers, as the interaction with water may change the relative stability of the conformers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In pseudoephedrine, for example, hydration results in a substantial rearrangement of its conformational landscape, altering the conformation at the global minimum from an extended (Aga) to a folded (Gga) conformation.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, the number of local minima increases steeply with the number of constituents in the cluster.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Consequently, a full study of the adrenaline hydrates will be a formidable task.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">In this paper, we present the initial investigation of the 1∶1 and 1∶2 adrenaline hydrates.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">We investigate the different water-binding sites, and we comment on the most appropriate theoretical methodology to compute the relative stability of hydrates containing different adrenaline conformers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, we explore the suitability of force-field calculations using a DMA (distributed multipole analysis)-based rigid-body model potential for scanning the potential energy surface of the hydrates.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Methodology</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Electronic structure calculations</HEADER><P><s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The catechol OH groups have two possible orientations forming an intramolecular hydrogen bond: C<SB>δ</SB>-<IT>syn</IT> (the catechol hydrogens are <IT>syn</IT> with respect to the C<SB>δ</SB>–H group) and C<SB>δ</SB>-<IT>trans</IT> (the catechol hydrogens are <IT>trans</IT> with respect to the C<SB>δ</SB>–H group).</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">There is, in fact, a third orientation for the catechol OH groups.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this one the catechol hydrogens point away from each other, preventing the catechol OH groups to form an intramolecular hydrogen bond.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">This orientation was also identified as a local minimum on the potential energy surface of catechol,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit5 cit6">4–6</REF> and caffeic acid (which consists of a catechol moiety and a propenoate side chain).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is however much less favourable than the orientations forming an intramolecular hydrogen bond.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have therefore not considered this particular orientation of the catechol OH groups.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">We first explored the conformational landscapes of adrenaline and pseudoadrenaline holding the catechol OH groups in the C<SB>δ</SB>-<IT>trans</IT> orientation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">To provide starting structures for geometry optimisations, the <IT>γ</IT><SB>1</SB> = <IT>γ</IT>(C<SB>δ</SB>–C<SB>γ</SB>–C<SB>β</SB>–C<SB>α</SB>), <IT>γ</IT><SB>2</SB> = <IT>γ</IT>(C<SB>γ</SB>–C<SB>β</SB>–C<SB>α</SB>–N), <IT>γ</IT><SB>3</SB> = <IT>γ</IT>(C<SB>β</SB>–C<SB>α</SB>–N–C) torsion angles were initially set to 0°, 60°, 120°, 180°, 240° and 300°, and <IT>γ</IT><SB>4</SB> = <IT>γ</IT>(C<SB>γ</SB>–C<SB>β</SB>–O–H) was set to 60°, 180° and 300°.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">For <IT>γ</IT><SB>1</SB>, <IT>γ</IT><SB>2</SB> and <IT>γ</IT><SB>3</SB> we initially used torsion angle step sizes of 60°.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">As the eclipsed conformations were found not to be local minima on the potential energy surface, part of the conformational search considered only staggered conformations.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The resulting conformations were subjected to HF/6-31G* geometry optimisations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The geometries of all conformers with energies less than 20 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> above the global minimum were re-optimised with density functional theory (DFT) using the B3LYP<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit9">8,9</REF> functional and the 6-31+G* basis set.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The C<SB>δ</SB>-<IT>syn</IT> conformers of the ten most stable A and of the ten most stable PA conformers were located using B3LYP/6-31+G*.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">One of the A C<SB>δ</SB>-<IT>syn</IT> conformers (AG3a-2) appeared to be unstable.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The relative energies of the resulting nineteen A and twenty PA conformers were evaluated by single-point MP2/6-31+G* and MP2/aug-cc-pVDZ calculations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Zero-point energies (scaled by 0976<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF>). and scaled (0976<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF>. for OH, 0956<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF>. for NH) harmonic vibrational frequencies were calculated at the B3LYP/6-31+G* level of theory.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Calculation of interaction energies</HEADER><P><s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The A–H<SB>2</SB>O and PA–H<SB>2</SB>O structures considered in this work were optimised with B3LYP/6-31+G*.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The interaction energies were corrected for BSSE (basis set superposition error) by using the counterpoise procedure.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The deformation energies were taken into account as well.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">These are computed as the difference of the energy of A/PA (or H<SB>2</SB>O) at the geometry the monomer adopts in the complex, and the energy of the free molecule at its equilibrium geometry <IT>r</IT><SB>e</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">As discussed in our recent paper on NA–H<SB>2</SB>O,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">2</REF> there are two possible choices for the geometry of the free adrenaline.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">If one is interested in how strongly water binds to a <IT>particular</IT> conformer, then the equilibrium geometry of this particular conformer should be used.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The resulting interaction energy is called the <IT>specific</IT> water interaction energy (Δ<IT>E</IT><SP>H<SB>2</SB>O</SP>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, if one wants to compute relative interaction energies of A–H<SB>2</SB>O complexes consisting of different A conformers, then one should use the equilibrium energy of the most stable conformer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Relative energies calculated like this are corrected for BSSE, in contrast to relative energies based on the A–H<SB>2</SB>O total energies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Unless specified otherwise, we will use the second definition in the current paper.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">To provide the interaction energies at 0 K, Δ<IT>E</IT><SB>0</SB>, the (harmonic, scaled by 0.976) zero-point energies (ZPE) of AW and the separated fragments (computed in the harmonic approximation) were taken into account: Δ<IT>E</IT><SB>0</SB> = Δ<IT>E</IT> + <IT>E</IT>ZPEAW − <IT>E</IT>ZPEA(global)(<IT>r</IT><SB>e</SB>) − <IT>E</IT>ZPEW(<IT>r</IT><SB>e</SB>)(For the specific water interaction energy , one should take the zero-point energy of adrenaline at the equilibrium geometry of the particular conformer one is interested in, instead of that of the global minimum).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the current paper, the interaction energies are listed as <IT>D</IT><SB>e</SB> (=−Δ<IT>E</IT>) and <IT>D</IT><SB>0</SB> (=−Δ<IT>E</IT><SB>0</SB>), so that positive values denote an attractive interaction.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The interaction energies of π-type hydrogen bonds are difficult to evaluate accurately, due to the large contribution of the dispersion energy to the interaction, which is known to converge slowly with addition of high angular momentum polarisation functions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Current standard density functionals cannot evaluate the dispersion energy quantitatively.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">MP2 in principle allows the calculation of dispersion-type interactions; however, MP2 calculations with large basis sets readily become intractable for the size of systems studied in this work.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">An earlier study on indole-H<SB>2</SB>O and methylindole-H<SB>2</SB>O<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF> showed that MP2 calculations employing the compact <IT>interaction</IT>-<IT>optimised</IT> DZP<IT>i</IT> basis set<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16 cit17">16,17</REF> do give accurate interaction energies, for conventional <IT>and</IT> π-type H-bonded complexes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None">We have therefore computed the structures and geometries of the π-bonded complexes with MP2/DZP<IT>i</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The effect of BSSE on the intermolecular geometry can be quite large<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15 cit18">15,18</REF> when using the DZP<IT>i</IT> basis set.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">To correct for this in an approximate way, the hydrogen-bond distances in these complexes were corrected for BSSE by numerically locating the distance for which the counterpoise-corrected <IT>D</IT><SB>e</SB> has its maximum.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit15 cit17 cit18">1,15,17,18</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The electronic-structure calculations were performed with Gaussian 98 (revisions A.9 and A.11)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19">19</REF> and NWChem (version 4.1)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF> on clusters of 1.7 GHz Pentium 4 and 2.0 GHz dual Xeon PCs running Linux.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">An Origin 2000 and a cluster of Sun 900 MHz V880 servers at the HiPerSPACE Computing Centre at University College London were used as well.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="New" advantage="None">As usual, only the valence electrons were correlated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Gaussian's “ultrafine” integration grid was used for the DFT calculations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The optimisations were converged using Gaussian's “tight” criteria for the cutoffs on forces and step size.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Model potential calculations</HEADER><P><s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The model potential used, dubbed MP2fit/DMA, was developed in a study on uracil-water,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF> and used recently in an investigation of protonated nicotine interacting with water and a third body.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">It consists of an atom–atom 6–exp potential to describe the repulsion and dispersion terms, and a DMA (distributed multipole analysis) model for the electrostatic contribution.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">All individual terms of this potential are pairwise additive, and thus, it can readily be extended to complexes containing more than two molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The potential has different parameters for each atom type (C, N, O, H), and it distinguishes between hydrogens attached to C, polar hydrogens (attached to O or N), and water hydrogens.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The DMA model uses atomic multipoles up to hexadecapole, derived from <IT>ab initio</IT> wavefunctions (MP2/6-311++G(2d,2p) for water, MP2/6-311G** for adrenaline), and includes all terms in the atom–atom multipole expansion up to <IT>R</IT><SB><IT>ab</IT></SB><SP>−5</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The DMA was derived from the wavefunctions calculated with Gaussian 98 by using the GDMA<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF> program.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">As the MP2fit/DMA potential is a rigid-body potential, the DMA for adrenaline needs to be recomputed for each different conformer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="New" advantage="None">The monomer geometries used were obtained by geometry optimisations at the same level of theory as used to calculate the DMAs.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The model potential calculations were done with the program Orient.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Further details on the potential model are provided in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25">ref. 25</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER><IT>Ab initio</IT> and density functional theory results</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Adrenaline and pseudoadrenaline</HEADER><P><s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The structures of the sixteen most stable A and PA conformers (based on the single-point MP2/aug-cc-pVDZ energies) are shown in Fig. 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">To classify the A and PA conformers we used the same notation as employed in our previous study on NA,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF> which is based on previous studies on 2-amino-1-phenylethanol<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10 cit26">10,26</REF> and the ephedra:<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27 cit28 cit29">27–29</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">(<IT>i</IT>) The A/G notation denotes the arrangements (<IT>anti</IT> or <IT>gauche</IT>) of the C<SB>γ</SB>–C<SB>β</SB>–C<SB>α</SB>–N and O–C<SB>β</SB>–C<SB>α</SB>–N atom chains, respectively.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">(<IT>ii</IT>) In NA, which contains an NH<SB>2</SB> group instead of the NH(CH<SB>3</SB>) group in A and PA, the AG and GG conformers have either a short OH⋯N (AG1, GG1), or a short NH⋯O (AG2/3, GG2/3) contact.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">(The AG2/3 and GG2/3 families differ depending on which amino H atom is involved in the H-bonding).</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">In A and PA, the corresponding AG2/3 and GG2/3 families will have an NH⋯O (if the free hydrogen in the corresponding NA structure is methylated) or a CH⋯O contact (if the hydrogen-bonding H atom is methylated).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">(<IT>iii</IT>) The catechol OH groups can have two different orientations (C<SB>δ</SB>-<IT>syn</IT> and C<SB>δ</SB>-<IT>trans</IT>) and the side chain can be above or below the ring.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is notated by “a” (C<SB>δ</SB>-<IT>syn</IT>, above plane), “b” (C<SB>δ</SB>-<IT>trans</IT>, above plane), “c” (C<SB>δ</SB>-<IT>trans</IT>, below plane) and “d” (C<SB>δ</SB>-<IT>syn</IT>, below plane).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">C<SB>δ</SB>-<IT>syn</IT> and C<SB>δ</SB>-<IT>trans</IT> conformations corresponding to the same side chain conformation differ slightly in energy due to interaction of the catechol hydroxyl groups with the side chain functional groups.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">This was also observed for caffeic acid<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF> for which the C<SB>δ</SB>-<IT>syn</IT> conformers were found to have a slightly lower energy than the C<SB>δ</SB>-<IT>trans</IT> conformers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In A and PA the “a” conformers, which have a C<SB>δ</SB>-<IT>syn</IT> orientation of the catecholic hydroxyls, appear to be favoured.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The conformers with an intramolecular OH⋯N hydrogen bond (AG1, GG1) are more stable than the NH⋯O hydrogen-bonded structures (AG2, AG3, GG2).</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is in agreement with the larger polarity of OH as compared to NH, as well as with studies on the hydrogen-bonding abilities of oxygen and nitrogen in different hydrogen-bonding environments (oxygens covalently bound to two non-hydrogen atoms of which at least one is sp<SB>2</SB> hybridised<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30">30</REF> and hydrogen bonds to monocyclic aromatic heterocycles<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit31">31</REF>), which showed that nitrogen atoms are stronger hydrogen-bond acceptors than oxygens.</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Rablen <IT>et al.</IT> likewise found that nitrogens are better hydrogen-bond acceptors than sp<SP>3</SP>-hybridised oxygens.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit32">32</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">(However, Vargas <IT>et al.</IT> found that NH⋯O interactions are more stable than NH⋯N interactions,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit33">33</REF> which is in contradiction with the presumed larger hydrogen-bond acceptor ability of N as compared to O).</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">In our previous study on noradrenaline we found that the twenty most stable NA conformers are of the AG or GG types (AG1, GG1, AG2, AG3 and GG2).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The twenty most stable A conformers (based on the B3LYP energies) include the equivalents of the AG1, GG1 and AG3 conformers found for NA, a second AG3 family and a GA family.</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">For completeness, we have also optimised the structures of the AG2 and GG2 adrenaline conformers with B3LYP/6-31+G* (followed by single-point MP2/6-31+G* and MP2/aug-cc-pVDZ calculations).</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The relative energies of the resulting 27 A conformers, listed in decreasing order of stability based on the MP2/aug-cc-pVDZ energies, are collected in Table S1 of the ESI.<SUP TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" /></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The twenty most stable PA conformers (based on the B3LYP energies) include the equivalent conformers of the AG1, GG1 and AG2 conformers found for NA, as well as a GA and GG3 family, which were not among the most stable NA conformers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="New" advantage="None">We have also calculated the relative energies of the AG3 and GG2 families, which were not among the twenty most stable PA conformers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The relative energies Δ(<IT>E</IT><SB>e</SB>) and Δ(<IT>E</IT><SB>0</SB>) of the resulting 28 PA conformers, in decreasing order of stability based on the MP2/aug-cc-pVDZ Δ(<IT>E</IT><SB>e</SB>) values, are listed in Table S2 of the ESI.<SUP TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" /></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">At the B3LYP level of theory, PA is slightly more stable than A; this order is reversed however at the MP2 level of theory.</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Even though A and PA are roughly isoenergetic, it is not likely that there will be interconversion between the two diastereoisomers in supersonic expansion experiments, as interconversion <IT>via</IT> umbrella-inversion of the chiral amino group is expected to have a high barrier.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have calculated the HF/6-31G* relaxed potential energy profile for the umbrella inversion starting from the AG1a conformer, and optimised the geometry of the transition state for this process (see Fig. 3).</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The barrier height for this process is calculated to be 26.6 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">As studies on conformational relaxation in supersonic jets indicate that barriers larger than 6 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> are sufficient to prevent conformational relaxation,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit34 cit35">34,35</REF> it is very unlikely that A ↔ PA interconversion will take place at the low temperatures of supersonic jet experiments.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">There are significant differences between the B3LYP and MP2 relative energies of A and PA.</annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is demonstrated more effectively in Figs. 4 and 5, which show the relative energies Δ(<IT>E</IT><SB>0</SB>) of the A and PA conformers grouped together in their conformational families.</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">B3LYP underestimates the relative stability of the GG1 conformers, which contain a short N–H⋯π (A) or CH⋯π (PA) contact, of the GG2 conformers, which also contain a short N–H⋯π (PA) or CH⋯π (A) contact, and of the GA conformers, which contain a short NH⋯π interaction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, for conformers that contain π-type interactions, B3LYP is less reliable for calculating relative energies.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although B3LYP predicts the adrenaline GG1a conformer to be less stable than AG1a by 2.4 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> (3.0 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> after zero-point vibrational corrections), at the single-point MP2/aug- cc-pVDZ level of theory this energy gap has decreased to a mere 0.49 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> (1.06 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> after vibrational corrections).</annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The narrow energy gap between the adrenaline AG1 and GG1 conformers was also observed for NA<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF> and APE (2-amino-1-phenylethanol),<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF> the benzene analogue of NA.</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, whereas both AG1 and GG1 APE conformers were observed experimentally, the NA experiments, surprisingly showed only one NA conformer, which was assigned as AG1a.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="Old" advantage="None">(In the NA experiments, gas-phase NA was generated <IT>via</IT> laser ablation rather than evaporation using a heated nozzle, which may influence the observed conformer distribution).</annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Similarly, the most intense band in the UV spectrum of APE was assigned to the extended AG conformer, even though MP2 calculations predicted the GG structure to be slightly more stable.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot3" novelty="None" advantage="None">As different levels of theory yield different results on the relative stability of AG1a and GG1a, assignment of AG1a or GG1a as the global minimum cannot be based on the calculated energy differences alone.</annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is likely that also for adrenaline the AG1a conformer will be the preferred structure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, as for NA, this issue cannot be resolved without spectroscopic investigation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">To aid future spectroscopic assignment, we have listed the harmonic frequencies of the hydride stretches of the AG1a and GG1a conformers, calculated at the B3LYP/6-31+G* level of theory, in Table 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac20" novelty="None" advantage="None">Frequencies of the other conformers are available upon request.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The NH stretch modes have near-zero intensity, and cannot be expected to be observed experimentally.</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">One of the catechol OH groups is hydrogen bonded to its neighbour, resulting in a red-shifted stretch mode.</annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The “free” catechol OH stretch band, (OH)<SB>free, cat</SB>, and the stretch band of the hydrogen-bonded catechol OH, (OH–O)<SB>cat</SB>, occur at nearly identical frequencies/intensities in AG1a and GG1a, and therefore cannot be used to distinguish between the two conformers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Unfortunately, also the frequency of the hydrogen-bonded side-chain OH stretch mode, OH–N, is very similar in AG1a and GG1a, though the AG1a mode has a larger intensity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The PA OH–N mode, on the other hand, is sufficiently different in AG1a and GG1a to aid assignment of future observed conformers.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 6 compares the relative energies Δ(<IT>E</IT><SB>0</SB>) of the corresponding NA, A and PA conformers obtained from single-point MP2 calculations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The adrenaline AG2 conformers are much less stable than the corresponding NA and PA conformers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is because the A conformer has a CH⋯O instead of an NH⋯O interaction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Similarly, the pseudoadrenaline AG3 conformers are destabilised by the replacement of an intramolecular NH⋯O by a less favourable CH⋯O interaction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the GG2 family both A and PA are destabilised with respect to the corresponding NA conformers, as the NH⋯π interaction is replaced by a CH⋯π contact in A, while in PA the NH⋯O interaction is replaced by a CH⋯O contact.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Adrenaline-H<SB>2</SB>O</HEADER><P><s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj5" novelty="New" advantage="None">We have computed ten different AG1c–H<SB>2</SB>O and ten different AG3b–H<SB>2</SB>O structures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac21" novelty="None" advantage="None">AG1c belongs to the most stable conformer family, AG1, whereas AG3b belongs to the first family of conformers with an intramolecular NH⋯O hydrogen bond.</annotationART></s> <s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Table 2 shows the computed interaction energies of the AG1c–H<SB>2</SB>O hydrates.</annotationART></s> <s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Their structures, located with B3LYP/6-31+G*, are shown in Fig. 7.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac22" novelty="None" advantage="None">Previous studies on the hydration of ethanolamine neurotransmitters and their analogues found two different categories of 1∶1 hydrates: <IT>insertion</IT> structures, in which the water inserts between two functional groups of the host molecule, and <IT>addition</IT> structures, formed by the addition of a water molecule to one of the functional groups.</annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac22" novelty="None" advantage="None">The global minimum is an insertion structure for 1∶1 clusters of 2-aminoethanol with phenol,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit36">36</REF> and for the 1∶1 hydrates of 2-phenoxy-ethanol,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit37">37</REF> APE,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30">30</REF> and the ephedrine/pseudoephedrine pair.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac22" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the most stable 1∶1 hydrate of NA (which has a catechol ring instead of the benzene ring in 2-phenoxy- ethanol, APE and the ephedra), was found to be an <IT>addition</IT> structure; the water molecule binds to one of the catechol OH groups,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">2</REF> indicating that the hydroxyl groups of the catechol ring provide a more attractive water-binding site than the ethanolamine side chain.</annotationART></s> <s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the current study we find that this addition structure is also the most stable 1∶1 hydrate of the AG1c adrenaline conformer (see Table 2 and Fig. 7): in this structure (labelled catOH–O<SB>w</SB>), the water binds to one of the catechol OH groups to form an OH⋯OH⋯O<SB>w</SB>H<SB>w</SB> daisy chain of hydrogen bonds.</annotationART></s> <s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" advantage="None">A related structure (catO–H<SB>w</SB>O<SB>w</SB>) with a similar hydrogen-bond chain but with water acting as the hydrogen bond donor is distinctly less stable.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac23" novelty="None" advantage="None">There are two different insertion-type structures, with water being located either between the chain OH and NH<SB>2</SB> groups (OH–O<SB>w</SB>H<SB>w</SB>–N) or between the two catechol OH groups (catOH–O<SB>w</SB>H<SB>w</SB>–catO).</annotationART></s> <s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The two insertion structures have large monomer deformation energies, reflecting the energy penalty associated with opening up the dihedral angle between the two functional groups, to make space for the water molecule.</annotationART></s> <s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Despite this energy penalty, the OH–O<SB>w</SB>H<SB>w</SB>–N insertion structure is only slightly less stable than the global minimum (catOH–O<SB>w</SB>).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac24" novelty="None" advantage="None">The water molecule can further bind to the side-chain NH group (NH–O<SB>w</SB>), to either of the lone pairs of the side-chain oxygen (the two O–H<SB>w</SB>O<SB>w</SB> structures), and to the π-electron cloud of the catechol ring.</annotationART></s> <s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac24" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the first π-bonded structure, OH–O<SB>w</SB>H<SB>w</SB>–π, the water forms an additional hydrogen bond with this OH group.</annotationART></s> <s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac24" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the second π-bonded structure, O<SB>w</SB>H<SB>w</SB>–π, the water binds to the other face to the catechol ring, where there is no possibility to form an additional strong hydrogen-bonded contact (although there is some additional stabilisation due to the two CH⋯O<SB>w</SB> interactions), and this structure is therefore less stable than the OH–O<SB>w</SB>H<SB>w</SB>–π minimum.</annotationART></s> <s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Table 2 shows that the O–H<SB>w</SB>O<SB>w</SB>–π structure is not stable on the B3LYP/6-31+G* potential energy surface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="143"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj6" novelty="New" advantage="None">As the effect of BSSE on the intermolecular geometry can be quite large in π-bonded complexes,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15 cit18">15,18</REF> we re-optimised the hydrogen-bond distances of the two π-bonded structures with counterpoise corrections.</annotationART></s> <s sid="144"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs20" novelty="None" advantage="None">The resulting interaction energies are given in parentheses in Table 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="145"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">This re-optimisation has negligible effect on the B3LYP results, but it significantly increases the MP2/DZP<IT>i</IT> interaction energy, thereby further increasing the discrepancy between the MP2 and DFT results.</annotationART></s> <s sid="146"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs21" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 7 shows that the re-optimisation significantly increases the MP2 hydrogen-bond distances.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="147"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs22" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 7 shows two nearly iso-energetic catO–H<SB>w</SB>O<SB>w</SB> structures, just differing in the position of the free (not hydrogen-bonded) water hydrogen, which can be on either side of the aromatic ring.</annotationART></s> <s sid="148"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">To investigate the barrier for interconversion between the (a) and (b) structure, we have calculated the relaxed potential energy profile for rotation of the free water hydrogen around the O<SB>cat</SB>–O<SB>w</SB> axis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="149"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs23" novelty="None" advantage="None">As can be seen in Fig. 8, the catO–H<SB>w</SB>O<SB>w</SB> (a) minimum is very shallow, with an almost non-existent barrier for conversion to the (b) structure, and it is therefore surprising that the (a) structure was found at all!</annotationART></s> <s sid="150"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs23" novelty="None" advantage="None">Also shown in Fig. 8 is the counterpoise-corrected potential energy profile.</annotationART></s> <s sid="151"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The counterpoise-corrected barrier, though larger than the uncorrected barrier, is still only 0.8 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="152"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">It can therefore be expected that the two minima will be indistinguishable even at the very low vibrational temperatures of supersonic jet experiments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="153"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac25" novelty="None" advantage="None">Indeed, plots of the H-density derived from diffusion Monte Carlo studies on hydrogen-bonded complexes like uracil–(H<SB>2</SB>O)<SB><IT>n</IT></SB> (<IT>n</IT> = 1–3)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF> and cytosine–(H<SB>2</SB>O)<SB>2</SB><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit38">38</REF> show a large-amplitude, banana-shaped, zero-point vibrational motion of the free water hydrogen atoms, covering the corresponding minima differing only in the position of the free water hydrogen (above or below the plane of the biomolecule).</annotationART></s> <s sid="154"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac25" novelty="None" advantage="None">This delocalised zero-point motion indicates that even at 0 K these minima cannot be differentiated experimentally.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="155"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs24" novelty="None" advantage="None">Table 3 shows the computed interaction energies of the 1∶1 AG3b–H<SB>2</SB>O hydrates.</annotationART></s> <s sid="156"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs25" novelty="None" advantage="None">Their structures, located with B3LYP/6-31+G*, are displayed in Fig. 9.</annotationART></s> <s sid="157"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac26" novelty="None" advantage="None">The AG3b hydrates in which water binds to the catechol OH groups are very similar in structure and interaction energy to their corresponding AG1c hydrates.</annotationART></s> <s sid="158"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac26" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, because AG3b has an NH⋯O hydrogen bond instead of the OH⋯N bond in AG1c, hydrates in which water binds to the side chain can be radically different.</annotationART></s> <s sid="159"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, the insertion structure in which the water molecule is located between the side-chain OH and NH<SB>2</SB> functional groups contains an OH⋯O<SB>w</SB>H<SB>w</SB>⋯N hydrogen-bond chain in AG1c–H<SB>2</SB>O, but an O⋯H<SB>w</SB>O<SB>w</SB>⋯NH hydrogen-bond chain in AG3b–H<SB>2</SB>O resulting in a 5 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> weaker interaction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="160"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The N⋯HO<SB>w</SB> interaction in the AG1c NH–O<SB>w</SB> hydrate, on the other hand, is replaced by a stronger N⋯H<SB>w</SB>O<SB>w</SB> hydrogen bond in AG3b–H<SB>2</SB>O.</annotationART></s> <s sid="161"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The specific water interaction energy (32 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>) shows that this is the most favourable water-binding site.</annotationART></s> <s sid="162"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The N–H<SB>w</SB>O<SB>w</SB> AG3b–H<SB>2</SB>O structure is of comparable stability to the most stable AG1c–H<SB>2</SB>O structure (catOH–O<SB>w</SB>), despite the 2.5 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> smaller stability of the AG3b conformer.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="163"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod11" novelty="None" advantage="None">We re-optimised the hydrogen-bond lengths with counterpoise corrections for a selection of the AG3b–H<SB>2</SB>O minima (see Table 3 for the resulting interaction energies and Fig. 9 for the hydrogen-bond distances).</annotationART></s> <s sid="164"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">The effect is very small for the B3LYP calculations, but the MP2/DZP<IT>i</IT> interaction energies are increased by 2.2–2.4 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="165"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs26" novelty="None" advantage="None">Unexpectedly, the effect is of similar magnitude for the π-bonded and conventional hydrogen-bonded structures.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="166"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The catOH–O<SB>w</SB> hydrates of AG1a and GG1a, the two most stable adrenaline conformers, are the most likely candidates for experimental observation, since the catOH–O<SB>w</SB> hydrate was found to be the observed NA–H<SB>2</SB>O structure.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">2</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="167"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs27" novelty="None" advantage="None">Table 4 lists the calculated infrared frequencies of these two structures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="168"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac27" novelty="None" advantage="None">(Infrared frequencies of the other hydrates are available upon request).</annotationART></s> <s sid="169"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs28" novelty="None" advantage="None">Comparison of the frequencies of the bare molecule (Table 1) with those of the hydrates (Table 4) reveals a strong red shift of the (OH)<SB>cat</SB> frequency, accompanied by a large increase in intensity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="170"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is due to hydrogen bonding with the water molecule, as was also observed for NA–H<SB>2</SB>O.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">2</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="171"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac28" novelty="None" advantage="None">Finally, we would like to comment on the calculation of the interaction energies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="172"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac29" novelty="None" advantage="None">As explained in the Methodology section, the interaction energies should be computed relative to the most stable conformer, more precisely, the most stable conformer for the method and basis set used.</annotationART></s> <s sid="173"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod12" novelty="None" advantage="None">For B3LYP/6-31+G* and single-point MP2 calculations with the 6-31+G* or aug-cc-pVDZ basis sets this is the AG1a conformer, but for MP2/DZP<IT>i</IT> this is the GG1a conformer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="174"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, the B3LYP/6-31+G* interaction energy of a particular AG1a–H<SB>2</SB>O hydrate will be the same as its specific water interaction energy, but the corresponding MP2/DZP<IT>i</IT> interaction energy will contain an energy penalty term reflecting the difference in stability of the AG1a and GG1a conformers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="175"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs29" novelty="None" advantage="None">In Table 5 we have listed the specific interaction energies, and <IT>D</IT><SB>e</SB>, for the catOH–O<SB>w</SB> hydrates of AG1a and GG1a.</annotationART></s> <s sid="176"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">As can be seen, B3LYP/6-31+G* favours the AG1a hydrate, whereas MP2/DZP<IT>i</IT> favours the GG1a hydrate.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Results from model potential calculations</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Adrenaline–H<SB>2</SB>O</HEADER><P><s sid="177"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac30" novelty="None" advantage="None">To understand the effect of water on the geometry of the biomolecule, one has to study clusters containing numerous water molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="178"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac30" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, there are several major problems with geometry optimisations of molecular clusters consisting of more than two constituents.</annotationART></s> <s sid="179"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac30" novelty="None" advantage="None">Firstly, the number of local minima increases steeply with the number of constituents in the cluster, and secondly, the convergence of the calculations slows down due to the coupling of inter- and intramolecular degrees of freedom.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit39">39</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="180"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac30" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, the individual energy calculations become much more computationally demanding.</annotationART></s> <s sid="181"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, to find all possible minima for the A–(H<SB>2</SB>O)<SB><IT>n</IT></SB> clusters of several low-lying adrenaline conformers using methods like DFT or MP2 becomes a near-impossible task.</annotationART></s> <s sid="182"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot4" novelty="None" advantage="None">We therefore need to find a computationally cheap, but reliable, method for exploring the potential energy surface of the A–(H<SB>2</SB>O)<SB><IT>n</IT></SB> (n &gt; 1) clusters.</annotationART></s> <s sid="183"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac31" novelty="None" advantage="None">The semi-empirical AM1 and PM3 methods are not suitable for this, as these methods failed to accurately predict the structure and relative stabilities of the different serotonin conformers.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit40">40</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="184"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj7" novelty="New" advantage="None">In this section, we explore the suitability of force-field calculations using the MP2fit/DMA<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF> rigid-body model potential for scanning the potential energy surface of the hydrates.</annotationART></s> <s sid="185"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The DMA electrostatic model of this potential accurately describes non-spherical features of the charge distribution, such as π-electron clouds and lone pairs, which play an important role in establishing the water-binding sites in the biomolecule.</annotationART></s> <s sid="186"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The model potential yields the interaction between two rigid monomer fragments, and thus, the MP2fit/DMA results should be compared to the B3LYP and MP2 <IT>specific</IT> water interaction energies.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="187"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj8" novelty="New" advantage="None">We will first investigate the performance of the model potential for locating the 1∶1 hydrates of the AG1c and AG3b conformers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="188"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs30" novelty="None" advantage="None">The resulting interaction energies are included in Tables 2 and 3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="189"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac32" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results are very encouraging.</annotationART></s> <s sid="190"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">All minima are found (we failed to locate one of the two O–H<SB>w</SB>O<SB>w</SB> AG1c hydrates, but as mentioned above, structures that only differ in the free H<SB>w</SB> orientation are basically the same structure).</annotationART></s> <s sid="191"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">The model potential generally yields interaction energies that are 2–4 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> larger than the corresponding B3LYP values, except for the π-bonded structures and the AG3c N–H<SB>w</SB>O<SB>w</SB> minimum, for which the model potential yields much larger interaction energies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="192"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The discrepancy between the DFT and MP2fit/DMA results for the π-bonded structures is due to the inability of DFT to properly describe these structures, rather than deficiencies in the model potential.</annotationART></s> <s sid="193"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is confirmed by the good agreement between the MP2fit/DMA and MP2/DZP<IT>i</IT> results for the π-bonded structures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="194"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac33" novelty="None" advantage="None">The discrepancy for the N-H<SB>w</SB>O<SB>w</SB> structure indicates a possible deficiency in the potential's parameters for N. The repulsion and dispersion parameters of O and H were adjusted to yield good agreement with MP2 data on the minima and transition states of uracil-water,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25">25</REF> but the N parameters were not attuned to <IT>ab initio</IT> data (they were derived from empirical fits to organic crystal structures and heats of sublimation<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit41 cit42 cit43">41–43</REF>), and thus, the N parameters may not be optimal for reproducing the gas-phase structures.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="195"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac34" novelty="None" advantage="None">Of particular interest are the insertion-type structures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="196"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac35" novelty="None" advantage="None">Because the MP2fit/DMA is a rigid-body potential, the adrenaline molecule cannot adjust its geometry to facilitate the water molecule to migrate between two of its functional groups.</annotationART></s> <s sid="197"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both insertion structures (OH–O<SB>w</SB>H<SB>w</SB>–N/O–H<SB>w</SB>O<SB>w</SB>–HN and catOH–O<SB>w</SB>H<SB>w</SB>–catO) were found with the model potential calculations, demonstrating that the rigidity of the model potential does not prevent these structures to be found.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Adrenaline-(H<SB>2</SB>O)<SB>2</SB></HEADER><P><s sid="198"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac36" novelty="None" advantage="None">Earlier work on uracil-(H<SB>2</SB>O)<SB>2</SB> and uracil-(H<SB>2</SB>O)<SB>3</SB> showed that the MP2fit/DMA potential yields good agreement with <IT>ab initio</IT> (MP2/DZP<IT>i</IT>) interaction energies and hydrogen-bond distances, despite the lack of many-body terms in the potential model.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="199"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac36" novelty="None" advantage="None">As the three-body contribution is about 25% for uracil-(H<SB>2</SB>O)<SB>2</SB>, this indicates that the model potential's repulsion and dispersion parameters, which have been determined by empirical parameterisation, must have absorbed some of the water-water non-additivity.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit44">44</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="200"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj9" novelty="New" advantage="None">In this section, we investigate the model potential suitability for A–(H<SB>2</SB>O)<SB>2</SB> clusters.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="201"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod14" novelty="None" advantage="None">We created AG3b–(H<SB>2</SB>O)<SB>2</SB> starting structures by systematically varying the position of the two water molecules in steps of 2 Å, in three orthogonal directions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="202"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Two different rotational orientations of the water molecules were considered.</annotationART></s> <s sid="203"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Structures in which one of the moieties overlapped with another one (as indicated by an intermolecular distance smaller than 1.2 Å) were discarded.</annotationART></s> <s sid="204"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Structures in which a water molecule was too far from the adrenaline molecule (closest intermolecular contact larger than 4 Å) were discarded as well.</annotationART></s> <s sid="205"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The geometries of the resulting 33 540 geometries were optimised with the MP2fit/DMA model potential.</annotationART></s> <s sid="206"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="Old" advantage="None">One geometry optimisation took approximately 1 minute of CPU time on a 1.7 GHz Pentium 4 PC.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="207"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs31" novelty="None" advantage="None">We found as many as 170 different minima; however, some of these are very similar in structure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="208"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs32" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 10 lists the twelve most stable structures found with MP2fit/DMA, in decreasing order of stability.</annotationART></s> <s sid="209"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">Structures 1, 4 and 11 are <IT>bridge</IT> structures: the two water molecules bridge the adrenaline chain oxygen and nitrogen functional groups.</annotationART></s> <s sid="210"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">In all these, the adrenaline chain oxygen acts as a hydrogen-bond acceptor.</annotationART></s> <s sid="211"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac37" novelty="None" advantage="None">Zwier suggested that such water bridges may be a preferred structural motif in cases where it can be formed.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit45">45</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="212"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs33" novelty="None" advantage="None">Structures 1 and 4 are very similar, with just small differences in the position of the free water hydrogens.</annotationART></s> <s sid="213"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs34" novelty="None" advantage="None">Structure 11 has a different hydrogen-bonding pattern than 1 and 4 (O⋯HO⋯HOH⋯N instead of O⋯HOH⋯OH⋯N).</annotationART></s> <s sid="214"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs35" novelty="None" advantage="None">In structures 2, 3, 5 and 6 the water molecules form a dimer structure, which is bonded to the adrenaline nitrogen.</annotationART></s> <s sid="215"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac38" novelty="None" advantage="None">We call these <IT>dimer addition</IT> structures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="216"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs36" novelty="None" advantage="None">The different dimer addition structures just differ in the position of the free water hydrogens, or in the direction of the hydrogen-bond chain itself.</annotationART></s> <s sid="217"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs37" novelty="None" advantage="None">The remaining five structures are <IT>double addition</IT> structures, formed by the addition of the two water molecules to two different functional groups of adrenaline: In structures 7 and 10 one water molecule binds to the nitrogen, while the other binds to the chain oxygen, whereas in structures 8 and 9 the second water binds to one of the catechol hydroxyl groups.</annotationART></s> <s sid="218"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs38" novelty="None" advantage="None">Structure 12 is a <IT>mixed insertion/addition</IT> structure: the first water molecule is inserted between the chain O and the NH group, whereas the second water molecule is added to the nitrogen.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="219"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod15" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have reoptimised the structures of these twelve hydrates, and of two lower-lying hydrates (23 and 28), with B3LYP/6-31+G*.</annotationART></s> <s sid="220"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs39" novelty="None" advantage="None">In structure 23 the two waters form a ring structure involving one of the catechol hydroxyls.</annotationART></s> <s sid="221"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs40" novelty="None" advantage="None">Structure 28 contains a water dimer bridging the chain OH and π-electron binding sites.</annotationART></s> <s sid="222"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" advantage="None">Structure 23 obeys the basic structural principle of XW<SB>2</SB> clusters in which X corresponds to an aromatic alcohol (catechol, in this case), which are equivalent to a water trimer in which one of the free hydrogens is replaced by the aromatic ring.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit39">39</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="223"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs41" novelty="None" advantage="None">Table 6 compares the MP2fit/DMA and B3LYP specific water interaction energies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="224"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs42" novelty="None" advantage="None">Most B3LYP-optimised structures are very similar to their corresponding MP2fit/DMA structures, but there are some important differences.</annotationART></s> <s sid="225"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None">AW2-8 and AW2-9 converge to the same minimum when reoptimised with B3LYP.</annotationART></s> <s sid="226"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs43" novelty="None" advantage="None">Two other structures (5 and 7) are not stable on the B3LYP potential energy surface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="227"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs44" novelty="None" advantage="None">Most worryingly though, we have found an additional structure with B3LYP (labelled AW2-global, see Fig. 10).</annotationART></s> <s sid="228"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs45" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this structure, the two waters bridge the chain OH and NH functional groups.</annotationART></s> <s sid="229"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs46" novelty="None" advantage="None">The adrenaline chain oxygen acts as a proton <IT>donor</IT> (in contrast to the other bridge structures, 1, 4 and 11, in which the oxygen acts as an acceptor).</annotationART></s> <s sid="230"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None">To allow this particular water-binding arrangement, the OH group has to rotate by as much as 60° around the C<SB>β</SB>–O bond, changing the hydroxyl hydrogen from a staggered to an eclipsed position with respect to the C<SB>β</SB> hydrogen.</annotationART></s> <s sid="231"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None">This internal rotation is not possible with the rigid-body MP2fit/DMA potential.</annotationART></s> <s sid="232"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Despite this large conformational distortion of adrenaline, costing 10 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>, the AW2-global structure is the most stable AG3b–(H<SB>2</SB>O)<SB>2</SB> hydrate located in this study.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="233"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">In general, B3LYP gives smaller AG3b–(H<SB>2</SB>O)<SB>2</SB> interaction energies than MP2fit/DMA.</annotationART></s> <s sid="234"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Though it is possible that DFT underestimates the AG3b–(H<SB>2</SB>O)<SB>2</SB> interaction energies, it is unlikely that they are underestimated by as much as 20 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="235"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, it is more likely that MP2fit/DMA overestimates the interaction energies, even though the potential did not overestimate uracil-(H<SB>2</SB>O)<SB>2</SB> interaction energies.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit46">46</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="236"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac39" novelty="None" advantage="None">As the model potential proved unsuitable to locate the A–(H<SB>2</SB>O)<SB>2</SB> structures, further investigation of this problem has not been pursued.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Discussion</HEADER><P><s sid="237"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac40" novelty="None" advantage="None">Even though environmental effects play an important role in modelling biological processes, an understanding of the intrinsic energetics of flexible biomolecules is essential for disentangling the relative importance of the intrinsic and environmental effects.</annotationART></s> <s sid="238"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res29" novelty="None" advantage="None">The most stable adrenaline/pseudoadrenaline conformers, in the gas phase, are those forming intramolecular hydrogen bonds: both the extended AG1 and the folded GG1 conformers contain an intramolecular OH⋯N hydrogen bond.</annotationART></s> <s sid="239"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac41" novelty="None" advantage="None">Naturally, under physiological conditions, adrenaline will not adopt its gas-phase geometry.</annotationART></s> <s sid="240"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac42" novelty="None" advantage="None">The structure of adrenaline in blood will be affected by environmental factors such as protonation, solvation and interaction with other molecules present, whereas the structure of the neurotransmitter in its receptor binding site will be influenced by competing hydrogen-bonding interactions with binding-site residues.</annotationART></s> <s sid="241"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac42" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, by studying the shape of biomolecules in the gas phase, the environmental effects can be eliminated, allowing the molecule-solvent interaction to be studied in a controlled environment.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="242"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac43" novelty="None" advantage="None">A recent computational study provided a prediction for the structure and function of G protein-coupled receptors, including the β1-adrenergic receptor.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit47">47</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="243"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac43" novelty="None" advantage="None">The study shows the two catechol OH groups forming hydrogen bonds with serine residues, whereas the chain hydroxyl and the amino group form hydrogen bonds with an aspartic acid, in good agreement with earlier mutation experiments.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit48 cit49 cit50 cit51">48–51</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="244"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac43" novelty="None" advantage="None">The study predicts that the catechol hydrogens point away from each other, an unfavourable orientation not considered in the current work.</annotationART></s> <s sid="245"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac43" novelty="None" advantage="None">Calculations show that this catechol group orientation is about 19 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> higher in energy than corresponding conformers in which the catechol OH groups form an intramolecular hydrogen bond.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit52">4,52</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="246"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac43" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, environmental factors appear to have a profound effect on the structure of the neurotransmitter.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="247"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac44" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our initial investigation of the adrenaline hydrates in this paper provides a first step in studying the environmental effects on the structure of adrenaline.</annotationART></s> <s sid="248"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hydration is believed to play an important role in the drug-receptor recognition process.</annotationART></s> <s sid="249"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac45" novelty="None" advantage="None">It has been proposed that the water surrounding the neurotransmitter and its receptor invokes the initial recognition process, possibly by a change in the receptor geometry induced by the structure-breaking effects of the catechol ring.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit53">53</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="250"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj10" novelty="New" advantage="None">In this study we have studied the 1∶1 hydrates of the AG1c and the 1∶1 and 1∶2 hydrates of the AG3b conformer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="251"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac46" novelty="None" advantage="None">For a complete study of adrenaline hydration, one would have to include several of the low-lying conformers, as the interaction with water may change their relative stability, and one would have to look at larger clusters (containing more water molecules) as well.</annotationART></s> <s sid="252"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac46" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is a formidable task, and would best be done in combination with an experimental study, which can provide guidance to the type of hydrates observed experimentally.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="253"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The current study shows the limitations of using a rigid-body potential for calculating the adrenaline hydrates.</annotationART></s> <s sid="254"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res30" novelty="None" advantage="None">While the model potential did find all relevant 1∶1 hydrates, including the insertion-type structures, it failed to locate the most stable 1∶2 hydrate, characterised by a large internal rotation around the C<SB>β</SB>–O bond.</annotationART></s> <s sid="255"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" advantage="None">A similar effect was observed for protonated nicotine-(H<SB>2</SB>O)<SB>2</SB>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF> Also for this system, the interaction with water induces a large conformational distortion, costing 12 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>, which allows the two water molecules to bridge the pyridine and pyrrolidinium rings.</annotationART></s> <s sid="256"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs47" novelty="None" advantage="None">Good agreement with the DFT results was obtained only when the distorted nicotine geometry (and its corresponding DMA) was used in the MP2fit/DMA model potential calculations.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="257"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, the model potential calculations can only be used as a guiding tool to find the most stable hydrates, as its rigid-body character prevents any water-induced conformational changes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="258"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac47" novelty="None" advantage="None">The study of the hydrates of flexible biomolecules remains a difficult and computationally expensive task.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Summary</HEADER><P><s sid="259"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj11" novelty="New" advantage="None">In this study, we have investigated the conformational structures of adrenaline (A) and pseudoadrenaline (PA) at the MP2 and DFT levels of theory.</annotationART></s> <s sid="260"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res32" novelty="None" advantage="None">The calculations predict the extended AG1a and folded GG1a adrenaline conformers to be nearly isoenergetic.</annotationART></s> <s sid="261"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res33" novelty="None" advantage="None">The pseudoadrenaline AG1a conformer on the other hand is more stable than GG1a by 3 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="262"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac48" novelty="None" advantage="None">It would be very interesting to see which A and PA conformers are formed in supersonic jet experiments.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="263"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj12" novelty="New" advantage="None">We have explored the molecular structures of the 1∶1 hydrates of the AG1c and the 1∶1 and 1∶2 hydrates of the AG3b adrenaline conformer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="264"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res34" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the most stable AG1c–H<SB>2</SB>O structure, the water molecule is bound as a proton acceptor to the <IT>p</IT>-OH catechol group, in a similar way as the most stable NA–H<SB>2</SB>O structure observed and predicted by theory.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">2</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="265"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res35" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the most stable AG3b–H<SB>2</SB>O structure the water molecule is bound as a proton donor to the chain nitrogen.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="266"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs48" novelty="None" advantage="None">The MP2fit/DMA rigid-body model potential, which contains an accurate DMA model to describe the electrostatic energy contribution to the potential energy, correctly predicts all AG1c–H<SB>2</SB>O and AG3b–H<SB>2</SB>O structures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="267"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs49" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the model potential fails to locate the most stable AG3b–(H<SB>2</SB>O)<SB>2</SB> structure located with B3LYP.</annotationART></s> <s sid="268"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None">This structure is characterised by a large conformational distortion of the adrenaline moiety, which cannot be described by the rigid-body model potential.</annotationART></s> <s sid="269"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None">This shows the limitation of rigid-body calculations in studies of biomolecular clusters.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="270"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None">To aid future spectroscopic assignment, we have provided infrared frequencies of the OH and NH stretch modes of the two most stable adrenaline conformers, AG1a and GG1a, and their most plausible singly hydrated clusters.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
