<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b316514k" hasDoc="yes" version="1168" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Kinetics of the reactions of the OH radical with 2-methyl-1-propanol, 3-methyl-1-butanol and 3-methyl-2-butanol between 241 and 373 K</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">Absolute rate constants have been measured for the gas-phase reactions of hydroxyl radicals with 2-methyl-1-propanol (<IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB>), 3-methyl-1-butanol (<IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB>) and 3-methyl-2-butanol (<IT>k</IT><SB>3</SB>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Experiments were carried out using two different techniques, the relative rate method and the pulsed laser photolysis-laser induced fluorescence technique.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The kinetic data were used to derive the following Arrhenius expressions in the temperature range 241–373 K(in units of cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>):<IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB> = (3.1±0.9) × 10<SP>−12</SP>exp[(352±82)/<IT>T</IT>]<IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB> = (2.8±0.9) × 10<SP>−12</SP>exp[(503±98)/<IT>T</IT>]<IT>k</IT><SB>3</SB> = (2.6±0.6) × 10<SP>−12</SP>exp[(456±65)/<IT>T</IT>]At 298 K, the reaction rate constants obtained by the two methods were in very good agreement.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results are presented, discussed and used to estimate the atmospheric lifetimes for the studied alcohols.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Alcohols are emitted into the atmosphere by a wide number of anthropogenic and natural processes.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The main sources are due to their use as solvent in different industries.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">For example, 2-methyl-1-propanol (isobutanol) is commonly used in coatings, as an additive in gasoline, an intermediate for glycol ethers and agricultural chemicals, and in anti-corrosion and anti-wear additives in engine oils.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">As a chemical intermediate, 2-methyl-1-propanol is used to make esters and ethers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">3-methyl-1-butanol (isopentanol) is used as a chemical intermediate and solvent, and in pharmaceutical products and medicines.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The release of these oxygenated volatile organic compounds is likely to contribute to the formation of ozone and other components of photochemical smog such as aldehydes, ketones and PAN-type compounds in urban areas.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">To assess the impact of these chemical species on the environment, a detailed understanding of the kinetics and mechanisms of their atmospheric degradation is required.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The gas-phase atmospheric oxidation of alcohols is primary initiated by reaction with OH radicals.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2 cit3">2,3</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Several kinetic studies of the OH reaction with alcohols have been reported previously.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2 cit3">2,3</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, only a limited number of studies have been conducted on the absolute measurements of the OH reaction rate constant with alcohols with more than four carbon atoms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None">In this article, we report the rate coefficient data for the reactions of OH radicals with 2-methyl-1-propanol (<IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB>), 3-methyl-1-butanol (<IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB>) and 3-methyl-2-butanol (<IT>k</IT><SB>3</SB>): OH + (CH<SB>3</SB>)<SB>2</SB>CHCH<SB>2</SB>OH→products: <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB>OH + (CH<SB>3</SB>)<SB>2</SB>CHCH<SB>2</SB>CH<SB>2</SB>OH→products: <IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB>OH + (CH<SB>3</SB>)<SB>2</SB>CHCH(OH)CH<SB>3</SB>→products: <IT>k</IT><SB>3</SB>Experiments were carried out using two different techniques.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The pulsed laser photolysis–laser induced fluorescence (PLP-LIF) technique was used to determine the absolute rate coefficients for the above reactions in the temperature range 241–373 K at around 100 Torr while the relative method enabled us to conduct the measurements at room temperature and atmospheric pressure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">As far as we know, this work provides the first temperature dependence studies for the three reactions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The only existing data reported in the literature are those of Hai <IT>et al</IT>. for 2-methyl-1-propanol<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF> Saunders <IT>et al</IT>. for 3-methyl-1-butanol<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF> and Wallington <IT>et al</IT>. for 3-methyl-2-butanol.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The present work also aims at extending the kinetic data base to be used to develop structure-reactivity relationships for OH reaction with oxygenated VOCs.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Experimental section</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Relative measurements</HEADER><P><s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="New" advantage="None">The experimental set-up used to measure the relative rate constant consisted of a 120 L Teflon bag and lamps positioned in a wooden box with the internal faces covered with aluminium foil.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Measured amounts of reagents were flushed from calibrated bulbs into the Teflon bag through a stream of ultra pure air.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The photoreactor was then filled to its full capacity at atmospheric pressure with ultra-pure air.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">OH radicals were produced by photolysing H<SB>2</SB>O<SB>2</SB> using lamps emitting at 254 nm (Sylvania G30W) and illuminating the hole gas sample.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">A gas chromatograph equipped with flame ionisation detector (GC-FID, CP-3800 or Star 3600 CX, Varian) was used for the quantitative analysis of the reactants.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Chromatographic separation was achieved by using a DB-1 capillary column (J&amp;W Scientific, 30 m, 0.25 nm id, 5 μm film).</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The column was operated at the temperature of 318 K, and helium was used as the carrier gas.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Absolute measurements</HEADER><P><s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The pulsed laser photolysis–laser induced fluorescence (PLP-LIF) technique and the methodology used have been described in detail previously [<IT>e.g.</IT> in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">ref. 7</REF>], only a brief description is given here.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hydroxyl radicals were produced by photolysis of H<SB>2</SB>O<SB>2</SB> at <IT>λ</IT> = 248 nm (KrF excimer laser) and their concentration was monitored at various reaction times ranging from about 10 μs to 10 ms by pulsed laser induced fluorescence.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">A Nd:YAG-pumped frequency-doubled dye laser was used to excite the OH radicals at <IT>λ</IT> = 282 nm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fluorescence from the OH radicals was detected by a photomultiplier, fitted with a 309 nm narrow bandpass filter.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The output pulse from the photomultiplier was integrated for a preset period by a gated charge integrator.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Typically the fluorescence signal from 10 different delay times and 100 probe laser shots were averaged to generate OH concentration-time profiles over at least three lifetimes.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">H<SB>2</SB>O<SB>2</SB> was introduced into the reaction cell by passing a small flow of helium through a glass bubbler containing H<SB>2</SB>O<SB>2</SB> solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Alcohols were premixed with helium in a 10 L glass bulb to form 0.2–0.6% mixture at a total pressure of about 850 Torr.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The gas mixture, the photolytic precursor (H<SB>2</SB>O<SB>2</SB>), and the bath gas (helium) flowed through the cell with a linear velocity ranging from 3 to 10 cm s<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The gas mixture illuminated was then renewed every two laser shots.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The concentrations of the reactants were calculated from their mass flow rates, the temperature, and the pressure in the reaction cell.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">All flow rates were measured with mass flow meters calibrated by measuring the rate of pressure increase in a known volume.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The pressure in the cell was measured with a capacitance manometer connected at the entrance of the cell.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The helium carrier gas (UHP certified to &gt;99.9995% (Alphagas)) was used without purification.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The 50 wt % H<SB>2</SB>O<SB>2</SB> solution, from Prolabo, was concentrated by bubbling helium through the solution to remove water for several days prior to use and constantly during the experiment.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">2-methyl-1-propanol (≥99.8 %), 3-methyl-1-butanol (≥99.5) and 3-methyl-2-butanol (≥99.5%) were from Fluka, they were further purified by repeated freeze, pump, and thaw cycles and fractional distillation before use.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Results and discussion</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Relative rate measurements</HEADER><P><s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Relative rate constants were measured by comparing the OH reaction rate with alcohols to that with reference compounds:OH + alcohol → products: <IT>k</IT><SB>alcohol</SB>OH + reference → products: <IT>k</IT><SB>ref</SB>Assuming that the compounds are only consumed by reaction with OH, it can be shown that:ln([alcohol]<SB>0</SB>/[alcohol]<SB><IT>t</IT></SB>) = (<IT>k</IT><SB>alcohol</SB>/<IT>k</IT><SB>ref</SB>)ln([ref]<SB>0</SB>/[ref]<SB><IT>t</IT></SB>)where the subscripts 0 and <IT>t</IT> indicate concentrations before irradiation and at time <IT>t</IT>, respectively.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rate constant for the reaction of OH with the three alcohols were measured at (298 ± 3) K and 760 Torr, relatively to the rate constant of OH with 1-butanol and 1,3-dioxolane.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The concentrations of alcohols and references were in the range 30–100 ppm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The compounds showed a good stability when they were mixed in the chamber with H<SB>2</SB>O<SB>2</SB> and kept in the dark for about 1 h.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Moreover, in absence of H<SB>2</SB>O<SB>2</SB>, the photolysis of the mixtures (alcohols and references in air) for more than one hour did not show any decrease in the concentrations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 1 shows an example of the obtained relative loss of alcohols versus that of the reference compounds in the presence of OH.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In Table 1, the obtained rate constant ratios are given along with the derived rate constants for the OH reactions with the three alcohols.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rate constants of the reaction of OH with the references used in this work were taken as (8.47 ± 0.34) × 10<SP>−12</SP> for 1-butanol,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF> and (11.1 ± 0.9) × 10<SP>−12</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP> for 1,3-dioxolane.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">While averaging the values from different experiments, we obtained:<IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB> = (0.92 ± 0.15) × 10<SP>−11</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>.<IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB> = (1.4 ± 0.2) × 10<SP>−11</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>.<IT>k</IT><SB>3</SB> = (1.25 ± 0.2) × 10<SP>−11</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>.The quoted errors represent twice the standard deviation, to which we have added an estimated error of 10% on the reference rate constants.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Absolute measurements</HEADER><P><s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Kinetic experiments have been performed under pseudo-first-order conditions with the concentration of alcohols in large excess over that of OH concentration ([alcohol]<SB>0</SB> &gt; 100[OH]<SB>0</SB>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Typically, the initial OH concentration, [OH]<SB>0</SB>, was around 2×10<SP>11</SP> molecule cm<SP>−3</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rate of disappearance of the OH radical followed a simple exponential rate law:[OH]<SB><IT>t</IT></SB> = [OH]<SB>0</SB>e<SP>−<IT>k</IT>′<IT>t</IT></SP> where <IT>k</IT>′ = <IT>k</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB> [alcohol] + <IT>k</IT>′<SB>0</SB><IT>k</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB> represents the rate constants for the reaction of OH with the three alcohols.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The decay rate <IT>k</IT>′ is the first-order OH disappearance rate in the presence of the alcohol and <IT>k</IT>′0 is the first-order rate constant for OH removal in absence of alcohol (attributed to the diffusion of OH radicals out of the detection zone and to their reaction with H<SB>2</SB>O<SB>2</SB>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Typically, alcohol and H<SB>2</SB>O<SB>2</SB> concentrations were in the ranges (1.6–92)×10<SP>13</SP> and (1–10)×10<SP>13</SP> molecule cm<SP>−3</SP>, respectively. <IT>k</IT>′0 and <IT>k</IT>′ were in the ranges 60–140 s<SP>−1</SP> and 200–13000 s<SP>−1</SP>, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Experiments were conducted in the temperature range 241–373 K and a total pressure of (106 ± 5) Torr of helium.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In all conditions, the OH decays were found to be exponential over at least three lifetimes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The high [alcohol]/[OH]<SB>0</SB> ratios and low OH concentrations made negligible contribution from secondary reactions involving the products of reactions to the measured rate constants.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The contribution of the reaction of OH with photofragments of alcohol was negligible since alcohols are not photolysed at 248 nm,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF> the wavelength used to generate OH radicals.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">As expected, variation in the photolysis fluence (3–26 mJ cm<SP>−2</SP>) had no effect on the determined rate constants.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The three alcohols were purified to better than 99.5% and hence loss of OH radicals by reaction with impurities in the gas mixtures is expected to be insignificant.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 2 shows examples of the plots of <IT>k</IT>′ versus the alcohol concentrations obtained at 298 K.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The obtained values of <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB>–<IT>k</IT><SB>3</SB> and the experimental conditions are listed in table 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The room temperature rate constant taken as the average of all values obtained at (298 ± 2) K are:<IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB> = (1.0 ± 0.1)×10<SP>−11</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>.<IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB> = (1.5 ± 0.1)×10<SP>−11</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>.<IT>k</IT><SB>3</SB> = (1.2 ± 0.1)×10<SP>−11</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>.The quoted errors for <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB>–<IT>k</IT><SB>3</SB> include 2<IT>σ</IT> from the least-squares analysis and the systematic error (5%, due to uncertainties in measured concentrations).</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">These values are in good agreement with those obtained by the relative method.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The measured values of <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB>–<IT>k</IT><SB>3</SB> shown in Table 2 are plotted in the Arrhenius form in Fig. 3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">An un-weighted least squares analysis of the ln <IT>k</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB><IT>vs.</IT> 1/<IT>T</IT> plot yields the following expressions for the temperature dependence of <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB>–<IT>k</IT><SB>3</SB> in the temperature range 241–373 K (in units of cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP> ):<IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB> = (3.1±0.9) × 10<SP>−12</SP>exp[(352±82)/<IT>T</IT>]<IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB> = (2.8±0.9) × 10<SP>−12</SP>exp[(503±98)/<IT>T</IT>]<IT>k</IT><SB>3</SB> = (2.6±0.6) × 10<SP>−12</SP>exp[(456±65)/<IT>T</IT>]Uncertainties are 2<IT>Aσ</IT><SB>ln<IT>A</IT></SB> and 2<IT>σ</IT><SB><IT>E</IT>/<IT>R</IT></SB>, for <IT>A</IT> and <IT>E</IT>/<IT>R</IT>, respectively.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rate constants obtained in this work are compared with the previously reported data in Table 3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">For isobutanol, the measured value of <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB> at room temperature is in good agreement with that obtained by Wu <IT>et al</IT>. using the relative rate method.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">These authors measured <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB> relative to the rate constant of OH reactions with propane and cyclohexane and obtained (9.08±0.35) × 10<SP>−12</SP> and (9.94±0.47) × 10<SP>−12</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Wu <IT>et al</IT>. measured also the rate constant for the reaction of OH with 3-methyl-1-butanol using the same references, they obtained (13.8±0.5) × 10<SP>−12</SP> and (13.7±1.1) × 10<SP>−12</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP> with propane and cyclohexane, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our measured value of <IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB> and that of Wu <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF>. are in agreement with that previously reported by Saunders <IT>et al</IT>. using the discharge flow–laser induced fluorescence (DF-LIF) technique at 1 Torr total pressure and 298 K (<IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB> = (13.1±2.6) × 10<SP>−12</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">For 3-methyl-2-butanol, our value of <IT>k</IT><SB>3</SB> at room temperature agrees with that reported earlier by Wallington <IT>et al</IT>. obtained using the flash photolysis–resonance fluorescence technique (<IT>k</IT><SB>3</SB> = (12.4±0.7) × 10<SP>−12</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">This work provides the first temperature dependence parameters for the OH reaction with 2-methyl-1-propanol, 3-methyl 1-butanol and 3-methyl 2-butanol.</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results show a negative temperature dependence for <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB>, <IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB> and <IT>k</IT><SB>3</SB> similarly to other alcohols for which temperature dependence data are available such as n-propanol, i-propanol and n-butanol.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj5" novelty="New" advantage="None">The present rate constant values <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB>–<IT>k</IT><SB>3</SB> can be compared with those calculated from the structure–activity relationship (SAR) of Atkinson based on group reactivity using the revised substituent factors <IT>F</IT>(–OH) = 2.9 and <IT>F</IT>(–CH<SB>2</SB>OH) = <IT>F</IT>(CHOH) = <IT>F</IT>(COH) = 2..6<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11 cit12">11,12</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">To calculate <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB>–<IT>k</IT><SB>3</SB> we used also the following parameters as defined by Kwok and Atkinson: <IT>F</IT>(–CH<SB>3</SB>) = 1, <IT>F</IT>(–CH<SB>2</SB>–) = <IT>F</IT>(CH–) = <IT>F</IT>(C) = 1.23, <IT>k</IT><SB>prim</SB> = 0.136, <IT>k</IT><SB>sec</SB> = 0.934, <IT>k</IT><SB>tert</SB> = 1.94 and <IT>k</IT><SB>OH</SB> = 0.14 (k are in units of 10<SP>−12</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>) where <IT>F</IT>(–CH<SB>3</SB>), <IT>F</IT>(–CH<SB>2</SB>–), <IT>F</IT>(CH–), and <IT>F</IT>(C) are the substituent factors and <IT>k</IT><SB>prim</SB>, <IT>k</IT><SB>sec</SB>, <IT>k</IT><SB>tert</SB> and <IT>k</IT><SB>OH</SB> represent the rate constants for the H-atom abstraction from –CH<SB>3</SB>, –CH<SB>2</SB>–, CH–, and –OH, respectively.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The calculated <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB>–<IT>k</IT><SB>3</SB> values compared to the experimental ones (in brackets) are <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB> = 0.89 (0.96) ; <IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB> = 0.92 (1.45) and <IT>k</IT><SB>3</SB> = 1.28 (1.23) (units of 10<SP>−11</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">While the experimental values of <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB> and <IT>k</IT><SB>3</SB> are in good agreement with the calculated ones, that of <IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB> is a factor of 1.6 higher than that calculated using the SAR.</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">It has to be noticed that this kind of discrepancy between the experimental and calculated rate constants values for the reaction of OH with hydroxyl-containing organic compounds has already been mentioned earlier.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12 cit13">12,13</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The measured <IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB> value supports the statement of Bethel <IT>et al</IT>. indicating that accurate estimation of OH radical rate constants for all hydroxyl-containing compounds (to within better than a factor of two) does not appear possible using the general approach of the SAR developed by Atkinson.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">One of the possible reasons for this discrepancy is that the SAR of Atkinson considers only effects of the OH substituent on H-atom abstraction at the α- and the β- positions for hydroxyl-containing compounds while the available data shows that the oxygenated functional groups have long-range effects with respect to H-atom abstraction at sites remote from the substituent groups.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">This long-range effect indicates an alternative pathway to the direct concerted hydrogen abstraction process such as the formation of a hydrogen-bonded complex in which, first, a hydrogen bond is formed between the H atom of the OH radical and the O atom of the oxygenated compound then a second hydrogen bond is formed between the O atom of the OH radical and a H atom in the hydrocarbon chain, resulting in intermolecular H-atom transfer via a cyclic transition state.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3 cit14">3,14</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">In all cases, the resulting reaction is an abstraction of a hydrogen atom from the oxygenated substrate.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">At room temperature, reaction of OH radicals with alcohols proceeds mainly by an H-atom abstraction process from the C–H bonds of the CH<SB>3</SB>–, –CH<SB>2</SB>- and CH– groups with a minor contribution of the H-atom abstraction from the -OH group.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2 cit15 cit16 cit17 cit18 cit19 cit20">2,15–20</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Product distribution studies on the reaction of OH radicals with long chain linear alcohols in the presence of NO<SB><IT>x</IT></SB> in air have shown that H-atom abstraction from different positions (α, β, or γ) to the –OH group makes a significant contribution to the total reaction.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2 cit11 cit12 cit13 cit14 cit15 cit16">2,11–16</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Under atmospheric conditions, the resulting hydroxy alkyl radicals react with oxygen.</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The α-hydroxy alkyl radicals formed through H-atom abstraction from the CH<SB><IT>x</IT></SB> group bonded to OH react solely with O<SB>2</SB> to lead to carbonyls:<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2 cit20">2,20</REF>RR′CHOH + OH → RR′C˙OH + H<SB>2</SB>ORR′C˙OH + O<SB>2</SB> → RR′C(O) + HO<SB>2</SB>The other hydroxy alkyl radicals (β, γ, <IT>etc.</IT>) react with O<SB>2</SB> and NO to lead to different alkoxy hydroxy radicals which then react with O<SB>2</SB> or decompose.</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, recent mechanistic studies have suggested that isomerization of this type of intermediate oxy radicals may also be important in the oxidation of long chain alcohols, through a six-membered transition state, leading to the formation of hydroxyketones and hydroxyaldehydes.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16 cit17 cit18 cit19">16–19</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the gas phase, the primary degradation step of alcohols in the troposphere is reaction with OH radicals since other processes such as reactions with O<SB>3</SB> and NO<SB>3</SB>, and photolysis are of minor importance.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2 cit3">2,3</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The measured OH reaction rate constants (<IT>k</IT>) along with a typical OH concentration of [OH] = 2 × 10<SP>6</SP> molecule cm<SP>−3</SP>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF> can be used to estimate the tropospheric lifetimes (<IT>τ</IT> = 1/<IT>k</IT>[OH]) of the studied alcohols.</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The derived lifetimes are around 10 h for the three alcohols which indicate that these compounds are quickly removed from the atmosphere and give rise to other stable products that have longer lifetimes such as acetone.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
