<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b404146a" hasDoc="yes" version="1168" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Pressure dependence of the reaction H + O<SB>2</SB> (+Ar) → HO<SB>2</SB> (+Ar) in the range 1–900 bar and 300–700 K</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">The reaction H + O<SB>2</SB> (+Ar) → HO<SB>2</SB> (+Ar) was studied in a high pressure flow cell in the bath gas argon at pressures between 1 and 900 bar and temperatures between 300 and 700 K. H atoms were generated by laser flash photolysis of NH<SB>3</SB> at 193.3 nm, HO<SB>2</SB> radicals were monitored by light absorption at 230 nm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results are consistent with experimental low pressure rate constants <IT>k</IT><SB>0</SB> = [Ar] 2.5 × 10<SP>−32</SP>(<IT>T</IT>/300 K)<SP>−1.3</SP> cm<SP>6</SP> molecule<SP>−2</SP> s<SP>−1</SP> and theoretical high pressure rate constants <IT>k</IT><SB>∞</SB> = 9.5 × 10<SP>−11</SP>(<IT>T</IT>/300 K)<SP>+0.44</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP> from the literature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The intermediate falloff curve was found to be best represented by <IT>k</IT>/<IT>k</IT><SB>∞</SB> = [<IT>x</IT>/(1 + <IT>x</IT>)]<IT>F</IT><SB>cent</SB><SP>1/(1+(<IT>a</IT>+log<IT>x</IT>)<SP>2</SP>/(<IT>N</IT> ± Δ<IT>N</IT>)<SP>2</SP>)</SP> with <IT>x</IT> = <IT>k</IT><SB>0</SB>/<IT>k</IT><SB>∞</SB>, <IT>a</IT> ≈ 0.3, <IT>N</IT> ≈ 1.05, Δ<IT>N</IT> ≈ 0.1 (+Δ<IT>N</IT> for (<IT>a</IT> + log <IT>x</IT>) &lt; 0 and −Δ<IT>N</IT> for (<IT>a</IT> + log <IT>x</IT>) &gt; 0), and <IT>F</IT><SB>cent</SB>(Ar) ≈ 0.5 independent of the temperature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">A comparison with literature data between 300 and 1200 K does not confirm major deviations from third order kinetics in earlier medium pressure experiments.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="1.">Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is well known that the chain-terminating reaction H + O<SB>2</SB> (+M) → HO<SB>2</SB> (+M) is of central importance in the oxidation of hydrogen-containing molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Its rate at low pressures has been measured repeatedly<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF> since about 1945<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">2</REF> and the uncertainty of the third order low pressure rate constant <IT>k</IT><SB>0</SB> today is estimated to be about ±25%.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Investigations of a transition to the high pressure range of the reaction have been made only rarely.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In experiments at 300 K up to pressures of 200 bar of the bath gas Ar the pseudo-second order rate constant <IT>k</IT> was found to fall about a factor of 10 below the extrapolated <IT>k</IT><SB>0</SB>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Studies of the H<SB>2</SB>–O<SB>2</SB>–NO<SB><IT>x</IT></SB> reaction in Ar between 800 and 900 K and at pressures of 1–14 bar could not detect substantial deviations from third order.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">More recent shock tube measurements<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6">5,6</REF> at Ar-pressures up to 110 bar and temperatures around 1300 K realized marked deviations from the third order low pressure limit.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">These experiments, however, were disputed<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF> on the basis of statistical adiabatic channel/classical trajectory (SACM/CT) predictions<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF> of the high pressure rate constant <IT>k</IT><SB>∞</SB> combined with calculations of <IT>k</IT>([M]) in the falloff range of the reaction.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The pressure dependence of the reaction may appear to be of only limited interest for normal combustion since deviations from third order occur only at comparably high pressures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, because of the large importance of the reaction in combustion, even modest deviations may become relevant when precise rate constants are required.</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is particularly true when the bath gas is a very efficient collider such as water.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">There is considerable interest in the high pressure properties of the reaction in the field of supercritical water oxidation where temperatures are of the order of 800–1000 K and water pressures are around 250 bar.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10 cit11 cit12">10–12</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to decide the above mentioned dispute<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6 cit7">6,7</REF> and to provide data for the construction of precise high temperature falloff curves, we have designed a new high pressure flow cell and investigated the reaction at pressures of the bath gas argon up to 900 bar and over the temperature range 300–700 K. These experiments now allow us to characterize the pressure dependence of the reaction up to temperatures such as they are of interest for combustion and supercritical water oxidation applications.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.">Experimental technique</HEADER><P><s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our high pressure flow cell was made from highly heat resistent stainless steel (Inconel alloy 718 from Special Metals Co.).</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The internal diameter of the cylindrical cell was 22 mm and its optical pathlength was 100 mm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The cell was closed with quartz windows of 20 mm thickness at both ends.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Reaction mixtures were slowly flowing through the cell in such a way that the complete volume was exchanged between individual runs of the experiments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The cell could be heated up to 900 K at pressures up to 1000 bar, the temperatures in the cell were controlled by thermocouples.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reaction mixtures were preheated before flowing through the cell; gas temperatures in the cell were found to be constant within about 2%.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Reaction mixtures consisting of 10<SP>−4</SP>–1% of O<SB>2</SB>, 0.1–100 ppm of NH<SB>3</SB> and the bath gas Ar (99.9999%) were prepared in storage vessels and compressed by an oil-free membrane compressor.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">H atoms were produced by laser flash photolysis of NH<SB>3</SB> using an ArF excimer laser at 193 nm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">HO<SB>2</SB> radicals were monitored by light absorption at 230 nm using a high pressure Hg–Xe arc lamp as light source.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Typically about 1000 runs were averaged.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Rise times of the HO<SB>2</SB> signals of the order of 1 μs and decay times of the order of 15 μs were observed, see Fig. 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rise of the HO<SB>2</SB> signal was almost entirely dominated by the reaction H + O<SB>2</SB> → HO<SB>2</SB> and it was only marginally influenced by secondary reactions which were modelled by a complete mechanism such as characterized by the data given in .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">ref. 1</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The HO<SB>2</SB> profile of Fig. 1 documents the quality of the signal and demonstrates the different time scales of the rise of the HO<SB>2</SB> concentration and its decrease due to loss processes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The pseudo-first-order rate constants for HO<SB>2</SB> formation were strictly proportional to the concentration of O<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">More details of our experimental technique, the modelled mechanism and results for other bath gases such as helium and nitrogen will be described in a later publication.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">At this stage we only report the results obtained in argon because a comparison with the high pressure measurements from <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3 cit4 cit5 cit6">refs. 3–6</REF> can be made for this bath gas.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.">Results</HEADER><P><s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Without tabulating the individual measured points in this communication, Fig. 2 summarizes our results in a doubly reduced falloff plot. <IT>k</IT>/<IT>k</IT><SB>∞</SB> is shown as a function of <IT>k</IT><SB>0</SB>/<IT>k</IT><SB>∞</SB>, employing the recommended experimental low pressure rate constant <IT>k</IT><SB>0</SB> = [Ar]2.5 × 10<SP>−32</SP>(<IT>T</IT>/300 K)<SP>−1.3</SP> cm<SP>6</SP> molecule<SP>−2</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>from the evaluation in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">ref. 1</REF>, and the theoretical high pressure rate constant <IT>k</IT><SB>∞</SB> = 9.5 × 10<SP>−11</SP>(<IT>T</IT>/300 K)<SP>+0.44</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>from .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">ref. 8</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The latter was calculated with an <IT>ab initio</IT> potential energy surface of HO<SB>2</SB> and employing an SACM/CT approach.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results of this treatment in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14 cit15 cit16">refs. 14–16</REF> were compared with calculations made on the DMBE IV potential energy surface<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF> and the expression for <IT>k</IT><SB>∞</SB> given in eqn. (3) was confirmed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 2 indicates that a common reduced falloff plot can represent all data from 300 to 700 K. We found that the conventional<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF> symmetric falloff expression with <IT>x</IT> = <IT>k</IT><SB>0</SB>/<IT>k</IT><SB>∞</SB> and <IT>N</IT> ≈ 0.75 − log <IT>F</IT><SB>cent</SB> did only provide a fair fit of the data from Fig. 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Instead an asymmetric falloff expression<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9 cit19">9,19</REF>produced better agreement with the data and with the modelled falloff curves.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">This fit is included in Fig. 2 with the parameters <IT>a</IT> ≈ 0.3, <IT>N</IT> ≈ 0.75 − log <IT>F</IT><SB>cent</SB> ≈ 1.05, Δ<IT>N</IT> ≈ 0.1 (+Δ<IT>N</IT> for (<IT>a</IT> + log <IT>x</IT>) &lt; 0 and −Δ<IT>N</IT> for (<IT>a</IT> + log <IT>x</IT>) &gt; 0).</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The center broadening factor <IT>F</IT><SB>cent</SB>(Ar) ≈ 0.5 as well as the parameters <IT>a</IT> and Δ<IT>N</IT> were found to be essentially independent of the temperature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Eqns. (2), (3), and (5) serve for the construction of full sets of falloff curves such as shown in Fig. 3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The agreement between the present results and the given expression, of course, is the result of fixing the fit parameters.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">One realizes that the experiments from <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">ref. 4</REF> correspond practically to the low pressure limit.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The experiments from <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6">refs. 5 and 6</REF>, on the other hand, are found to be somewhat further into the transition range between <IT>k</IT><SB>0</SB> and <IT>k</IT><SB>∞</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, in agreement with the conclusions from <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">ref. 6</REF>, one finds that the highest points from <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">ref. 6</REF> for some unknown technical reason are probably too low.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">One has to realize that the precision of the shock wave experiments was not good enough to provide precise information on the shape of the falloff curve such as this was possible in the present work.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Nevertheless, it cannot be ruled out that complications, which were not considered in the theoretical modelling of <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">ref. 9</REF>, at high temperatures lead to additional broadenings of the falloff curves.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Such complications, <IT>e.g.</IT>, may arise from nonstatistical lifetime distributions of HO<SB>2</SB>* such as suggested for H<SB>2</SB>O<SB>2</SB>* in .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">ref. 20</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, unless such effects are clearly proven to exist, the falloff curves derived in the present work should be used in all practical applications.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.">Conclusions</HEADER><P><s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The present experiments have provided strong experimental support for the previously modelled<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7 cit8 cit9">7–9</REF> falloff curves of reaction (1) over wide ranges of temperatures and pressures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">After accounting for different values of <IT>k</IT><SB>0</SB> in different bath gases,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF> eqns. (2), (3), and (5) will provide an adequate basis for representing <IT>k</IT> in the fields of high pressure combustion and supercritical water oxidation.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
