<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b408850f" hasDoc="yes" version="1168" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Miniaturised nucleic acid analysis</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The application of micro total analysis systems has grown exponentially over the past few years, particularly diversifying in disciplines related to bioassays.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The primary focus of this review is to detail recent new approaches to sample preparation, nucleic acid amplification and detection within microfluidic devices or at the microscale level.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">We also introduce some applications that have as yet to be explored in a miniaturised environment, but should benefit from improvements in analytical efficiency and functionality when transferred to planar-chip formats.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The studies described in this review were published in commonly available journals as well as in the proceedings of three major conferences relevant to microfluidics (Micro Total Analysis Systems, Transducers and The Nanotechnology Conference and Trade Show).</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although an emphasis has been placed on papers published since 2002, pertinent articles preceding this publication year have also been included.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The polymerase chain reaction (PCR) has succeeded in revolutionising the analysis of nucleic acids.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Disciplines both directly and indirectly related to the life sciences can readily exploit PCR, and with various genome study initiatives increasingly making available sequence data, this trend is set to continue into the future.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Most striking has been the synonymous advent of real-time PCR and delivery of a robust quantitative gene measuring tool.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="No">However, the post-genome era brings with it new problems and exposes old fissures that have undermined the application of PCR.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The scaling-up of pre-existing procedures for higher throughput would be inappropriate for continuous environmental monitoring and population studies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Indeed, when attempted this approach reveals the necessary requirement to integrate gene analysis into a process that serves best to eliminate both sampling and experimental error.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Miniaturisation of PCR integrated bioassays potentially possesses all of the desired qualities and comes with additional benefits relating to sample tracking, contamination, and savings in finances and time.</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="No">Long ignored issues relating to the meaningfulness of data are starting to be questioned.</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Biological matter is comprised from the unit of life, the cell, and gene analysis is portrayed in terms of gene abundance, presence, or absence, within a particular biological sample.</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Tissues are heterogeneous, in that many types of different cells co-exist within biological samples.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="No">However, most PCR experimental testing to date does not clearly relate the gene content measured to the contribution made by all specific cell types.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">Increasingly the need to analyse from the single cell is gaining in popularity, and once again the packaging and process offered by integrated miniaturised PCR offers great promise.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Indeed, when considered alongside the potential to dissect the PCR process itself to understand more how to increase and maintain PCR efficiency, the miniaturisation of PCR and future PCR applications seem to become permanently entwined.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The majority of developments in miniaturisation have stemmed from institutes with strong analytical, engineering, fabrication and optical specialisations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The influx of interdisciplinary interest offers distinct and critical benefits to the application driven life sciences.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">Therefore, to allow researchers from engineering and life science backgrounds to reflect on the recent progress and to help traverse interdisciplinary boundaries, we have compiled a concise review of papers based around nucleic acid assay miniaturisation and microfluidic PCR, and set these against a framework of biological applications.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reader is also directed to other reviews covering either a wide range of applications,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2">1,2</REF> or specific fields such as DNA and protein analysis,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF> genomics and proteomics analysis<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF> or molecular diagnostics<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Theoretical aspects</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Description of the polymerase chain reaction (PCR)</HEADER><P><s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The PCR is a three-step amplification process first introduced by Saiki and co-workers in .1985<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">This in-vitro enzyme-mediated method facilitates the generation of nucleic acid sequences based on the choice of specific primers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">During the first step—called denaturation—the hydrogen bonding stabilising the double stranded DNA template is broken to form two complementary single strands (see Fig. 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In order to provide the energy necessary to break the bonding, this step is commonly performed at temperatures between 94 °C and 96 °C.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The temperature is then lowered for the annealing step: primers (synthetic sequences of single stranded DNA—normally 17–25 nucleotides long—which flank the target region to be amplified) specifically bind to the complementary sequences of the DNA template.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">At this stage, the temperature is primer-dependant and usually varies between 50 °C and 65 °C.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Finally the temperature is raised to allow extension: the template is typically replicated by a thermostable DNA polymerase.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">This temperature is often close to 72 °C, which is related to the temperature optimum of the DNA polymerase in conjunction with retaining hybridisation specificity of primers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The denaturation-annealing-extension cycle is repeated, typically between 25 and 40 times.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Although these three steps are performed at three different temperatures, it is not uncommon to combine the annealing and the extension into one operation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Interestingly, at the end of the 1st cycle, the product obtained is defined only at one end, as the replication is a function of time at the extension temperature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is only at the end of the 2nd cycle that the specific product is first produced.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Another interesting point is that two types of replication occur at the same time: semi-specific products such as those from cycle 1 lead to linear replication, whereas truly specific products or amplicons that are defined at both ends lead to exponential replication.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although the linear replication process is negligible in terms of amounts of DNA produced, it is a crucial intermediary step in PCR as it is through linear replication that a specific amplicon is obtained, thus rendering exponential amplification possible.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since 1985, different parameters for the PCR have been extensively studied to optimise the reaction and maximise amplification yield throughout a number of constraints imposed by different bioassays.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">The extraction of a thermostable enzyme, <IT>Taq</IT>, from the bacterium <IT>Thermus aquaticus</IT> was the first breakthrough.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7 cit8 cit9">7–9</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="No">Prior to this discovery, the enzyme was heat labile and lost its activity after each denaturation step.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="No">Consequently, the polymerase had to be replenished after each cycle which was arduous, but importantly increased the risks of contamination during PCR as the sample vial had to be re-opened, and made optimisation almost impossible to achieve.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">The introduction of a thermostable enzyme obviated this cumbersome procedure and also enabled the automation of the process.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Ensuing <IT>Taq</IT> polymerase engineering succeeded in enhancing processivity (which is defined for polymerases as the number of nucleotides added per unit to a strand during one sequence of binding and dissociation from the primer template) and fidelity (capability of a polymerase to faithfully replicate a DNA strand without expansion or deletion in the number of base pairs, nor substitution of the bases (AT ↔ CG)).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this study, a recombinant <IT>Taq</IT> polymerase-thioredoxin displayed an increase in processivity when compared to the wild-type <IT>Taq</IT> polymerase (from 50–80 nt to &gt;300 nt).</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Other enzymes such as <IT>Pfu</IT>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF> KlenTaq,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF><IT>Vent</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF> or <IT>Tfi</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF> have been applied to PCR.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Significantly, some enzymes are nowadays modified to block their activity until they are heat activated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is for example the case of PfuUltra<SP>™</SP> Hotstart DNA polymerase, which is commercialised by Stratagene.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this instance, heat labile antibodies neutralise the enzyme activity until they are denaturated during the initial PCR denaturation step.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Such a procedure limits the formation of non-specific products, as it impairs the enzyme activity until thermocycling temperatures are reached.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Priming methods comparing poly(A) tails and random hexamers for cDNA synthesis were studied by Resuehr and co-workers,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF> while Halford <IT>et al.</IT> studied the effect of primer-dimer formation over the PCR yield.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Protocols to optimise PCR reactions are nowadays readily available.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17 cit18">17,18</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">PCR has also been studied from a more theoretical approach and statistical models describing the reaction are often based on the branching theory.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19">19</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Based on this theory, the number of molecules generated by a PCR reaction starting with a single molecule after n cycles is: (1 + p)<SP>n</SP>, where p is the probability for a molecule to duplicate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Such an equation leads to two consequences.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Firstly, the value p is positively linked to the PCR yield.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Secondly, for large values of p, the distribution of the DNA population becomes multinodal, presenting multiple probability peaks.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is due to the amplification during the initial cycle becoming critical and a failure for the original molecule to replicate having a lasting impact.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is consequently essential to optimise the PCR parameters in order to obtain the most favourable conditions and enhance the PCR yield.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Strand-displacement based amplification</HEADER><P><s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although PCR is the most popular DNA amplification technique, other methods also exist<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF> and are potentially suitable for microfluidic-based devices.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">For example, S<IT>ingle Strand Displacement Amplification</IT> (SSDA) is an isothermal technique first introduced by Walker <IT>et al.</IT> in .1992<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">Comparably to PCR, this method allows exponential amplification of double-stranded DNA.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The <IT>Multiple Strand Displacement Amplification</IT> (MSDA) technique is similar to SSDA, with the only difference being that during extension of the complementary strand, new annealing sites are generated for the first primer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac20" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although MSDA can be applied with specific primers, it has also been used with random hexamers, leading to the amplification of entire genomes.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac20" novelty="None" advantage="None">Such an amplification process produces tree-like molecules leading to amplified molecules of different lengths.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac20" novelty="None" advantage="None">Indeed the generated strands are not cleaved from the strand molecule from which the amplification originated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">A few products using this technique are commercially available, such as GenomiPhi<SP>™</SP> DNA amplification offered by Amersham Biosciences, and REPLI-g<SP>™</SP> from Molecular Staging.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Notomi <IT>et al.</IT> developed another method for DNA amplification: <IT>Loop-mediated isothermal AMPlification</IT> (LAMP).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">This technique is based on MSDA but instead of using a set of two specific primers, or random hexamers, it involves 3 sets of specific primers.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Other DNA amplification techniques</HEADER><P><s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Lizardi and co-workers used circularisable oligonucleotide priming to investigate amplification of circular DNA templates.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="Old" advantage="None">This method, called <IT>Rolling-Circle Amplification</IT> (RCA), produces a single-stranded product initialised by only one primer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">Although this technique might seem limited as it only applies to circular templates with an appropriate promoter, a wider variety of applications are technically possible as circular templates include viruses and plasmids.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac21" novelty="None" advantage="None">RCA has been coupled to other techniques such as MSDA,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF> or RCA itself (<IT>Circle-to-Circle Amplification</IT>).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25">25</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The <IT>Ligase Chain reaction</IT> was initially introduced by Landefren <IT>et al.</IT> in 1988 and is based on the ability of two oligonucleotides to hybridise next to each other given an appropriate complementary DNA target molecule.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26">26</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Although this method was introduced as a single-base-modification detection method, it has since been used for the sole purpose of DNA replication.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27">27</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The merging of PCR with gene micro-array applications has been demonstrated by <IT>Solid Phase DNA Amplification</IT> (SPA).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28 cit29">28,29</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac22" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this method, the primers are surface-bound and thus do not freely diffuse in solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="Old" advantage="None">A Monte Carlo Lattice model was proposed by Mercier and co-workers to discribe solid phase amplification.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19">19</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">As the amount of DNA generated is directly dependent on the number of primers immobilised at the surface, SPA would highly benefit from on-chip applications where area-to-volume ratios are greatly enhanced.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The application of PCR to define specific sequences for subsequent use as micro-array probes has also recently been described by Greiner <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30">30</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Substrates used and surface treatments to minimise bio-molecule adsorption</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Substrates</HEADER><P><s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac23" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although microfluidic devices were originally structured in silicon or glass, polymers such as poly(dimethylsiloxane) (PDMS), Poly(methylmethacrylate) (PMMA) and Polycarbonate (PC) have increasingly been used as alternative substrate materials.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac23" novelty="None" advantage="None">The search for new substrate materials is still a burgeoning area, and many recent microfluidic devices for PCR have been fabricated using SU-8, PEEK, PTFE, Cyclic-Olefin-Copolymer (COC) or Zeonor (polymer commonly used for compact discs and DVDs).</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac23" novelty="None" advantage="None">For a more detailed overview of some of the materials used, the reader should refer to references in Table 1.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Surface treatment</HEADER><P><s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac24" novelty="None" advantage="None">The efficiency of biological reactions is often limited by interactions between the microchannel surfaces and the bio-molecules present in solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac24" novelty="None" advantage="None">This issue is even more exacerbated by the wide variety of possible substrate material (see Table 1) in conjunction with the vast range of biological matter used as analyte; consequently various surface treatments have been investigated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="Old" advantage="None">One of the most widely used processes to prevent on-chip adsorption of molecules consists of silanisation, a method first introduced by Hjertén in .1985<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit58">58</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac25" novelty="None" advantage="None">For example, El-Ali <IT>et al.</IT> performed a gas phase silanisation of a SU-8 chamber surface in order to enhance its PCR compatibility.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit44">44</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac26" novelty="None" advantage="None">Similarly, Shin and co-workers studied different silane compositions to decrease protein adsorption at glass surfaces.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit59">59</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac27" novelty="None" advantage="None">Noteworthy is that even though silanisation has been successfully applied to microfluidic devices, criticisms regarding the reproducibility of such coatings have been argued.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit60">60</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac27" novelty="None" advantage="None">To circumvent this issue, several methods have been investigated, and for instance, different strategies were implemented to prevent protein adsorption in PDMS microfluidic devices.</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac27" novelty="None" advantage="None">Choi <IT>et al.</IT> favoured a mixture of poly(ethylene glycol) and poly(acrylic),<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit61">61</REF> while Xiao and co-workers used a polyacrylamide gel.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit49">49</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac27" novelty="None" advantage="None">Alternatively, Shin and co-workers coated PDMS micro-channels with parylene in order to prevent adsorption on the chip surface.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit62">62</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac27" novelty="None" advantage="None">An additional approach was introduced when Kirby <IT>et al.</IT> studied the effect of polarity and surface charge on cell adsorption by controllably modifying the zeta potential at the surface of their device<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit39">39</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Sample preparation</HEADER><P><s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac28" novelty="None" advantage="None">The following section addresses recent studies in the areas of cell culturing, cell identification and cell trapping, cell lysis and DNA extraction within microfluidic formats.</annotationART></s></P><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Cell culture</HEADER><P><s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac29" novelty="None" advantage="None">Much attention has focussed on the transfer of cell culturing techniques to planar chip formats.</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met14" novelty="Old" advantage="None">For example, Grodrian <IT>et al.</IT> applied the principle of segmented flow on chip for parallel cell culture by separating culture media plugs with immiscible fluid.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit63">63</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Alternatively, Tan and co-workers recreated a tissue-like structure in a micro-fluidic environment using cell-matrix assemblies and biopolymers,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit64">64</REF> while Schaak <IT>et al.</IT> have performed cell culture in droplets.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit65">65</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met16" novelty="Old" advantage="None">To assess the viability of the cultured cells Goto and co-workers implemented a protocol to detect nitric oxide released by macrophages<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit66">66</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Cell identification and cell trapping</HEADER><P><s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac30" novelty="None" advantage="None">Biological samples are most often present as a complex matrix.</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac30" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is therefore of paramount importance to be able to differentiate cells or targets of interest from other biological material.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met17" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Different approaches have been implemented on chip, where for example, Lin <IT>et al.</IT> introduced an in-vitro impedance measurement of cells to distinguish between abnormal cells and normal cells under different frequency domains.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit67">67</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met18" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Alternatively, Emmelkamp and co-workers chose an optical detection technique for sorting cells based on their intrinsic fluorescence signal within a microfluidic structure.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit36">36</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac31" novelty="None" advantage="None">After having detected the cell of interest, the next step is usually some form of isolation and concentration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met19" novelty="Old" advantage="None">To this extent, different techniques have been implemented on chip, such as dielectrophoresis (DEP).</annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac32" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fuchs and co-workers have used DEP to trap individual particles among a few thousand cells suspended in a liquid on a microelectronic chip.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit68">68</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac32" novelty="None" advantage="None">Similarly, during a study of blood components and their inhibitory effects on PCR, Wolff and co-workers captured cells on electrodes by DEP while inhibitors were eluted by washing.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit69">69</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met20" novelty="Old" advantage="None">An alternative to conventional DEP has been proposed by Lapizco-Encinas <IT>et al.</IT> and involved electrodeless DEP for cell trapping.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit70">70</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met21" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Capillary electrophoresis was also used by Park <IT>et al.</IT> to demonstrate the capture and subsequent release of DNA fragments within PEEK tubing.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit50">50</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac33" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although DEP and electrophoresis are widely used techniques for cell trapping, other methods have also been investigated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met22" novelty="Old" advantage="None">For example, Denoual <IT>et al.</IT> presented a microfluidic device in which cells could be directed to cell traps by the fluid flow.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit71">71</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met23" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Lettieri and co-workers have also introduced a microfluidic device for performing controlled micro re-circulating flow capable of DNA trapping.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit72">72</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met23" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Two flows (an electroosmotic flow and a pressure-driven flow) were opposed and molecules were trapped by adjusting the different velocities.</annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met24" novelty="Old" advantage="None">From another perspective Goubault <IT>et al.</IT> captured rare cells using magnetic filaments and adjusted the specific/non-specific discrimination ratio by optimising flow rates,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit73">73</REF> while Lu and co-workers presented a rapid organelle separation by free flow isoelectric focusing.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit74">74</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met25" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Electrophoresis has also been used to increase sample concentration, where Halle <IT>et al.</IT> introduced a micro-fluidic free-flow zone electrophoresis device to concentrate biological particles in buffer<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit75">75</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Cell lysis and DNA extraction/manipulation</HEADER><P><s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met26" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In order to extract the different nucleic acid analytes from within a cell, controlled lysis is usually performed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met26" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Although regularly achieved by heating the cell,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit54 cit76 cit77">54,76,77</REF> other lysis methods have been developed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met26" novelty="Old" advantage="None">For example, strong ultrasonic fields were applied by Tachibana <IT>et al.</IT>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit78">78</REF> whereas Marmottant and co-workers presented an experiment during which gentle bubble oscillations were successfully applied to rupture lipid membranes.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit79">79</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met26" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Lu and co-workers also presented a miniaturised device for controlled cell lysis in order to release sub-cellular materials.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit80">80</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met26" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Chemical lysis was performed by both Schilling <IT>et al.</IT>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit81">81</REF> and Hong and co-workers.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit82">82</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac34" novelty="None" advantage="None">Once cell lysis has been performed, the issue of DNA extraction can be addressed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met27" novelty="Old" advantage="None">For example, Reddy and co-workers presented an organic-aqueous liquid extraction on a micro-device in order to purify DNA obtained directly from cells.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit83">83</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met28" novelty="Old" advantage="None">On the other hand, Bienvenue <IT>et al.</IT> implemented a sol-gel technique to extract DNA.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit34">34</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac35" novelty="None" advantage="None">Other groups have favoured more targeted approaches to isolate DNA from its medium.</annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met29" novelty="Old" advantage="None">For example, Washizu and co-workers used electrostatic fields for direct DNA manipulations<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit84">84</REF> and Mohanty <IT>et al.</IT> applied dielectrophoresis and electrical impedance spectroscopy for single cell manipulation within microfluidic systems.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit85">85</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met30" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Finally, Sundararjan and co-workers demonstrated immobilisation and programmable release of single DNA molecules by electrical heating<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit86">86</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Microfluidic DNA amplification</HEADER><P><s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac36" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since its introduction PCR sustains a tremendous impact in several fields, including clinical diagnostics, medical sciences and forensics.</annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac37" novelty="None" advantage="None">However this technique presents several drawbacks.</annotationART></s> <s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="No">For example, the costs associated with each reaction are still quite high (mostly due to the price of the enzyme), even if current parallel processing has attenuated costs.</annotationART></s> <s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met14" novelty="Old" advantage="No">It is also well documented that PCR is highly prone to contamination due to its efficiency and high sensitivity.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit87 cit88">87,88</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met31" novelty="None" advantage="Yes">Additionally, a common advantage of miniaturised systems over macro apparatus is their reduced thermal mass: as they present less inertia to temperature changes ramping rates for heating or cooling are drastically increased, and this gives rise to more rapid gene amplification, and may present benefit for some of the conformation fluorescence resonance energy transfer (FRET) probes used in real-time PCR.</annotationART></s> <s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac38" novelty="None" advantage="None">Whilst several of the more successful and reproducible applications of PCR are manifested in qualitative analyses, increasingly the requirements of PCR testing are placing a burden on elucidating a robust means to accurate and precise gene quantitation.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit89">89</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac38" novelty="None" advantage="None">For example, the definition of therapeutically significant disease thresholds could be used to more effectively treat infections or other diseases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met32" novelty="New" advantage="None">Therefore the cumbersome processes that endure sample losses and sample degradation, ultimately compromise gene quantitation can be circumvented by employing closed μTAS.</annotationART></s></P><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Well-based amplification</HEADER><P><s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac39" novelty="None" advantage="None">A microfluidic approach to DNA amplification would present several advantages.</annotationART></s> <s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac39" novelty="None" advantage="None">Not only could system features easily be integrated to ease complex sample handling and tracking, but also possible risks of contamination would be reduced.</annotationART></s> <s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac39" novelty="None" advantage="None">Indeed several operations (such as sample preparation, PCR and DNA detection) could ultimately be integrated into one device.</annotationART></s> <s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac39" novelty="None" advantage="None">By rendering the system quasi-autonomous, interactions with the sample would be minimised and the number of possible sources of contamination would be greatly lessened.</annotationART></s> <s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac39" novelty="None" advantage="None">These attractive features explain why the miniaturisation of the PCR apparatus has been of a growing interest in the scientific community.</annotationART></s> <s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met33" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The first on-chip PCR devices were presented by Northrup and co-workers in 1993<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit90">90</REF> and Wilding <IT>et al.</IT> in .1994<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit91">91</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met33" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Both devices consisted of a silicon chip with a micro-well in which the sample was loaded (see Fig. 2).</annotationART></s> <s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met33" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The entire chip was heated and cooled to provide the adequate thermocycling conditions.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac40" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since its introduction, this model has been replicated by numerous groups, sometimes with major amendments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met34" novelty="Old" advantage="None">These include integration of electrophoretic product sizing on a monolithic device,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit92">92</REF> as well as optimisation of conditions to provide faster PCR (under 7 minutes),<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit93">93</REF> single-molecule detection,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit94">94</REF> real-time applications<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit95">95</REF> and multiplexing.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit96 cit97">96,97</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="143"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met34" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The use of micro-arrays<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit96 cit98 cit99">96,98,99</REF> and drop-metering<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit100">100</REF> provided these micro-devices with high throughput (more than 10,000 parallel reactions have been reported<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit101 cit102 cit103 cit104">101–104</REF>) and better fluid-handling capabilities, whereas thermocycling conditions, such as temperature uniformity<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit105">105</REF> and heat transfer optimisation,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit106">106</REF> were closely studied.</annotationART></s> <s sid="144"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac41" novelty="None" advantage="None">A high versatility in terms of thermocycling conditions was shown by Kajiyama and co-workers when they presented independently-addressable wells.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit107">107</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="145"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac41" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, a variety of applications were successfully demonstrated, such as ligase chain reaction<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit108">108</REF> and isothermal nucleic acids amplification (NASBA).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit109">109</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="146"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac42" novelty="None" advantage="None">There have only been few devices based on a well approach that differed significantly from the original design presented by Northrup.</annotationART></s> <s sid="147"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met35" novelty="Old" advantage="None">For example, Oda <IT>et al.</IT> addressed the invasive characteristics of heating elements conventionally used by replacing the heaters with a transparent contact-free heating technique based on infra-red wavelengths.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit110">110</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="148"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac43" novelty="None" advantage="None">This device has since been developed further.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit35 cit111">35,111</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="149"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met36" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Pal and co-workers performed PCR using induction heating, another non-contact heating method.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit112">112</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="150"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met36" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In this paper the chips were mounted onto a ferrous ring, while the inductor was made of a copper wired wound around a ferrite core.</annotationART></s> <s sid="151"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met36" novelty="Old" advantage="None">By alternating the current going through the inductor, magnetic fields were produced.</annotationART></s> <s sid="152"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met36" novelty="Old" advantage="None">They then induced Eddy currents in the ferrous ring, which generated localised heat without any physical contact.</annotationART></s> <s sid="153"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met37" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In 2003, Krishnan <IT>et al.</IT> presented an original device relying on convection to provide thermocycling conditions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit113">113</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="154"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met37" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Two heaters sandwiched the Rayleigh-Bénard cell and were maintained at constant temperatures, namely 97 °C at the bottom and 61 °C at the top.</annotationART></s> <s sid="155"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met37" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Due to the difference in temperature, a convection flow developed in the cell, with an upward flux in the centre and downward fluxes on the sides.</annotationART></s> <s sid="156"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met37" novelty="Old" advantage="None">As the sample moved up and down in the cell, PCR conditions were provided and DNA was amplified.</annotationART></s> <s sid="157"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac44" novelty="None" advantage="None">This device was later modified by Wheeler and co-workers.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit114">114</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="158"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac45" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is to be noted that these devices are fairly flexible in terms of design: the well geometry can be tailored to a specific application, or arrays of wells are easily manufactured.</annotationART></s> <s sid="159"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac45" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, they still do not take full advantage of lithographic techniques.</annotationART></s> <s sid="160"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac45" novelty="None" advantage="None">For example, it would be difficult to implement efficient mixing structures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="161"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac45" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, because the temperature of the entire chip needs to be altered for thermocycling, they display unnecessary inertia.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Continuous flow-through based amplification</HEADER><P><s sid="162"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac46" novelty="None" advantage="None">A dynamic, moving-sample system particularly addresses previously described issues relating to full process integration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="163"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac46" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of continuous-flow chips for example, transition times to change temperature depends only on the sample pumping rate and the time the sample needs to reach temperature equilibrium.</annotationART></s> <s sid="164"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac46" novelty="None" advantage="None">Also heat inertia is reduced to a minimum because only the sample thermal mass needs to be taken into consideration rather than the chip plus sample as in the case of microwell PCR, with a direct consequence of enhanced rates of heating and cooling.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="165"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met38" novelty="Old" advantage="None">One approach to continuous flow-through based amplification was introduced in 1994 by Nakano and co-workers when they used capillary-based systems.</annotationART></s> <s sid="166"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met38" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Their concept consisted of a capillary going through three different oil baths in a loop.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit115">115</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="167"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met38" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The length of capillary in each bath determined the duration of the annealing, extension and denaturation steps.</annotationART></s> <s sid="168"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met38" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The sample was continuously pumped through the capillary unidirectionally and DNA amplification occurred as the sample was going through each temperature cycle.</annotationART></s> <s sid="169"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met39" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Based on a comparable concept, Curcio and co-workers performed a high-throughput DNA analysis system in a Teflon tube by separating different sample plugs with immiscible organic plugs.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit116">116</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="170"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met40" novelty="Old" advantage="None">A similar experiment was performed in a capillary by Park <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit117">117</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="171"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met41" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Friedman and co-workers proposed a static sample approach to nucleic acid amplification in .1998<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit118">118</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="172"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met41" novelty="Old" advantage="None">They enclosed the PCR sample inside a capillary, the ends of which were blocked by rubber pads.</annotationART></s> <s sid="173"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met41" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Each capillary was coated with a transparent Indium Tin Oxide (ITO) layer, ensuring that thermal cycling conditions could be independently controlled.</annotationART></s> <s sid="174"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met42" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Finally Chiou <IT>et al.</IT> presented a bi-directional sample pumping system.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit119 cit120">119,120</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="175"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met42" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In this device, the capillary was rested on three heating blocks and the sample was pumped back and forth to provide thermal cycling.</annotationART></s> <s sid="176"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met42" novelty="Old" advantage="None">An optical system stopped the pumping mechanism when the sample reached the desired temperature zone.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="177"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met43" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The first continuous-flow PCR chip presented in 1998 by Kopp and co-workers provided the basis for subsequent developments.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit121">121</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="178"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met43" novelty="Old" advantage="None">It consisted of a serpentine channel that passed through three heating zones maintained at constant temperature by copper blocks (see Fig. 3).</annotationART></s> <s sid="179"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met43" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">Remarkably, specifically amplified products were detected after 20 cycles in 1.5 minutes.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="180"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met44" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Device improvements have included optimisation of the PCR conditions to prevent any cross-contamination during injection series,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit122">122</REF> modification of the design to combine RNA Reverse-Transcription and PCR<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit123">123</REF> as well as a sensitivity study.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit124">124</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="181"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met45" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Applications such as high throughput and single molecule amplification<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit125">125</REF> and infectious biological agent monitoring<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit126">126</REF> have also been reported.</annotationART></s> <s sid="182"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met46" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Different approaches have been used to simulate the temperature distribution in continuous-flow PCR chips, such as finite element analysis,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit127">127</REF> CFD-ACE+ (computational fluid dynamics and multi-physics software)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit128 cit129">128,129</REF> and Lattice Boltzmann simulations.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit130">130</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="183"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met46" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">Although the continuous-flow approach allows for fast heating and cooling rates (thus improving product specificity) parallelisation is not easily applicable as it would significantly complicate the design and most likely increase the footprint of the PCR chip.</annotationART></s> <s sid="184"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met46" novelty="Old" advantage="No">In addition, this type of device is restrictive in terms of number of cycles: the number of meanders is decided during the design procedure and cannot be modified to increase the number of cycles once the chip is manufactured.</annotationART></s> <s sid="185"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met47" novelty="Old" advantage="None">However, Liu <IT>et al.</IT> circumvented this drawback by manufacturing a rotary device,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit131">131</REF> where a12nL-sample was introduced in the chip and subsequently pumped at a rate to enable 2–3 revolutions per minute.</annotationART></s> <s sid="186"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met47" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Integrated heaters provided the temperature zones necessary for thermocycling.</annotationART></s> <s sid="187"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met47" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Although the number of cycles could easily be adjusted (by changing the number of revolutions) the manufacturing process required additional and complex steps.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Novel approaches to DNA amplification</HEADER><P><s sid="188"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac47" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although the majority of microfluidic devices for PCR utilise batch or continuous-flow strategies, new approaches for DNA amplification have started to emerge.</annotationART></s> <s sid="189"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met48" novelty="Old" advantage="None">For example, an on-chip sample-shunting technique has been introduced by Auroux <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit43 cit132">43,132</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="190"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met48" novelty="Old" advantage="None">This approach, based on shunting the sample back and forth over heating zones in a straight channel by applying alternate pressure, combines the cycling flexibility of the well-chips with the quick temperature transition of the continuous-flow PCR micro-structure (see Fig. 4).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="191"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac48" novelty="None" advantage="None">A theoretical evaluation of a system based on this concept was provided by Bu and co-workers.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit133">133</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="192"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met49" novelty="Old" advantage="None">A sample-shunting device using ferrofluidics for actuators has also been introduced by Hardt <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit134">134</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="193"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met50" novelty="Old" advantage="None">From another perspective, Pollack and co-workers used an electrowetting process to control droplets containing PCR reagents and demonstrated that such fluid handling did not inhibit DNA amplification.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit135">135</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="194"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac49" novelty="None" advantage="None">A few approaches have also been developed on macro-scale apparatus and could also be of interest for microfluidic PCR.</annotationART></s> <s sid="195"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met51" novelty="Old" advantage="None">For example, high-speed PCR could be achieved on chip by using a microwave-assisted technique first demonstrated by Fermér <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit136">136</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="196"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met52" novelty="Old" advantage="None">DNA amplification in a water-in-oil emulsion, presented by Nakano <IT>et al.</IT>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit137">137</REF> could be pushed to further limits thanks to the better fluid handling provided by micro-devices.</annotationART></s> <s sid="197"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met53" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In addition, since cells can be manipulated in a microfluidic environment (see section ‘Sample Preparation’), another application could be <IT>in situ</IT> (meaning inside a cell) DNA amplification.</annotationART></s> <s sid="198"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met53" novelty="Old" advantage="None">This technique, first introduced in 1990 by Haase <IT>et al.</IT>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit138">138</REF> has since been optimised<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit139">139</REF> and has been combined to reverse transcription<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit140">140</REF> and to LAMP amplification,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit141">141</REF> offering enhanced flexibility in terms of possible applications.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Inhibitors and enhancers</HEADER><P><s sid="199"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac50" novelty="None" advantage="None">One of the main concerns when performing on-chip PCR is the loss in efficiency.</annotationART></s> <s sid="200"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac50" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although this problem can be sometimes traced to inhibitory materials used during micro-device fabrication (<IT>e.g.</IT>, residual chromium from chrome masks in glass chip fabrication<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit142">142</REF> or thermocouples<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit110">110</REF>), the most predominant problem is the elevated adsorption of the PCR components onto the chip surface due to the increase of the surface-to-volume ratio in a micrometer-scale environment.</annotationART></s> <s sid="201"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac50" novelty="None" advantage="None">For example, Erill and co-workers pinpointed that the component the most prone to adsorption was the <IT>Taq</IT> polymerase enzyme.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit143">143</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="202"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac50" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although surface coating strategies such as silanisation are possible solutions (see section ‘Surface treatment’), their effectiveness is sometimes questionable due to a lack of reproducibility.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit60">60</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="203"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac51" novelty="None" advantage="None">A second approach, called <IT>dynamic passivation</IT>, includes passivating reagents directly in the PCR mixture.</annotationART></s> <s sid="204"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met54" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The most common additives are polymers such as polyethylene glycol (PEG)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit144">144</REF> and polyvinylpyrrolidone (PVP)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit144">144</REF> or proteins such as bovine serum albumin (BSA).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit143">143</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="205"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met55" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Interestingly, Robinson <IT>et al.</IT> studied the influence of the molecular weight of PVP over the coating efficiency, as well as the effect of analytes in solution over BSA adsorption.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit145">145</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="206"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met56" novelty="None" advantage="None">Additional dynamic coatings have also been studied by Giordano <IT>et al.</IT> and include hydroxyethylcellulose (HEC), epoxy (poly)dimethylacrylamide (EPDMA), and diaminobutane (DAB).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit146">146</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="207"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac52" novelty="None" advantage="None">Cui and co-workers investigated the effect of single-walled carbon nanotubes on the PCR yield.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit147">147</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="208"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac52" novelty="None" advantage="None">Results showed that the nanotubes increased the amount of DNA amplified when they were introduced in concentrations below 3 µg/µL.</annotationART></s> <s sid="209"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met57" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Finally, Yoon and co-workers examined the influence of pH, potential and electrode polarity in an electrowetting–based microdevice in order to prevent bio-molecule adsorption<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit148">148</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>DNA detection methods</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Sequence independent detection methods</HEADER><P><s sid="210"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met58" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Due to cost-effectiveness, the use of intercalators (molecules that upon binding to double-stranded DNA exhibit significant enhancements in their fluorescence quantum efficiencies) in combination with gel electrophoresis is probably the most widely used method in biological laboratories for the detection of post-PCR products.</annotationART></s> <s sid="211"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met58" novelty="Old" advantage="None">With this technique, the DNA molecules are effectively labelled with an intercalator dye and subsequently separated according to their sizes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="212"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met58" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Popular intercalating dyes include ethidium bromide and SYBR<SP>®</SP> Green, but other intercalators have also been studied such as BEBO,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit149">149</REF> YOYO<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit150">150</REF> and TO-PRO-.3<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit151">151</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="213"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met58" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">The use of intercalators to detect DNA molecules presents two main advantages: it enables real-time detection<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit152 cit153">152,153</REF> and it is highly versatile, as the dyes have been selected to bind selectively to dsDNA.</annotationART></s> <s sid="214"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met58" novelty="Old" advantage="No">However, indiscriminate binding is also a major drawback: both specific and non-specific products will generate the same type of signal, making it difficult to differentiate between them.</annotationART></s> <s sid="215"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met59" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Integrating a size separation method or denaturing gradient profile often assists the identification of authentic amplicons.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="216"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met60" novelty="Old" advantage="None">One of the most widely used on-chip detection techniques for DNA molecules is capillary electrophoresis (CE).</annotationART></s> <s sid="217"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met60" novelty="Old" advantage="None">CE was first demonstrated on chip by Manz <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit154">154</REF>. and has since then been applied in many fields,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit155">155</REF> including the analysis of PCR products.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit156">156</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="218"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met60" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Recent applications include the detection of short tandem repeats by Mitnik and co-workers,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit157">157</REF> while Tseng <IT>et al.</IT> studied the effect of bubble cells on the resolution and the sensitivity of DNA separation during CE.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit158">158</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="219"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met60" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Efforts to develop matrices for on-chip CE with lower viscosity comprised a novel sieving buffer based on hydroxypropylmethylcellulose presented by Han <IT>et al.</IT>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit159">159</REF> as well as a study of a series of poly(ethylene oxide) matrices by Xu and co-workers.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit160">160</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="220"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met60" novelty="Old" advantage="None">A high-throughput device capable of genotyping simultaneously 384 samples in less than 325s was presented by Emrich <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit161">161</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="221"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac53" novelty="None" advantage="None">Other sequence-independent detection methods have also been investigated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="222"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met61" novelty="Old" advantage="None">For example, Messina <IT>et al.</IT> introduced a high-frequency sensor that enabled the differentiation between pre-amplification and post-PCR products.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit162">162</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="223"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met61" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Zangmeister and co-workers developed a novel fluorescence detection method based on the displacement of a fluorescent-tagged oligomer by the untagged target molecule<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit163">163</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Sequence-specific detection methods</HEADER></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Real-time probes</HEADER><P><s sid="224"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac54" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is the authors' belief that, although real-time probes are not yet widely used for on-chip detection due to complex detection system requirements, they will soon be routinely implemented for on-chip quantitative and qualitative real-time PCR (RQ-PCR).</annotationART></s> <s sid="225"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac55" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this section the reader will find a brief overview of some of the commercially available real-time probes.</annotationART></s></P><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>Hydrolysis probes</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="4"><HEADER>TaqMan<SP>®</SP> probes</HEADER><P><s sid="226"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met62" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The selectivity of real-time PCR was greatly improved with the introduction of fluorogenic probes (oligonucleotides whose sequences are complementary to part of the target molecules),<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit164">164</REF> such as the TaqMan<SP>®</SP> or hydrolysis probes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="227"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met62" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The detection principle is based on the quenching phenomenon known as Fluorescence Resonance Energy Transfer (FRET).</annotationART></s> <s sid="228"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met62" novelty="Old" advantage="None">FRET corresponds to the transfer of energy from a fluorescent reporter molecule (R) to a quencher molecule (Q), leading to light emission by Q at a longer wavelength than the donor.</annotationART></s> <s sid="229"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met62" novelty="Old" advantage="None">After hybridisation (and during annealing) the probe is cleaved due to the 5′ nuclease activity of the enzyme.</annotationART></s> <s sid="230"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met62" novelty="Old" advantage="None">As FRET is impaired, the reporter's emission can be detected.</annotationART></s> <s sid="231"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met62" novelty="Old" advantage="None">RQ-PCR optimisation using TaqMan<SP>®</SP> probes has been performed and include the study of the best possible combinations between commonly used fluorophores and quenchers by Marras <IT>et al.</IT>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit165">165</REF> as well as quantitative co-amplification of multiple targets (multiplexing) by Wang and co-workers.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit166">166</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="232"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met63" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Based on a similar approach, Gilliland <IT>et al.</IT> introduced PCR quantitation by competitive PCR<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit167">167</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="4"><HEADER>Cycling probe technology</HEADER><P><s sid="233"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met64" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Duck <IT>et al.</IT> developed in 1990 the Cycling Probe Technology (CPT).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit168">168</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="234"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met64" novelty="Old" advantage="None">This detection method is based on a chimeric DNA-RNA-DNA probe labelled at one end with a reporter and at the other end with a quencher.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit169">169</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="235"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met64" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Upon hybridisation with the target sequence, the enzyme RNaseH specifically cleaves the RNA region of the probe, resulting in fluorescence emission.</annotationART></s> <s sid="236"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met64" novelty="Old" advantage="None">This method has been implemented on chip with success in Professor Harrisson's group<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit170 cit171 cit172">170–172</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="4"><HEADER>DNAzyme</HEADER><P><s sid="237"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met65" novelty="Old" advantage="None">A detection method similar to the CPB and also based on a hybridisation probe was recently released by BD Biosciences: the BD Qzyme<SP>™</SP> Assay.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit173">173</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="238"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met65" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The innovative component is the DNAzyme, a catalytically active oligonucleotide capable of cleaving nucleic acid substrates at specific locations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="239"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met65" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The DNAzyme operates in coordination with a DNAzyme-specific fluorogenic target that is cleaved during the PCR process, and consequently the fluorescent signal enables the real-time monitoring of DNA amplification.</annotationART></s> <s sid="240"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met65" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Since the introduction of the DNAzyme probes, several applications have been reported in the literature such as quantitation of nucleic acid sequences in real-time,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit174">174</REF> study of the probe fluorescence signal<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit175">175</REF> and elaboration of a circular probe<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit176">176</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="4"><HEADER>MGB<SP>™</SP> technology</HEADER><P><s sid="241"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met66" novelty="Old" advantage="None">A new probe approach based on Minor Groove Binders (MGB) has recently been introduced by Epoch Biosciences.</annotationART></s> <s sid="242"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met66" novelty="Old" advantage="None">MGB are flat molecules that can fit in the minor groove and interact with the phosphate-sugar backbone either by hydrogen bonds or by hydrophobic interactions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="243"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met66" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Such characteristics were proved to stabilise DNA hybridisation, resulting in shorter primers retaining higher melting temperatures<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit177">177</REF> and increased probe specificity.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit178">178</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="244"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met66" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Similar MGB technology is now used both by Applied Biosystems for their TaqMan<SP>®</SP> chemistry and by Epoch Biosciences for their MGB Eclipse Probe Systems.</annotationART></s> <s sid="245"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met66" novelty="Old" advantage="None">MGBs are used in conjunction with fluorogenic probe technologies and are gaining in popularity with the increasing requirement to place probes over exact regions of target sequences, such as exon-exon boundaries used in splicosomic studies.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>Conformation probes</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="4"><HEADER>Molecular Beacons</HEADER><P><s sid="246"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met67" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Operating on a comparable FRET principle as TaqMan<SP>®</SP> probes, Molecular Beacons were introduced by Tyagi and co-workers.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit179 cit165 cit180">179,165,180</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="247"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met67" novelty="Old" advantage="None">They consist of single-stranded oligonucleotides arranged in a stem-loop structure, with a reporter probe attached to one of the stem arms and a quencher to the other.</annotationART></s> <s sid="248"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met67" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The loop portion is complementary to part of the target sequence, whereas the stem portion flanks the loop and are self complementary and unable to hybridise to any of the target sequence.</annotationART></s> <s sid="249"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac56" novelty="None" advantage="None">To simplify, Molecular Meacons exist in two different states.</annotationART></s> <s sid="250"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac56" novelty="None" advantage="None">When they are in a loop-stem structure, the fluorescence signal is quenched by FRET or proximity effects.</annotationART></s> <s sid="251"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac56" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the contrary, during the annealing step, the loop part hybridises to the target molecule to separate the reporter and quencher dyes and a signal can be detected.</annotationART></s> <s sid="252"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met67" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Molecular Beacons have been used in a microfluidic environment to detect the breast cancer gene BRCA1 by Culha and co-workers,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit181">181</REF> and also as a mean to study DNA hybridisation kinetics and to perform DNA melting temperature analysis by Dodge <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit182">182</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="253"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met68" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Based on a similar concept, Nazarenko and co-workers introduced self-quenched primers.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit183">183</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="254"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met68" novelty="Old" advantage="None">These single-fluorophore labelled primers emit fluorescence with different intensities depending on their conformation: a weak emission is noticed when the primers are in a stem-loop configuration, whereas the fluorescence signal is at its maximum when the primers are incorporated in a double-stranded DNA helix.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="4"><HEADER>Scorpions</HEADER><P><s sid="255"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met69" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Scorpion primers are an alternative to Molecular Beacons.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit184">184</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="256"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac57" novelty="None" advantage="None">A Scorpion primer consists of a three-part molecule based on the following model: (PCR primer) – (blocker molecule) – (probe).</annotationART></s> <s sid="257"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met69" novelty="Old" advantage="None">During the PCR process, the primer hybridises to the target molecule and is then extended.</annotationART></s> <s sid="258"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met69" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Upon denaturation, the extended-DNA-strand/target hybrid is dissociated and so are the two arms of the Scorpion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="259"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met69" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Once the temperature reduced for the annealing/extension phase, the probe-part of the Scorpion anneals to the extended strand, the quenching process is impaired and fluorescence is detected.</annotationART></s> <s sid="260"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met69" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Upon extension the probe is displaced and recovers its quenched conformation with a resultant drop in the fluorescence signal.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>Hybridisation probes</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="4"><HEADER>LC probes</HEADER><P><s sid="261"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met70" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Roche Molecular Diagnostics have also developed a mutation analysis kit based on hybridisation probes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="262"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac58" novelty="None" advantage="None">As with ligase chain detection, the probes are specifically designed to target the amplicon at adjacent sites.</annotationART></s> <s sid="263"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met70" novelty="Old" advantage="None">However, one probe is labeled at the 3′ end with fluorescein (the “donor” probe), whereas the two other probes are labeled with an acceptor dye on the 5′ end (either LC-Red 640 or LC-Red 705, each dye corresponding to a mutation possibility).</annotationART></s> <s sid="264"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met70" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The detection principle is based on FRET: the single-base-mutation is detected depending on the wavelength at which the signal is detected, as LC-Red 640 and LC-Red 705 emit at two different wavelengths.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="4"><HEADER>AEGIS platform</HEADER><P><s sid="265"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met71" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The latest developments in DNA diagnostic technologies include the expansion of the DNA alphabet.</annotationART></s> <s sid="266"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met71" novelty="Old" advantage="None">EraGen Biosciences, Inc. developed the AEGIS (An Extended Genetic Information System) platform that extends the DNA alphabet by up to 8 new bases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="267"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac59" novelty="None" advantage="None">Two of the new bases, isoC and isoG, have already been combined to the natural DNA bases to produce the company's diagnostic technology.</annotationART></s> <s sid="268"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met72" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The GENE-CODE system is a real-time nucleic acid detection system based on the reduction in fluorescent signal during PCR.</annotationART></s> <s sid="269"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met72" novelty="Old" advantage="None">During the amplification process, a site-specific quencher is inserted opposite a complementary AEGIS base in one of the primers, resulting in signal diminution by FRET phenomenon.</annotationART></s> <s sid="270"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met72" novelty="Old" advantage="None">This technology is still fairly new but clinical diagnostics assays based on the AEGIS bases isoC and isoG are already commercially available (such as the VERSANT HIV Assay developed by Bayer Diagnostics).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="271"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met72" novelty="Old" advantage="No">Although real-time PCR methods using hydrolysis probes, conformation probes or hybridisation probes are powerful techniques, they are inherently limited in some cases, as pointed out by Gardner and co-workers regarding TaqMan<SP>®</SP> probes.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit185">185</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="272"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met72" novelty="Old" advantage="No">These probes are indeed highly specific, rendering the detection of viruses with substantial genetic variation among strains, such as the HIV virus, impractical.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>RQ-PCR data analysis strategies</HEADER><P><s sid="273"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac60" novelty="None" advantage="None">At the same time as the above techniques enabled quantitative PCR, the issue relating to data analysis became a paramount concern.</annotationART></s> <s sid="274"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac60" novelty="None" advantage="None">Not only were systematic errors in fluorescence measurements investigated,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit186">186</REF> but different methods of analysis were also introduced.</annotationART></s> <s sid="275"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met73" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The most widely used procedure of analysis is the threshold method.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit187">187</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="276"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met73" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Based on the background fluorescence signal, a certain level of fluorescence signal (usually around 10 times the value of the average background fluorescence value during early cycles) is imposed as the threshold limit.</annotationART></s> <s sid="277"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met73" novelty="Old" advantage="None">After plotting the fluorescence signal obtained during PCR against the number of cycles performed, the intersection of this curve with the threshold limit can be determined.</annotationART></s> <s sid="278"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met73" novelty="Old" advantage="None">It is often called the threshold value, or C<SB>T</SB> value, and represents the number of cycles necessary to generate an exact amount of DNA.</annotationART></s> <s sid="279"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met73" novelty="Old" advantage="None">With this method, C<SB>T</SB> values can be compared and DNA template concentrations can be calculated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="280"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac61" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although this method is well accepted among the scientific community, new approaches have been proposed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="281"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met74" novelty="Old" advantage="None">For example, Rutledge and co-workers studied the mathematics of quantitative PCR and offered an alternative analysis tool based on DNA mass at threshold limit,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit188">188</REF> whereas Liu <IT>et al.</IT> favoured the kinetic curves to extrapolate the initial amount of gene transcript.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit189">189</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="282"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met75" novelty="Old" advantage="None">New algorithms have also been developed to promote automatic analysis of real-time PCR data<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit190">190</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Single Nucleotide Polymorphism (SNP)</HEADER><P><s sid="283"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac62" novelty="None" advantage="None">Whilst quantitative PCR assays present a significant challenge for microfluidic applications, the development of qualitative assays such as the analysis of genetic mutations has attracted much attention.</annotationART></s> <s sid="284"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met76" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Single Nucleotide Polymorphisms (SNPs) are frequent non-random base substitutions, present at 1 per 1000 base pairs within the genome, and are avidly studied for association with diseases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="285"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met76" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Several techniques to detect SNPs have been implemented on chip.</annotationART></s> <s sid="286"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met77" novelty="Old" advantage="None">For example, Kimbal and co-workers applied Temperature Gradient Gel Electrophoresis (TGGE) in a polycarbonate micro-device.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit191">191</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="287"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met78" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Buch <IT>et al.</IT> combined standard gel electrophoresis to TGGE in their 2-D separation device.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit192">192</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="288"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met78" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In the first dimension, molecules were separated by gel electrophoresis according to their sizes, while TGGE allowed a SNP analysis in subsequent perpendicular channels.</annotationART></s> <s sid="289"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met78" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Using hydroxy-ethylcellulose as a sieving matrix, Liu and co-workers used TGCE and successfully separated a mixture of wild type DNA, mutant type DNA and the corresponding heteroduplexes.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit193">193</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="290"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met79" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Ito <IT>et al.</IT> favoured Affinity Capillary Electrophoresis (ACE) to develop a gene mutation assay.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit194">194</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="291"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met80" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Zhong and co-workers performed SNP genotyping by applying a combination of allele-specific oligonucleotides attached to the chip surface, detector probes and a thermostable DNA ligase.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit195">195</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="292"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met81" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Another approach was presented by Russom <IT>et al.</IT>: they analysed SNPs by extending allele-specific fluorescently labelled nucleotides<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit196">196</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Hybridisation based detection</HEADER><P><s sid="293"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac63" novelty="None" advantage="None">DNA hybridisation is widely exploited to achieve high selectivity and sensitivity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="294"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac63" novelty="None" advantage="None">Different approaches have been applied on chip.</annotationART></s> <s sid="295"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met82" novelty="Old" advantage="None">For example, Lai and co-workers developed an enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay on a compact disk platform,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit56">56</REF> while Cai <IT>et al.</IT> determined by electrochemical impedance spectroscopy that DNA hybridisation is strongly frequency-dependent.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit197">197</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="296"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met83" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Trau and co-workers applied PCR reactors combined to microarrays to genotype Chinese medicine plants.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit198">198</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="297"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met84" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Magnetic beads were also used in microfluidics devices to immobilise by hybridisation alternatively the target template,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit54">54</REF> the capture probe<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit42">42</REF> or various sensing agents.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit48">48</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="298"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met84" novelty="Old" advantage="None">A different approach was introduced by McKendry <IT>et al.</IT>:<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit199">199</REF> using cantilever assays they were able to determine the sequences of unlabeled DNA molecules present at nanomolar concentrations.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Integrated systems</HEADER><P><s sid="299"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac64" novelty="None" advantage="None">One of the main challenges in miniaturisation is the integration of functional components to perform several operations without the need for macro apparatus or manual user input.</annotationART></s> <s sid="300"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None">A few groups have started to tackle this issue and a brief overview of the integrated systems available at the moment is given in this section.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="301"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac65" novelty="None" advantage="None">A number of instances of integrated on-capillary systems have been recently presented in the literature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="302"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met85" novelty="Old" advantage="None">For example, Li and co-workers developed a system that could perform cell counting, cell-lysis, PCR, on-column hybridisation and product detection.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit200">200</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="303"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met86" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In addition, an integrated on-capillary arrangement capable of cell-lysis, reverse transcription PCR and product analysis was reported by Matsunaga <IT>et al.</IT>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit77">77</REF> while a set-up capable of PCR, sequencing and purification in capillaries was introduced by Hashimoto <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit201">201</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="304"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac66" novelty="None" advantage="None">Several examples of on-chip integrated systems have also been published in the literature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="305"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac67" novelty="None" advantage="None">One of the devices combining the most operations was presented by Liu <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit54 cit76">54,76</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="306"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met87" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Their device enabled the following steps: cell capture, cell concentration, cell lysis, purification, PCR, SNP assaying and hybridisation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="307"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met87" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In addition, valves, mixers and pumps were incorporated onto the chip.</annotationART></s> <s sid="308"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met88" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Another system offering various capabilities—namely cell capture, cell lysis, purification and DNA amplification—was introduced by El-Ali and co-workers.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit44">44</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="309"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Other structures have also been investigated, and for a more detailed overview of some of the most recent, the reader should refer to Table 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="310"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac68" novelty="None" advantage="None">As can be seen in this table, the pre-PCR steps that are integrated the most include cell capture,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit44 cit54 cit76 cit82 cit202 cit203 cit204 cit205">44,54,76,82,202–205</REF> cell lysis<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit44 cit54 cit76 cit82 cit202 cit203 cit204 cit206 cit207">44,54,76,82,202–204,206,207</REF> and sample purification.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit35 cit44 cit54 cit76 cit82 cit203 cit205 cit208">35,44,54,76,82,203,205,208</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="311"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac69" novelty="None" advantage="None">The well-approach PCR<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit41 cit44 cit54 cit76 cit208 cit209 cit210 cit211 cit212 cit213 cit214 cit215 cit216 cit217">41,44,54,76,208–217</REF> seems to be favored for integrated systems when compared to the continuous-flow process.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit35 cit123 cit125 cit206 cit218 cit219 cit220">35,123,125,206,218–220</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="312"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">This might be due to an increased simplicity in sample handling for the former method.</annotationART></s> <s sid="313"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac70" novelty="None" advantage="None">The physical elements the most integrated are heaters<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit41 cit44 cit125 cit205 cit206 cit209 cit210 cit211 cit212 cit213 cit214 cit216 cit217 cit218 cit219">41,44,125,205,206,209–214,216–219</REF> and valves.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit41 cit54 cit76 cit82 cit202 cit206 cit209 cit210 cit212 cit216 cit217 cit218">41,54,76,82,202,206,209,210,212,216–218</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="314"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac71" novelty="None" advantage="None">DNA amplification is mostly performed to increase the detection sensitivity either of a specific molecule among a heterogeneous population or to characterise and/or measure a given section of a target.</annotationART></s> <s sid="315"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac71" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, even though the merits of PCR are widely recognised, the process of DNA amplification impairs the speed, the cost-effectiveness and even sometimes the accuracy and the sensitivity of such detection methods.</annotationART></s> <s sid="316"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met89" novelty="Old" advantage="None">To resolve this issue, U.S.</annotationART></s> <s sid="317"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met89" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Genomics has developed a unique method with which single molecules from an un-amplified sample can be detected using the GeneEngine<SP>™</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="318"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met89" novelty="Old" advantage="None">This system relies on isolating the target from the sample, fluorescently tagging it and finally injecting it into the test platform where each molecule is subsequently detected by laser illumination.</annotationART></s> <s sid="319"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met89" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Using DirectMolecular<SP>™</SP> Analysis, quantitation, SNP analysis and molecule interaction quantification can be performed by colour coincidence counting.</annotationART></s> <s sid="320"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met89" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">Analysis in less than one minute and femtomolar range sensitivity are claimed to be achieved.</annotationART></s> <s sid="321"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met90" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Alternatively, DirectLinear<SP>™</SP> Analysis enables the sequencing of single linear genomic DNA molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="322"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met90" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Sequence-specific probes are first hybridised to the DNA molecule.</annotationART></s> <s sid="323"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met90" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The strand is then stretched and the probes are detected linearly by the GeneEngine<SP>™</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="324"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met90" novelty="Old" advantage="None">A spatially resolved map of specific sequence locations on the DNA can then be generated, leading to a ‘genetic barcode’ for each individual molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="325"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac72" novelty="None" advantage="None">Applications of such barcodes include genetic comparison of samples or populations, SNP detection and genome mapping or microorganisms.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Conclusion</HEADER><P><s sid="326"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac73" novelty="None" advantage="None">The future of high throughput gene analysis will benefit greatly from the implementation of micro Total Analysis Systems, particularly for the analyses requiring multi-step procedures such as those including sample preparation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="327"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac73" novelty="None" advantage="None">Microfluidic devices will serve therefore to provide a level of standardisation not presently achievable with current laboratory standard operating procedures, especially those based upon minute quantities of samples.</annotationART></s> <s sid="328"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac73" novelty="None" advantage="None">As the development of microfluidic devices continues, newly devised microstructures need to utilise the better production and micro-engineering procedures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="329"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac73" novelty="None" advantage="None">Importantly however, the devices should also innately incorporate the requirements of each bioassay to enable them to be customised to the exact requirements of the specific bioassay and thus permit the optimum co-selection of device and choice of assay chemistry.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
