<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b415321a" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">The anomeric effect in 1,3-benzodioxole: additional evidence from the rotational, vibration–rotation and rovibronic spectra<XREF TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" /></annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The millimetre wave pure rotation and vibration–rotation spectrum of 1,3-benzodioxole has been studied and the vibrational spacing between the two lowest vibrational states in the five membered ring puckering potential has been determined with considerable accuracy, at Δ<IT>E</IT><SB>01</SB> = 259 726.035(10) MHz or 8.663 5280(4) cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, rotationally resolved analysis of two hot bands near the reported origin band in the laser-induced fluorescence spectrum has been carried out and was found to rule out the current literature assignment of this spectrum.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The new information has been used to reassign the lowest vibrational transitions in the far-infrared and the Raman spectrum of 1,3-benzodioxole in terms of a one dimensional potential with a central barrier of 108 cm<SP>−1</SP>, which successfully accounts for all states up to <IT>υ</IT> = 5, and for the observed variation in rotational constants.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Considerable reassignment of the published spectra, as well as new experimental work is still necessary for a confident determination of the low-energy region of the molecular potential of 1,3-benzodioxole.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Determination of the effects which are responsible for the preferred structural conformations of molecules is often less than straightforward.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is useful to keep in mind that the understanding of such a basic feature, as the staggered geometry of ethane, has come only recently,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF> from a careful computational study showing that this geometry results from hyperconjugation and not from steric repulsion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In cases of molecules which have conformers of comparable energy separated by small energy barriers the situation is often much more complex.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Even the geometry at the global minimum, and not only its origin may be uncertain.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Several spectroscopic studies of 1,3-benzodioxole (BDO) have been carried out, and were devoted to elucidation of details of its large amplitude motion, which is a convolution of ring puckering, flapping and ring twisting.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The molecule is shown in Fig. 1, where the parameters used to describe the ring puckering and flapping motions are also indicated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Earlier investigations led to conflicting conclusions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The results of a far infrared (FIR) investigation<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">2</REF> were interpreted in terms of planarity of the molecule, whereas a single vibronic level fluorescence (SVLF) study<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF> suggested that the molecule is non-planar, with the barrier to planarity attributed to a twisting motion at the oxygen atoms in positions 1 and 3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The pure rotational spectra of the ground state and of several, mainly ring puckering, vibrational satellites, also indicated unambiguously that the molecule is non-planar, but that the barrier to planarity is due to the puckering motion of the five membered ring.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The puckered conformation of BDO has been interpreted<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6 cit7">5–7</REF> to originate from the anomeric effect, which is a stereoelectronic effect that involves the donation of electron density from a lone pair on one oxygen atom to the adjacent carbon-oxygen bond.</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Such interaction, believed to be the result of n–s* overlap, reaches its maximum value when the –C–O–C–O torsional angle is at 90° and is excluded in case of a planar ring.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the puckering of the ring increases the magnitude of the anomeric effect, there can be a stabilization of a nonplanar structure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The studies reported in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6 cit7">refs. 5–7</REF> combined the analysis of far-infrared and Raman spectra with that of laser-induced fluorescence (LIF) from electronic transitions between the ground (S<SB>0</SB>) and the first excited electronic (S<SB>1</SB>) states.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">ref. 6</REF> a partial reassignment was made of the fundamental transition of the butterfly motion, with respect to <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">refs. 2</REF> and <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF> while in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">ref. 7</REF> the potential energy surface of the ring puckering and butterfly motions was determined for the first time in the S<SB>1</SB> state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Following the experimental results, two theoretical studies confirmed the anomeric effect to be the main effect in determining the bent conformation of BDO in both S<SB>0</SB> and S<SB>1</SB> states.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit9">8,9</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">We will use throughout the text the notation <IT>υ</IT><SB>p</SB>, <IT>υ</IT><SB>f</SB> and <IT>υ</IT><SB>t</SB> to label the vibrational states of ring-puckering, flapping (or butterfly) and twisting motions, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In normal mode numbering the pertinent quantum numbers are <IT>υ</IT><SB>39</SB>, <IT>υ</IT><SB>38</SB> and <IT>υ</IT><SB>20</SB>, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The electronic transitions will be labelled using the notation <IT>N</IT><IT>n</IT>1<IT>n</IT>0, where <IT>N</IT> labels the normal mode, <IT>n</IT><SB>0</SB> is the vibrational quantum number for this mode in S<SB>0</SB>, and <IT>n</IT><SB>1</SB> is the corresponding value in S<SB>1</SB>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Analysis using a 2D model comprising of ring-puckering and butterfly motions, was performed in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6 cit7">refs. 6 and 7</REF> although some unusually large discrepancies between the observed and the calculated transition frequencies were obtained.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Since rotationally resolved techniques allow for unambiguous identification of vibrational states, some of us measured the rotationally resolved spectrum of several strong, mainly cold bands of the LIF spectrum of the S<SB>1</SB> ← S<SB>0</SB> (π* ← π) electronic transition of BDO.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">It was found that, for S<SB>1</SB>, the rotational constants of state <IT>υ</IT><SB>p</SB> = 2 obtained from the 3920 and 3921 transitions as assigned in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">ref. 7</REF>, were incompatible with each other.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">A new assignment of the ring-puckering states in S<SB>1</SB>, needed to understand the molecular geometry and the anomeric effect, is still missing.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to succeed in the reassignment, we need to be sure of the assignment in S<SB>0</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the <IT>υ</IT><SB>p</SB> = 1–0 (Δ<IT>E</IT><SB>01</SB>) splitting has not been measured experimentally, but deduced from the centrifugal distortion effects,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF> this was the primary target of additional measurements.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">At the same time we searched for the rotationally resolved spectrum of the 3911 transition, measuring some weak hot bands close to the band at 34 783.53 cm<SP>−1</SP>, so far attributed to the origin.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Experimental details</HEADER><P><s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">BDO (99% purity) was purchased from Aldrich, and was used without any further purification.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The millimetre wave spectra were recorded in Warsaw, and the rovibronic spectra in Florence, as described below.</annotationART></s></P><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Rotational and vibration–rotation spectra</HEADER><P><s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">We used the broadband millimetre wave spectrometer based on backward wave oscillator (BWO) sources, which has been described in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">ref. 11</REF> and references cited therein.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The spectrometer uses source modulation, and the frequency of the source is locked to the controlling 3 GHz synthesizer by means of two phase lock loops.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The millimetre wave spectrum was recorded at frequencies from 170 to 279 GHz, by means of two different mm-wave sources.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Measurements were made on a static sample kept at room-temperature and pressure of 20–50 mTorr, which was held in a 3 m long absorption cell of 10 cm diameter.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Rovibronic spectra</HEADER><P><s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The fluorescence excitation spectra were recorded using the experimental apparatus in Florence, described in detail elsewhere.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The sample was introduced directly into the molecular beam source and was heated to 50 °C, to reach a suitable concentration of BDO in the molecular beam, while the 50 μm-diameter nozzle was maintained at a slightly higher temperature (55 °C) to avoid condensation and clogging of the nozzle.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The carrier gas was pure helium at a pressure of 6 × 10<SP>5</SP> Pa for the cold bands, and 8 × 10<SP>4</SP> Pa for the hot bands.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The molecular beam was obtained by selecting the central part of the expansion with a 400 μm-diameter skimmer, placed at 10 mm from the nozzle.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">On passing through the skimmer the molecular beam entered a second, differentially pumped, chamber in which it could interact with the UV radiation and where the LIF signal was collected.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The excitation source was a ring dye laser (Coherent 699-21) with Rhodamine 6G as lasing medium pumped by an argon ion laser.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ring laser was operating in single mode, and was actively frequency stabilized.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">To obtain the UV radiation the frequency of the ring laser was doubled using an external cavity (Wavetrain, LAS), and we obtained up to 20 mW of UV power, at the crossing point with the molecular beam.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The UV linewidth was 3 MHz.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fluorescence radiation was collected by a system of two spherical mirrors and two lenses, and it was focused on the photocathode of a photomultiplier tube (EMI 9893Q/350).</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The photomultiplier tube signal was then sent to a photon counter (SRS 400).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The frequency scan of the laser was monitored by a 150 MHz free spectral range étalon (to check the regularity of the scan and to control that the laser does not jump from the selected cavity mode), and by a wavelength-meter (Burleigh Wavemeter) to check the absolute calibration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The accuracy of the laser wavelength measurement is of 0.04 cm<SP>−1</SP> in the UV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The data acquisition and the laser scan were controlled by a personal computer.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Results</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Rovibronic spectra</HEADER><P><s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Upon realising from measurement of bands displaced from 94 to 383 cm<SP>−1</SP> from the origin band<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF> that the assignment of <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">ref. 7</REF> was in question, we considered it crucial to assign the 3911 transition, expected to lie close to the origin band.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">This would have supplied the Δ<IT>E</IT><SB>01</SB> splitting in S<SB>1</SB>, to compare with the value of Δ<IT>E</IT><SB>01</SB> in S<SB>0</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">We found, in the proximity of the origin at 34 785.53 cm<SP>−1</SP>, two candidate hot bands, one displaced by −14.5 cm<SP>−1</SP>, and a second one by +1.5 cm<SP>−1</SP> (Fig. 2).</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results of fitting the measured frequencies for these two bands, using a rigid rotor Hamiltonian and the program Jb95,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF> are given in Table 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The measured and the obs. − calc. frequencies are listed in supplementary Tables S1 and S2.<SUP TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" /> The rotational constants of the lower states for the two new bands are compared in Table 2 with those for the lowest excited vibrational states of S<SB>0</SB> known from the microwave investigation.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">It can be seen that the <IT>B</IT> and <IT>C</IT> constants differ by close to ten times the experimental errors from the values in the S<SB>0</SB><IT>υ</IT><SB>p</SB> = 1 state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Neither of the two new transitions appears to originate from that state, so none of these bands can be satisfactorily assigned to the 3911 transition on the basis of rotational constants.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition assignment of the lower frequency band to 3911 would require a considerable difference between the Δ<IT>E</IT><SB>01</SB> values in S<SB>1</SB> and S<SB>0</SB>, and a much larger Δ<IT>E</IT><SB>01</SB> spacing in the S<SB>0</SB> state (by at least 15 cm<SP>−1</SP>) than the reported value of 8.1–8.3 cm<SP>−1</SP>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the other hand assignment of the +1.5 cm<SP>−1</SP> band would require the 3921 band to be within about 8.2 + 1.5 = 9.7 cm<SP>−1</SP> of the 3920 band, whereas candidate bands according to the assignment of <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">ref. 7</REF> and the measurements in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">ref. 10</REF> are 7.53(11) cm<SP>−1</SP> apart.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">If we compare the S<SB>0</SB> rotational constants obtained from the two new bands with the values for the lowest lying vibrational satellites in S<SB>0</SB> obtained from the pure rotational spectrum, we can see that they most closely match those of <IT>υ</IT><SB>p</SB> = 2 and of the combination state (<IT>υ</IT><SB>p</SB> = 2, <IT>υ</IT><SB>t</SB> = 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">A correspondence with <IT>υ</IT><SB>t</SB> = 1 also cannot be excluded.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">For any of these to be the case the 000 band, the origin, would actually have to be at a considerably lower value, by <IT>ca.</IT> 300 cm<SP>−1</SP>, than the reported frequency.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have indeed seen some indications of the presence of very weak bands in that region.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The inconsistencies discussed above provide further evidence, in addition to that already reported in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">ref. 10</REF> that the assignment of the ring puckering progression in S<SB>1</SB>, as given in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">ref. 7</REF> is most probably incorrect.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">It appears that the key 39<SB>1</SB><SP>1</SP> band, and even the actual band origin are still to be identified.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">Since the value Δ<IT>E</IT><SB>01</SB> = 8.4 cm<SP>−1</SP> in the S<SB>0</SB> state was not an experimental one, but was derived from experimental centrifugal distortion constants we made an attempt to measure it directly, with millimetre/submillimetre wave spectroscopy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results are given in the following section.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Millimetre wave rotational and vibration–rotation spectra</HEADER><P><s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The measurements of the pure rotational spectrum in the ground, <IT>υ</IT><SB>p</SB> = 0, and in the first excited ring puckering state, <IT>υ</IT><SB>p</SB> = 1, were first extended to the millimetre wave region by using predictions based on the rotational constants of .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">ref. 4</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The spectrum is relatively weak, since BDO has a small dipole moment equal to 0.237(5) D and 0.222(4) D in the ground, and in the first excited state, respectively.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The dipole moment is in the form of the <IT>μ</IT><SB><IT>a</IT></SB> dipole moment component, so that only <IT>a</IT>-type rotational transitions would be expected.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the asymmetry of the molecule is appreciable, with the asymmetry parameter <IT>κ</IT> = −0.643 for the ground state, the spectrum was expected to be devoid of many of the characteristic features that normally serve to aid the assignment.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Nevertheless, as the molecule is close to planarity it gives rise to the type-II bandheads,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14 cit15">14,15</REF> which are characteristic of high-<IT>J</IT> transitions in such molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The bandheads are produced by specific overlaps of <SP><IT>a</IT></SP>R-type transitions with differing values of <IT>J</IT> and <IT>K</IT><SB>−1</SB>, such that <IT>J</IT> decreases and <IT>K</IT><SB>−1</SB> increases by 1 away from the leading line in the band.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Such bands were indeed observed for both states, as visible in the specimen spectrum reproduced in Fig. 3, and their measurement allowed for rapid expansion of the pure rotational data set.</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">An attempt to fit such data demonstrated that it was no longer viable to carry out single state fits as was possible with the less extensive data sets of .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">ref. 4</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="New" advantage="None">In the present case it was necessary to carry out simultaneous fits of data for <IT>υ</IT><SB>p</SB> = 0 and <IT>υ</IT><SB>p</SB> = 1, by taking account of the high order, Coriolis-type interaction connecting such states.</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">We used the block diagonal Hamiltonian of the form<IT>H</IT> = Δ<IT>E</IT><SB>01</SB> + <IT>H</IT><SB>r</SB><SP>(0)</SP> + <IT>H</IT><SB>r</SB><SP>(1)</SP> + <IT>H</IT><SB>c</SB><SP>(01)</SP>,where <IT>H</IT><SB>r</SB><SP>(0)</SP> and <IT>H</IT><SB>r</SB><SP>(1)</SP> are single state Watson’s asymmetric rotor terms in representation I<SP><IT>r</IT></SP> and reduction <IT>A.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The interstate coupling term <IT>H</IT><SB>c</SB><SP>(01)</SP> has been expressed in the reduced axis system Hamiltonian suggested by Pickett<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF><IT>H</IT><SB>c</SB><SP>(01)</SP> = (<IT>F</IT><SB><IT>ac</IT></SB> + <IT>F</IT><SB><IT>acJ</IT></SB><IT>P</IT><SP>2</SP> + <IT>F</IT><SB><IT>acK</IT></SB><IT>P</IT><SB><IT>a</IT></SB><SP>2</SP>)(<IT>P</IT><SB><IT>a</IT></SB><IT>P</IT><SB><IT>c</IT></SB> + <IT>P</IT><SB><IT>c</IT></SB><IT>P</IT><SB><IT>a</IT></SB>),which is equivalent to a second order Coriolis coupling term.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The empirical centrifugal distortion expansion of the <IT>F</IT><SB><IT>ac</IT></SB> coupling constant proved to be necessary for fitting vibration–rotation transitions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The measured frequencies were fitted using Pickett’s SPFIT program.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18 cit19">18,19</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Pure rotational <SP>a</SP>R<SB>0,1</SB>-type transitions were measured for <IT>υ</IT><SB>p</SB> = 0 and <IT>υ</IT><SB>p</SB> = 1 states at frequencies up to 210 GHz, which are near the maximum of the rotational absorption profile, see Fig. 4.</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The values of rotational quantum numbers ranged up to <IT>J</IT> = 90 and <IT>K</IT><SB>−1</SB> = 40.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The pure rotational data set by itself already allowed the Δ<IT>E</IT><SB>01</SB> vibrational energy level spacing to be determined to within several tens of MHz, at which point location of vibration–rotation transitions became feasible.</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the dipole moment change induced by the puckering vibration will be perpendicular to the ring plane and along the <IT>c</IT>-inertial axis, the vibration–rotation transitions are expected to follow <IT>c</IT>-type selection rules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Their initial prediction was made by assuming that the associated vibrational dipole moment was at least comparable in magnitude to the permanent dipole moment.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The calculated intensity profiles are shown in Fig. 4 and take the form of a considerably distorted P, Q, R structure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The compact Q branch at 260–270 GHz was thought to offer the best chance for observation, while the comparably intense R branch was outside the frequency range of the available spectrometer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The prediction proved to be sufficiently accurate to readily locate the Q-branch interstate transitions, which were indeed found to be considerably more intense than the pure rotational transitions, see Fig. 5.</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The vibrational transition moment proved to be sufficiently high to observe also the P-type interstate transitions, some of which are marked in Fig. 3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="New" advantage="None">We assigned and measured a total of 181 <IT>υ</IT><SB>p</SB> = 1 ← 0 transitions and fitted them together with pure rotational transitions in <IT>υ</IT><SB>p</SB> = 0 and <IT>υ</IT><SB>p</SB> = 1 states, also using the SPFIT program.</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The resulting spectroscopic constants are reported in Table 3, and the measured transition frequencies and obs. − calc. differences are collected in Table S3 of the ESI.<SUP TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" /> The vibrational spacing has been determined with a very high accuracy, Δ<IT>E</IT><SB>01</SB> = 259 726.035(10) MHz, that is 8.663 5280(4) cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Part of the reason for this accuracy is the low level of intercorrelations affecting Δ<IT>E</IT><SB>01</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is interesting to compare relatively small values of the Δ<SB><IT>JK</IT></SB> constants in Table 3 with 0.644(10) and −0.575(11) kHz determined, respectively for <IT>υ</IT><SB>p</SB> = 0 and <IT>υ</IT><SB>p</SB> = 1 states in single state fits.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">This provides direct evidence for the level of effective centrifugal distortion contributions introduced by the inversion potential, which was the basis for the derivation of additional information on the potential carried out in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">ref. 4</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Potential function</HEADER><P><s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the first time, we have a precise experimental value for the ground state ring puckering splitting in S<SB>0</SB>, whereas in previous analyses<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit6">4,6</REF> this could only be determined indirectly.</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The present value of 8.663 5280(4) cm<SP>−1</SP> is found to be intermediate between previous estimates.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Two values, 8.1 and 8.31 cm<SP>−1</SP> were determined from potentials fitted to observables from pure rotation spectra<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF> and far-infrared data of .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">ref. 2</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">A value of 9.6 cm<SP>−1</SP> was also inferred upon reinvestigation of the far-infrared spectrum,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF> and was found to be consistent with the potential fitted therein to far-infrared, Raman, and fluorescence spectra.</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Until now assignment of transitions involving higher quanta was considered reliable, such as that of <IT>υ</IT><SB>p</SB> = 2 ← 0, for which values of 99.1 and 100 cm<SP>−1</SP> were derived from far-infrared and dispersed fluorescence spectra,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF> respectively.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In view of the uncertainty concerning the reliability of the assignment we decided to re-examine the available data by going back to the simple one-dimensional analysis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">An isolated ring-puckering mode would be expected to be well described by a double minimum potential, as has been the case for 1,3-dioxole.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">An economic form of such a potential, such as the reduced quartic–quadratic<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF><IT>V</IT>(<IT>z</IT>) = <IT>A</IT>(<IT>z</IT><SP>4</SP> + <IT>Bz</IT><SP>2</SP>),is defined by only two parameters, and central barrier to planarity, <IT>V</IT><SB>0</SB>, is simply given by <IT>AB</IT><SP>2</SP>/4.</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Even in the presence also of other low-frequency normal modes this type of 1D-potential section should provide a sufficiently accurate description, at least in the energy region below excitation of other modes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since there is a consensus between theory and experiment that both the twisting and the flapping modes are well above 200 cm<SP>−1</SP> in frequency<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit6 cit10">4,6,10</REF> there should be several puckering energy levels in the intermolecular potential below the first excited states of the twisting or flapping motions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition the several operable (and for practical purposes mutually exclusive) selection rules, Δ<IT>υ</IT><SB>p</SB> = 1,3 in the far-infrared, and Δ<IT>υ</IT><SB>p</SB> = 2,4 in Raman<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20 cit22">20,22</REF> are expected to generate quite a sizable number of observable transitions between only the several lowest vibrational states.</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met14" novelty="Old" advantage="None">We used the program ANHARM from the PROSPE web-site<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF> for these calculations, together with the new Δ<IT>E</IT><SB>01</SB> and vibrational frequencies from .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">ref. 6</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">We decided to retrace the assignment from scratch and the results are collected in Table 4.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">For a double minimum potential the compression of the first two vibrational states by the presence of the central barrier at the planar configuration is accompanied by a somewhat smaller compression of the next higher pair of states, which leads to the second lowest vibrational frequency.</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">It was immediately found that for the <IT>ab initio</IT> estimate <IT>V</IT><SB>0</SB> = 150(50) cm<SP>−1</SP> for BDO<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF> the use of the current value of Δ<IT>E</IT><SB>01</SB> leaves only the 58.2 cm<SP>−1</SP> line in the infrared spectrum as the only realistic candidate for <IT>υ</IT><SB>p</SB> = 3 ← 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is in fact the assignment of .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">ref. 6</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The use of these two lines to predict the <IT>υ</IT><SB>p</SB> = 2 ← 1 transition leads to a frequency of 76 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The most probable assignment is therefore the nearest line to high frequency, at 79.5 cm<SP>−1</SP>, since there is no candidate to low frequency.</annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">In fact the 58.2 cm<SP>−1</SP> line is rather broad and structured, so it is better to use 8.66 and 79.5 cm<SP>−1</SP> transitions to define the potential, whereupon we immediately find that the 148.2 cm<SP>−1</SP> line can be assigned to <IT>υ</IT><SB>p</SB> = 3 ← 0.</annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The only other transition involving quanta up to <IT>υ</IT><SB>p</SB> = 3, namely <IT>υ</IT><SB>p</SB> = 3 ← 1 is indeed also found in a consistent position in the Raman spectrum, at 138.5 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have thus satisfactorily assigned all transitions up to <IT>υ</IT><SB>p</SB> = 3, and we note that the agreement for <IT>υ</IT><SB>p</SB>= 3 ← 2 would be improved if the mean frequency of its broad profile and not the low frequency peak were used.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Nevertheless assignment of transitions involving the <IT>υ</IT><SB>p</SB> = 4 level meets difficulties, while there are plausible candidates for transitions to the <IT>υ</IT><SB>p</SB> = 5 level, but not involving <IT>υ</IT><SB>p</SB> = 4.</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">We note that the calculated energy of 231 cm<SP>−1</SP> for <IT>υ</IT><SB>p</SB> = 4 is close to the estimated positions <IT>υ</IT><SB>t</SB> = 1 and of <IT>υ</IT><SB>f</SB> =.1<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit9">4,9</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">There could therefore be several mechanisms by which the position of this level could be perturbed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">If we assume a small 6 cm<SP>−1</SP> upward shift in the position of <IT>υ</IT><SB>p</SB> = 4 then it becomes possible to assign five more vibrational transitions, as seen in Table 4.</annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is noted that all of the assigned transitions are consistent with those with the selection rule Δ<IT>υ</IT><SB>p</SB> = 1,3 being observable in the infrared, and those for Δ<IT>υ</IT><SB>p</SB> = 2,4 being observable in Raman, and that relative intensities are in fair agreement with the calculated ones.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None">A further test of the derived 1D potential was carried out by checking its ability to reproduce a second reliable piece of experimental data namely changes of rotational constants and inertial planar moments with <IT>υ</IT><SB>p</SB> measured in .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">ref. 4</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">For this purpose we used a different form of the double minimum potential<IT>V</IT>(<IT>τ</IT>) = <IT>V</IT><SB>0</SB>[1 − (<IT>τ</IT>/<IT>τ</IT><SB>e</SB>)<SP>2</SP>]<SP>2</SP>,where <IT>V</IT><SB>0</SB> is the barrier to inversion and <IT>τ</IT><SB>e</SB> is the equilibrium value of the inversion angle (see Fig. 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">This potential was augmented with a flexible model, available for one and two-dimensional motions,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24 cit25">24,25</REF> and the molecular framework was constructed by using the parameters listed in .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">ref. 4</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Vibrational energies in Table 4 were reproduced with <IT>V</IT><SB>0</SB> = 108.5(11) cm<SP>−1</SP>, <IT>τ</IT><SB>e</SB> = 22.50(6)° and the changes in rotational constants and second moments of inertia required two additional adjustable parameters describing the variation in the CCO valence angle <IT>α</IT> with puckering excitation<IT>α</IT>(<IT>τ</IT>) = <IT>α</IT><SB>0</SB> + Δ<IT>α</IT>(<IT>τ/τ</IT><SB>e</SB>)<SP>2</SP>.The results of this calculation are compared with experimental values in Table 5.</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">It should be noted that observation of the zigzag behaviour in rotational constants in the range <IT>υ</IT><SB>p</SB> = 1–3 is indicative straightaway that these levels are in the vicinity of the central barrier.</annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the derived 1D potential <IT>υ</IT><SB>p</SB> = 0 and 1 are 50 and 41 cm<SP>−1</SP> below the barrier, respectively, while <IT>υ</IT><SB>p</SB> = 2 is 38 cm<SP>−1</SP> above the barrier.</annotationART></s> <s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Reproduction of the planar moments and rotational constants as documented in Table 5 is seen to be excellent.</annotationART></s> <s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">The <IT>A</IT> rotational constant is a possible exception, but its behaviour is known to be the most difficult to reproduce, since it is associated with the smallest moment of inertia.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The barrier of 108 cm<SP>−1</SP> corresponding to the present 1D assignment is somewhat lower than analogous 1D values of 124 cm<SP>−1</SP> (<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">ref. 4</REF>) and 128 cm<SP>−1</SP>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is also lower than barrier heights of 126 cm<SP>−1</SP>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF> and 164 cm<SP>−1</SP>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF> derived on application of a more sophisticated two-dimensional model.</annotationART></s> <s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have, in fact, also sought a 2D model solution that would encompass the 1D solution described above.</annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have found that the density of lines in the spectra is such that if the criterion for reproducing frequencies is reduced to, say, 3 cm<SP>−1</SP>, and the relative intensity criteria are also relaxed, then it is not possible to achieve a unique fit.</annotationART></s> <s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">The number of parameters in the 2D-fit and their flexibility is such that they are able to equally successfully encompass many radically different assignments of transitions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">A confident assignment of the <IT>υ</IT><SB>f</SB> = 1 ← 0 transition would be the minimum requirement for an attempt at a more reliable analysis with that model.</annotationART></s> <s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the other hand observation of the <IT>υ</IT><SB>p</SB> = 2 ← 0 transition in the Raman spectrum near 88 cm<SP>−1</SP> would be enough to confirm the present 1D analysis.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Conclusions</HEADER><P><s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The present work has delivered several new, precise pieces of information pertaining to the molecular dependence of the chemically relevant anomeric effect.</annotationART></s> <s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Augmentation of the available lower resolution data by information from rotationally resolved spectroscopy revealed considerable deficiencies in previously published spectral analysis, suggesting that a considerable re-assignment of the ring puckering transitions in 1,3-benzodioxole is required for both the S<SB>0</SB> and the S<SB>1</SB> states.</annotationART></s> <s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The origin of the S<SB>1</SB> ← S<SB>0</SB> electronic transition almost certainly has to be re-assigned, it is expected to lie at a lower frequency than that reported in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3 cit5 cit6 cit7">refs. 3 and 5–7</REF> and further work on this problem is in progress in the Florence laboratory.</annotationART></s> <s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is now clear that, while there is little doubt that the puckering barrier in 1,3-benzodioxole is considerably lower than the value of 275 cm<SP>−1</SP> in 1,3-dioxole,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF> its precise elucidation is proving rather difficult, as evidenced by the number of previous reports devoted to this problem.</annotationART></s> <s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">While a full 2D analysis of the dynamics of the five-membered ring would be more appropriate, it is mandatory to first reach a confident assignment of several more states, in particular those with <IT>υ</IT><SB>f</SB> &gt; 0.</annotationART></s> <s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the other hand the success of the 1D analysis suggests that near the minimum of the potential the dynamics is dominated by the puckering.</annotationART></s> <s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is also worth noting how close the actual value of Δ<IT>E</IT><SB>01</SB> = 8.663 5280(4) cm<SP>−1</SP> turned out to be to the value of 8.31 cm<SP>−1</SP> calculated on previous application of the 1D model to all data from pure rotational spectroscopy<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
