<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b310932a" hasDoc="yes" version="1194" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">An enzyme-immobilization method for integration of biofunctions on a microchip using a water-soluble amphiphilic phospholipid polymer having a reacting group</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">A water-soluble phospholipid polymer having an active ester group in the side chain, poly[2-methacryloyloxyethyl phosphorylcholine (MPC)-<IT>co</IT>-<IT>n</IT>-butyl methacrylate (BMA)-<IT>co</IT>-<IT>p</IT>-nitrophenyloxycarbonyl polyethyleneglycol methacrylate (MEONP) (PMBN), was used for the immobilization of an enzyme on a plastic microchip.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The MPC polymers with BMA units were adsorbed onto the poly(methyl methacrylate) (PMMA) microchip, and the active ester group in the MEONP unit reacted with the amino groups of the proteolytic enzyme, trypsin.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Trypsin was immobilized on the sample reservoir, and catalyzed the hydrolysis of the fluorescently labeled ArgOEt to Arg.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The consequent separation of product from the substrate, and their detection, were integrated on the microchip and this meant that all procedures from the enzymatic activity to product detection were completed in less than three minutes.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the past decade, there has been an explosion of interest in the fields of microfluidic systems.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2 cit3 cit4 cit5 cit6 cit7">1–7</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Microfabricated fluidic devices are potentially powerful tools for chemical or biological assays.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">These devices offer a rapid analysis, reduced sample consumption and cost.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Specific and efficient biological reactions may significantly benefit with microfluidic devices that offer the means for handling small volume samples (<IT>i.e.</IT>, nL to µL) in confined reaction zones.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Various biological assays have been performed in these devices, such as enzymatic reactions<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2 cit3">2,3</REF> or immunoassays.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit5">4,5</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">These reactions were performed using a homogeneous enzyme in a channel,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">2</REF> or immobilized enzymes<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF> or an antibody<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF> on packed beads, or an encapsulated enzyme in a hydrogel.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF> </annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Recently, much attention has been devoted to the use of phospholipid polymer materials for modifying the surfaces of biomaterials in order to improve their biocompatibility, namely the ability to inhibit nonspecific protein adsorption or cell adhesion.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit9 cit10">8–10</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the field of capillary electrophoresis, various kinds of phospholipids are used as a wall coating for the prevention of protein adsorption.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11 cit12">11,12</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Ishihara <IT>et al.</IT> developed new polymeric materials having the typical phospholipid polar group, 2-methacryloyloxyethyl phosphorylcholine (MPC) copolymer, with various alkyl methacrylates or styrene to change the characteristics, such as solubility, so as to be adapted to the surroundings.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13 cit14">13,14</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The MPC polymers are very useful for not only artificial organs but also for medical devices and pharmaceutical applications due to their excellent properties; <IT>i.e.</IT>, resistance to protein adsorption and cell adhesion by adsorption onto the substrate surface.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15 cit16">15,16</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">To extend the biological applications, the phospholipid polymer for bioconjugation, poly[MPC-<IT>co</IT>-<IT>n</IT>-butyl methacrylate (BMA)-<IT>co</IT>-<IT>p</IT>-nitrophenyloxycarbonyl polyethyleneglycol methacrylate (MEONP)] (PMBN) (Fig. 1), was designed and synthesized.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="None" advantage="Yes">The MEONP unit has an active ester group in the side chain, which can conjugate with a specific biomolecule <IT>via</IT> its hydrolysis.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Considering that PMBN has the hydrophobic unit, BMA, it was anticipated that the PMBN could be adsorbed on the poly(methyl methacrylate) (PMMA) surface and mediate the conjugation of biomolecules such as enzymes <IT>via</IT> the active ester units.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">In this study, we developed a novel enzyme-immobilization method on a PMMA microchip using PMBN for integration of the biofunctions on the microchip.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Experimental</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Materials and chemicals</HEADER><P><s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">4-Fluoro-7-nitro-2,1,3-benzoxadiazole (NBD-F) and anhydrous ethylenediamine were purchased from Tokyo Kasei (Tokyo, Japan).</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Trypsin from porcine pancreas and l-Arg were purchased from Sigma-Aldrich (Milwaukee, WI).</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Arg ethyl ester dihydrochloride was purchased from Wako Pure Chemicals (Osaka, Japan).</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The PMBNs were synthesized as described in the previous report.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Two kinds of PMBN were tested, and the mole fractions of each monomer unit in the PMBN were MPC/BMA/MEONP = 0.4/0.5/0.1 and 0.3/0.6/0.1, described as PMBN40 and PMBN30, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Water was purified by MilliQ apparatus (Millipore, Bedford, MA).</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Apparatus</HEADER><P><s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Separations were performed on a microfabricated PMMA chip, <IT>i</IT>-chip 3 DNA (Hitachi, Tokyo, Japan).</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The schematic layout is shown in Fig. 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The microchip has dimensions of 85 mm × 50 mm square with three simple cross channels of 100 µm in width and 30 µm in depth.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The distance between the sample reservoir (SR) and the sample waste (SW) was 10 mm, whereas the distance from the buffer reservoir (BR) and the buffer waste (BW) was 44 mm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp9" novelty="None" advantage="None">A small plastic tip was attached to each reservoir and each waste for sample or buffer introduction and removal, respectively.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The microchip electrophoresis system was the same as described in our previous report.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp11" novelty="None" advantage="None">50 mM Tris–HCl buffer (pH 7.5) was used as the running buffer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The voltage settings were also based on a previously published report.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp12" novelty="None" advantage="None">In all experiments, the potentials of 100, –90, –500 V were applied to SR, BR and SW, respectively, for the 40 s sample introduction, while BW was grounded.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp13" novelty="None" advantage="None">This ensured minimal sample introduction bias in the injection cross section.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The voltage program for the separation of analytes was 500, 900, 500 V for SR, BR and SW, respectively, and BW was grounded.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp15" novelty="None" advantage="None">After every run, each reservoir was replaced with fresh buffer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp16" novelty="None" advantage="None">A cleaning procedure was performed by flowing the buffer in the channel for 2 min using the same voltage program as that for sample separation.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp17" novelty="None" advantage="None"><IT>(Caution! The electrophoresis uses high voltages and special care should be taken when handling the electrophoresis electrodes).</IT></annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Derivatization of samples with NBD-F</HEADER><P><s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Samples were derivatized with NBD-F according to the procedure by Imai <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Derivatized samples were diluted with the running buffer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Before use, all solutions were filtered through a 0.22 µm membrane (Millipore, Bedford, MA) and degassed by ultrasonication.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Trypsin immobilization on the microchip</HEADER><P><s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp19" novelty="None" advantage="None">All channels were filled with 50 mM Tris–HCl (pH 7.5) and the other three reservoirs except for the SR were filled with 50 µL of the buffer to prevent the PMBN solution from permeating into the channels and the other reservoirs.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp20" novelty="None" advantage="None">A 10 µL volume of the 0.3% (w/v) PMBN aqueous solution was carefully added to the SR and allowed to stand for 5 min so that the PMBN could adsorb onto the PMMA surface of the SR.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp21" novelty="None" advantage="None">After the solution was removed, the SR was dried using air.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp22" novelty="None" advantage="None">The PMBN solution was again added to the SR and the same procedure was repeated once more.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp23" novelty="None" advantage="None">A 10 µL solution of trypsin (10% (w/v)) in 50 mM Tris–HCl (pH 7.0) containing 20 mM CaCl<SB>2</SB> was carefully added to the SR and allowed to react with the adsorbed PMBN at 4 °C for 2 days.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp24" novelty="None" advantage="None">After the unreacted trypsin was removed, the SR was washed and filled with 50 mM Tris–HCl (pH 7.5) before analysis.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>On-chip tryptic digestion</HEADER><P><s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp25" novelty="None" advantage="None">Before reaction, the channels were filled with 50 mM Tris–HCl (pH 7.5).</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp26" novelty="None" advantage="None">Also the three reservoirs except for the SR were filled with 50 µL of the same buffer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp27" novelty="None" advantage="None">A 40 µL volume of the substrate solution containing an internal standard, NBD–ethylenediamine, was added to the SR and voltage was applied immediately.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Results and discussion</HEADER><P><s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The chemical structure of PMBN is shown in Fig. 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">PMBN consists of three components, MPC, BMA, and MEONP units.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">They were polymerized by a conventional radical polymerization technique in ethanol using 2,2′-azobisisobutyronitrile as the initiator.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">PMBN is amphiphilic, having both a hydrophilic MPC unit and a hydrophobic BMA unit.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In aqueous solution, BMA forms aggregates and adsorbs onto the hydrophobic substrate surface; in this case, the PMMA chip surface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the other hand, the hydrophilic MPC unit is oriented toward the aqueous solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">MEONP works as an active ester unit to conjugate with specific biomolecules having amino groups.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="New" advantage="None">In this study, trypsin, a proteolytic enzyme, was immobilized on the SR surface <IT>via</IT> the hydrolysis of the active ester units for the fabrication of the biochip which integrates the tryptic reaction of the substrate, separation of products, and detection (Fig. 2).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="New" advantage="None">After PMBN was adsorbed onto the SR surface, the trypsin solution was added to the SR for immobilization.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reaction time for the trypsin immobilization was examined, and it was optimized by measuring the enzymatic activity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The enzymatic activity increased with a reaction time for the trypsin immobilization up to 2 days.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">For any longer time, the enzymatic activity was not changed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, 2 day reaction was thought to be enough for the trypsin immobilization on the SR.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">When trypsin solution was added to the SR without adsorption of PMBN and removed after 2 days, the tryptic activity was not observed, which indicates that the non-covalent adsorption of trypsin on the well surface was negligible.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">We used two kinds of PMBN, that is, PMBN40 and PMBN30.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Trypsin immobilized <IT>via</IT> PMBN40 was not stable, and the activity decreased to 20% of the initial activity after 5 analyses.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the other hand, trypsin immobilized <IT>via</IT> PMBN30 was more stable and the activity was not changed after 15 analyses.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Presumably, PMBN30 having a more hydrophobic BMA unit than PMBN40 facilitated its adsorption onto the PMMA surface and contributed to the stability of the trypsin activity.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 3 illustrates the typical electrophorogram of NBD–ArgOEt and NBD–Arg along with the internal standard, NBD–ethylenediamine, when 1.0 mM NBD–ArgOEt was introduced into the microchip.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Immobilized trypsin successfully hydrolyzed NBD–ArgOEt to NBD–Arg, and 0.45 mM NBD–Arg was produced.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, the three peaks were completely separated in 120 seconds.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The migration times were almost the same as those separated on a chip without PMBN and trypsin coating, which indicates that the PMBN and trypsin coating has little influence on electroosmotic mobility.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">This microchip can be used for at least 2 days.</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the other hand, a soluble trypsin, which was stored in the same running buffer of 50 mM Tris–HCl (pH 7.5) at 25 °C, almost completely lost its activity within 1 day.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19">19</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">These results show the stability of the linkage of trypsin to well surfaces, and that the stability of trypsin was enhanced by immobilization because autolysis of the enzyme was prevented<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF>. </annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Conclusion</HEADER><P><s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The water-soluble amphiphilic phospholipid polymer, PMBN, could be used for the immobilization of an enzyme on a PMMA microchip.</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The preparation method is very easy, and this method is applicable to a variety of biomolecules with amino groups to react with PMBN.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">This technique will permit the fabrication of a biochip that contains a discrete area for bioreactions and further expands the scope of microchip analysis.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
