<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b313251j" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Degradation of three oxygenated alkoxy radicals of atmospheric interest: HOCH<SB>2</SB>O˙, CH<SB>3</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>O˙, CH<SB>3</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>O˙. RRKM theoretical study of the β-C–H bond scission and the 1,6-isomerisation kinetics</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">A detailed theoretical study on the pressure and temperature dependence of the rate constants <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB>, <IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB>, <IT>k</IT><SB>3</SB> for the thermal β-C–H dissociation of the three radicals: HOCH<SB>2</SB>O˙, CH<SB>3</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>O˙, CH<SB>3</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>O˙ is presented.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">This investigation is extended to the rate constant <IT>k</IT><SB>4</SB> for the 1,6-H-shift isomerisation of CH<SB>3</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>O˙.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">High-level <IT>ab initio</IT> computations (CCSD(T)//MP2) have been performed and combined with RRKM theory to obtain rate constants.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The β-C–H scission pathway is predicted to occur with an activation energy of 10–13 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Estimation of the competition between the β-C–H and β-C–O decompositions, the isomerisation process, and the reaction with oxygen has been done.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">At 760 Torr and 298 K, <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB>, <IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB>, <IT>k</IT><SB>3</SB>, <IT>k</IT><SB>4</SB> are 4.4 × 10<SP>4</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>, 5.2 × 10<SP>4</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>, 4.2 × 10<SP>3</SP> s<SP>−1</SP> and 5.6 × 10<SP>3</SP> s<SP>−1</SP> respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">An interesting result is that the isomerisation through a seven-membered transition state may compete with the H-atom elimination from the CH<SB>3</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>O˙ radical.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="I.">Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None">In this paper, we present a theoretical study of the three following β-C–H dissociations of oxygenated alkoxy radicals:HOCH<SB>2</SB>O˙ + M → HCOOH + H˙ + MCH<SB>3</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>O˙ + M → CH<SB>3</SB>OCHO + H˙ + MCH<SB>3</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>O˙ + M → CH<SB>3</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>OCHO + H˙ + Mand of the isomerisation process:CH<SB>3</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>O˙ + M → ˙CH<SB>2</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>OH + Mfor which one pressure data were available at room temperature from experimental measurements.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2 cit3">1–3</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Actually, because of the increasing use as industrial solvents and fuel additives of oxygenated compounds such as ethers, their tropospheric oxidation has received significant attention.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Dimethyl ether (DME) CH<SB>3</SB>OCH<SB>3</SB>, and dimethoxymethane (DMM) CH<SB>3</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>OCH<SB>3</SB>, have been proposed as possible alternative diesel fuels.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Atmospheric degradation of these compounds is initiated by ˙OH radical attack which abstracts an alkyl hydrogen, and the alkyl radical formed will rapidly add oxygen to give peroxy radicals RO<SB>2</SB>˙.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In polluted atmosphere, peroxy radicals react with NO to give the corresponding alkoxy radicals RO˙.</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of DME, these successive reactions CH<SB>3</SB>OCH<SB>3</SB> + ˙OH → CH<SB>3</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>˙ + H<SB>2</SB>OCH<SB>3</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>˙ + O<SB>2</SB> + M → CH<SB>3</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>O<SB>2</SB>˙ + MCH<SB>3</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>O<SB>2</SB>˙ + NO → CH<SB>3</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>O˙ + NO<SB>2</SB>produce the simplest α-alkoxyalkoxy radical CH<SB>3</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>O˙.</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">By similar reactions, ˙OH oxidation of DMM gives two different alkoxy radicals, CH<SB>3</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>O˙ and CH<SB>3</SB>OCH(O˙)OCH<SB>3</SB> depending on the group (–CH<SB>3</SB> or –CH<SB>2</SB>) from which there is H-abstraction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The most common reactions of alkoxy radicals are reaction with O<SB>2</SB> (if an α-H is present), isomerisation <IT>via</IT> 1,5 H-shift through a 6-membered transition state and decomposition by β-C–C or β-C–O bond fission (if an ether oxygen atom is present).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, a kinetic study of the self-reaction of the peroxy radical CH<SB>3</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>O<SB>2</SB>˙<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF> complemented by a detailed product analysis has provided evidence for a mechanism involving the rapid thermal decomposition of the alkoxy radical CH<SB>3</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>O˙ by H-atom elimination occurring in competition with the reaction with O<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">CH<SB>3</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>O˙ + M → CH<SB>3</SB>OCHO Methylformate (MF) + H˙ + MCH<SB>3</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>O˙ + O<SB>2</SB> → CH<SB>3</SB>OCHO Methylformate (MF) + HO<SB>2</SB>˙ The authors<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF> have obtained a value of the decomposition rate constant of about 3 × 10<SP>3</SP> s<SP>−1</SP> (assuming k<SB>O<SB>2</SB></SB> ≈ 10<SP>−14</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>) at 25 Torr total pressure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Moreover, it is shown in this work that the rate constant <IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB> for H-atom elimination exhibits a pressure dependence in the 25–800 Torr pressure range.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the same way, Wallington <IT>et al.</IT>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">2</REF> in a FTIR-smog chamber study of the atmospheric chemistry of DMM, analysed the fate of CH<SB>3</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>O˙ by measuring the yield of methoxymethylformate (MMF) and suggested the occurence of the two pathways: CH<SB>3</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>O˙ + M → CH<SB>3</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>OCHO (MMF) + H˙ + MCH<SB>3</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>O˙ + O<SB>2</SB> → CH<SB>3</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>OCHO (MMF) + HO<SB>2</SB>˙They observed that the yield of MMF, although sensitive to the O<SB>2</SB> partial pressure, does not approach zero at the lowest O<SB>2</SB> pressure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">This gives evidence for the occurrence of reaction (3).</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">From a fit to their experimental data, they obtained the ratio k<SB>9</SB>/<IT>k</IT><SB>3</SB>, and then <IT>k</IT><SB>3</SB> ≈ 4 × 10<SP>3</SP> s<SP>−1</SP> at 296 K and 700 Torr total pressure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Moreover, their experimental results suggest that isomerisation (4) could be a competing atmospheric loss process.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">CH<SB>3</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>O˙ + M → ˙CH<SB>2</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>OH + MIn the same study, the authors analysed the fate of the other alkoxy radical, CH<SB>3</SB>OCH(O˙)OCH<SB>3</SB> (produced by ˙OH attack to the –CH<SB>2</SB> group of the DMM), by measuring the yield of dimethylcarbonate (DMC) and found it independent of the molecular oxygen partial pressure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">They concluded that collision-induced H-atom elimination was the prime channel: CH<SB>3</SB>OCH(O˙)OCH<SB>3</SB> + M → CH<SB>3</SB>OC(O)OCH<SB>3</SB> (DMC) + H˙ + MThis conclusion has been successfully used in the computer simulation performed by Geiger and Becker.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Veyret <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF>. have provided the first evidence for H-atom elimination from HOCH<SB>2</SB>O˙ (reaction (1)) to explain a chain process in the photooxidation of formaldehyde.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">From their kinetic simulation at 298 K and 343 K, they proposed an order of magnitude of <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB> ≈ 1200 s<SP>−1</SP> at 298 K for 10–30 Torr total pressure of formaldehyde.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, it appears that H-atom elimination may be a general decomposition mechanism for alkoxy bearing an oxygen functionality.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Numerous theoretical studies have recently been devoted to the reactivity of alkoxy radicals.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">In particular, decomposition<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6 cit7">6,7</REF> and isomerisation<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7 cit8">7,8</REF> reactions have been investigated and structure-activity relationships (SAR) have been developed for the activation barrier or the rate constants.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac20" novelty="None" advantage="None">More recently, Rayez <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF>. examined a novel rearrangement (α-ester rearrangement) of an oxygenated alkoxy radical and Ferenac <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF>. studied the effect of oxygen-containing functional groups on the β-C–C and β-C–O decomposition and on the isomerisation of alkoxy radicals.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac21" novelty="None" advantage="None">Some theoretical results have also been presented about the β-C–H scission reactions of alkoxy<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7 cit11 cit12">7,11,12</REF> (including oxygenated alkoxy<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF>).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">There is currently a considerable interest for the reactions of alkoxy radicals and especially for oxygenated alkoxy radicals, but only a few studies have concerned this particular reaction of H-atom elimination.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In particular, no theoretical approaches have been used for providing general characteristics of this type of reactions and, at the end, to built SAR.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">Thus, it was interesting to study the thermal β-C–H scission of some oxygenated alkoxy radicals, namely HOCH<SB>2</SB>O˙, CH<SB>3</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>O˙ and CH<SB>3</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>O˙ (reactions (1)–(3)), as well as the isomerisation process (4) for CH<SB>3</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>O˙.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our main objective in this study is to provide and compare the thermal unimolecular rate constants, <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB>, <IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB>, <IT>k</IT><SB>3</SB>, <IT>k</IT><SB>4</SB> obtained from RRKM calculations of the falloff curves.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">We evaluate also the magnitude of the H-atom elimination (and of the isomerisation) relatively to the β-C–O decomposition and to reaction with O<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="II.">Computational details</HEADER><P><s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The thermal rate constants of the unimolecular reactions (1) and (2) are obtained by applying the RRKM theory to predict the falloff behaviour using the KISTHEP package<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF> validated by comparison with the program FALLOFF.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">For the CH<SB>3</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>O˙ radical, the two competitive reaction channels (β-C–H scission and isomerisation) are treated simultaneously with the program FALLOFF.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Kinetics calculations were first performed with input data (structural and thermochemical parameters) obtained from CCSD(T)//MP2 <IT>ab initio</IT> calculations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">A good agreement between the results of RRKM calculations and experimental data was obtained by slightly adjusting the value of the calculated threshold energy of the corresponding unimolecular reactions.</annotationART></s></P><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Quantum chemistry calculations</HEADER><P><s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None"><IT>Ab initio</IT> computations were carried out using the Gaussian98 software package.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The HF-DFT (B3LYP)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF>/6-31G** theoretical level was used to yield an estimation of the enthalpy of (reactions (1)–(3)) and of the activation energy of the reactions that may compete with the β-C–H scission.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In order to obtain reliable energetics, calculations were then performed at higher levels of theory: (i) G2-theory<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF> and (ii) CCSD(T)/cc-pVDZ//MP2(Frozen Core)/cc-pVDZ.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In the last case, using cc-pVDZ basis set, all geometries were fully optimized at the unrestricted second-order Mőller-Plesset perturbation (UMP2) level of theory using the “frozen-core” approximation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is to be noticed that UHF wave functions for the β-C–H transition states were contaminated by higher-lying spin states, with values of 〈S<SP>2</SP>〉 ∼ 0.85, while for the isomerisation one it was less contaminated (〈S<SP>2</SP>〉 ∼ 0.78).</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Harmonic vibrational frequencies and zero-point energies (ZPE) were also computed at the UMP2/cc-pVDZ level of theory and are not scaled.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Single and double coupled-cluster theory with inclusion of a perturbative estimation for triple excitation<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF> was used to improve the accuracy on calculated energies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="Old" advantage="None">All transition states have been characterized by one imaginary frequency (first order saddle points) on the potential energy surface (PES).</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Intrinsic reaction coordinate analyses (IRC) were performed at both HF-DFT(B3LYP) and UMP2 levels of theory in order to confirm that a specific transition state connects the designated local minima.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Thermal unimolecular rate constants</HEADER><P><s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The microcanonical rate constants are calculated by the standard RRKM expression: <IT>k</IT>(<IT>E</IT>) = <IT>αG</IT>(<IT>E</IT>)/<IT>hN</IT>(<IT>E</IT>) where <IT>α</IT> is the reaction path degeneracy, <IT>G</IT>(<IT>E</IT>) is the total number of states of the transition state with energy less than or equal to <IT>E</IT>, and <IT>N</IT>(<IT>E</IT>) is the density of states of the radical.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">To account for the two possible H-eliminations, the reaction path degeneracy <IT>α</IT> was set to two; more details are given in the next Section.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the possible 1,6-H-shift isomerisation of CH<SB>3</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>O˙ radicals, reaction (4), <IT>α</IT> was set at 3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">All species are treated as symmetric tops and the external <IT>K</IT>-rotor, associated with the smallest moment of inertia, is treated as an active degree of freedom completely coupled to the vibrations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Taking into account the possibility of several simultaneous unimolecular channels, the thermal rate constant for each channel is obtained by using the following expression:<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19">19</REF> where <IT>Q</IT> is the partition function of the active degrees of freedom of the radical, <IT>Q</IT>‡<IT>i</IT>,rot and <IT>Q</IT><SB>rot</SB> are the partition functions for adiabatic rotations of the transition state and of the radical, respectively, <IT>E</IT><SB><IT>i</IT>,0</SB> is the threshold energy, <IT>ω</IT> = <IT>β</IT><SB>c</SB><IT>Z</IT><SB>LJ</SB>[M] is the effective collision frequency where <IT>β</IT><SB>c</SB> is the collisional efficiency, <IT>Z</IT><SB>LJ</SB> is the Lennard-Jones collision frequency and [M] is the total gas concentration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None"><IT>Z</IT><SB>LJ</SB> was calculated for the alkoxy radicals of interest using the parameters of selected nearest species (see details below).</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to account for the centrifugal effect in the rate constant calculation, the factor <IT>Q</IT>‡<IT>i</IT>,rot/<IT>Q</IT><SB>rot</SB> was included in the expression of <IT>k</IT><IT><SB>i</SB></IT>(<IT>T</IT>) and <IT>k</IT><IT><SB>i</SB></IT>(<IT>E</IT>) is evaluated at the energy <IT>E</IT> including 〈Δ<IT>E</IT><SB><IT>j</IT></SB>〉 with 〈Δ<IT>E</IT><SB><IT>j</IT></SB>〉 = (1 − <IT>I</IT><SP>‡</SP>/<IT>I</IT>)<IT>k</IT><SB>B</SB><IT>T</IT> where <IT>I</IT><SP>‡</SP> and <IT>I</IT> are the average of the two largest moments of inertia.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="III.">Results and discussion</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Structural parameters</HEADER><P><s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The geometries of the alkoxy radicals investigated are presented in Fig. 1, where the relevant geometrical parameters have been indicated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the following, R1, R2, R3 refer to the three alkoxy radicals investigated and TS1, TS2, TS3 designate the corresponding transition states for β-C–H scissions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">It can be pointed out that reactant R1 has <IT>C</IT><SB>1</SB> symmetry, that is, the hydroxyl H-atom is twisted out of the OCO plane (HOCO = 54.3° at the MP2 level of theory), thus leading to the existence of two optical isomers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">This result is obtained whatever the level of theory used and can be explained by orbital analysis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Out of plane position of hydrogen atom allows for a largest delocalisation of the two electrons in molecular orbital depicted Fig. 2, and simultaneously accounts for the (i) minimization of interaction between the 2p lone pairs of each oxygen, (ii) optimisation of the intramolecular hydrogen bonding forces involving the in-plane 2p lone pair on the open-shell oxygen atom, (iii) maximisation of the π overlap, involving the hydroxyl oxygen 2p orbital (out of plane) and a CH<SB>2</SB> fragment orbital, that describes the unpaired electron π delocalisation across the OCO skeleton atoms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reactant R2 geometry is consistent with the one predicted by Francisco<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF> in his study of the CH<SB>3</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>O˙ radical structure.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">As aforementioned, we have taken a reaction path degeneracy <IT>α</IT> of two in the following rate constant calculations for each alkoxy decomposition, reactions (1), (2) and (3).</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Unlike the β-C–O decomposition (see Fig. 3), it is clear that H-elimination can occur by two distinct paths since two physically distinct β-C–H bonds can dissociate in each reactant (R1, R2, R3) to form a carbonyl group (see Fig. 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although these two H-atoms are differently situated and the two corresponding elimination paths are different, we have assumed, for computational purposes, that the loss of reactant proceeds with the same rate constant by each of the two pathways.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">This can be rationalized by examining the structure of each transition state (see TS1, TS2, TS3 in Fig. 1) and keeping in mind that the two pathways differ only by the position of the leaving H-atom: situated above or under the HCOO plane.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">For reaction (1), the two corresponding transition states have exactly the same properties, while some differences appear for reactions (2) and (3) due to asymmetrical environment around the leaving H-atom.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">For instance, our CCSD(T)//MP2 computations give a difference in potential energy of 0.3 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> between these two similar transition states for reaction (3).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">From an electronic structure point of view, the decomposition of the studied alkoxy radicals by β-C–H bond rupture involves transition state geometries (TS1, TS2, TS3) with more product-like character.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">For instance, in the transition state TS3 the C–O bond is shortened by about 0.13 Å (C–O<SB>reactant</SB> = 1.36 Å, C–O<SB>TS3</SB> = 1.23 Å) which corresponds to 90 percent of the final shortening (C–O<SB>products</SB> = 1.21 Å).</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The breaking C–H bond in the transition state is significantly longer (by about 32 percent) than in the unperturbed radical.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The structural parameters (vibrational frequencies and rotational constants) of reactants and transition states obtained at the MP2 level of theory for reactions (1)–(3) are presented in Table 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is worth noting that the transition state structures are well localized on the PES, with moments of inertia slightly lower than those of the corresponding radicals.</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">This results in very small entropies of activation leading to low preexponential factors for these decomposition reactions (≈5 × 10<SP>12</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">It can be noticed that we have found, for reaction (2), another H-elimination channel involving at the beginning of this process a conformer of the reactant: R2′ (see Fig. 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">At the CCSD(T) level of theory, the calculated barrier is however about 2 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> larger, showing that this channel is not favoured.</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is interesting to note that R3 conformer geometry reveals an intramolecular hydrogen bond.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">More explicitly, it forms a seven-membered ring structure making possible the isomerisation process (4).</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None">This possibility is examined below.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The corresponding structure of the transition state (TS7) is given in Fig. 4 and structural parameters are reported in Table 1.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Relative energies</HEADER><P><s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">As can be seen from Table 2, the enthalpies of β-C–H scission (1), (2) and (3) at 0 K (Δ<SB>r</SB><IT>H</IT>°(0 K)) are of the same order of magnitude for each level of theory.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">For instance, the heat of reactions (1)–(3) derived from the G2 method are −1.0, −1.4 and −1.2 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The estimated enthalpy of each reaction indicates it to be thermoneutral at the two levels of theory G2 (about −1 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>) or CCSD(T)//MP2 (between −2 and −3 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac22" novelty="None" advantage="None">Using isodesmic reactions for reaction (2), Good and Francisco<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF> have estimated a ΔH value of 3.0 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>, consistent with our findings.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is not surprising that B3LYP gives values significantly different with respect to the other methods since a larger basis set would be necessary to better describe the large electronic changes occurring between reactant and products.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Barrier heights (Δ<IT>H</IT><SP>‡</SP>°(0 K)) for the β-C–H bond dissociations investigated in this work are summarized in Table 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">Comparison of these values to each other shows no significant difference at each level of theory for the three reactions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">The studied β-C–H bond scissions involve a sizeable energy barrier (9–14 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac22" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hippler <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF>. have computed activation barriers for such β-C–H bond dissociations for a set of twelve non-oxygenated alkoxy radicals and found values lying between 19 and 26 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fact that our computed barriers are about twice smaller than their values provides strong evidence for an effect of oxygen-substituents which increases the β-C–H dissociation rate.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">Preceding the products, a shallow minimum has been spotted on the PES for each reaction corresponding to a weak-bound complex that is formed by just a few kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> binding energy between H-atom and the corresponding co-product.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to establish the relative importance of the H-atom elimination and of the β-C–O dissociation, an alternative reaction pathway, we also present an estimation of the energetic features for the latter channel for each alkoxy radical, at B3LYP theoretical level: HOCH<SB>2</SB>O˙ + M → HO˙ + H<SB>2</SB>CO + MCH<SB>3</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>O˙ + M → CH<SB>3</SB>O˙ + H<SB>2</SB>CO + MCH<SB>3</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>O˙ + M → CH<SB>3</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>O˙ + H<SB>2</SB>CO + MThe values of calculated barriers (20–30 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>, Table 2) agree favourably with those obtained by Ferenac <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF>. at the same level of theory for other similar oxygenated alkoxy radicals (CH<SB>3</SB>CH<SB>2</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>O˙: 20 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>, CH<SB>3</SB>COOCH<SB>2</SB>O˙: 22 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None">Good and Francisco<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF> have obtained an activation barrier of 23.1 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> at the G2 level of theory for reaction (12), which is in good agreement with our HF-DFT (B3LYP) value (21.4 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None">The large activation energies obtained for the β-C–O bond scission (together with the Arrhenius factors found for this process at 298 K: <IT>A</IT> ≈ 1–2 × 10<SP>13</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>) clearly show that this process is not favourable, as found by Good and Francisco<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF> for the CH<SB>3</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>O˙ radical.</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac23" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is in line with experimental findings of Wallington <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">2</REF>. and Geiger and Becker<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF> who suggest that decomposition of CH<SB>3</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>O˙ <IT>via</IT> reaction (13) is of minor importance.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res29" novelty="None" advantage="None">There are no possible isomerisation reaction by 1,5 H-shift through a six-membered transition state for these three alkoxy radicals.</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac24" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, Wallington <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">2</REF>. suggest that an unknown reaction, accounting for about 9% of the fate of CH<SB>3</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>O˙, should be an isomerisation reaction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res30" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our CCSD(T)//MP2 calculations show that the 1,6-H-shift (reaction (4)) (Δ<IT>H</IT><SP>‡</SP>°(0 K) = 10.7 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>) is more favoured than the 1,4 H-shift (Δ<IT>H</IT><SP>‡</SP>°(0 K) = 20.6 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In view of our results (G2 and CCSD(T)//MP2 in Table 2), this 1,6-isomerisation channel through a 7-membered transition state may be energetically competitive with the β-C–H scission.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Concerning the CH<SB>3</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>O˙ radical, the 1,2 and 1,4 H-shifts have not been taken into account in our kinetic treatment.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" advantage="None">Indeed, the corresponding B3LYP activation energies (Δ<IT>H</IT><SP>‡</SP>°(0 K) = 27.6 and 24.4 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> respectively) are very large compared to the β-C–H one (Δ<IT>H</IT><SP>‡</SP>°(0 K) = 13.3 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>) (the B3LYP predicted Arrhenius <IT>A</IT> factors being similar at 298 K: <IT>A</IT><SB>β-C–H</SB> = 6 × 10<SP>12</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>, <IT>A</IT><SB>isom</SB> = 2–4 × 10<SP>12</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>).</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Rate constants</HEADER><P><s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Structural parameters (vibrational frequencies and rotational constants) listed in Table 1 are employed in the RRKM calculations for H-elimination reactions (1), (2) and (3) and isomerisation reaction (4).</annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac25" novelty="None" advantage="None">There are no data available for the Lennard-Jones parameters, σ and ε/k, of the three studied alkoxy radicals.</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met14" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Values were evaluated from tabulated values of nearest species or were based on the recommendation of Gilbert and Smith<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF> using the boiling point of similar species.</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">These estimated values are also reported in Table 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac26" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the HOCH<SB>2</SB>O˙ radical, experiments<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF> were performed in formaldehyde as buffer gas.</annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore the evaluated Lennard-Jones parameters of this species are reported in Table 1 along with those of N<SB>2</SB> used as buffer gas for the two other alkoxy radicals.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">When N<SB>2</SB> is the buffer gas, the collisional efficiency <IT>β</IT><SB>c</SB> is taken equal to 0.2 which is a reasonable value at 298 K. For reaction (1), the collisional efficiency of formaldehyde is unknown.</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Here, we have choosen to use <IT>β</IT><SB>c</SB> = 0.2 as for N<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res32" novelty="None" advantage="None">As discussed below, doubling this value has no significant effect on the <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB> pressure dependence under atmospheric conditions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod11" novelty="None" advantage="None">As proposed by Troe,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF> a temperature dependence for <IT>β</IT><SB>c</SB> ∝ <IT>T</IT><SP>−1</SP> was used in calculations.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met15" novelty="Old" advantage="None">As above-mentioned, in first step of the calculation, all the energetic input data used in the statistical RRKM calculations were taken from the CCSD(T)//MP2 results.</annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Then, taking into account that the <IT>ab initio</IT> values of the barrier height <IT>E</IT><SB>0</SB> are calculated with uncertainties of about 1–2 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>, <IT>E</IT><SB>0</SB> was adjusted in order to fit at best the available kinetic experimental data.</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The best fit was obtained with <IT>E</IT><SB>0</SB> = 9.6, 10.7, 12.6 and 11.5 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> for reactions (1), (2), (3) and (4), respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">These values are reported in Table 3, along with the values obtained from CCSD(T)//MP2 calculations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">It can be seen that the adjustments (0.8–2.5 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>) are within the margin of errors (both experimental and theoretical).</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Those values show that the β-C–H scission pathway can be predicted to occur with an activation energy of 10–13 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod12" novelty="None" advantage="None">It should be noted that in the particular case of the CH<SB>3</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>O˙ radical, the 1,6-H-shift isomerisation reaction (4) was taken into account, using the data reported by Wallington <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">2</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac27" novelty="None" advantage="None">In air conditions, they report that the β-C–H scission accounts for 7% of the total reaction, the 1,6-H-shift isomerisation for 9% and the reaction with oxygen for 84%.</annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac28" novelty="None" advantage="None">Consequently, at 296 K and 760 Torr, the experimental values are <IT>k</IT><SB>3</SB> ≈ 4 × 10<SP>3</SP> s<SP>−1</SP> and <IT>k</IT><SB>4</SB> ≈ 5 × 10<SP>3</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The falloff curves are shown in Fig. 5 for reactions (1)–(4).</annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res33" novelty="None" advantage="None">As can be anticipated for reactions having similar threshold energies, the increasing complexity of the radical from HOCH<SB>2</SB>O˙ to CH<SB>3</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>O˙ results in a decrease of the broadening of the falloff.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to compare, the predicted pressure dependence of the β-C–H dissociation rate constants <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB>, <IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB> and <IT>k</IT><SB>3</SB>, the values of the high-pressure limiting rate constant <IT>k</IT><SB>∞</SB> and the ratio <IT>Γ</IT> = <IT>k</IT><SB>760</SB>/<IT>k</IT><SB>∞</SB> (<IT>k</IT><SB>∞</SB> ≡ <IT>k</IT><SB>TST</SB> obtained using adjusted <IT>E</IT><SB>0</SB>) are listed in Table 3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res34" novelty="None" advantage="None">The same calculation was performed for upper tropospheric conditions (220 K and 150 Torr).</annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res35" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is interesting to point out that, for reactions (1) and (2) at 298 K and 760 Torr total pressure, the rate constant is still strongly pressure dependent (<IT>Γ</IT> = 0.05 and 0.35, respectively).</annotationART></s> <s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res36" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is in good agreement with measurements of Jenkin <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF>. for reaction (2).</annotationART></s> <s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res37" novelty="None" advantage="None">The same situation is observed at 150 Torr and 220 K (upper tropospheric conditions).</annotationART></s> <s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res38" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast, reactions (3) and (4) are near the high pressure limit (<IT>Γ</IT> = 0.85 and 0.90, respectively).</annotationART></s> <s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res39" novelty="None" advantage="None">It appears from falloff curves (Fig. 5) that the extrapolated values at 760 Torr of the rate constants of reactions (1) and (2) are about one order of magnitude higher than that of reactions (3) and (4).</annotationART></s></P><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>Uncertainties on <IT>E</IT><SB>0</SB> values</HEADER><P><s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res40" novelty="None" advantage="None">From the calculated falloff of the rate constant <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB> (HOCH<SB>2</SB>O˙), it is deduced that the experimental value<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF> of the rate constant, obtained at 25 Torr, is in the low-pressure part of the falloff with <IT>k</IT><SB>25</SB>/<IT>k</IT><SB>∞</SB> ≈ 10<SP>−3</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res41" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore errors on <IT>β</IT><SB>c</SB> and <IT>Z</IT><SB>LJ</SB> are directly propagated on the calculated value of the rate constant and thus, on the deduced value of <IT>E</IT><SB>0</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None">For example, doubling the formaldehyde collisional efficiency (<IT>β</IT><SB>c</SB> = 0.4 rather than 0.2) leads to a new fitted <IT>E</IT><SB>0</SB> value of 10.1 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> (instead of 9.6 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res42" novelty="None" advantage="None">Similarly, by inspection of Fig. 5, it is clear that the <IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB> experimental value of Jenkin <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF>. for CH<SB>3</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>O˙ radical, obtained at 25 Torr, is in the low-pressure part of the falloff.</annotationART></s> <s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met16" novelty="Old" advantage="None">This experimental value is obtained relatively to the rate constant of the reaction with O<SB>2</SB>, with [O<SB>2</SB>] in the range (1–6) × 10<SP>17</SP> molecule cm<SP>−3</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res43" novelty="None" advantage="None">This results in large uncertainty on the experimental value of the dissociation rate constant of (1–6) × 10<SP>3</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res44" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, we consider that the calculated values of <IT>E</IT><SB>0</SB>, obtained by fitting of our statistical calculations to experimental results, have an uncertainty of ±1 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res45" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is worth noting that, for reaction (2), our RRKM calculated falloff fitted to the experimental value of rate constant at 25 Torr, has predicted the kinetic behaviour which is experimentally observed at 760 Torr<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF> for this reaction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac29" novelty="None" advantage="None">In fact, it is indicated in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">ref. 1</REF> that the rate constant is pressure dependent and that competition with the O<SB>2</SB> reaction exists at 760 Torr, [O<SB>2</SB>] &gt; 10<SP>18</SP> molecule cm<SP>−3</SP>, which corresponds to rate constants &gt;1 × 10<SP>4</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res46" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is in good agreement with our calculated value of 5.2 × 10<SP>4</SP> s<SP>−1</SP> at 760 Torr.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res47" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition to β-C–H bond scission (3) our calculations show that the 1,6-isomerisation (4) through a seven-membered transition state is a possible competing loss process for the CH<SB>3</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>O˙ radical.</annotationART></s> <s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" advantage="None">For these two competitive unimolecular (reactions (3) and (4)), <IT>ab initio</IT> calculations predict dissociation barrier heights of the same order of magnitude (at the G2 and CCSD(T) levels of theory, Table 2).</annotationART></s> <s sid="143"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Similar values are returned by RRKM kinetic analysis of experimental results (in Table 3).</annotationART></s> <s sid="144"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, our <IT>ab initio</IT> calculations give theoretical support to the Wallington <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">2</REF>. assumption suggesting that a competing isomerisation is likely to occur.</annotationART></s> <s sid="145"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, further calculations are needed (for example CASPT2 computations) to confirm this.</annotationART></s> <s sid="146"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res48" novelty="None" advantage="None">Actually, due to the existence of spin contamination (see computational details), the computed β-C–H activation energy for reaction (3) is less reliable than the isomerisation one.</annotationART></s> <s sid="147"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res49" novelty="None" advantage="None">The predicted relatively low barrier height ≈11 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> for this isomerisation seems to arise from the presence of an oxygen atom next to the CH<SB>3</SB> group.</annotationART></s> <s sid="148"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac30" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is to link to the observation of Dibble <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF>. who studied the 1,5 H-shift isomerisation reactions of CH<SB>3</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>CH<SB>2</SB>O˙ and CH<SB>3</SB>CH<SB>2</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>O˙ radicals.</annotationART></s> <s sid="149"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac31" novelty="None" advantage="None">They observed that the activation barrier for isomerisation is lower by about 10 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> when the oxygen is adjacent to the methyl group from which abstraction occurs than when it is closer to the alkoxy radical center.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="150"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res50" novelty="None" advantage="None">Estimation can be made of the competition between the β-C–H scission and the reaction with oxygen (the isomerisation process (4) has also been considered for CH<SB>3</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>O˙ radical).</annotationART></s> <s sid="151"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res50" novelty="None" advantage="None">Assuming k<SB>O<SB>2</SB></SB> ≈ 10<SP>−14</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP> (see <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">ref. 4</REF>), about 45% of HOCH<SB>2</SB>O˙, 50% of CH<SB>3</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>O˙ and 7% of CH<SB>3</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>O˙ dissociate, and 9% of CH<SB>3</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>O˙ undergo isomerisation under conditions of the lower troposphere (760 Torr, 298 K and 20% O<SB>2</SB>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="152"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res51" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the upper troposphere (150 Torr, 220 K and 20% O<SB>2</SB>), due to the barrier heights and the falloff effect of the unimolecular reactions, dissociations and isomerisation are negligible compared to reaction with oxygen.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="153"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res52" novelty="None" advantage="None">Pressure and temperature dependencies of the β-C–H scission rate constant can be presented using the conventional Troe's equation:<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF> in order to provide a quick and convenient way of calculating the pressure dependence of the rate constant values in the range (220 K–300 K).</annotationART></s> <s sid="154"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res53" novelty="None" advantage="None">The three parameters <IT>k</IT><SB>0</SB>, <IT>k</IT><SB>∞</SB> and <IT>F</IT><SB>c</SB> have been derived from the non-linear fitting of the above equation to the presented RRKM results at two temperatures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="155"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res54" novelty="None" advantage="None">The resulting expressions of <IT>k</IT><SB>0</SB>(<IT>T</IT>), <IT>k</IT><SB>∞</SB>(<IT>T</IT>) and <IT>F</IT><SB>c</SB>(<IT>T</IT>) are given in Table 4, along with those corresponding to <IT>F</IT><SB>c</SB> = 0.6.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="IV.">Conclusion</HEADER><P><s sid="156"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac32" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the last few decades, there have been indications from experimental studies that rapid H-atom elimination might be a general decomposition mechanism for alkoxy radicals bearing an oxygen functionality.</annotationART></s> <s sid="157"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">A theoretical study on the fate of the three following alkoxy radicals: HOCH<SB>2</SB>O˙, CH<SB>3</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>O˙ and CH<SB>3</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>O˙ is presented.</annotationART></s> <s sid="158"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The presence of an ether functional group in alkoxy radicals appears to lower the β-C–H bond scission activation energy (by about 10 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="159"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">From our RRKM analysis based on <IT>ab initio</IT> data, under tropospheric conditions, the rate constants <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB> and <IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB> for the two first radicals are about one order of magnitude higher than for the largest radical.</annotationART></s> <s sid="160"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, it turns out that in the tropospheric pressure range, <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB> and <IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB> are strongly pressure dependent while <IT>k</IT><SB>3</SB> is near the high-pressure limit.</annotationART></s> <s sid="161"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results of the present investigation show that the competition between the β-C–H bond scission and reaction with O<SB>2</SB>, can only be significant under conditions of the lower troposphere.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="162"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res55" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition to β-C–H bond scission and reaction with O<SB>2</SB>, our calculations show that possible competing loss process for CH<SB>3</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>OCH<SB>2</SB>O˙ radical is the 1,6-isomerisation, through a seven-membered transition state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="163"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res56" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is a very unusual case, since typically only the 1,5 isomerisation is considered.</annotationART></s> <s sid="164"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Such a behaviour may be expected for larger oxygenated alkoxy radicals.</annotationART></s> <s sid="165"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">This may be interesting for atmospheric modelling since isomerisation leads to products different from those generated by the β-C–H bond scission and reaction with O<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
