<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b315089e" hasDoc="yes" version="1168" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Theoretical studies of the unimolecular and bimolecular tautomerization of cytosine<XREF TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" /></annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Computational investigations of the unimolecular and bimolecular tautomerization of isolated and dimeric cytosine have been performed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Stationary and transition states of the isolated and dimeric cytosine systems were characterized at the MP2(full)/6-311+G(2d,2p)//MP2(full)/6-31G* and MP2(full)/6-311+G(2d,2p)//B3LYP/6-31G* levels of theory, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the solid phase, cytosine exists in a single tautomeric state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast, experiments conducted in the gas phase find that cytosine exists as a mixture of several tautomeric forms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The energy barriers for unimolecular tautomerization of the tautomeric form found in solids to those observed in the gas phase are high and vary between 142.2 and 169.9 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The formation of dimers with dual hydrogen bonding interactions results in a significant lowering of the barriers to tautomerization, thus facilitating tautomerization during the sublimation process.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Based on such bimolecular tautomerization mechanisms, we believe that the relative populations of the cytosine tautomers produced in the gas phase <IT>via</IT> thermal vaporization cannot be accurately predicted without considering intermolecular hydrogen bonding interactions present in the condensed phase.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Nucleic acid bases are constituents of DNA and RNA and play important roles in the genetic code transformation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">They occur as one predominant isomer, but can exist in other minor tautomeric forms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The presence of these minor tautomers in nucleic acids can lead to base-pair mismatches and result in gene mutation.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2">1,2</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Previous theoretical studies<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3 cit4 cit5 cit6 cit7 cit8 cit9 cit10 cit11 cit12 cit13 cit14 cit15 cit16 cit17">3–17</REF> have examined a variety of the possible tautomers of isolated cytosine and found that six lie relatively low in energy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Several of these six tautomers have been calculated to be of very similar stability such that the relative energy ordering of these tautomers is sensitive to the theoretical approach employed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">In the present work, we examine these six most stable tautomers of cytosine as shown in Fig. 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The keto–amino form (C<SB>1</SB>) is the “canonical” structure of cytosine found in DNA and RNA.</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Indeed, X-ray diffraction (XRD) studies find that this is the only tautomeric form that occurs in cytosine crystals.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18 cit19">18,19</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Similarly, XRD<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19">19</REF> and neutron diffraction<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF> studies find that C<SB>1</SB> is the only form observed in cytosine monohydrate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, experimental<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21 cit22">21,22</REF> and theoretical<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17 cit23">17,23</REF> studies indicate that cytosine adopts predominantly the C<SB>1</SB> form in aqueous solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast, resonance enhanced multiphoton ionization (REMPI) experiments<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF> find that both keto–amino (C<SB>1</SB>) and enol–amino (C<SB>2</SB> and possibly C<SB>3</SB>) tautomers coexist in the gas phase.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">A mixture of C<SB>1</SB> and C<SB>2</SB> (and possibly C<SB>3</SB>) as well as the keto–imino (C<SB>4</SB>) tautomers have also been observed in IR matrix isolation studies.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25">25</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Similarly, molecular beam microwave (MW) spectroscopy studies indicate that the C<SB>1</SB>, C<SB>2</SB>, and C<SB>4</SB> tautomers coexist in the gas phase.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26">26</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The IR matrix isolation and MW spectroscopy studies discussed above both made use of solid cytosine, which is commercially available only as the C<SB>1</SB> tautomer, and heated it to sublimation to produce the gas phase mixture of tautomers observed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">While in the REMPI experiments,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF> the solid cytosine sample was desorbed into the gas phase by laser ablation jet-cooling.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">In an attempt to understand the experimental observation of a mixture of cytosine tautomers in the gas phase, Russo <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF>. calculated the relative stabilities of the C<SB>1</SB>, C<SB>2</SB>, C<SB>3</SB>, and C<SB>4</SB> tautomers and the barriers for unimolecular tautomerization processes that allow interconversion of these species.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Their studies indicate that the barriers for the C<SB>1</SB> → C<SB>2</SB> and C<SB>1</SB> → C<SB>4</SB> unimolecular tautomerization processes (156.5 and 181.6 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>, respectively) are too large to be overcome by thermal vaporization.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast, the C<SB>2</SB> → C<SB>3</SB> unimolecular tautomerization requires significantly less energy, 38.9 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>, suggesting that interconversion of these tautomers may occur <IT>via</IT> thermal vaporization.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, direct conversion of C<SB>1</SB> to C<SB>3</SB> is expected to require significantly greater energy than the two step process, C<SB>1</SB> → C<SB>2</SB> → C<SB>3</SB>, and therefore is not likely to occur.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, these results suggest that formation of C<SB>3</SB> from C<SB>1</SB><IT>via</IT> thermal vaporization of cytosine is also not possible.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the REMPI studies<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF> the authors suggest that tautomerization of C<SB>1</SB> → C<SB>2</SB> (and possibly C<SB>3</SB>) takes place in the desorption step or be can induced by multiple collisions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Because of the energetic nature of laser ablation this may be possible, but these conclusions do not explain the observation of the tautomeric mixture observed in the MW and IR matrix isolation studies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to reconcile these findings, it is clear that alternative mechanisms by which C<SB>1</SB> can be converted to C<SB>2</SB> and C<SB>4</SB> must exist that are energetically accessible <IT>via</IT> thermal vaporization.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our interest in resolving this apparent discrepancy arose from studies we have been performing that examine the threshold collision-induced dissociation (TCID) behavior of complexes of cytosine to a variety of metal ions in order to extract the corresponding metal ion binding affinities.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our initial results indicated that theory seriously over estimated the binding affinities of cytosine.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">However, this conclusion was based upon the assumption that the canonical form of cytosine, C<SB>1</SB>, was the form accessed upon thermal vaporization.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although C<SB>1</SB> may be formed upon thermal vaporization, the poor agreement between theory and experiment in our studies, as well as the previous experimental studies of cytosine, suggests that it is not the only tautomer accessed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac20" novelty="None" advantage="None">It should be noted that the TCID technique is a threshold technique and therefore the thermochemistry derived from such studies is only sensitive to the lowest energy dissociation pathway available.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac21" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, the measured thresholds can only provide the metal ion binding affinity of the tautomeric form present in the mixture generated upon thermal vaporization that has the lowest binding affinity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">And thus for appropriate interpretation of our TCID results it is necessary that we determine which tautomeric forms of cytosine are accessed in the thermal vaporization process.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is possible that tautomerization could also occur during complex formation or collision-induced dissociation of the metal ion–cytosine complexes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">However these issues will not be dealt with here, but instead will be discussed in a later paper that deals with these experimental measurements.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None">In the present work, we re-examine the unimolecular tautomerization processes studied by Russo <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF>. and extend these studies to include two additional tautomers, C<SB>5</SB> and C<SB>6</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="New" advantage="None">In addition, we also examine three bimolecular tautomerization processes of dimeric cytosine as an alternative means by which the C<SB>2</SB> and C<SB>4</SB> tautomers might be formed from solid cytosine, C<SB>1</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">This paper is, to our knowledge, the first theoretical work to investigate bimolecular tautomerization processes of dimeric cytosine thus providing an alternative mechanism that might explain how the tautomerization energy barriers might be overcome by thermal vaporization.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac22" novelty="None" advantage="None">It should be noted that three of the six low-energy tautomers of isolated cytosine, C<SB>2</SB>, C<SB>3</SB>, and C<SB>6</SB>, are not accessible in DNA and RNA because the ribose would not migrate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac23" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, the bimolecular tautomerization of cytosine dimers is probably also not accessible in DNA and RNA because cytosine is base paired with guanine, not itself.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa3" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, if the results of studies of isolated cytosine and other nucleobases are to be put into appropriate biological context and act as models to provide insight into tautomerization processes that may occur in DNA and RNA, then a complete and accurate understanding of all tautomeric forms and mechanisms by which they may be accessed is necessary.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac24" novelty="None" advantage="None">For example, the canonical form of cytosine present in nucleic acids, C<SB>1</SB>, might be converted to C<SB>4</SB><IT>via</IT> an analogous double proton transfer mechanism in the C:G base pair, where the N1 H atom of guanine is transferred to N3 of cytosine, while an amino H atom of cytosine is transferred to the carbonyl oxygen atom of guanine.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus the bimolecular double proton transfer mechanisms examined here might provide insight into mutation of DNA resulting from tautomerization of cytosine or other bases during replication.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Computational details</HEADER><P><s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">To obtain structures and energetics for the isolated cytosine tautomers and the transition states (TSs) for unimolecular tautomerization (<IT>i.e.</IT> interconversion <IT>via</IT> intramolecular proton transfer), <IT>ab initio</IT> theory calculations were performed using Gaussian .98<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27">27</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Geometry optimizations and vibrational analyses were performed at the MP2(full)/6-31G* level.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">When used to calculate zero point, thermal, and free energy corrections, the MP2(full)/6-31G* vibrational frequencies are scaled by a factor of 0..9646<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28">28</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The optimized geometries, rotational constants, and scaled vibrational frequencies thus obtained for each tautomer and unimolecular transition state examined are available as ESI and are listed in Tables S1 through S4.<SUP TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" /></annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Single point energy calculations were performed at the MP2(full)/6-311+G(2d,2p) level using the MP2(full)/6-31G* optimized geometries.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="None" advantage="None">To obtain accurate energetics, zero point energy corrections were included.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj5" novelty="New" advantage="None">As a probe of alternative mechanisms for tautomerization during sublimation, transition states for bimolecular tautomerization of cytosine dimers (<IT>i.e.</IT>, interconversion <IT>via</IT> intermolecular double proton transfer) were studied.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="Old" advantage="No">With the computational resources available, we were unable to perform these calculations at the same level of theory employed for the monomers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Therefore, geometry optimizations and vibrational analyses were performed at the B3LYP/6-31G* level of theory.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="Old" advantage="None">When used to calculate zero point, and thermal and free energy corrections the B3LYP/6-31G* vibrational frequencies are scaled by a factor of 0..9804<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28">28</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The optimized geometries, rotational constants, and scaled vibrational frequencies determined for each cytosine dimer and bimolecular transition state are available as ESI and are given in Tables S5 through S8.<SUP TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" /></annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Single point energy calculations were carried out at the MP2(full)/6-311+G(2d,2p) level using the B3LYP/6-31G* optimized geometries.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="Old" advantage="None">To obtain accurate energetics, zero point energy and basis set superposition error (BSSE) corrections were included in the full counterpoise approximation<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29 cit30">29,30</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Results and discussion</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Isolated cytosine tautomers</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>Relative stabilities</HEADER><P><s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac25" novelty="None" advantage="None">Previous theoretical studies<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9 cit10 cit12 cit13 cit14">9,10,12–14</REF> are in general agreement that of all of the possible tautomeric forms of cytosine, there are six low-energy tautomers C<SB>1</SB>, C<SB>2</SB>, C<SB>3</SB>, C<SB>4</SB>, C<SB>5</SB>, and C<SB>6</SB> (Fig. 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In agreement with most of these studies, the calculations performed here find that C<SB>2</SB> is the most stable tautomer in the gas phase.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">C<SB>3</SB>, the tautomer derived from C<SB>2</SB><IT>via</IT> 180° rotation of the hydroxy group about the C2–O bond is found to be the next most stable tautomer, lying only 3.1 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> higher in energy than C<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac26" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although the absolute differences in the stabilities of the C<SB>2</SB> and C<SB>3</SB> tautomers differ somewhat depending upon the level of theory employed, all previous studies also find that C<SB>2</SB> is more stable than C<SB>3</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Because the chemical bonding in C<SB>2</SB> and C<SB>3</SB> is the same, <IT>i.e.</IT>, C<SB>2</SB> and C<SB>3</SB> are simply rotamers of each other, the relative stabilities of these tautomers are easily understood based upon their dipole moments 3.72 and 5.11 D, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The C<SB>1</SB> tautomer, the most stable and only tautomer observed in solid cytosine, is found to be the next most stable gas phase tautomer, lying 5.9 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> higher in energy than C<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The dipole moment of the C<SB>1</SB> tautomer, 7.20 D, is larger than those of C<SB>2</SB> and C<SB>3</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although the chemical bonding of C<SB>1</SB> differs somewhat compared to C<SB>2</SB> and C<SB>3</SB>, a simple correlation between the relative stabilities of these tautomers and their dipole moments still exists.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac27" novelty="None" advantage="None">It should be noted that although there is general agreement that C<SB>2</SB> is the most stable tautomeric form of cytosine in the gas phase, density functional theory calculations tend to over estimate the stability of the C<SB>1</SB> tautomer and actually find it to be more stable than C<SB>2</SB> when certain basis sets are employed.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13 cit16">13,16</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The C<SB>4</SB> tautomer is found to be the next most stable cytosine tautomer, lying 13.3 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> higher in energy than the C<SB>2</SB> tautomer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The dipole moment of C<SB>4</SB> is calculated to be 5.46 D. This suggests that if the relative stabilities of the cytosine tautomers could be predicted based solely upon their dipole moments as the above correlation for the C<SB>1</SB>, C<SB>2</SB>, and C<SB>3</SB> tautomers suggests, then C<SB>4</SB> would be expected to be more stable than C<SB>1</SB>, but less stable than C<SB>2</SB> and C<SB>3</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac28" novelty="None" advantage="None">Indeed, Fogarasi<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF> argues that some high level theoretical calculations find that the C<SB>1</SB> and C<SB>4</SB> tautomers are of very nearly identical stability, but was unable to rationalize this claim based upon comparison to the estimated populations of these tautomers observed in the IR matrix isolation and molecular beam MW studies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The lesser stability of the C<SB>4</SB> tautomer calculated here and in other studies as well as the lower population of this tautomer observed in the experimental studies suggests that the imino functionality is less favorable than the amino functionality.</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The C<SB>5</SB> tautomer is found to be the next most stable cytosine tautomer, lying 20.6 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> higher in energy than the C<SB>2</SB> tautomer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The C<SB>5</SB> tautomer can be derived from C<SB>4</SB><IT>via</IT> 180° rotation of the imino hydrogen atom about the C4N bond.</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">However in order for this rotation to occur, the π bond must be broken and thus the interconversion of C<SB>4</SB> and C<SB>5</SB> should require more energy than the interconversion of C<SB>2</SB> and C<SB>3</SB> as is found here and will be discussed later.</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The dipole moment of C<SB>5</SB>, 2.78 D, is smaller than that of C<SB>4</SB> and in fact is the smallest of all of the tautomeric forms examined here.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">This indicates that the relative stabilities of the tautomers cannot be explained based simply upon their dipole moments and that other factors must be examined.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac29" novelty="None" advantage="None">All previous theoretical studies agree than C<SB>5</SB> is less stable than C<SB>4</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The decreased stability of C<SB>5</SB> compared to C<SB>4</SB> arises from steric repulsion between the hydrogen atom bound to N3 and the imino hydrogen atom, which causes the N3–C4–NH bond angle to increase by ∼8° compared to that observed for the other tautomers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">C<SB>6</SB> is calculated to be the least stable of the cytosine tautomers examined here, lying 37.4 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> higher in energy than C<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac30" novelty="None" advantage="None">Most previous theoretical studies concur that C<SB>6</SB> is the least stable of these six tautomeric forms of cytosine.</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The calculated dipole moment of C<SB>6</SB> is 8.88 D, the largest of all six tautomers examined here.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The very large dipole moment and the steric repulsion between the hydrogen atom bound to N3 and the adjacent amino hydrogen atom results in decreased stability of this tautomer and leads to an ∼2° decrease in the H–N–H angle.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">In summary, the calculations performed here find that the relative energies of the six tautomers examined follow the order C<SB>2</SB> &lt; C<SB>3</SB> &lt; C<SB>1</SB> &lt; C<SB>4</SB> &lt; C<SB>5</SB> &lt; C<SB>6</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our results as well as those from earlier theoretical work<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9 cit12 cit13">9,12,13</REF> performed at fairly high levels of theory that support this trend are summarized in Table 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although absolute consistency in these trends is not found in every theoretical study performed, the calculations or arguments that suggest that C<SB>1</SB> and C<SB>4</SB> are more stable have not been adequately supported by either the theoretical or experimental studies.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The above discussion of relative stabilities of the cytosine tautomers is based upon 0 K energetics.</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Because experimental studies are carried out at elevated temperatures, typically 298 K, but much higher temperatures in the cytosine studies discussed above, ∼490 K for the IR matrix isolation experiments<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25">25</REF> and ∼570 K for the molecular beam MW experiments,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26">26</REF> it is more appropriate to examine the relative stabilities of the tautomers at these temperatures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met14" novelty="Old" advantage="None">To ascertain the relative stabilities of these tautomers at the appropriate experimental temperatures, we also calculated thermal energy corrections at 298, 490, and 570 K. The relative free energies of the cytosine tautomers at these temperatures are also summarized in Table 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">As expected, the absolute differences in stability decrease with increasing temperature, but the thermal corrections are not large enough to result in a change in the stability order over this range of temperatures.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>Relative populations</HEADER><P><s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac31" novelty="None" advantage="None">As discussed above, the matrix isolation IR study of cytosine reported the observation of a mixture of C<SB>1</SB>, C<SB>2</SB> and C<SB>4</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac32" novelty="None" advantage="None">Based upon comparison between the measured IR intensities and those predicted from <IT>ab initio</IT> calculations, the authors estimated the population ratios of the C<SB>1</SB>, C<SB>2</SB>, and C<SB>4</SB> tautomers present in their experiments as 0.4–0.5∶1.0∶0.1–0.25, respectively.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25">25</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac33" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rotamers of C<SB>2</SB> and C<SB>4</SB> (<IT>i.e.</IT>, C<SB>3</SB> and C<SB>5</SB>) were not reported, with no explanation provided to explain their absence.</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">By examining the vibrational frequencies of C<SB>2</SB> and C<SB>3</SB>, and those of C<SB>4</SB> and C<SB>5</SB> (Table S2<SUP TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" />), it can be seen that they are virtually identical.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, these rotamers cannot really be distinguished by their IR spectra.</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">The molecular beam MW spectroscopy study of cytosine also reported the observation of a mixture of C<SB>1</SB>, C<SB>2</SB> and C<SB>4</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac34" novelty="None" advantage="None">Based upon comparison between the measured MW intensities and those predicted from <IT>ab initio</IT> calculations and the dipole moment components, the authors estimated the population ratios of the C<SB>1</SB>, C<SB>2</SB>, and C<SB>4</SB> tautomers present in their experiments as 1.0∶1.0∶0.25, respectively.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26">26</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac35" novelty="None" advantage="None">The C<SB>3</SB>, C<SB>5</SB> and C<SB>6</SB> tautomers were not observed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" advantage="None">The identification of the tautomers based solely on their rotational constants (Table S2<SUP TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" />) alone could not absolutely discount the absence of C<SB>3</SB> and C<SB>5</SB>, however, the differences in the magnitude and direction of the dipole moments of the rotamers (Fig. 1) makes it possible to distinguish them in their MW spectra and thus confirms the absence of these species in the MW experiments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None">Because the cytosine vapor in both the matrix isolation IR and molecular beam MW studies was generated by thermal vaporization, albeit at somewhat different temperatures, it can be concluded that C<SB>3</SB> and C<SB>5</SB> were also not generated in the matrix isolation IR studies.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None">Using the relative stabilities of the cytosine tautomers determined from our calculations at 298, 490, and 570 K, we estimated the Maxwell–Boltzmann populations of these species based solely on their relative stabilities.</annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">These populations are summarized in Table 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Also listed in Table 2 are the estimated populations of the cytosine tautomers derived from Fogarasi's coupled cluster electron correlation study and those estimated from the matrix isolation IR and molecular beam MW experiments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res29" novelty="None" advantage="None">As can be seen in Table 2, our estimated relative populations for the C<SB>1</SB>, C<SB>2</SB>, and C<SB>4</SB> tautomers are in good agreement with those measured experimentally.</annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res30" novelty="None" advantage="None">Good agreement is also found between experiment and Fogarasi's estimated populations for the C<SB>1</SB> and C<SB>2</SB> tautomers, but his results tend to overestimate the relative population of the C<SB>4</SB> tautomer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">This suggests that the coupled cluster results tend to overestimate the stability of the C<SB>4</SB> tautomer as discussed above.</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast, a major discrepancy between theory and experiment exists for the C<SB>3</SB> tautomer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res32" novelty="None" advantage="None">Based solely on the relative stabilities of the tautomers, both our results and those of Fogarasi predict that C<SB>3</SB> should have an appreciable population in the gas phase; whereas experiments do not find any direct evidence that C<SB>3</SB> coexists with C<SB>1</SB>, C<SB>2</SB> and C<SB>4</SB> in gas phase mixture of tautomers generated by thermal vaporization of cytosine.</annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res33" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, it is clear that population estimates based solely upon the relative stabilities of the isolated cytosine tautomers are not reliable.</annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the following sections we will examine several possible mechanisms by which tautomerization of cytosine may occur and the influence of these mechanisms on the relative populations of the various tautomers generated by thermal vaporization.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Unimolecular tautomerization of cytosine</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>Barrier heights</HEADER><P><s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac36" novelty="None" advantage="None">In earlier work Russo <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF>. investigated the relative stabilities and unimolecular tautomerization processes that allow interconversion of the four most stable tautomers of cytosine: C<SB>1</SB>, C<SB>2</SB>, C<SB>3</SB>, and C<SB>4</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac37" novelty="None" advantage="None">Their calculations were carried out at the B3LYP/6-311+G(2df,2p) level of theory.</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac38" novelty="None" advantage="None">As mentioned earlier, density functional theory tends to overestimate the stability of the C<SB>1</SB> tautomer, and at the level of theory employed in their work the relative stabilities of these tautomers follow the order of C<SB>1</SB> &lt; C<SB>2</SB> &lt; C<SB>3</SB> &lt; C<SB>4</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac39" novelty="None" advantage="None">Their studies also found that the barriers for the C<SB>1</SB> ↔ C<SB>2</SB> and C<SB>1</SB> ↔ C<SB>4</SB> unimolecular tautomerization processes are too large to be overcome by thermal vaporization.</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac39" novelty="None" advantage="None">The C<SB>2</SB> ↔ C<SB>3</SB> unimolecular tautomerization was found to require significantly less energy such that it was concluded that thermal vaporization may provide enough energy to allow interconversion of these tautomers, but this process is only relevant if C<SB>1</SB> can first undergo tautomerization to C<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac40" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, they concluded that because the energy barriers were so large the possibility of acquiring of C<SB>2</SB>, C<SB>3</SB> and C<SB>4</SB> from heating C<SB>1</SB> in the gas phase is very small.</annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj6" novelty="New" advantage="None">Because density functional theory does not determine the correct relative stabilities of these tautomers, we reinvestigated these tautomerization processes and extended our studies to include the unimolecular tautomerization processes involving C<SB>5</SB> and C<SB>6</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">There are five direct unimolecular tautomerization processes that allow interconversion of the six tautomers of cytosine <IT>via</IT> simple proton transfer, C<SB>5</SB> ↔ C<SB>4</SB> ↔ C<SB>1</SB> ↔ C<SB>2</SB> ↔ C<SB>3</SB> ↔ C<SB>6</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">These unimolecular tautomerization processes can be divided into three groups:.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>1–2 Proton transfer</HEADER><P><s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Three of the unimolecular tautomerization pathways involve a 1–2 proton transfer between adjacent atoms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The C<SB>1</SB> ↔ C<SB>2</SB> and C<SB>3</SB> ↔ C<SB>6</SB> transformations correspond to simple keto–enol tautomerization, while C<SB>4</SB> ↔ C<SB>1</SB> interconversion corresponds to an amino–imino tautomerization.</annotationART></s> <s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">During these unimolecular tautomerization processes, a σ-bond is broken and a new σ-bond is formed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res34" novelty="None" advantage="None">As a result, these processes exhibit very large activation energy barriers, C<SB>1</SB> → C<SB>2</SB> (142.2 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>), C<SB>1</SB> → C<SB>4</SB> (169.1 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>), and C<SB>3</SB> → C<SB>6</SB> (158.9 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>).</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER><IT>cis</IT>–<IT>trans</IT> Isomerization</HEADER><P><s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The C<SB>4</SB> ↔ C<SB>5</SB> unimolecular tautomerization corresponds to a <IT>cis</IT>–<IT>trans</IT> isomerization.</annotationART></s> <s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">During this unimolecular tautomerization process, the hydrogen atom remains bonded to the imino nitrogen atom, but the imino π bond is broken and reformed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res35" novelty="None" advantage="None">Because π bonds are weaker than σ bonds the activation energy barrier for this process is somewhat smaller than for the 1–2 proton transfer tautomerization processes, C<SB>4</SB> → C<SB>5</SB> (94.3 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>).</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>σ-Bond rotation</HEADER><P><s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The C<SB>2</SB> ↔ C<SB>3</SB> unimolecular tautomerization corresponds to 180° rotation about the C2–OH σ bond.</annotationART></s> <s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res36" novelty="None" advantage="None">This conversion does not require bond breakage and thus exhibits a much lower energy barrier, C<SB>2</SB> → C<SB>3</SB> (35.2 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The relative energies of the cytosine tautomers and the transition states for unimolecular tautomerization at 0 K determined here are summarized in Table 3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac41" novelty="None" advantage="None">Also listed in Table 3 are the results of Russo <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 2 shows the potential energy landscape for the unimolecular tautomerization of the isolated tautomers of cytosine at 0 K determined here.</annotationART></s> <s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res37" novelty="None" advantage="None">Overall, our results are in qualitative agreement with those of Russo <IT>et al.</IT>, the primary differences being that we find a different stability order for the four lowest energy tautomers and the barriers we calculate for the C<SB>1</SB> ↔ C<SB>2</SB> and C<SB>1</SB> ↔ C<SB>4</SB> transformations are ∼8–18 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> lower.</annotationART></s> <s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res38" novelty="None" advantage="None">Based upon the 0 K energetics, Russo <IT>et al.</IT> concluded that the unimolecular tautomerization of C<SB>1</SB> to generate the mixture of tautomers observed in the matrix isolation IR and molecular beam MW experiments (C<SB>1</SB>, C<SB>2</SB>, and C<SB>4</SB>) cannot occur in the gas phase by heating solid cytosine under its decomposition temperature, ∼600 K. To confirm this conclusion, we also calculated the thermal and free energy corrections for the tautomers and their unimolecular transition states at 298, 490, and 570 K. As the temperature is increased from 0 to 298 K, the unimolecular tautomerization barriers decrease for all processes, and specifically by 5.9 and 6.8 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> for the C<SB>1</SB> → C<SB>2</SB> and C<SB>1</SB> → C<SB>4</SB> transformations, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res39" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, as the temperature is increased beyond 298 K, to 490 and 570 K, the barriers change very little and actually increase.</annotationART></s> <s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res40" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, our conclusions remain the same as those of Russo <IT>et al.</IT>; thermal vaporization of cytosine below its decomposition temperature does not provide sufficient energy to overcome the unimolecular tautomerization barriers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res41" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is worth noting that the unimolecular tautomerization energy barriers can be overcome given sufficient energy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac42" novelty="None" advantage="None">Szczesniak <IT>et al.</IT> observed the C<SB>1</SB> → C<SB>2</SB> transformation in isolated cytosine upon absorption of UV radiation at 220 nm (543.7 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25">25</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac43" novelty="None" advantage="None">Absorption of a single phonon at 220 nm provides 543.7 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>, more than enough energy to overcome the calculated unimolecular tautomerization barrier.</annotationART></s> <s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res42" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus it is clear that another mechanism by which C<SB>1</SB> can be converted to C<SB>2</SB> and C<SB>4</SB> under thermal vaporization conditions must exist.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>Tunneling effects on the unimolecular tautomerization rates</HEADER><P><s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Reactions involving light species such as H<SP>+</SP> or H, (<IT>e.g.</IT>, the tautomerization processes examined here) can experience enhanced rates as a result of tunneling processes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="143"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac44" novelty="None" advantage="None">Tunneling can easily increase the rate constant by a factor of 3 or more.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit31">31</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="144"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Using the simplest tunneling correction of the Wigner transformation coefficient<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit32 cit33 cit34 cit35">32–35</REF> given by <IT>K</IT>(<IT>T</IT>) = 1 + (<IT>ħ</IT>|<IT>ω</IT><SP>‡</SP>|/<IT>kT</IT>)<SP>2</SP>/24 where <IT>ω</IT><SP>‡</SP> is the imaginary frequency of the unbound normal mode at the saddle point, <IT>ħ</IT> is Planck's constant divided by 2π, and <IT>k</IT> is the Boltzmann constant, we calculated corrections for the unimolecular tautomerization processes that convert the tautomeric form found in solids to those observed in the gas phase, C<SB>1</SB> ↔ C<SB>2</SB> (<IT>ω</IT><SP>‡</SP> = −1820 cm<SP>−1</SP>) and C<SB>1</SB> ↔ C<SB>4</SB> (<IT>ω</IT><SP>‡</SP> = −1880 cm<SP>−1</SP>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="145"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res43" novelty="None" advantage="None">The tunneling correction coefficient for these processes varies between ∼2.00 ± 0.21 assuming an experimental temperature of 500 to 600 K for thermal vaporization of cytosine.</annotationART></s> <s sid="146"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res44" novelty="None" advantage="None">The tunneling correction coefficients for the other unimolecular tautomerization processes examined here, C<SB>2</SB> ↔ C<SB>3</SB> (<IT>ω</IT><SP>‡</SP> = −496 cm<SP>−1</SP>), C<SB>3</SB> ↔ C<SB>6</SB> (<IT>ω</IT><SP>‡</SP> = −1812 cm<SP>−1</SP>), and C<SB>4</SB> ↔ C<SB>5</SB> (<IT>ω</IT><SP>‡</SP> = −1089 cm<SP>−1</SP>) are smaller and vary between 1.06 and 2.13 over the same range of temperatures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="147"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res45" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although tunneling effects result in a doubling of the rate of tautomerization, they do not explain why cytosine vapor exists as mixture of tautomers with C<SB>2</SB> the predominant form.</annotationART></s> <s sid="148"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus our conclusion remains, another mechanism by which C<SB>1</SB> can be converted to C<SB>2</SB> and C<SB>4</SB> under thermal vaporization conditions must exist.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Cytosine dimers</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>Assisted tautomerization mechanisms</HEADER><P><s sid="149"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">As discussed above, the pathways for unimolecular tautomerization of C<SB>1</SB> to produce the gas phase mixture of tautomers observed experimentally, C<SB>1</SB>, C<SB>2</SB>, and C<SB>4</SB>, require significantly more energy than provided by thermal heating under cytosine's decomposition temperature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="150"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac45" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast, proton transfer processes that take place between two species stabilized by intermolecular hydrogen bonds generally exhibit much lower energy barriers to tautomerization, particularly when dual hydrogen bonding interactions exist between the two molecules where one molecule acts as a proton donor and the other as a proton acceptor in one hydrogen bonding interaction, and each plays the reverse role in the second hydrogen bonding interaction.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit36 cit37 cit38 cit39 cit40 cit41 cit42 cit43 cit44 cit45 cit46 cit47 cit48 cit49 cit50">36–50</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="151"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac46" novelty="None" advantage="None">For example, studies of gas-phase tautomerization mechanisms based on the formation of hydrated complexes<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit51">51</REF> or dimers of the nucleic acid bases<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit52 cit53 cit54">52–54</REF> have found that proton transfer is facilitated by such dual hydrogen bonding interactions between the base and a water molecule or between the two bases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="152"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, the formation of such dimers might provide an energetically accessible pathway by which the experimentally observed mixture of cytosine tautomers might be generated upon thermal vaporization.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>Structures of the cytosine dimers</HEADER><P><s sid="153"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac47" novelty="None" advantage="None">Because thermal vaporization of solid cytosine is the means by which the cytosine vapor is generated in the experimental studies mentioned above,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25 cit26">25,26</REF> it is worthwhile to review its crystal structure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="154"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac48" novelty="None" advantage="None">X-ray diffraction studies<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF> have found that C<SB>1</SB> is the only tautomeric form present in crystalline cytosine.</annotationART></s> <s sid="155"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">A schematic representation of the crystal structure derived from this work is reproduced in Fig. 3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="156"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res46" novelty="None" advantage="None">The unit cell is orthorhombic with a layered structure in which each cytosine molecule engages in a total of six hydrogen bonding interactions with four neighboring cytosine molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="157"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res47" novelty="None" advantage="None">The N1 hydrogen atom interacts with the N3 nitrogen atom of the first neighbor, the carbonyl oxygen atom interacts with an amino hydrogen atom on the first and second neighbors, the N3 nitrogen atom interacts with the N1 hydrogen atom of the third neighbor, and the amino hydrogen atoms interact with the carbonyl oxygen atoms of the third and fourth neighbors.</annotationART></s> <s sid="158"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res48" novelty="None" advantage="None">Only one structurally distinct dimer involving dual hydrogen bonds can be formed directly from the crystal structure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="159"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">We designate this cytosine dimer as C<SB>1</SB>∶C<SB>1,α</SB> as shown in Fig. 4a.</annotationART></s> <s sid="160"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res49" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although an alternative structurally distinct dimer can also be formed, it only involves a single hydrogen bond and therefore could not act to relay hydrogen atoms between the two molecules to facilitate tautomerization.</annotationART></s> <s sid="161"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res50" novelty="None" advantage="None">During the vaporization process, thermal motion of the cytosine molecules may allow the formation other hydrogen bonding structures and thus alternative dimers may be formed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="162"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">If this occurs, two alternative C<SB>1</SB>∶C<SB>1</SB> dimers, C<SB>1</SB>∶C<SB>1,β</SB> and C<SB>1</SB>∶C<SB>1,γ</SB>, might also be generated as shown in Fig. 4b and c, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="163"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac49" novelty="None" advantage="None">Based upon previous theoretical studies,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit55 cit56">55,56</REF> these three C<SB>1</SB>∶C<SB>1</SB> dimers are the most stable of all of the possible cytosine dimers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="164"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac50" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, C<SB>1</SB>∶C<SB>1,α</SB> has been reported in gas phase by Nir <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit55">55</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="165"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res51" novelty="None" advantage="None">Other C<SB>1</SB>∶C<SB>1</SB> dimer conformations are possible, but are not likely to be of importance because they only engage in one hydrogen bonding interaction and thus proton transfer produces radical species of much lower stability and would require much greater energies for their generation.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Bimolecular tautomerization of cytosine</HEADER><P><s sid="166"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac51" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the dimer associated tautomerization studies,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit51 cit52 cit53 cit54">51–54</REF> the synchronous proton transfer between two pairs of proton donors and acceptors was obtained by computation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="167"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac52" novelty="None" advantage="None">Compared with stepwise tautomerization processes, in which one proton is transferred in each step, the simultaneous double-proton-transfer mechanism exhibits a much lower barrier.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit52">52</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="168"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res52" novelty="None" advantage="None">Tautomerization <IT>via</IT> simultaneous double proton transfer of the three C<SB>1</SB> dimers examined here leads to three new cytosine dimers: C<SB>1</SB>∶C<SB>1,α</SB> ↔ C<SB>2</SB>∶C<SB>4</SB>, C<SB>1</SB>∶C<SB>1,β</SB> ↔ C<SB>2</SB>∶C<SB>2</SB> and C<SB>1</SB>∶C<SB>1,γ</SB> ↔ C<SB>4</SB>∶C<SB>4</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="169"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res53" novelty="None" advantage="None">The corresponding transition states for these bimolecular tautomerization processes were also calculated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="170"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The relative energies of the dimers and the corresponding transition states are listed in Table 4.</annotationART></s> <s sid="171"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">To provide an overall view of the bimolecular tautomerization processes, the calculated structures and relative energies of the dimers and transition states are shown as reaction coordinate diagrams at 0 K in Fig. 4a, b, and c, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="172"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res54" novelty="None" advantage="None">In all cases, the reactant C<SB>1</SB>∶C<SB>1</SB> dimers are more stable the corresponding product dimers, C<SB>2</SB>∶C<SB>4</SB>, C<SB>2</SB>∶C<SB>2</SB>, and C<SB>4</SB>∶C<SB>4</SB>, indicating that intermolecular interactions can alter the relative stability of the cytosine tautomers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="173"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac53" novelty="None" advantage="None">Similar results were also found in the theoretical study of alternative cytosine dimers by Czerminski <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit57">57</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="174"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res55" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although this observation relates only to dimeric clusters, it likely extends to higher order clusters and may provide an explanation as to why C<SB>1</SB> is the only tautomeric form found in the solid state.</annotationART></s></P><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>Barrier heights for bimolecular tautomerization</HEADER><P><s sid="175"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Based on our calculations, the simultaneous double-proton-transfer mechanism significantly reduces the activation energy as compared to the corresponding unimolecular tautomerization processes for isolated cytosine monomers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="176"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res56" novelty="None" advantage="None">The bimolecular tautomerization of C<SB>1</SB>∶C<SB>1,α</SB> is not directly comparable to the unimolecular tautomerization processes as it generates two different tautomers, C<SB>2</SB> and C<SB>4</SB>, in a single process.</annotationART></s> <s sid="177"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res57" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the bimolecular tautomerizations of the C<SB>1</SB>∶C<SB>1,β</SB> and C<SB>1</SB>∶C<SB>1,γ</SB> generate two C<SB>2</SB> and C<SB>4</SB> molecules, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="178"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res58" novelty="None" advantage="None">The calculated barrier heights at 0 K for the C<SB>1</SB>∶C<SB>1,α</SB>, C<SB>1</SB>∶C<SB>1,β</SB>, and C<SB>1</SB>∶C<SB>1,γ</SB> bimolecular tautomerization processes are 26.6, 10.1, and 41.2 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>, respectively, compared to 142.2 and 169.1 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> for the C<SB>1</SB> → C<SB>2</SB> and C<SB>1</SB> → C<SB>4</SB> unimolecular tautomerization processes.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>Tautomerization mechanisms</HEADER><P><s sid="179"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res59" novelty="None" advantage="None">Another important feature of the bimolecular tautomerization processes is that both the dimers and bimolecular transition states are of much greater stability than the isolated monomers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="180"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac54" novelty="None" advantage="None">The heat of sublimation of cytosine, <IT>i.e.</IT>, the difference in enthalpy of solid <IT>versus</IT> gas phase cytosine, was determined to lie in the range between 147 and 176 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> at 423–483 K.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit58 cit59 cit60">58–60</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="181"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res60" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is approximately four times larger than the difference in stability of two C<SB>1</SB> isolated monomers and the three C<SB>1</SB>∶C<SB>1</SB> dimers at 0 K, and 40 to 50 times larger than their difference in stability at 490 K. Therefore, the relative stability of cytosine in various environments is temperature dependent.</annotationART></s> <s sid="182"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res61" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, it is clear that the extensive hydrogen bonding network present in solid cytosine provides additional stabilization compared to the dimer, and that the hydrogen bonding in the dimer likewise stabilizes cytosine compared to isolated molecules so long as the temperature is not so high as to provide enough internal energy to break the hydrogen bonding interactions and allow entropy to take over and vaporize the cytosine molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="183"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">This suggests that C<SB>1</SB> might be converted into other tautomeric forms during the sublimation process by the following three mechanisms:</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="184"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">(1) C<SB>1</SB> is evaporated into the gas phase as C<SB>1</SB> monomers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="185"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Two C<SB>1</SB> monomers associate in the gas phase to form one of the three types of C<SB>1</SB>∶C<SB>1</SB> dimers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="186"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">It should be noted that although the cytosine sample may be heated to 500–600 K, that the vaporized molecules may undergo cooling to near room temperature as a result of collisions with other vaporized cytosine molecules and/or bath gases present under the vaporization conditions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="187"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Because the dimer association energy is greater than the barrier to bimolecular tautomerization, these dimers may tautomerize to produce alternative cytosine dimers (C<SB>2</SB>∶C<SB>4</SB>, C<SB>2</SB>∶C<SB>2</SB>, and C<SB>4</SB>∶C<SB>4</SB>) that may dissociate to produce C<SB>2</SB> and C<SB>4</SB> monomers upon collision or absorption of heat.</annotationART></s> <s sid="188"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp10" novelty="None" advantage="None">This mechanism is particularly favorable for the conversion of C<SB>1</SB> into C<SB>2</SB>, because C<SB>2</SB> is more stable than C<SB>1</SB> in the gas phase.</annotationART></s> <s sid="189"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Because of the difficulty of evaporating cytosine solid, the concentration of C<SB>1</SB> in the gas phase is likely to be very low, and the possibility of two cytosine molecules associating into a dimer might not be very significant.</annotationART></s> <s sid="190"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp12" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, in the region very close to the heated cytosine sample, it is reasonable to believe that the density of cytosine molecules is large enough that such association of cytosine might be feasible under the experimental vaporization conditions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="191"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp12" novelty="None" advantage="None">If tautomerization were to occur <IT>via</IT> this mechanism, then the relative populations of C<SB>1</SB>, C<SB>2</SB>, and C<SB>4</SB> produced <IT>via</IT> thermal vaporization of solid cytosine would depend upon the relative gas phase stabilities of the isolated cytosine tautomers and cytosine dimers.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="192"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp13" novelty="None" advantage="None">(2) C<SB>1</SB>∶C<SB>1</SB> dimers are directly evaporated into the gas phase and may be converted into the corresponding cytosine dimers (C<SB>2</SB>∶C<SB>4</SB>, C<SB>2</SB>∶C<SB>2</SB>, and C<SB>4</SB>∶C<SB>4</SB>) <IT>via</IT> bimolecular tautomerization pathways.</annotationART></s> <s sid="193"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The mixture of C∶C dimers thus generated then dissociate into monomers upon collisions with other cytosine molecules or bath gases present, or by the absorption of heat.</annotationART></s> <s sid="194"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp15" novelty="None" advantage="None">If tautomerization were to occur <IT>via</IT> this mechanism, then the relative populations of C<SB>1</SB>, C<SB>2</SB>, and C<SB>4</SB> produced <IT>via</IT> thermal vaporization of solid cytosine would again depend upon the relative gas phase stabilities of the isolated cytosine tautomers and cytosine dimers.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="195"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp16" novelty="None" advantage="None">(3) Tautomerization <IT>via</IT> double proton transfer might occur in the solid phase resulting in a mixture of cytosine tautomers being present in the heated solid.</annotationART></s> <s sid="196"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Then as the solid absorbs enough energy to overcome the hydrogen bonding and other stabilizing interactions, the cytosine sample is evaporated into the gas phase as a mixture of the tautomers generated in the heated solid state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="197"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp18" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this case, the additional hydrogen bonding interactions with adjacent cytosine molecules not directly involved in the specific tautomerization mechanism occurring at a given sight probably provide additional stabilization that might further facilitate the tautomerization process.</annotationART></s> <s sid="198"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, it seems plausible that such a solid-state tautomerization mechanism might dominate the tautomerization processes that occur upon thermal heating of cytosine.</annotationART></s> <s sid="199"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp20" novelty="None" advantage="None">If tautomerization were to occur <IT>via</IT> this mechanism, then the relative populations of C<SB>1</SB>, C<SB>2</SB>, and C<SB>4</SB> produced <IT>via</IT> thermal vaporization of solid cytosine could not be predicted simply based upon the relative stabilities of the isolated gas phase cytosine tautomers and cytosine dimers, but that the extended intermolecular hydrogen bonding interactions would also need to be considered.</annotationART></s> <s sid="200"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp20" novelty="None" advantage="None">The bimolecular double proton-transfer tautomerization mechanism can only be regarded as an approximate model for the actual tautomerization process that might occur in the solid phase.</annotationART></s> <s sid="201"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp21" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to obtain a better description of the tautomerization processes in the solid phase and accurately predict the relative populations of the various tautomers that would be produced upon thermal vaporization, larger molecular clusters should be investigated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="202"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp22" novelty="None" advantage="None">Simulated annealing or direct dynamics simulations might also provide additional insight into this much more complicated process.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>Relative populations</HEADER><P><s sid="203"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp23" novelty="None" advantage="None">The crystal structure of cytosine suggests that only the tautomerization processes associated with the C<SB>1</SB>∶C<SB>1,α</SB> dimer, <IT>i.e.</IT>, formation of equal amounts of C<SB>2</SB> and C<SB>4</SB> in the solid state is likely to occur.</annotationART></s> <s sid="204"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp24" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the relative populations of C<SB>2</SB> and C<SB>4</SB> estimated from the matrix isolation IR and MW spectroscopy experiments<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25 cit26">25,26</REF> suggest that C<SB>2</SB> is generated in much greater abundance than C<SB>4</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="205"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp25" novelty="None" advantage="None">As suggested earlier, thermal motion as a result of heating the solid cytosine sample may allow alternative C<SB>1</SB>∶C<SB>1</SB> dimers to be formed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="206"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp26" novelty="None" advantage="None">If this is the case, then the relative stabilities of the cytosine dimers as well as the relative stabilities of the C<SB>1</SB>, C<SB>2</SB>, and C<SB>4</SB> monomers could be used to obtain a better estimate for the relative populations of tautomers generated <IT>via</IT> thermal vaporization.</annotationART></s> <s sid="207"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res62" novelty="None" advantage="None">Based upon this simple idea, the relative populations of the C<SB>1</SB>, C<SB>2</SB>, and C<SB>4</SB> tautomers generated upon thermal vaporization over the temperature range from 500 to 600 K are estimated as 0.2–0.5∶1.0∶0.01–0.05, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="208"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res63" novelty="None" advantage="None">This estimate agrees reasonable well with the C<SB>1</SB> and C<SB>2</SB> populations estimated from the matrix isolation IR study, but the MW study suggests that the estimated population of C<SB>1</SB> is somewhat low.</annotationART></s> <s sid="209"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res64" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both studies also suggest that the estimated C<SB>4</SB> population is also too low.</annotationART></s> <s sid="210"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus it seems clear that accurate prediction of the relative populations of the various tautomers that would be produced upon thermal vaporization can only be achieved if the influence of the extended intermolecular hydrogen bonding interactions present in the condensed phase are examined in greater detail.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Comparison of theory and experiment</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>Solid state structure of cytosine</HEADER><P><s sid="211"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res65" novelty="None" advantage="None">Based upon the calculated relative stabilities of the three C<SB>1</SB>∶C<SB>1</SB> dimers, C<SB>1</SB>∶C<SB>1,α</SB> (4.4 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>), C<SB>1</SB>∶C<SB>1,β</SB> (0.0 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>), and C<SB>1</SB>∶C<SB>1,γ</SB> (12.9 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>), we might expect that the hydrogen bonding structures analogous to C<SB>1</SB>∶C<SB>1,α</SB> and C<SB>1</SB>∶C<SB>1,β</SB> might coexist in the solid state, while the hydrogen bonding structure analogous to C<SB>1</SB>∶C<SB>1,γ</SB> is much less likely to be present.</annotationART></s> <s sid="212"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac55" novelty="None" advantage="None">As mentioned above, the X-ray diffraction experiment<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF> found that the only hydrogen bonding configuration that exists in crystalline cytosine is that analogous to the C<SB>1</SB>∶C<SB>1,α</SB> dimer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="213"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met15" novelty="Old" advantage="None">This contradiction might be resolved based upon the following considerations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="214"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met16" novelty="Old" advantage="None">First, the relative stabilities of the cytosine dimers are based upon isolated gas phase dimers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="215"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, in the solid phase, the relative stabilities of the various C<SB>1</SB>∶C<SB>1</SB> hydrogen bonding interactions may be altered by the extended intermolecular interactions present in the solid state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="216"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to evaluate this conclusion, additional calculations of higher order clusters would need to be performed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="217"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res66" novelty="None" advantage="None">Second, the XRD data were obtained for crystalline cytosine, while the IR and MW experiments made use of amorphous cytosine powder.</annotationART></s> <s sid="218"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None">It may be possible that the cytosine molecules are aligned differently in the powder than in the crystals, and hydrogen bonding interactions analogous to the C<SB>1</SB>∶C<SB>1,β</SB> and C<SB>1</SB>∶C<SB>1,γ</SB> dimers might also exist.</annotationART></s> <s sid="219"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, powder XRD experiments may provide additional structural information.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>Gas phase dimer populations</HEADER><P><s sid="220"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res67" novelty="None" advantage="None">Because the relative stabilities of C<SB>1</SB>∶C<SB>1,β</SB> (0 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>), C<SB>1</SB>∶C<SB>1,α</SB> (4.4 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>), C<SB>2</SB>∶C<SB>2</SB> (4.8 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>), and C<SB>1</SB>∶C<SB>1,γ</SB> (12.97 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>) are very similar, and the energy barriers for tautomerization of these dimers <IT>via</IT> double proton-transfer are relatively small, it might be expected that C<SB>1</SB>∶C<SB>1,α</SB>, C<SB>1</SB>∶C<SB>1,β</SB>, C<SB>1</SB>∶C<SB>1,γ</SB>, and C<SB>2</SB>∶C<SB>2</SB> would coexist in the gas phase.</annotationART></s> <s sid="221"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res68" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast, the other cytosine dimers examined in this work are sufficiently less stable, C<SB>2</SB>∶C<SB>4</SB> (22.76 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>), and C<SB>4</SB>∶C<SB>4</SB> (42.80 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>), that they would not be expected to have significant populations in the gas phase at temperatures below the decomposition temperature of cytosine.</annotationART></s> <s sid="222"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac56" novelty="None" advantage="None">In agreement with our results, molecular dynamics/quenching calculations,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit56">56</REF> found that the C<SB>1</SB>∶C<SB>1,α</SB> dimer is the most populated species of all possible dimeric clusters.</annotationART></s> <s sid="223"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac57" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, it was also found that the C<SB>1</SB>∶C<SB>1,β</SB> and C<SB>1</SB>∶C<SB>1,γ</SB> dimers are also populated in reasonable abundance (note: the C<SB>2</SB>∶C<SB>2</SB> dimer was not examined in this work).</annotationART></s> <s sid="224"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac58" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, C<SB>1</SB>∶C<SB>1,α</SB> was the only dimer observed in the REMPI spectra of laser desorbed jet-cooled cytosine.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit55">55</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="225"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Considering that similar experiments for the cytosine monomers found that both C<SB>1</SB> and C<SB>2</SB> are formed under analogous experimental conditions, and that these tautomers are calculated to have larger differences in relative stability, it is not obvious why the C<SB>1</SB>∶C<SB>1</SB>,<SB>β</SB> and C<SB>2</SB>∶C<SB>2</SB> dimers were not formed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="226"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res69" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the calculated relative stabilities of the cytosine dimers are sensitive to the computational method employed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="227"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met17" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The relative stabilities of the cytosine dimers determined here were derived from MP2(full)/6-311+G(2d,2p)//MP2(full)/6-31G* calculations, while the molecular dynamics/quenching calculations were performed at a slightly lower level of theory.</annotationART></s> <s sid="228"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp27" novelty="None" advantage="None">This suggest that either calculations at higher levels of theory might be needed to obtain accurate relative stabilities of the cytosine dimers, that the spectra of these dimers overlap and cannot really be distinguished in the spectra, or that there is some dynamical effects that occur in the REMPI experiments that favor the formation of C<SB>1</SB>∶C<SB>1,α</SB> over the other dimers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="229"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp28" novelty="None" advantage="None">Additional experiments such as molecular beam MW experiments that are sensitive to large differences in the dipole moments of the cytosine dimers might be helpful in understanding this apparent discrepancy between theory and experiment.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Conclusions</HEADER><P><s sid="230"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res70" novelty="None" advantage="None">The relative stabilities of the cytosine tautomers, C<SB>2</SB> &lt; C<SB>3</SB> &lt; C<SB>1</SB> &lt; C<SB>4</SB> &lt; C<SB>5</SB> &lt; C<SB>6</SB>, as determined at the MP2(full)/6-311+G(2d,2p)//MP2(full)/6-31G* level of theory including zero point energy and basis set superposition error corrections were found to be in agreement with the overwhelming majority of data from previous theoretical and experimental studies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="231"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Based upon the calculated relative stabilities of these tautomers, it might be expected that the C<SB>1</SB>, C<SB>2</SB>, C<SB>3</SB>, and C<SB>4</SB> tautomers would be generated in measurable populations in the gas phase.</annotationART></s> <s sid="232"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res71" novelty="None" advantage="None">Indeed several experimental studies found that C<SB>1</SB>, C<SB>2</SB>, and C<SB>4</SB> are generated from vaporization or laser desorption of solid cytosine, however no direct evidence for the formation of C<SB>3</SB> has been observed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="233"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res72" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is reasonable that C<SB>1</SB> exists, because it is the only tautomeric form present in the original solid sample and should be able to be sublimated into the gas phase directly by heating.</annotationART></s> <s sid="234"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res73" novelty="None" advantage="None">At first glance it seems surprising that although C<SB>3</SB> is more stable than C<SB>1</SB>, there is no evidence that C<SB>3</SB> is formed, while the less stable tautomer C<SB>4</SB> has been observed in gas phase.</annotationART></s> <s sid="235"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res74" novelty="None" advantage="None">This apparent contradiction can be understood based on both the unimolecular and bimolecular tautomerization mechanisms examined here.</annotationART></s> <s sid="236"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res75" novelty="None" advantage="None">The C<SB>2</SB> and C<SB>4</SB> tautomers can be formed directly from C<SB>1</SB> by either unimolecular or bimolecular tautomerization processes, whereas formation of C<SB>3</SB> directly from C<SB>1</SB> is not possible <IT>via</IT> either mechanism.</annotationART></s> <s sid="237"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res76" novelty="None" advantage="None">The barriers to unimolecular tautomerization for the C<SB>1</SB> → C<SB>2</SB> and C<SB>1</SB> → C<SB>4</SB> tautomerization processes are too large to be overcome by thermal vaporization.</annotationART></s> <s sid="238"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res77" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, formation of dual hydrogen bonds in cytosine dimers facilitate the tautomerization processes, C<SB>1</SB>∶C<SB>1,α</SB> → C<SB>2</SB>∶C<SB>4</SB>, C<SB>1</SB>∶C<SB>1,β</SB> → C<SB>2</SB>∶C<SB>2</SB>, and C<SB>1</SB>∶C<SB>1,γ</SB> → C<SB>4</SB>∶C<SB>4</SB> and thus provide an energetically accessible mechanism for the formation C<SB>2</SB> and C<SB>4</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="239"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Tautomerization <IT>via</IT> double proton-transfer seems feasible both in the gas and condensed phases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="240"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Whether or not the actual tautomerization occurs in the gas phase or in the solid sample is not clear, but the additional stabilization provided by neighboring cytosine molecules in the solid should make the tautomerization processes even more favorable.</annotationART></s> <s sid="241"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The formation of C<SB>3</SB> can only be achieved <IT>via</IT> unimolecular tautomerization of C<SB>2</SB>, but requires additional energy (∼30 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>) to overcome the activation barrier.</annotationART></s> <s sid="242"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res78" novelty="None" advantage="None">It seems extremely unlikely that the C<SB>2</SB> monomers would be formed with enough internal energy to overcome this barrier, and therefore explains why C<SB>3</SB> was not observed in the experiments published to date.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="243"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res79" novelty="None" advantage="None">Because it is not clear whether tautomerization occurs in the gas phase or in the solid or both, accurate estimation of the relative populations of the C<SB>1</SB>, C<SB>2</SB>, and C<SB>4</SB> tautomers is not possible.</annotationART></s> <s sid="244"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res80" novelty="None" advantage="None">The populations measured in the IR and MW experiments agree fairly well with those estimated solely on the basis of the relative stabilities of these three tautomers, but also appear to agree with consideration of the dimer stabilities as well.</annotationART></s> <s sid="245"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con16" novelty="None" advantage="None">In any event, it seems clear that intermolecular interactions between the cytosine molecules must be involved in the mechanism by which cytosine undergoes tautomerization to produce a mixture of tautomeric species in the gas phase.</annotationART></s> <s sid="246"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res81" novelty="None" advantage="None">Additional experiments and theoretical studies could shed light on the gas phase <IT>versus</IT> condensed phase contributions to this process.</annotationART></s> <s sid="247"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although the cytosine dimers examined here cannot be formed in DNA and RNA, the similarity of these systems to the DNA base pairs suggests that such bimolecular double proton transfer mechanisms might provide a means by which mutation of DNA can be achieved and explained.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
