<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b316385g" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Nonadiabatic coupling and vector correlation in dissociation of triatomic hydrogen</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">We determine experimentally the vector correlation among the three neutral ground state hydrogen atoms which appear in dissociation of neutral H<SB>3</SB>* molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The sum of the kinetic energies of the three H-atoms is fixed by selecting the energy of the H<SB>3</SB>* molecule by laser excitation in the range between 0.85 and 3.60 eV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The highly structured maps of correlation in the motion of the three atoms provide a direct view of the internal molecular couplings which initiate dissociation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">We discuss this feature in a model calculation and in terms of a new quantum chemical calculations of the potential energy surfaces of H<SB>3</SB>*.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER /><P><s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">A basis of quantum chemistry is the Born–Oppenheimer (BO) approximation, according to which nuclei move on single adiabatic potential energy surfaces created by the much faster moving electrons.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This approximation permits the definition of isolated electronic molecular states and their energy levels.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Many interesting aspects of molecular dynamics such as molecule formation and dissociation arise from the breakdown of this approximation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is due to small terms in the molecular Hamiltonian which originate from the finite response time of electron motion to changing nuclear position.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">A direct access to the dependence of these couplings on molecular coordinates has eluded experimental observation to date, except for diatomics.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None">In our experiment we monitor the reaction H<SB>3</SB>* → H(1s) + H(1s) + H(1s).for individual, state-selected H<SB>3</SB>* molecules and determine separately for each molecule the three atomic momentum vectors in coincidence using technologies described previously.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2 cit3 cit4">2–4</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">We prepare metastable triatomic hydrogen molecules in a fast (3 keV) beam by charge transfer neutralization of H<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rotationless 2p <SP>2</SP>A<SB>2</SB>″ state of H<SB>3</SB> is immune against rapid predissociation.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">This state is present in the neutral beam of H<SB>3</SB> molecules in a range of vibrational levels {<IT>v</IT><SB>1</SB>,<IT>v</IT><SB>2</SB>}, where <IT>v</IT><SB>1</SB> and <IT>v</IT><SB>2</SB> describe the symmetric stretch and degenerate bending mode vibrational quantum numbers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Photoexcitation spectra of H<SB>3</SB> and D<SB>3</SB> have been studied in detail<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF> and firm electronic, vibrational, and rotational assignments of the spectra have emerged, backed by MQDT theory based solely <IT>on ab-initio</IT> parameters.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="New" advantage="None">In the photodissociation experiment described here the molecules are photoexcited inside the cavity of a narrowband dye laser which is tuned to a specific absorption transition to a molecular Rydberg state below the ionization threshold.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="New" advantage="Yes">In this way the total energy of the molecule, <IT>W</IT>, defined relative to three separated hydrogen atoms, H(1s) + H(1s) + H(1s), is precisely fixed in the experiment.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This situation is indicated in Fig. 1, which gives a cut through the potential energy surfaces of H<SB>3</SB> along the symmetric stretch coordinate.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Following photoexcitation the molecules typically predissociate on time scales of 1–10 ns,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF> their center of mass propagating at an energy of 3 keV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The photofragments separate spatially from this direction according to their transverse momentum and they are detected in coincidence using position- and time-sensitive multihit-detectors<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF> after a free-flight of 1510 mm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Over this flight distance the fragments separate in space by as much as 100 mm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">High speed time-to-digital converters permit to measure the spatial coordinates of the impact positions of the neutral atoms with a resolution of &lt;100 µm and the arrival time differences between the three atoms with a resolution of &lt;100 ps.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">A triple-coincidence logic-routine<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF> examines the positions and arrival-times to distinguish process (1) from the fragmentation channel H<SB>3</SB>* → H<SB>2</SB>(<SP>1</SP>Σ+g) + H(1s).For each triple coincidence event, the momentum vectors {<IT>k⃑</IT><SB>1</SB>,<IT>k⃑</IT><SB>2</SB>,<IT>k⃑</IT><SB>3</SB>} in the center-of-mass frame are evaluated from the time and position information.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">After recording the dissociation of ≈10<SP>4</SP> molecules, we obtain a map of preferred momentum correlation, under which the selected H<SB>3</SB>* state escapes into the three-particle continuum.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="Old" advantage="None">These data are coded into a Dalitz plot (see below) after accounting for the geometric detection efficiency.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The exit channel in reaction (1) is well defined in terms of three plane waves with center-of-mass momenta <IT>k⃑</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Neglecting spin- and orbital angular momenta it may be written as the product wavefunction of the three hydrogen atoms <IT>ψ</IT><SP><IT>c</IT></SP> = <IT>Φ</IT><SB>1</SB>(<IT>k⃑</IT><SB>1</SB>)<IT>Φ</IT><SB>2</SB>(<IT>k⃑</IT><SB>2</SB>)<IT>Φ</IT><SB>3</SB>(<IT>k⃑</IT><SB>3</SB>).Since the molecular state under study is selected in the laser-excitation step the energy condition holds (<IT>m</IT> being the hydrogen mass), in addition to momentum conservation <IT>k⃑</IT><SB>1</SB> + <IT>k⃑</IT><SB>2</SB> + <IT>k⃑</IT><SB>3</SB> = 0.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">A unique map of three correlated momentum vectors can be represented in a Dalitz<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF> plot.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">This probability-density plot gives the vector correlation in terms of the reduced energies of the three atoms where <IT>ε</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB> = |<IT>k⃑</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB>|<SP>2</SP>/(2<IT>mW</IT>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 2 illustrates the meaning of the position of an event in the Dalitz plot in terms of the orientation and magnitude of the fragment momenta.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus islands of preferrred population in a Dalitz plot refer to specific orientations of final-state fragment momenta.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this work we determined the correlation map for about twenty electronic and vibrational molecular states of H<SB>3</SB> and D<SB>3</SB> in the energy range between 0.85 and 3.60 eV above the three-particle asymptote H(1s) + H(1s) + H(1s).</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Typical examples are shown in Fig. 3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Pronounced islands of high probability appear, their location depending on the type of electronic excitation, on the vibrational state, and on nuclear mass.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The initial electronic states have nearly identical nuclear geometry because the adiabatic potential energy surfaces of the excited states are all close to the geometry of the parent ion core H<SB>3</SB><SP>+</SP>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The tightly bound ion is of <IT>D</IT><SB>3h</SB> geometry with a proton separation of 1.64 <IT>a</IT><SB>0</SB> at the potential minimum.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The attached Rydberg electron adds small modifications to the binding, leading to small (&lt;5%) variations in the proton separation at equilibrium.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">However the electronic, rovibrational, and nuclear symmetries of the excited states differ and thereby control the coupling matrix elements for predissociation into the ground state continuum.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">This feature dictates the appearance of the Dalitz plots as we will discuss below.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">At present, no rigorous theory has treated a molecular three-body problem such as (1), however a formal discussion can be given.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The initially bound H<SB>3</SB>* molecule is prepared at time <IT>t</IT><SB>0</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">At low vibrational excitation its heavy particle wavefunction <IT>ψ</IT><SP><IT>R</IT></SP>(<IT>t</IT><SB>0</SB>) is restricted by locally quadratic potentials.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is characterized by products of harmonic oscillator wavefunctions <IT>χ</IT> in the symmetric stretch and bending normal mode coordinates, <IT>Q</IT><SB>s</SB> and <IT>Q</IT><SB>b</SB>, with {<IT>i</IT>,<IT>j</IT>} quanta of vibrational excitation <IT>ψ</IT><IT>R</IT><IT>i</IT>,<IT>j</IT>(<IT>t</IT><SB>0</SB>) = <IT>χ</IT><SB><IT>i</IT></SB>(<IT>Q</IT><SB>s</SB>)<IT>χ</IT><SB><IT>j</IT></SB>(<IT>Q</IT><SB>b</SB>).In a time-dependent approach we may formally view process (1) as a sequence of two steps.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">In a first phase the bound molecular state accesses the repulsive ground state surface of H<SB>3</SB><IT>ψ</IT><SP><IT>m</IT></SP>(<IT>t</IT><SB>1</SB>) = <IT>ψ</IT><IT>R</IT><IT>i</IT>,<IT>j</IT>(<IT>t</IT><SB>0</SB>)where <IT>ψ</IT><SP><IT>m</IT></SP>(<IT>t</IT><SB>1</SB>) is a continuum wavepacket at molecular distances and the operator  describes the modification of the normal mode wave functions due to the coupling.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">This phase is followed by the evolution of the wavepacket on the continuum energy surface<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF> where  is the Hamiltonian describing the motion of the three atoms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the limit of <IT>t</IT> → ∞ the function <IT>ψ</IT><SP>c</SP>(<IT>t</IT>) approaches eqn. (3).</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Significant pieces of information required to carry out the propagation in eqns. (7) and (8) have been developed recently.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Among these are studies of some of the nonadiabatic<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14 cit15">14,15</REF> and Jahn–Teller induced couplings<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF> as well as time-dependent dynamics simulations.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13 cit14 cit15 cit17">13–15,17</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">A simple model based on a geometry- and state-independent coupling operator  fails to explain the finer details in the measured correlation maps.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The projection of the wavepacket in eqn. (7) depends sensitively on the overlap of the initial H<SB>3</SB>* state with the continuum and restrictions imposed on the projection by symmetry considerations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the basis of symmetry arguments we know that s A′<SB>1</SB> states are predissociated by the degenerate bending mode, d E″ states by rotational coupling,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19">19</REF> and p E′ states by Jahn–Teller coupling.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">This difference implies that for each electronic state different areas of phase space play the leading role in step (7) and hence dictate a specific form of .</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">We therefore conclude that our experiment provides a direct image of the action of the operator , which couples excited molecular states with the final state continuum.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The dependence of  on electronic and nuclear coordinates and symmetries is embedded in an inverse problem of relating probability density in the Dalitz plot to phase-space density of the molecular level.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since final and initial states are precisely defined from our experiment, the challenge is to perform a quantum calculation with proper account of electronic and nuclear degrees of freedom.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The complexity of such a task is apparent from Fig. 4 which gives two selected cuts through the potential energy surfaces of H<SB>3</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">As H<SB>3</SB> is the primary example of a polyatomic system an <IT>ab initio</IT> treatment of the nonadiabatic couplings in this system will significantly extend our microscopic understanding of molecular dynamics.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Certainly the experiment has reached a level of sophistication which warrants an in-depth confrontation with this fundamental system of three protons and three electrons.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
