<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b316402k" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Reaction of O(<SP>3</SP>P) with the alkyl iodides: CF<SB>3</SB>I, CH<SB>3</SB>I, CH<SB>2</SB>I<SB>2</SB>, C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>5</SB>I, 1-C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>7</SB>I and 2-C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>7</SB>I</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The kinetics of the reactions between O(<SP>3</SP>P) and various alkyl iodides (RI) was investigated using the pulsed laser photolysis–resonance fluorescence (PLP–RF) technique at temperatures between 223 and 363 K. The reactions studied were O(<SP>3</SP>P) + CF<SB>3</SB>I (1), O(<SP>3</SP>P) + CH<SB>3</SB>I (2), O(<SP>3</SP>P) + CH<SB>2</SB>I<SB>2</SB> (3), O(<SP>3</SP>P) + C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>5</SB>I (4), O(<SP>3</SP>P) + 1-C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>7</SB>I (5), and O(<SP>3</SP>P) + 2-C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>7</SB>I (6).</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Arrhenius expressions (units of cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>) obtained were: <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB>(223–363 K) = (8.73 ± 1.29) × 10<SP>−12</SP>exp{−(216 ± 38)/<IT>T</IT>}, <IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB>(223–363 K) = (9.88 ± 1.67) × 10<SP>−12</SP>exp{(183 ± 50)/<IT>T</IT>}, <IT>k</IT><SB>3</SB> (256–363 K) = (7.36 ± 0.31) × 10<SP>−11</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>, <IT>k</IT><SB>4</SB>(223–363 K) = (1.58 ± 0.22) × 10<SP>−11</SP>exp{(239 ± 39)/<IT>T</IT>} <IT>k</IT><SB>5</SB>(223–363 K) = (1.10 ± 0.17) × 10<SP>−11</SP>exp{(367 ± 42)/<IT>T</IT>}, and <IT>k</IT><SB>6</SB>(223–363 K) = (1.84 ± 0.31) × 10<SP>−11</SP>exp{(296 ± 46)/<IT>T</IT>}.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">With the exception of <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB> and <IT>k</IT><SB>3</SB>, all the other rate coefficients display a negative temperature dependence, which highlights the importance of association complex formation in reactions of O(<SP>3</SP>P) + RI.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="1">Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Interest in the reactions of alkyl iodides (RI) with oxygen atoms (O(<SP>3</SP>P)) stems from a desire to understand the mechanism of these processes, which have multi-channel product pathways on singlet and triplet potential energy surfaces and which involve the initial formation of a R–I–O complex.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2 cit3 cit4 cit5">1–5</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Whereas IO elimination is the most important product channel for the smallest iodoalkanes, CH<SB>3</SB>I and CF<SB>3</SB>I (<IT>e.g.</IT>, <IT>Φ</IT>(IO) ≈ 0.8–0.9 for CF<SB>3</SB>I),<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF> the presence of a β-position C–H bond in the longer chain iodoalkanes enables the intramolecular abstraction of an H-atom <IT>via</IT> a five-membered transition state to eliminate HOI with a yield as high as ≈0.8 for <IT>e.g.</IT>, O(<SP>3</SP>P) + C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>5</SB>I.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The formation of HOI in a spin forbidden process has been used as a laboratory source of HOI, as has the spin allowed formation of IO and R′.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">O(<SP>3</SP>P) + RI → IO + R′ O(<SP>3</SP>P) + RI → HOI + R′R′ These reactions have found application in experiments designed to provide basic physico-chemical data on these molecules,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7 cit8">7,8</REF> and also parameters relevant to their atmospheric chemistry<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9 cit10">9,10</REF> and photochemistry.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11 cit12">11,12</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rate coefficients of reactions which proceed <IT>via</IT> formation of an association complex that can stabilise and rearrange to form products often display negative temperature dependences, <IT>i.e.</IT> the rate coefficients increase with decreasing temperature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This effect has been observed for CH<SB>3</SB>I, but there are no data describing the temperature dependences of the rate coefficients for larger RI.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this paper, we present the temperature dependences of the overall rate coefficients for the reactions of O(<SP>3</SP>P) with CF<SB>3</SB>I, CH<SB>3</SB>I, C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>5</SB>I, 1-C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>7</SB>I, 2-C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>7</SB>I and CH<SB>2</SB>I<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">For CH<SB>2</SB>I<SB>2</SB>, C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>5</SB>I, and 1-C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>7</SB>I these data are the first to be reported at any temperature.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2">Experimental</HEADER><P><s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The experiments were carried out at temperatures ranging from 223 to 363 K and pressures of 100 Torr He (or N<SB>2</SB>) using the pulsed laser photolysis, resonance fluorescence technique (PLP–RF).</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">For CF<SB>3</SB>I a systematic investigation of the pressure dependence was carried out at 223 K. The experimental set up for PLP–RF is essentially that which has already been described in the literature<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF> and is given briefly below.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The reactions were conducted in a thermostatted quartz reaction vessel of ≈500 ml volume with Brewster angle entrance and exit windows which could be heated to prevent condensation of ambient water vapour when working at low temperatures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Gas flows were regulated by calibrated mass flow controllers, and the pressure was monitored using 100 and 1000 Torr capacitance manometers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In some experiments CH<SB>2</SB>I<SB>2</SB> was passed through a Teflon needle valve instead of the flow controller, but no significant differences could be observed.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The temperature in the reaction zone was monitored with a J-type thermocouple, and regulated by circulating cryogenic fluid through a jacket.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Typical flow rates were ≈500 cm<SP>3</SP> (STP) min<SP>−1</SP> (sccm), sufficient to replenish the reaction volume between laser pulses, and prevent build up of products which could result in secondary loss processes of O(<SP>3</SP>P).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Pulsed photolysis radiation at 351 nm was provided by an excimer laser at a repetition rate of between 2 and 10 Hz.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The photolysis beam intersected the light from an O-atom resonance lamp at the focus of a MgF<SB>2</SB> lens that directed fluorescence to a VUV photomultiplier.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The resonance lamp was operated at a total pressure of 3 Torr He, and its emission was filtered by a 1 mm thick CaF<SB>2</SB> window, that prevented transmission of shorter wavelength emission from N and H atoms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Time dependent O(<SP>3</SP>P) signals were amplified, digitised and counted by a multichannel scaler usually operating at a resolution of 5 μs per channel, and averaging between 1000 and 3000 decay profiles.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Oxygen atoms were produced by the 351 nm photolysis of NO<SB>2</SB>: NO<SB>2</SB> + <IT>h</IT><IT>ν</IT> → NO + O(<SP>3</SP>P) Typically, NO<SB>2</SB> concentrations of (6 ± 1) × 10<SP>13</SP> molecules cm<SP>−3</SP> and laser fluences of 2–12 mJ cm<SP>−2</SP> were used, resulting in the formation of approximately (8–50) × 10<SP>10</SP> O(<SP>3</SP>P) cm<SP>−3</SP> per pulse.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The approximate sensitivity (S/N = 1) for detection of O(<SP>3</SP>P) was ≈2 × 10<SP>10</SP> atoms cm<SP>−3</SP> for a total integration time of 5–10 ms.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">An accurate measurement of the concentration of the alkyl iodides is necessary to derive rate coefficients (see below) and was carried out on-line by absorption spectroscopy using a 44 cm cell mounted at the exit of the reaction cell and maintained in a vacuum housing at room temperature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The intensity of either the 185 or 254 nm line of a low-pressure Hg lamp, was monitored by two photodiodes (one transmission, one reference) to derive the optical density (OD) due to the alkyl iodide.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In separate experiments the dependence of OD<SP>185</SP> or OD<SP>254</SP> on the concentration of RI was determined by flowing RI diluted in He through an optical absorption cell equipped with a monochromator and a diode array spectrometer to obtain a simultaneous measurement of absorption between ≈210 and 360 nm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">This was converted to a concentration by least squares fitting to evaluated literature spectra,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF> enabling effective cross sections at 254 and 185 nm to be derived as: <IT>σ</IT><SP>254</SP>(CF<SB>3</SB>I) = 4.19 × 10<SP>−19</SP>, <IT>σ</IT><SP>254</SP>(CH<SB>3</SB>I) = 1.14 × 10<SP>−18</SP>, <IT>σ</IT><SP>185</SP>(CH<SB>2</SB>I<SB>2</SB> = 3.33 × 10<SP>−17</SP>, <IT>σ</IT><SP>254</SP>(C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>5</SB>I) = 1.14 × 10<SP>−18</SP>, <IT>σ</IT><SP>254</SP>(1-C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>7</SB>I) = 1.35 × 10<SP>−18</SP>, <IT>σ</IT><SP>254</SP>(2-C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>7</SB>I) = 1.23 × 10<SP>−18</SP> cm<SP>2</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s></P><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.1">Materials</HEADER><P><s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The commercial gases used in this study had the following stated minimum purity: NO<SB>2</SB> (Aldrich 99.5%), He (Linde 99.999%), N<SB>2</SB> (Linde 99.999%), CF<SB>3</SB>I (ABCR GmbH 99%), all other RI (Aldrich, 99%).</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">All RI samples were vacuum-distilled before use and the gas phase checked for I<SB>2</SB> impurity by optical absorption at 450–610 nm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Only for CH<SB>2</SB>I<SB>2</SB> was I<SB>2</SB> detected, at a level of 0.2% of the RI concentration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">For CF<SB>3</SB>I an upper limit of 0.01% could be determined, and for all other RI this value was &lt;0.1 × 10<SP>−3</SP>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3">Results and discussion</HEADER><P><s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In all experiments the concentrations of O(<SP>3</SP>P) and RI were chosen so that pseudo first order conditions prevailed, <IT>i.e.</IT> [RI] ≫ [O(<SP>3</SP>P)] with a value of [RI]/[O(<SP>3</SP>P)] of between 400 and 8000.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the absence of secondary loss processes for O(<SP>3</SP>P), the concentration profile of O(<SP>3</SP>P) is then given by: [O(<SP>3</SP>P)]<IT><SB>t</SB></IT> = [O(<SP>3</SP>P)]<SB>0</SB> exp (−(<IT>k</IT>([RI] + <IT>d</IT>)<IT>t</IT>) where [O(<SP>3</SP>P)]<IT><SB>t</SB></IT> is the oxygen atom concentration at time <IT>t</IT>, and [O(<SP>3</SP>P)]<SB>0</SB> is the initial oxygen atom concentration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The term <IT>d</IT> represents the summed loss of O(<SP>3</SP>P) due to diffusion from the reaction zone and reaction with NO<SB>2</SB> and was typically 500–700 s<SP>−1</SP> (mainly due to reaction with NO<SB>2</SB>).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Plots of ln O(<SP>3</SP>P)-signal <IT>versus</IT><IT>t</IT> yield the first-order decay constant, <IT>k</IT>′, which is related to the bimolecular rate coefficient by: <IT>k′</IT> = <IT>k</IT>[RI] + <IT>d</IT> The assumption of no significant secondary loss of O(<SP>3</SP>P) could be tested by demonstrating that variation of the laser fluence, and thus the radical density and degree of conversion of RI had no influence on measured values of <IT>k</IT>′.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The one exception to this was encountered in experiments with CH<SB>2</SB>I<SB>2</SB>, in which formation of CH<SB>2</SB>I and I occurs directly by photolysis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is discussed in detail below.</annotationART></s></P><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.1">O(<SP>3</SP>P) + CF<SB>3</SB>I</HEADER><P><s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The O(<SP>3</SP>P) + CF<SB>3</SB>I reaction was studied at seven temperatures between 223 and 363 K and at four different pressures from 20 Torr to 310 Torr in He and at 100 Torr in N<SB>2</SB> at 223 K. A representative data set displaying O(<SP>3</SP>P) decays in the presence of various excess concentrations of CF<SB>3</SB>I (in this case at 243 K) is given in Fig. 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">A plot of <IT>k</IT>′ <IT>versus</IT> [CF<SB>3</SB>I], the slope of which defines the rate coefficient according to eqn. (ii), is given in Fig. 2 for 223 and 333 K. It is apparent from this figure that the reaction of O(<SP>3</SP>P) with CF<SB>3</SB>I has an activation barrier (rate coefficient increases with increasing temperature).</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The complete data set, covering temperatures between 223 and 363 K is given in Table 1 and displayed in Arrhenius form in Fig. 3.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Data from previous experimental studies, obtained using both resonance fluorescence detection of O(<SP>3</SP>P) and laser induced fluorescence detection of IO (the major product, see below) are also displayed in Fig. 3 and listed in Table 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fit line shown is to the Arrhenius expression, <IT>k</IT>(<IT>T</IT>) = <IT>A</IT>exp(−<IT>E</IT>/<IT>R</IT><IT>T</IT>), and is described by: <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB>(223–363 K) = (8.73 ± 1.29) × 10<SP>−12</SP>exp(−{216 ± 38}/<IT>T)</IT> The errors in <IT>E</IT>/<IT>R</IT> are 2<IT>σ</IT> random only, returned by the weighted (by 1/<IT>σ</IT><SP>2</SP>) fit to the data presented in Table 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The errors in the pre-exponential factor include both 2<IT>σ</IT> random error (as above for <IT>E</IT>/<IT>R</IT>) and also an additional 5% systematic error due to estimated uncertainty in the absorption cross sections of CF<SB>3</SB>I.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Table 2 compares the rate constants at 298 K and the Arrhenius parameters of this work with those obtained in previous studies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results from the most recent studies are in excellent agreement throughout the common temperature range.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although the temperature dependence of Hölscher <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF>. agrees with the present data, the absolute values are somewhat higher, as are those of Atkinson <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF>. and the older room temperature studies of Addison <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF>. and Watson <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Watson <IT>et al.</IT> monitored IF formation from the reaction sequence: O(<SP>3</SP>P) + CF<SB>3</SB>I → IO + CF<SB>3</SB>O(<SP>3</SP>P) + CF<SB>3</SB> → F<SB>2</SB>CO + FF + CF<SB>3</SB>I → IF + CF<SB>3</SB> Given the indirect nature of this determination, the result of (6.5 ± 1.5) × 10<SP>−12</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP> can be considered in satisfactory agreement with the present determination.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The result of Addison <IT>et al.</IT>, <IT>k</IT><SB>3</SB> = (1.1 ± 0.3) × 10<SP>−11</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF> was obtained by direct observation of O(<SP>3</SP>P) by resonance absorption in the presence of excess CF<SB>3</SB>I and is a factor of ≈2 larger than the present result.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Atkinson used cavity ring down detection of the IO product to obtain (5.8 ± 1.5) × 10<SP>−12</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP> at 295 K.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Possible causes for determining rate coefficients that are too high include (a) the presence of reactive impurities (<IT>e.g.</IT>, I<SB>2</SB>), (b) the secondary loss of O(<SP>3</SP>P) <IT>via</IT> reaction with IO or (c) underestimated CF<SB>3</SB>I concentrations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="None" advantage="Yes">As discussed already, all of these potential sources of error could be minimised in the present PLP–RF study.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">As mentioned above, IO is a known product of reaction (1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The thermodynamically accessible product channels (from Gilles <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF>.) are: O(<SP>3</SP>P) + CF<SB>3</SB>I → IO + CF<SB>3</SB>O(<SP>3</SP>P) + CF<SB>3</SB>I → IF + CF<SB>2</SB>OO(<SP>3</SP>P) + CF<SB>3</SB>I → I + F + CF<SB>2</SB>OO(<SP>3</SP>P) + CF<SB>3</SB>I → I + CF<SB>3</SB>OO(<SP>3</SP>P) + CF<SB>3</SB>I + M → M + CF<SB>3</SB>IO Product formation in this reaction has been extensively investigated by Gilles <IT>et al.</IT>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF> who determined that channel (1a) dominates with temperature independent yields of IO of ≈0.8–0.9, whereas no evidence has been found for the formation of CF<SB>3</SB>O<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF> or IF.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Gilles <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF>. speculated that an adduct (either CF<SB>3</SB>IO or CF<SB>3</SB>OI) could be formed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">They also provide an extended discussion of the earlier literature regarding product formation, which is not repeated here.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, since the work of Gilles <IT>et al.</IT>, <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF> indirect evidence for the presence of the pressure dependent channel at low temperatures (1e) has been given by Bloss <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF>. who, in contrast to Gilles <IT>et al.</IT>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF> observed a pressure dependence in the IO yield at 223 K. In addition, the work of Dillon and Heard<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19">19</REF> reveals an increase in the overall rate coefficient at 223 K with increasing pressure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">In agreement with the present work, a pressure dependence of <IT>k</IT><SB>1</SB> was not observed at room temperature.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to examine the presence of pressure effects at low temperatures, we carried out experiments at 223 K in the presence of between 10 and 310 Torr He, and at 100 Torr N<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results, shown in Fig. 4, indicate no significant pressure dependence at this temperature, in stark contrast to the result of Dillon and Heard.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19">19</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reason for this discrepancy remains unclear.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although the present data set weakens the arguments in favour of a termolecular channel, they do not rule it out, as the lack of pressure dependence could also be attributed to the reaction being at the high pressure limit at 10 Torr and 223 K.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.2">O(<SP>3</SP>P) + CH<SB>3</SB>I</HEADER><P><s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The PLP–RF data for CH<SB>3</SB>I (and the following RI) were obtained as described above, and the pseudo first-order decays and the plots of <IT>k</IT>′ <IT>versus</IT> [RI] were qualitatively similar to those for CF<SB>3</SB>I.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The complete data set obtained for reaction of O(<SP>3</SP>P) with CH<SB>3</SB>I is listed in Table 1, and plotted in Arrhenius form in Fig. 5, which also displays results of previous studies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">The temperature dependence of the rate coefficient is given by: <IT>k</IT><SB>2</SB>(223–363 K) = (9.88 ± 1.67) × 10<SP>−12</SP>exp{(183 ± 50)/<IT>T</IT>} where the error limits were derived as for eqn. (iii).</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">The absolute values of the rate coefficient and its temperature dependence obtained in the present study are in excellent agreement with the measurements of Gilles <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF>. which were also obtained using mainly O(<SP>3</SP>P) resonance fluorescence, but with some data obtained using LIF detection of IO.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">The data of Hölscher <IT>et al.</IT>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF> obtained using only LIF detection of IO, agree at temperatures close to 300 K, but are systematically higher by ≈10% at lower temperatures and display a stronger temperature dependence.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The estimate of Kwong <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF>. was based on an indirect flow tube study, and is orders of magnitude too low, suggesting that some of the assumptions made to describe the formation of excited I<SB>2</SB> (the only product detected) were erroneous, as some of the now recognised product channels were not considered.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The products of this reaction have been examined in detail by Gilles <IT>et al.</IT>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF> and the possible exothermic channels are listed below: O(<SP>3</SP>P) + CH<SB>3</SB>I → IO + CH<SB>3</SB>O(<SP>3</SP>P) + CH<SB>3</SB>I → OH + CH<SB>2</SB>IO(<SP>3</SP>P) + CH<SB>3</SB>I → H + I + HCHOO(<SP>3</SP>P) + CH<SB>3</SB>I → I + CH<SB>3</SB>OO(<SP>3</SP>P) + CH<SB>3</SB>I → HI + HCHOO(<SP>3</SP>P) + CH<SB>3</SB>I → CH<SB>3</SB>IO (or CH<SB>3</SB>OI) The observation of multiple product channels, and a negative temperature dependence are indicative of a complex mechanism, though in this case rearrangement to form HOI <IT>via</IT> internal abstraction from a five-membered ring is not possible.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Gilles <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF>. have determined product yields for IO (40–50%), OH (16%), H (7%), CH<SB>3</SB>O (&lt;3%) and HI (&lt;5%).</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.3">O(<SP>3</SP>P) + CH<SB>2</SB>I<SB>2</SB></HEADER><P><s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">CH<SB>2</SB>I<SB>2</SB> is the only di-iodoalkane investigated in this work, and hence the only one which has an absorption spectrum that extends out to 351 nm, the wavelength of the photolysis laser.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The absorption cross-section of CH<SB>2</SB>I<SB>2</SB> at 351 nm is reported as ≈3.2 × 10<SP>−19</SP> cm<SP>2</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF> which is similar in magnitude to that of NO<SB>2</SB>, the precursor of O(<SP>3</SP>P) in these experiments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="None" advantage="Yes">As CH<SB>2</SB>I<SB>2</SB> was present in concentrations similar to those of NO<SB>2</SB>, the photolytic generation of unwanted radicals (<IT>i.e.</IT> CH<SB>2</SB>I) at concentrations exceeding those of O(<SP>3</SP>P) is a potential problem.</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">CH<SB>2</SB>I<SB>2</SB> + <IT>h</IT><IT>ν</IT> (351 nm) → CH<SB>2</SB>I + IFor experiments with CH<SB>2</SB>I<SB>2</SB>, two problems were encountered, which were not apparent for the other RI examined in this study.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Firstly, the signal due to O(<SP>3</SP>P) was modified by a post laser-pulse offset, which was also observed in the absence of NO<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">This offset signal was constant on the time scales of a typical experiment, suggesting photolytic generation of a non-reactive species that can scatter the light from the resonance lamp, with I atoms from reaction (10) being the obvious candidate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met14" novelty="New" advantage="None">The data were therefore treated by correcting for the measured offset, or by modifying eqn. (i) to account for time independent offset.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both gave the same result, and the second option, which saves considerable experimental time, was adopted.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">A more serious problem was the observation of a laser fluence dependence in the first-order decay constant of O(<SP>3</SP>P), with faster decay constants obtained at higher laser fluence.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None">This clearly indicated that O(<SP>3</SP>P) was being removed by reaction with CH<SB>2</SB>I or other reactive species formed in secondary processes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None">At laser fluences ≤3 mJ cm<SP>−2</SP> values of <IT>k</IT>′ were, within experimental uncertainty, independent of fluence.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp9" novelty="None" advantage="None">All subsequent experiments were therefore conducted at a laser fluence of ≈3 mJ cm<SP>−2</SP> and using higher NO<SB>2</SB> concentrations than for the other RI in order to generate sufficient O(<SP>3</SP>P) for detection.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The data thus obtained are listed in Table 1 and displayed in an Arrhenius plot in Fig. 6.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res29" novelty="None" advantage="None">The somewhat larger experimental uncertainty compared to those of the other RI reflects the problems mentioned above.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res30" novelty="None" advantage="None">Within the experimental uncertainty and the temperature range covered the rate coefficient can be considered independent of temperature, with a value of <IT>k</IT><SB>3</SB> = (7.36 ± 0.47) × 10<SP>−11</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP> obtained from a weighted average of the data in Table 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met15" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The error limits contain both random error (see footnote to Table 1) plus 5% systematic error related to uncertainty in the cross-section of CH<SB>2</SB>I<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.4">O(<SP>3</SP>P) + C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>5</SB>I</HEADER><P><s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" advantage="None">The present data yield a temperature dependent rate coefficient described by: <IT>k</IT><SB>4</SB> = (1.58 ± 0.22) × 10<SP>−11</SP> exp{(239 ± 39)/<IT>T</IT>} The room temperature rate coefficient is <IT>k</IT><SB>4</SB>(298 K) = (3.51 ± 0.24) × 10<SP>−11</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP> whereby the errors contain both random error (see footnote to Table 1) and an estimated 5% systematic error arising from uncertainty in the absorption cross section of C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>5</SB>I. This value can be compared with unpublished data of Gilles ((2.38 ± 0.73) × 10<SP>−11</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>) which was cited by Loomis <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res32" novelty="None" advantage="None">This value is significantly lower than the present result, and thus in contrast to the other data common to this work and the published data of Gilles <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF>. which are in excellent agreement.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac20" novelty="None" advantage="None">Previous studies of the dynamics of this reaction have shown the presence of at least two reaction pathways, generating HOI and IO:<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit8">5,8</REF> O(<SP>3</SP>P) + C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>5</SB>I → HOI + C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>4</SB>O(<SP>3</SP>P) + C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>5</SB>I → IO + C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>5</SB> with ≈80–90% of the reaction proceeding <IT>via</IT> the HOI forming channel at 298 K.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac21" novelty="None" advantage="None">The negative temperature dependence of <IT>k</IT><SB>4</SB> is thus consistent with formation of a long lived association complex (<IT>i.e.</IT> R–I–O) which can rearrange <IT>via</IT> a five-membered ring to form the products of channel (4a), or dissociate to form R + IO as in channel (4b).</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.5">O(<SP>3</SP>P) + 1-C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>7</SB>I and O(<SP>3</SP>P) + 2-C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>7</SB>I</HEADER><P><s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res33" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our data on these two reactions give Arrhenius expressions of: <IT>k</IT><SB>5</SB> = (1.10 ± 0.17) × 10<SP>−11</SP> exp{(367 ± 42)/<IT>T</IT>}<IT>k</IT><SB>6</SB> = (1.84 ± 0.31) × 10<SP>−11</SP> exp{(296 ± 46)/<IT>T</IT>} The errors are derived as in eqn. (iii).</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res34" novelty="None" advantage="None">The room temperature rate coefficients are: <IT>k</IT><SB>5</SB>(298 K) = (3.79 ± 0.31) × 10<SP>−11</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP> and <IT>k</IT><SB>6</SB>(298 K) = (4.97 ± 0.38) × 10<SP>−11</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP>, whereby the errors contain both random error (see footnote to Table 1) and an estimated 5% systematic error arising from uncertainty in the absorption cross-section of C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>7</SB>I. The room temperature result for 2-C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>7</SB>I is in excellent agreement with the value of (5.18 ± 0.44) × 10<SP>−11</SP> cm<SP>3</SP> molecule<SP>−1</SP> s<SP>−1</SP> presented by Gilles <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac22" novelty="None" advantage="None">As for C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>5</SB>I, the negative temperature dependence of both reactions indicates the formation of an association complex that can rearrange to form both IO and HOI:<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF> O(<SP>3</SP>P) + C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>7</SB>I → HOI + C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>6</SB>O(<SP>3</SP>P) + C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>7</SB>I → IO + C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>7</SB> The yield of IO in reaction (6b) has been determined as 0.21 at room temperature,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF> those of HOI or other product channels have not been determined.</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res35" novelty="None" advantage="None">The larger rate coefficient for 2-C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>7</SB>I compared to 1-C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>7</SB>I can be attributed to the six β-position H atoms available for formation of the five-membered ring for C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>7</SB>I compared to just two for 1-C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>7</SB>I, and to the greater electron density around the C–I bond due to two adjacent electron donating CH<SB>3</SB> groups.</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res36" novelty="None" advantage="None">Steric effects presumably reduce these effects so that the rate coefficients differ by a factor of only 1.35.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.6">Reactivity trends</HEADER><P><s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res37" novelty="None" advantage="None">The 298 K rate coefficients from this work are listed in Table 3 and reveal a strong trend in reactivity of various RI towards O(<SP>3</SP>P) with the slowest rate coefficient provided by CF<SB>3</SB>I, and the largest by the doubly substituted CH<SB>2</SB>I<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res38" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rate coefficients are between 3 and 7 orders of magnitude larger than those observed for reaction of O(<SP>3</SP>P) with the equivalent non-iodine substituted hydrocarbon, with <IT>k</IT>(O(<SP>3</SP>P) + CH<SB>3</SB>I)/<IT>k</IT>(O(<SP>3</SP>P) + CH<SB>4</SB>) = 3.7 × 10<SP>6</SP>, <IT>k</IT>(O(<SP>3</SP>P) + CH<SB>2</SB>I<SB>2</SB>)/<IT>k</IT>(O(<SP>3</SP>P) + CH<SB>4</SB>) = 1.50 × 10<SP>7</SP>, <IT>k</IT>(O(<SP>3</SP>P) + C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>5</SB>I)/<IT>k</IT>(O(<SP>3</SP>P) + C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>6</SB>) = 7.3 × 10<SP>4</SP> and <IT>k</IT>(O(<SP>3</SP>P) + C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>7</SB>I)/<IT>k</IT>(O(<SP>3</SP>P) + C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>8</SB>) = 4.9 × 10<SP>3</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac23" novelty="None" advantage="None">Rate coefficients for reaction of O(<SP>3</SP>P) with CH<SB>4</SB> and C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>6</SB> were taken from <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">ref. 21</REF> and for reaction of O(<SP>3</SP>P) with C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>8</SB> from <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">ref. 22</REF> Such large effects are not observed with substitution by <IT>e.g.</IT>, Cl.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac24" novelty="None" advantage="None">For example, the ratio <IT>k</IT>(O(<SP>3</SP>P) + CH<SB>3</SB>Cl)/<IT>k</IT>(O(<SP>3</SP>P) + CH<SB>4</SB>)) = 34 (rate coefficient for O(<SP>3</SP>P) + CH<SB>3</SB>Cl from a compilation<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res39" novelty="None" advantage="None">The great enhancement in rate coefficient together with the change in sign of its temperature dependence (O(<SP>3</SP>P) + RH or O(<SP>3</SP>P) + RBr have positive temperature dependences) indicate a change in mechanism, as does the existence of multiple reaction pathways for O(<SP>3</SP>P) + RI.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">These observations are further indicators of the participation of an association complex, the formation of which may involve charge donation from the electron rich iodine atom to the oxygen atom.</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac25" novelty="None" advantage="None">Indeed, as discussed by Gilles <IT>et al.</IT>,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF> the room temperature rate coefficient for reaction of O(<SP>3</SP>P) with several fluorinated alkyl iodides is correlated with the ionisation potential.</annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">In Fig. 7, we plot the natural logarithm of the 298 K rate coefficients obtained in this work along with those for other selected iodine containing alkanes as a function of ionisation potential.</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res40" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rate coefficients for reaction with O(<SP>3</SP>P) of the mono-substituted iodo-alkanes display a clear negative dependence on ionisation potential.</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met16" novelty="Old" advantage="None">We note that the trend line in Fig. 7 was derived by fitting only to those data points in which a negative temperature dependence has been established.</annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res41" novelty="None" advantage="None">When the pre-exponential factor is used in place of the room temperature rate coefficient, the correlation is barely discernible.</annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The observation of a positive temperature dependence for O(<SP>3</SP>P) + CF<SB>3</SB>I may imply that the rate coefficient is influenced by barriers to rearrangement of the association complex, and the dependence of <IT>k</IT> on ionisation potential may be modified.</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res42" novelty="None" advantage="None">The temperature dependence of the reaction between O(<SP>3</SP>P) and the other fluorinated species is presently unknown.</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The data for O(<SP>3</SP>P) + CH<SB>2</SB>I<SB>2</SB> does not fit well with this trend, possibly reflecting stabilisation of the association complex <IT>via</IT> involvement of two iodine atoms.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met17" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The rate coefficients obtained at 298 K can be compared to data obtained for the reactions of the same RI with both the OH radical and Cl atoms, which are also listed in Table 3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res43" novelty="None" advantage="None">With the exception of CH<SB>2</SB>I<SB>2</SB> (for which no rate coefficients for reaction with Cl or OH are available) some interesting trends are observed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res44" novelty="None" advantage="None">For both OH and Cl the rate coefficient increases with the number of C–H bonds from C<SB>1</SB> to C<SB>3</SB>, with a lower rate coefficient for 2-C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>7</SB>I than for 1-C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>7</SB>I, reflecting the reduced number of weaker secondary C–H bonds for 2-C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>7</SB>I compared to 1-C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>7</SB>I. For the reasons discussed above, the relative reactivity of O(<SP>3</SP>P) with 1-C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>7</SB>I and 2-C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>7</SB>I is reversed due to the larger number of β H-atoms that can be internally extracted as the association complex rearranges <IT>via</IT> a five-membered ring transition state to form HOI.</annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">We note that the general trend for the reactivity of O(<SP>3</SP>P) and Cl towards hydrocarbons, wherein Cl abstraction is usually orders of magnitude faster than O(<SP>3</SP>P) is reversed for most of the iodine substituted hydrocarbons investigated, again indicating the relatively minor role of abstraction compared to addition–elimination.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4">Summary and conclusions</HEADER><P><s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res45" novelty="None" advantage="None">Rate coefficients were obtained at different temperatures for the reaction of O(<SP>3</SP>P) with a series of iodine-substituted alkanes (CF<SB>3</SB>I, CH<SB>3</SB>I, CH<SB>2</SB>I<SB>2</SB> C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>5</SB>I, 1-C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>7</SB>I and 2-C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>7</SB>I).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res46" novelty="None" advantage="None">For reaction of CH<SB>2</SB>I<SB>2</SB>, C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>5</SB>I and 1-C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>7</SB>I with O(<SP>3</SP>P) atoms this work represents the first rate coefficient determination reported at any temperature and for CH<SB>2</SB>I<SB>2</SB>, C<SB>2</SB>H<SB>5</SB>I, 1-C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>7</SB>I, 2-C<SB>3</SB>H<SB>7</SB>I with O(<SP>3</SP>P) atoms the first study of the temperature dependence.</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res47" novelty="None" advantage="None">With the exception of CF<SB>3</SB>I and CH<SB>2</SB>I<SB>2</SB>, all the reactions display an increase in rate coefficient with decreasing temperature, and are several orders of magnitude faster than their non-iodine-substituted hydrocarbon analogues.</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of CF<SB>3</SB>I, the pressure dependence was investigated, and, in contrast to previous work, none was found at any temperature down to 223 K. These data substantiate the concept that, at low temperatures, the reactions between O(<SP>3</SP>P) and RI proceed mainly <IT>via</IT> formation of an association complex in which O(<SP>3</SP>P) adds to the I atom, and which can then rearrange to form a number of products.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
