<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b403127j" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Erythrocytes—the ‘house elves’ of photodynamic therapy<XREF TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" /></annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Photodynamic therapy (PDT) and fluorescence diagnosis (FD) are being developed for a number of clinical applications.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since fluorophores and photosensitising drugs are usually given systemically their effect on blood elements are of significant importance.Photodynamic effects on erythrocytes occur naturally in patients with erythropoietic protoporphyria (EPP).</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Exposure to small fluences, as obtained by the erythrocytes when they pass capillaries in the skin, leads to transfer of the photosensitiser protoporphyrin IX (PP IX), from EPP erythrocytes to endothelial cells.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="None" advantage="Yes">Thus, the erythrocytes are partly protected while the endothelial cells suffer photodamage.During photodynamic therapy <IT>in vivo</IT> erythrocytes are regularly photosensitised.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="None" advantage="No">This side effect is partly intended but mostly unwanted, and a summary of this topic is given.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">Furthermore, the effect of UV-A on erythrocytes that is accompanied with the formation of bilirubin is reviewed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Erythrocytes serve as convenient model cells for experimental research.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Such use of erythrocytes to screen new photosensitisers may be of limited value.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">A combination of photohaemolysis and haemoglobin oxygenation may become the basis for an assay for <IT>in vitro</IT> phototoxicity.Erythrocytes from birds are good model cells for exploration of physiological and molecular mechanisms involved in PDT.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">A potential mechanism of PDT induced behaviour resembling apoptosis in erythrocytes is provided.PDT for sterilisation of erythrocyte concentrates has a potential for medical use.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Photodynamic effects on the erythrocytes themselves should be avoided.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is realised by choosing a virus-selective photosensitiser, low fluences and treatment of the concentrates with agents like dipyridamole and antioxidants.Future aspects of applications of photosensitisation of red blood cells are discussed.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Photodynamic effects are defined as processes initiated by absorption of light in a dye molecule, a photosensitiser, followed by transfer of excitation energy from the dye molecule to oxygen, whereby the strongly oxidising and short lived agent singlet oxygen (<SP>1</SP>O<SB>2</SB>) is formed<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2">1,2</REF>.<SP>1</SP>O<SB>2</SB> can react with and destroy a number of biomolecules,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3 cit4">3,4</REF> including lipids, proteins and DNA.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Photodynamic effects in living cells are probably almost as old as the origin of life.</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The first scientific description of the effect was published by von Tappeiner and Raab in .1900<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6">5,6</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although the therapeutic potential of the photodynamic effect was recognised almost from the beginning,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF> it took nearly a whole century of research until the first photosensitiser received marked approval for photodynamic therapy (PDT) of cancer in December .1995<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In 1913 Meyer-Betz used intravenous injection of haematoporphyrin to demonstrate in his self-experiment the connection between diseases related to haem metabolism and photosensitisation of skin.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">As first described in 1953, an error in the last step of haem synthesis leads to fluorescent erythrocytes.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10 cit11">10,11</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">This inherited disease is called erythropoietic protoporphyria (EPP) according to the definition of Magnus <IT>et al.</IT> in .1961<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the first documentation of EPP dates back to .1926<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13 cit14">13,14</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None">Since photodynamic effects in erythrocytes are characteristic for EPP, a section of this paper is dedicated to this disease.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Potential possibilities for the use of the photosensitation in therapy were explored in the 1940s.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">This research was revived in the mid-seventies, partly due to the advent of lasers and fibre optic systems.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since that time numerous photosensitisers have been studied and tested for both PDT and fluorescence diagnosis (FD).</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Red blood cells, or blood in general, are often involved in PDT: (i) Blood is often used to transport the photosensitiser to the tissue.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">(ii) It is believed that the generation of reactive oxygen species, notably singlet oxygen, is the main molecular mechanism of photodynamic therapy.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, oxygen is needed for efficient PDT.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="New" advantage="None">Red blood cells are of particular interest since they constitute the oxygen transport system of the body.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Differences in the spectra of oxygenated and deoxygenated haemoglobin can be used to monitor the oxygenation of the tissue under treatment.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">(iii) The blood is used to control the sensitiser distribution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">After topical application of dyes the penetration depth of the dyes can be estimated from fluorescence spectra and from measurement of the speed by which the dyes reach the blood.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Liquid chromatography is a convenient method to determine photosensitiser concentrations in blood.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj5" novelty="New" advantage="None">(iv) In photodynamic treatment of systemically applied photosensitisers, photodynamic damage to erythrocytes may occur as a side-effect of PDT.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">This topic is summarised in the section ‘Photodynamic damage to erythrocytes as a side effect of <IT>in vivo</IT> photodynamic therapy’.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, none of the three first mentioned relations cause considerable photodynamic effects in red blood cells and are therefore not further discussed in this paper.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Upon irradiation with UV-A erythrocytes turn fluorescent.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is most probably due to the formation of bilirubin.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj6" novelty="New" advantage="None">The role of bilirubin in PDT is discussed in a separate paragraph.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Red blood cells often serve as model cells for <IT>in vitro</IT> PDT studies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">A recent investigation showed that even though erythrocytes are not ideal cells to evaluate or quantitatively compare photosensitisers, they are useful to elucidate the cellular and molecular principles of PDT.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19">19</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj7" novelty="New" advantage="None">This topic is discussed in the section ‘Red blood cells as model cells in experimental PDT research’.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the mid-1980s PDT was introduced in the field of virus destruction.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac20" novelty="None" advantage="None">Soon afterwards the potential for decontamination of blood components and blood bank-applications was recognised and models for viral inactivation in blood were developed.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21 cit22 cit23">21–23</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj8" novelty="New" advantage="None">The need for bacterial decontamination of blood components is rising.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Similar as for EPP it is advantageous to avoid photodynamic effects in erythrocytes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj9" novelty="New" advantage="None">Decontamination of red blood cell concentrates is reviewed in the section ‘Sterilisation of red blood cell concentrates’.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj10" novelty="New" advantage="None">Finally ideas for further research on photodynamic effects in red blood cells are given.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Erythropoietic protoporphyria</HEADER><P><s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac21" novelty="None" advantage="None">The porphyrias are metabolic diseases caused by disorders in the biosynthesis of haem.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac22" novelty="None" advantage="None">Interestingly, haem, a ferrous protoporphyrin constituting the prosthetic group of haemoglobin, is synthesised in all mammalian cells, with the exception of mature red blood cells, which do not contain mitochondria.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25">25</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac23" novelty="None" advantage="None">The haem synthesis pathway is well known<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26">26</REF> and is taken advantage of in PDT with 5-aminolaevulinic acid (ALA).</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac24" novelty="None" advantage="None">ALA is a naturally occurring early metabolite in the pathway.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac25" novelty="None" advantage="None">When applied exogenously, ALA induces the formation of protoporphyrin IX (PP IX).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27">27</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac26" novelty="None" advantage="None">Impaired activity of the enzyme ferrochelatase, which inserts the iron into PP IX, causes EPP.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac27" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ferrochelatase activity of EPP patients is decreased by 70 to 90% compared to that of controls.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28 cit29 cit30">28–30</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac28" novelty="None" advantage="None">The main part of haem synthesis takes place in the bone marrow, and haem accumulates in the maturing red blood cells during the phase of active haemoglobin synthesis.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit31">31</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac29" novelty="None" advantage="None">When the red blood cells enter the circulation, PP IX diffuses across the cell membrane and binds to the plasma proteins albumin and haemopexin.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit32">32</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although the intracellular PP IX concentration in erythrocytes decreases with cell age,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit33">33</REF> photosensitisation may take place under light exposure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This effect is illustrated in Fig. 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">It does not lead to haemolysis of erythrocytes but to a light-triggered displacement of protoporphyrin from erythrocytes to endothelial cells.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In a series of publications Brun, Sandberg and colleagues elucidated the process by <IT>in vitro</IT> experiments and proposed the following mechanisms:<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit34 cit35 cit36 cit37 cit38 cit39">34–39</REF> PP IX in erythrocytes is haemoglobin-bound, rather than membrane bound.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">When exposed to light, the binding site of PP IX is destroyed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since erythrocytes <IT>in vivo</IT> receive light while circulating in the upper dermal capillaries, they are exposed to pulses rather than to continuous irradiation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore the (haemoglobin-) released PP IX can diffuse through the cell membrane while the erythrocytes move through the ‘dark’ part of the circulation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, they get no membrane damage.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">PP IX is then bound to plasma proteins, like albumin and haemopexin, and further delivered to endothelial cells.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Additionally, PP IX can be directly transferred from the erythrocyte membranes to the membranes of endothelial cells: Endothelial cells, as well as erythrocytes, have smooth cell surfaces without microvilli.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the erythrocytes, normally having a diameter of 7 μm, are deformed during their passage through capillaries with a diameter of 4–5 μm, a close contact between the erythrocyte membrane and the endothelial cell membrane is established that facilitates transfer.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac30" novelty="None" advantage="None">These mechanisms result in the described clinical symptom: some EPP patients were able to tolerate several hours of sun exposure one day, while the next day only a few minutes exposure were enough to produce photodynamic effects in the sun-exposed skin.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit40">40</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac31" novelty="None" advantage="None">As a treatment of the photosensitivity sun protection agents, like dihydroxyacetone, as well as quenchers of reactive oxygen species, like beta-carotene, have been applied, both with limited success<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit41 cit42 cit43">41–43</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Photodynamic damage to erythrocytes as a side effect of <IT>in vivo</IT> photodynamic therapy</HEADER><P><s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac32" novelty="None" advantage="None">Damage to erythrocytes was reported after PDT with Photofrin II of cat brain in .1987<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit44">44</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac33" novelty="None" advantage="None">The erythrocytes appeared in tightly packed aggregates, which many times filled the luminal space completely.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac34" novelty="None" advantage="None">Individual erythrocytes of the aggregates occasionally showed morphological evidence of intravascular haemolysis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac35" novelty="None" advantage="None">In 1990 Orenstein <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit45">45</REF>. found that the lumen of the vessels were filled with swollen erythrocytes after PDT of chicken comb.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac36" novelty="None" advantage="None">These examples show that erythrocytes may be part of a mechanism inducing necrosis in tumours by blocking the vasculature.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit46 cit47 cit48">46–48</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac37" novelty="None" advantage="None">Erythrocyte aggregation might be triggered by a mechanism discussed in the section ‘Red blood cells as model cells in experimental PDT research’ or by photodamage to endothelial cells leading to release of clotting factors.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit49">49</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac38" novelty="None" advantage="None">The latter mechanism is similar to the first mentioned one.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit50">50</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The problem of unwanted photodamage to erythrocytes after systemic application of a photosensitiser could be avoided by using highly tissue specific photosensitisers or by application of third generation photosensitisers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="New" advantage="None">These are derivatives of second generation photosensitisers introduced into or attached to chemical devices.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="None" advantage="Yes">This modification increases the biological specificity to deliver photosensitisers to a defined cell type.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, photodamage of the erythrocyte during the transit of the photosensitiser can be avoided or at least significantly reduced.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>The UV-A induced formation of bilirubin and its photodegradation</HEADER><P><s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">A photodynamic effect on erythrocytes occurs after UV-A irradiation <IT>in vitro</IT>: Erythrocytes, when irradiated with UV-A, turn fluorescent.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">A fluorescence imaging experiment showing this effect is provided in Fig. 2, parts A and B. Microscopic spectroscopy shows that the fluorescence is emitted at wavelengths between 440 and 740 nm with a maximum at 508 nm (Fig. 2, part C).</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Due to the biochemical decomposition of haemoglobin<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit51">51</REF> and the shape of the spectrum<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit52">52</REF> it seems obvious that the UV-A induced fluorescence in erythrocytes is caused by bilirubin type photoproducts of haemoglobin.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac39" novelty="None" advantage="None">There are two well described photodynamic effects of bilirubin:</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac40" novelty="None" advantage="None">(i) The photosensitising effect of bilirubin is described for <IT>in vitro</IT> systems.</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac41" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is an efficient photosensitiser in general<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit53 cit54">53,54</REF> and especially in erythrocytes.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit55">55</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac42" novelty="None" advantage="None">UV-A penetrates the skin down to the dermis.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit56">56</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, blood vessels, and hence erythrocytes, can receive UV-A irradiation when the skin is irradiated, for example in UV-A treated psoriasis-patients or during extensive sun-bathing.</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac43" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the clinical reports of erythrocyte damage after UV-A irradiation are missing.</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is most probably because of the short time window of the dermal passage of the erythrocytes that does not allow the generation of bilirubin and its photodynamic action.</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The situation seems to be different when bilirubin is already present in the blood (see below).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac44" novelty="None" advantage="None">(ii) <IT>In vivo</IT> photodegradation of bilirubin (not exclusively by UV-A, more prominent by blue light) is observed in jaundiced newborns.</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The phototherapy concept for newborns suffering from hyperbilirubinaemia<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit57">57</REF> is in accordance with Fig. 2 (parts A and B) showing a fast bilirubin photodegradation or conversion in non-fluorescent isoforms.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although the bilirubin in the newborns originates from erythrocytes,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit57">57</REF> the photodynamic effect on erythrocytes is limited.</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac45" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, it was shown that bilirubin is bound by human erythrocytes.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit58">58</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac46" novelty="None" advantage="None">There are clinical reports of photodynamic damage on erythrocytes after phototherapy.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit59 cit60">59,60</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac47" novelty="None" advantage="None">Such damage, namely the osmotic fragility, was confirmed in an animal model<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit61">61</REF> as well as <IT>in vitro.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit62">62</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac48" novelty="None" advantage="None">Bruzell<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit63">63</REF> recently reviewed the role of bilirubin in jaundice.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Red blood cells as model cells in experimental PDT research</HEADER><P><s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac49" novelty="None" advantage="None">Erythrocytes are popular model cells since they are easy to obtain in large numbers with minimal consequences for the donor.</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac50" novelty="None" advantage="None">They are the most easily available living cells from humans.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit64">64</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In connection with the action of photosensitisers they can be used as model cells, either intact or as erythrocyte ghosts (<IT>i.e.</IT> with the haemoglobin washed out, so that only the membrane and the cytoskeleton remain).</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Examples are given in Fig. 3 and 4.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 3 shows data for several tetraphenylporphyrins, which were studied with respect to their ability to accumulate in biological membranes retaining their photophysical properties.</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Fluorescence lifetimes in erythrocyte ghosts were measured and compared with the corresponding lifetimes in organic solvents.</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Part A shows the structural formula of unsubstituted tetraphenylporphyrin, a totally ‘flat’ molecule.</annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast, diethyltetraphenylporphyrin and tetraethyltetraphenylporphyrin (Fig. 3B) have a pronounced non-planar, three-dimensional structure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The data are derived from X-ray scattering experiments.</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, there were no differences in the magnitude of the fluorescence lifetimes (Fig. 3C) in the solvents compared to the ghosts.</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac51" novelty="None" advantage="None">The differences in fluorescence lifetimes among different dyes are due to a different bending of the dye molecules.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit65">65</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac52" novelty="None" advantage="None">The long fluorescence lifetimes of dyes incubated in erythrocyte ghosts show that mainly monomers accumulate in the erythrocyte membranes.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit66">66</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj11" novelty="New" advantage="None">Another application of erythrocyte ghosts as model membranes is related to the generation of singlet oxygen yield during photodynamic action.</annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac53" novelty="None" advantage="None">The generation of singlet oxygen during PDT is known at least since the 1960s.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit67 cit68">67,68</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac54" novelty="None" advantage="None">Later it was also shown to occur in red blood cells.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit69">69</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac55" novelty="None" advantage="None">Oelckers <IT>et al.</IT> were able to detect singlet oxygen luminescence from the inside of a membrane in erythrocyte ghosts.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit70">70</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">This was the first demonstration ever of singlet oxygen luminescence originating from inside a native membrane.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 4 shows structurally similar tetrapyrroles, zinc tetrabenzoporphine and zinc phthalocyanine (part A), confocal sections of erythrocytes loaded with the two dyes (part B) and the erythrocyte survival curves after incubation with zinc tetrabenzoporphine and zinc phthalocyanine and exposure to red light (part C).</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac56" novelty="None" advantage="None">Benzoporphyrin derivatives as well as zinc phthalocyanines are effective photosensitizers in cell cultures.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit71 cit72">71,72</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac57" novelty="None" advantage="None">In erythrocytes, zinc phthalocyanine is more efficient than zinc tetrabenzoporphine since the cell survival is reduced to 0.001 after 60 and 120 min irradiation, respectively.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit73">73</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Sometimes it is informative to combine erythrocyte ghost experiments and measurements on intact erythrocytes:<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit74">74</REF> To measure the accumulation of a dye (<IT>e.g.</IT> PP IX) in the membrane in intact red blood cells is difficult because of the presence of haemoglobin.</annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="None" advantage="Yes">However, such measurements are easy to carry out in erythrocyte ghosts.</annotationART></s> <s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">Accumulation of the photosensitiser during incubation can be followed in erythrocyte ghosts and cell survival can be monitored by measuring haemolysis (Fig. 4C).</annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac58" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, this practice is controversial.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit75">75</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Photodynamic damage to erythrocyte membranes starts with potassium release.</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Haemolysis just indicates disruption of the cell membrane.</annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac59" novelty="None" advantage="None">Ball <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit76">76</REF>. found that potassium release and haemoglobin release are just time shifted with respect to each other.</annotationART></s> <s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac60" novelty="None" advantage="None">This indicates that these processes are causally connected.</annotationART></s> <s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">In accordance with the common practice in cell-culture assays, where cell death is monitored by membrane disruption (staining and counting of either dead or living cells),<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit77">77</REF> haemolysis of red blood cells can be regarded as a mode of measuring death of red blood cells.</annotationART></s> <s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="None" advantage="Yes">Spectroscopic measurements of haemoglobin are much easier and faster to carry out than cell staining and counting.</annotationART></s> <s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is another advantage of using red blood cells for this type of investigations.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">The mechanisms behind the above mentioned release of potassium prior to erythrocyte haemolysis are unknown.</annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod12" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, we propose a mechanism related to an operation of a non-selective cation channel<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit78">78</REF> in the erythrocyte membrane.</annotationART></s> <s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod13" novelty="None" advantage="None">This channel is activated by oxidative stress,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit79">79</REF> so the generation of a highly reactive singlet oxygen triggers transport through this channel.</annotationART></s> <s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The channel is permeable to calcium.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit80">80</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hence a coupling of the non-selective cation channel and the Gardos channel could occur as proposed by Kaestner and Bernhardt.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit81">81</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Gardos channel would then realise the potassium efflux, which is seen after PDT of erythrocytes.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit76 cit82">76,82</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, calcium entry into erythrocytes would activate phospolipid scramblase and led to a disruption of the asymmetrical phospholipid distribution.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit83 cit84">83,84</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod18" novelty="None" advantage="None">This process might be the reason of the observed aggregation of erythrocytes after PDT.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit85">85</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Additionally, the activation of non-selective cation channels leads to sodium influx and hence to swelling of the erythrocytes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">This swelling, in connection with the altered membrane stability due to the asymmetrical phospholipid distribution breakdown, might be the cause of haemolysis of the erythrocytes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac61" novelty="None" advantage="None">Haemolysis is well described by a so called ‘colloid-osmotic’ model.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit86 cit87 cit88">86–88</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac62" novelty="None" advantage="None">The phenomenology of the kinetics of this process has been reviewed by Grossweiner.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit89">89</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="143"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod20" novelty="None" advantage="None">Activation of the non-selective cation channel causes, beside breakdown of phosphatidylserine asymmetry, membrane blebbing.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit90 cit91">90,91</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="144"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">These symptoms may be indications of apoptotic death.</annotationART></s> <s sid="145"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is in agreement with a proposed ‘suicidal mechanism’ for red blood cells.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit81">81</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="146"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod21" novelty="None" advantage="None">The mechanism is summarised in Fig. 5.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="147"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac63" novelty="None" advantage="None">Erythrocytes were believed to be a good cell model for screening new potential dyes for PDT.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit92">92</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="148"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac64" novelty="None" advantage="None">A phototoxicity test based on the use of erythrocytes (Photo-RBC test) was developed by Beiersdorf AG.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit93">93</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="149"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="Old" advantage="None">This test is based on photohaemolysis as well as on haemoglobin oxidation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="150"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac65" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, recent studies have shown that photosensitisers with similar behaviour <IT>in vivo</IT> were behaving totally different in erythrocytes, and that dyes, which are efficient in cell cultures, are ineffective in erythrocytes.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19 cit73">19,73</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="151"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac66" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although, the universality of the photohaemolysis part of the Photo-RBC test must be questioned, the quality of the test lies in the combination of haemolysis with met-haemoglobin formation,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit94 cit95">94,95</REF> which is known to occur during extensive exposure to sunlight as a result of photodynamic reactions<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit96">96</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Sterilisation of red blood cell concentrates</HEADER><P><s sid="152"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot3" novelty="None" advantage="None">One promising application of photosensitisation is sterilisation of red blood cell concentrates.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit97">97</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="153"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac67" novelty="None" advantage="None">Phthalocyanine ‘Pc 4’, a silicon based phthalocyanine {HOSiPc-OSi(CH<SB>3</SB>)<SB>2</SB>(CH<SB>2</SB>)<SB>3</SB>N(CH<SB>3</SB>)<SB>2</SB>} and its derivatives, is one of the sensitisers most widely used for this application.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit97">97</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="154"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac68" novelty="None" advantage="None">It has been shown that Pc 4 can sensitise photoinactivation of vesicular stomatitis virus,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit98">98</REF> malaria (<IT>plasmodium falciparum</IT>)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit99">99</REF> and even multiple forms of the human immunodeficiency virus.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit100">100</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="155"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac69" novelty="None" advantage="None">It has been claimed that the damage to the red blood cells (haemolysis) is just slightly above that of control cells.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit101">101</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="156"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac70" novelty="None" advantage="None">The problem of enhanced red blood cell aggregation after PDT can be avoided using a mixture of antioxidants, consisting of vitamin E, mannitol and glutathione.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit85">85</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="157"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac71" novelty="None" advantage="None">Haemolysis of red blood cells after incubation with Pc 4 and exposure to red light depends on a number of experimental parameters like presence of antioxidants, incubation time and delivery vehicle.</annotationART></s> <s sid="158"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac72" novelty="None" advantage="None">For example negatively charged liposomes as a delivery vehicle minimise its binding to erythrocytes while not reducing virus inactivation.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit102">102</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="159"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac73" novelty="None" advantage="None">After the treatment and three weeks of storage the haemolysis can be as high as 43%, but under other conditions less than 0.5%.</annotationART></s> <s sid="160"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac74" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is still at least three times higher than that in control samples.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18 cit103">18,103</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="161"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="Old" advantage="None">A way to protect erythrocytes from haemolysis during PDT is the use of compounds similar in structure to the photosensitiser but that are not photosensitisers under the treatment conditions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="162"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac75" novelty="None" advantage="None">For example, the use of quinacrine to prevent binding of dimethyl-methylene blue to erythrocytes.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit104">104</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="163"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met14" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Another type of protection is the addition of dipyridamole.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit105">105</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="164"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod22" novelty="None" advantage="None">It inhibits the ion transport across the band 3 protein.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit106">106</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="165"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met14" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">Fortunately, virus inactivation is not affected by dipyridamole.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit105">105</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="166"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met15" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Dipyridamole needs to be removed from the blood samples before they can be used for transfusion, since band 3 protein mediates the oxygen transport across the membrane.</annotationART></s> <s sid="167"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is also questionable whether malaria inactivation can be achieved, if the red cells are to be protected.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="168"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp9" novelty="None" advantage="None">PDT may affect lymphocytes in a blood sample.</annotationART></s> <s sid="169"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac76" novelty="None" advantage="None">One day after PDT with Pc 4, 32% of all types of lympocytes survived, while four days later this percentage had decreased to 8%.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit107">107</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="170"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac77" novelty="None" advantage="None">These values are similar to what is found for gamma irradiation (20 Gy) of erythrocyte concentrates.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit108">108</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="171"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, PDT of blood leads to comparable lymphocyte damage as other potential methods.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="172"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The problem of bacterial contamination of erythrocyte concentrates and blood components is rising.</annotationART></s> <s sid="173"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac78" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thionine, a demethylated derivative of methylene blue, was tested as a photosensitizer for bacterial decontamination.</annotationART></s> <s sid="174"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac79" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, PDT using thionine was strongly inhibited in the presence of plasma.</annotationART></s> <s sid="175"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac80" novelty="None" advantage="None">This could be overcome when the photodynamic treatment is followed by a small exposure to UV-B light (1 J cm<SP>−2</SP>).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit109">109</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="176"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac81" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition to the above mentioned dyes, a number of other dyes have been investigated for blood sterilisation: benzoporphyrin derivatives,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF> merocyanine 540,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit110">110</REF> methylene violet,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit111">111</REF> pheophorbide derivatives<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit112">112</REF> and dimethyl-methylene blue<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit105 cit111">105,111</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Future aspects</HEADER><P><s sid="177"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Little is expected to be achieved with respect to improvement of the treatment of EPP from erythrocyte related research.</annotationART></s> <s sid="178"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac82" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the gene encoding for ferrochelatase has been cloned,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit113">113</REF> gene therapy holds particular promise as a future therapy.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit114">114</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="179"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac83" novelty="None" advantage="None">In mouse models a long time cure by gene therapy<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit115 cit116">115,116</REF> as well as stem cell therapy<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit117">117</REF> has already been successfully performed.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="180"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">PDT, through its action on erythrocytes, offers an opportunity to block the microvasculature supplying the tumour, and hence might provide a universal method of tumour destruction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="181"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot5" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, to achieve selective control remains a problem and is certainly a target for future research.</annotationART></s> <s sid="182"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac84" novelty="None" advantage="None">The generation of fluorescent bilirubin upon UV-A irradiation of erythrocytes has little clinical impact but a significant importance in imaging techniques of erythrocytes<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit118">118</REF> since a number of convenient fluorophores (<IT>e.g.</IT> the calcium ionophores indo-1 and fura-2) require UV-A excitation.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit119">119</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="183"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">As mentioned in the cell model section, human erythrocytes are convenient models for studies of fundamental principles of PDT.</annotationART></s> <s sid="184"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met16" novelty="None" advantage="No">A disadvantage is their lack of cell organelles, especially mitochondria, because the metabolism of the mitochondria is essential for ALA-PDT as well as for induction of apoptosis with other forms of PDT.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit120">120</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="185"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac85" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fortunately, erythrocytes are available from warm-blooded animals, which contain mitochondria.</annotationART></s> <s sid="186"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac86" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is the case for avian erythrocytes,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit121">121</REF> which can be conveniently used for relevant PDT studies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="187"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac87" novelty="None" advantage="None">The first investigation on photodynamic effects on cell organelles of chicken erythrocytes has been published,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit122">122</REF> although it did not focus on mitochondria.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="188"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Apoptosis seems to be a promising field, also when using erythrocytes, because ‘apoptosis like’ behaviour has been detected in human red blood cells, as described in the section ‘Red blood cells as model cells in experimental PDT research’ (Fig. 5).</annotationART></s> <s sid="189"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The involvement of this mechanism in photodynamic damage needs to be further explored.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="190"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac88" novelty="None" advantage="None">PDT of erythrocyte concentrates aimed at blood sterilisation is still under investigation and waiting for clinical applications.</annotationART></s> <s sid="191"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac89" novelty="None" advantage="None">Concerning viral sterilisation, this method has to compete with agents that target the viral nucleic acids by irreversible modification<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit123 cit124">123,124</REF> that has been tested in animals<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit125 cit126">125,126</REF> and is already in clinical trials.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit127">127</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="192"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Nevertheless, blood decontamination by PDT may have a future for <IT>in vivo</IT> use.</annotationART></s> <s sid="193"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac90" novelty="None" advantage="None">In animal experiments chloroquine resistant malaria strains were found to be more sensitive to Pc 4 than a chloroquine-sensitive strain (preliminary results)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit99">99</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
