<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b405115g" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">First observation of the rotational spectrum of the bromomethyl radical, CH<SB>2</SB>Br</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The first high resolution rotational spectrum of the bromomethyl radical in the gas phase has been observed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None">The radical was produced in a fast flow system by hydrogen abstraction of CH<SB>3</SB>Br by Cl or F atoms obtained from a 2450 MHz microwave discharge in Cl<SB>2</SB> or in CF<SB>4</SB>, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rotational, quartic centrifugal distortion constants have been obtained as well as the electron spin–rotation interaction constants.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The small positive inertial defect, <IT>Δ</IT><SB>0</SB> = 0.032 amu Å<SP>2</SP> deduced from the rotational constants of the CH<SB>2</SB><SP>79</SP>Br species clearly indicates that the radical is planar in its ground vibronic state.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER /><P><s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">It has been well established that halogen atoms and radicals play an important role in catalytic reactions contributing in the stratospheric ozone destruction.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2 cit3 cit4">1–4</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In particular, many studies have been devoted to the role of chlorine.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6 cit7 cit8 cit9">5–9</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Until recently, the chemistry of bromine-containing molecules and the adverse impact of bromine on the atmosphere have received little attention although there has been accumulating evidence for more than two decades that reactive bromine is also involved in the depletion of the ozone layer.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10 cit11 cit12">10–12</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The concentration of bromine in the stratosphere is much lower than that of chlorine.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">However several studies have demonstrated that bromine is much more destructive to the stratospheric ozone than chlorine.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Indeed, Garcia and Solomon have recently reported that bromine could be up to 100 times more efficient than chlorine, on an atom-per-atom basis.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Methyl bromide is considered to be the major source of bromine in the atmosphere.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">CH<SB>3</SB>Br is released into the atmosphere from both natural and anthropogenic sources.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The main known removal process of this halomethane occurs <IT>via</IT> hydrogen abstraction by its reaction either with the hydroxyl radical or with chlorine, leading to the formation of the monobromomethyl radical, CH<SB>2</SB>Br.</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">This radical reacts further with other open shell species to release Br atoms for secondary reactions with ozone.</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The monobromomethyl radical is therefore a key transient for which it is essential to obtain accurate information from high-resolution spectroscopy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Such information is crucial to allow kinetic and photochemical laboratory studies in order to achieve a better understanding of the role played by bromomethane in the processes leading to the destruction of stratospheric ozone.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition to its importance in atmospheric chemistry, the study of CH<SB>2</SB>Br is also of importance in order to compare its structure with those of its well-studied fluorine- and chlorine-analogues, CH<SB>2</SB>F<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF> and CH<SB>2</SB>Cl.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17 cit18">17,18</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">These studies have revealed that CH<SB>2</SB>F is nearly planar whereas CH<SB>2</SB>Cl is planar, the difference being attributed to the larger electronegativity of fluorine.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">CH<SB>2</SB>Br was first detected in electron impact experiments with CH<SB>2</SB>Br<SB>2</SB>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19">19</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">An early matrix infrared study has suggested that this elusive species has a planar structure because of the large positive quartic term in the out-of-plane bending potential function.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">This conclusion was later supported by EPR investigations.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Davies <IT>et al.</IT> have recently reported the detection of this radical in the gas phase by far infrared laser magnetic resonance.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">They have also interpreted the spectra in terms of a planar structure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, recent <IT>ab initio</IT> calculations<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF> indicate that CH<SB>2</SB>Br is most probably very slightly non-planar, if not planar.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Depending on the structure, the ground electronic state is either <SP>2</SP>A' (non-planar) or <SP>2</SP>B<SB>1</SB> (planar).</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot4" novelty="None" advantage="None">This shows that the planarity still needs to be confirmed by high-resolution spectroscopic studies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, high quality ground state constants will make the analysis of vibrational or electronic spectra of this radical significantly easier, and identification of CH<SB>2</SB>Br in such experiments more definitive if the ground state constants agree to within error with the millimeter wave values.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this letter, we report the detection and the identification of the first high resolution rotational spectrum of CH<SB>2</SB>Br in the gas phase.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The millimeter wave (mmw) spectrometer used has been described in detail elsewhere.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">It was adapted for the production of the CH<SB>2</SB>Br radical.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Briefly, it consists of a single-pass absorption system comprising a tunable mmw source, an absorption cell and a detector.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The mmw radiation was obtained from two phase-locked backward wave oscillators, one emitting in the 160–260 GHz frequency region (Istok), the other one oscillating between 418–470 GHz (Thomson C.S.F.).</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The detection of the absorption signals was achieved with a helium-cooled InSb hot electrons bolometer (Q.M.C.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Instruments).</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">For improved sensitivity, source modulation at 70 kHz was used together with lock-in detection at twice this frequency, resulting in a second-derivative lineshape.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Frequency scanning, data acquisition, signal processing and frequency measurement were controlled using a PC; the errors on the frequency measurement were estimated to be less than 50 kHz.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="Old" advantage="None">CH<SB>2</SB>Br was generated in a fast flow system by hydrogen abstraction of monobromomethane by chlorine or fluorine.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The 1 m long absorption cell in Pyrex was equipped with a coil for creating a magnetic field to confirm that the detected lines were paramagnetic by on/off measurement.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="Old" advantage="None">At one end a vertical Pyrex crosspiece was used to connect to a partially choked diffusion pump below the cell and to a pressure gauge mounted above the cell.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="Old" advantage="None">At the other end, a horizontal Pyrex crosspiece was used to introduce CH<SB>3</SB>Br vapour and Cl<SB>2</SB> or CF<SB>4</SB> separately.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="None" advantage="Yes">This method allowed <IT>in situ</IT> production of the reactive species.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met14" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The outer end of each crosspiece was sealed by a Teflon window mounted at Brewster angle in order to improve transmission and to reduce standing waves.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Cl<SB>2</SB> diluted with He (2:100) or CF<SB>4</SB> mixed with Ar (CF<SB>4</SB>:Ar = 1:10) were used as a source for atomic chlorine or fluorine, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met15" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Cl or F atoms were produced by a microwave discharge in a small quartz tube placed at the entrance of the second crosspiece and surrounded by a cavity fed by radiation from a magnetron at 2450 MHz.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The power of the microwave discharge was kept as low as possible (≈20 W).</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The optimised partial pressure for CH<SB>3</SB>Br was 7 × 10<SP>−3</SP> mbar, and the total pressure was 1.5 × 10<SP>−2</SP> mbar.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Before initiating our search for the spectra, we decided to extend the measurement of the spectra of CH<SB>2</SB><SP>35</SP>Cl and CH<SB>2</SB><SP>37</SP>Cl (natural abundances: <SP>35</SP>Cl: 75.77%, <SP>37</SP>Cl: 24.23%) in the 418–470 GHz frequency region.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have used the molecular constants published by Endo <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF>. to predict the spectra falling within this range.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The analysis of the spectra is now in progress for publication.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The observation of the spectral lines of the monochloromethyl radical has allowed us to optimize the experimental conditions in order to maximize our chance to detect transitions of the bromomethyl radical.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In particular, we found that the use of Cl<SB>2</SB> led to a much clearer spectrum than the use of CF<SB>4</SB>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met16" novelty="New" advantage="None">We have afterwards guided our search for CH<SB>2</SB>Br according to the rotational constants deduced from the <IT>ab initio</IT> structure<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF> of this radical in the ground state together with the centrifugal distortion constants obtained for CH<SB>2</SB>Cl.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The calculated A, B and C rotational constants are listed in Table 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The <IT>ab initio</IT> B + C value of CH<SB>2</SB><SP>79</SP>Br, 22 304 MHz,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF> agrees with the value reported by Davies <IT>et al.</IT>, 22 305 MHz.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">More importantly, this group has also assigned the main rotational quantum number <IT>N</IT> = 20 ← 19 to the unresolved lines lying at 14.88 cm<SP>−1</SP> (446 091 MHz).</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">This frequency falls in a range where our spectrometer has its highest sensitivity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Bromine has two stable isotopes of nearly equal abundances (<SP>79</SP>Br: 50.69%, <SP>81</SP>Br: 49.31%).</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The spectra of the two isotopomers should then be detected with the same intensity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Assuming a planar structure, the dipole moment of CH<SB>2</SB>Br lies along the C<SB>2</SB> symmetry axis, which is the axis of the least moment of inertia.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The rotational spectrum should hence display the characteristic <IT>a</IT>-type pattern of a slightly asymmetric prolate rotor (<IT>κ</IT> = −0.996).</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, owing to the electron spin–rotation interaction, each rotational level is split into two, leading to a fine structure in the spectrum.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">As a first estimate of the fine splittings, we have used for the prediction the <IT>ε</IT><SB><IT>ii</IT></SB> constants of CH<SB>2</SB>Cl<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF> (see Table 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The two components of the <IT>N</IT> = 20 ← 19, <IT>K</IT><SB><IT>a</IT></SB> = 0 lines of CH<SB>2</SB><SP>79</SP>Br were predicted at 444597 and 444680 MHz.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The four <IT>K</IT><SB><IT>a</IT></SB> = 1 components were calculated to lie at 440736, 440772, 450320 and 450767 MHz.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The corresponding calculated set of transition frequencies for the CH<SB>2</SB><SP>81</SP>Br species was shifted to the lower frequencies by about 1600 ± 40 MHz.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">We then carried out the search for the <IT>N</IT> = 20 ← 19 lines of CH<SB>2</SB>Br by scanning the 439–452 GHz frequency range.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The observed spectrum appeared so congested that we proceeded in two steps: at first we scanned using the experimental conditions described above.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met17" novelty="New" advantage="None">Subsequently we repeated the measurement by applying a magnetic field along the cell in order to both distinguish only the transitions sensitive to a magnetic field and to eliminate the numerous and often strong absorption lines of CH<SB>3</SB>Br.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This procedure led to the detection of more than 40 unidentified paramagnetic lines, most of them lying in the 443–447 GHz frequency region.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">These lines could also be observed using CF<SB>4</SB> for the production of fluorine instead of chlorine, but they disappeared when CH<SB>3</SB>Br was replaced with CH<SB>3</SB>Cl.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">At this stage, the chemical tests and the comparison with the <IT>ab initio</IT> calculations support strongly the detection of the two isotopomers of CH<SB>2</SB>Br.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Moreover, the majority of the transitions appeared as partly resolved doublets or triplets, sometimes as singlets.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This hyperfine structure could be due to the nuclear spins of bromine (<IT>I</IT>(<SP>79</SP>Br) = <IT>I</IT>(<SP>81</SP>Br) = 3/2) and of hydrogen (<IT>I</IT>(H) = ½).</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">By comparison with the predictions, we were quickly able to recognize two sets of lines of nearly equal intensity, each set displaying an identical pattern.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The average difference between the transitions of these two sets is 1609 MHz, a value very close to the calculated one.</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">A stick spectrum of the detected lines is shown on Fig. 1.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the electron spin–rotation interaction led obviously to a strong mixing of the various <IT>K</IT><SB><IT>a</IT></SB> components.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">It was therefore not possible to readily recognize a typical <IT>a</IT>-type R branch pattern of a prolate asymmetric top, preventing us from assigning the spectrum.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have consequently extended the measurement in the lower frequency region in order to observe the various <IT>K</IT><SB><IT>a</IT></SB> components of the <IT>N</IT> = 19 ← 18 series, focusing our search on the <SP>79</SP>Br species.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">This led to the detection of 22 new paramagnetic lines in the 422–425 GHz frequency span.</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, some <IT>K</IT><SB><IT>a</IT></SB> = 1 lines for both <IT>N</IT> series and for the two isotopic species turned out to be difficult to detect because they fall in frequency regions where strong transitions of CH<SB>3</SB>Br were observed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">These lines were finally observed after a more careful search.</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">An example of a <IT>K</IT><SB><IT>a</IT></SB> = 1 transition obtained by using either chlorine or fluorine is given in Fig. 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">The observation of the <IT>K</IT><SB><IT>a</IT></SB> = 1 transitions proved to be decisive in the identification of the spectrum of CH<SB>2</SB><SP>79</SP>Br.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">Indeed, after several attempts, a least squares fit of the <IT>K</IT><SB><IT>a</IT></SB> = 0, 1 and 2 components of the <IT>N</IT> = 20 ← 19 and <IT>N</IT> = 19 ← 18 series of CH<SB>2</SB><SP>79</SP>Br allowed us to assign the <IT>K</IT><SB><IT>a</IT></SB> = 3–6 components successfully.</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">The <IT>K</IT><SB><IT>a</IT></SB> = 0 lines of CH<SB>2</SB><SP>79</SP>Br have been observed at 445248 and 445465 MHz.</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">The four <IT>K</IT><SB><IT>a</IT></SB> = 1 components lie at 441317, 441377, 450320 and 450767 MHz.</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">The identification of the spectrum of CH<SB>2</SB><SP>81</SP>Br was then straightforward.</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met18" novelty="New" advantage="None">Repeating this procedure eventually led to the measurement of 59 rotational lines for the CH<SB>2</SB><SP>79</SP>Br isotopic species corresponding to <IT>N</IT> = 9, 10 and 19 ≤ <IT>N</IT> ≤ 21, <IT>K</IT><SB><IT>a</IT></SB> ≤ 6 in the 160–470 GHz frequency range.</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the CH<SB>2</SB><SP>81</SP>Br isotopomer, only 42 transitions corresponding to <IT>N</IT> = 9, 10 and 19 ≤ <IT>N</IT> ≤ 21, <IT>K</IT><SB><IT>a</IT></SB> ≤ 6 have been measured.</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met19" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The average frequencies of the hyperfine components have been used for the fit.</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">These frequencies were fitted to a Watson A-reduced Hamiltonian in the I<SP>r</SP> representation.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25">25</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met20" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Predictions and fittings were made using Pickett's programs SPFIT and SPCAT.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26">26</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" advantage="None">The adjusted rotational, centrifugal distortion and fine structure constants for the two isotopic species are listed in Table 1 together with the CH<SB>2</SB><SP>35</SP>Cl parameters for comparison.</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None">The <IT>ab initio</IT> rotational constants are in good agreement with those obtained from the fit.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None">Moreover, the experimentally determined <IT>B</IT> + <IT>C</IT> value of CH<SB>2</SB><SP>79</SP>Br, 22327.3 MHz, is very close to the one reported by Davies <IT>et al.</IT> (22305 MHz).</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac20" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, this group has noticed when studying the radical by LMR spectroscopy that all <IT>K</IT><SB><IT>a</IT></SB> components except <IT>K</IT><SB><IT>a</IT></SB> = 1 are very closely spaced<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF> (within 0.16 cm<SP>−1</SP>, <IT>i.e.</IT> 4800 MHz approximately, for the <IT>N</IT> = 30 ← 29 transition).</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res29" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 1 shows that our identification confirms their observation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res30" novelty="None" advantage="None">The centrifugal distortion constants of CH<SB>2</SB>Br given in Table 1 are of the same order of magnitude than the ones of CH<SB>2</SB>Cl.</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" advantage="None">Their signs are also identical.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res32" novelty="None" advantage="None">Finally, the <IT>ε</IT><SB><IT>aa</IT></SB> spin–rotation interaction constant is about four times larger in CH<SB>2</SB>Br than in CH<SB>2</SB>Cl.</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac21" novelty="None" advantage="None">Such a difference was already observed between the CH<SB>2</SB>Cl and CH<SB>2</SB>F radicals.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res33" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fact that reaction of CH<SB>3</SB>Br with Cl or F atoms led to the observed transitions together with the relatively good agreement between the experimental and <IT>ab initio</IT><IT>A</IT>, <IT>B</IT> and <IT>C</IT> constants for both isotopic species enables us to ascertain that we have observed the rotational spectrum of the monobromomethyl radical.</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is the first high-resolution spectroscopic identification of this species.</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">Work directed toward the analysis of the hyperfine structure is in progress.</annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The small positive value of the inertial defect, <IT>Δ</IT><SB>0</SB> = 0.032 amu Å<SP>2</SP> proves the planarity of CH<SB>2</SB>Br in the ground vibronic state.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
