<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b405149a" hasDoc="yes" version="1153" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Electronic absorption spectrum and low-lying electronic states of Co<SB>2</SB> isolated in solid neon</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">We report electronic absorption spectra in the mid-, near infrared and visible regions for cobalt dimers isolated in neon matrices.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition to the already reported transition near 2.8 eV and above, ten states can be observed spanning a wide energy range from 0.068 to 2.49 eV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">For four excited states in the IR range and two states in the visible, analysis of the vibronic systems leads to estimates of electronic energies, vibrational parameters and bond length variations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The data are compared to results of photodetachment experiments and recent theoretical predictions.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Within the first row transition metal (TM) dimer series, Co<SB>2</SB> should occupy an intermediate position between mid-row elements where high bonding orders imply significant “3d–3d” contribution to the bonding, and Ni<SB>2</SB> or Cu<SB>2</SB>, which are described as primarily “4s–4s” bonded.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Co<SB>2</SB> is, however, certainly the least known of the first row series, as its electronic ground state has not yet been experimentally established, nor its bond length actually measured.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">A mass spectrometric study<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF> has yielded an estimate for the dissociation energy (1.69 ± 0.26 eV), but this value relied on many assumptions for the electronic and vibrational partition function.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Important information has been provided by the Co<SB>2</SB><SP>−</SP> photodetachment study of Leopold and Lineberger,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">2</REF> the main points being ground state frequencies for Co<SB>2</SB> and Co<SB>2</SB><SP>−</SP> of 280 ± 20 cm<SP>−1</SP> and 240 ± 15 cm<SP>−1</SP>, respectively, and features indicative of excited states of Co<SB>2</SB> some 600 and 5000 cm<SP>−1</SP> above the ground state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Optical studies on Co<SB>2</SB> isolated in cryogenic matrices have evidenced strong UV absorptions near 270–280 nm and 340 nm, as well as a much weaker feature centered around 442 nm.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">All these electronic transitions appeared to be broad and structureless.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Next, Dong <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF>. using mass-selection/reneutralization of Co<SB>2</SB><SP>+</SP>confirmed the assignment to Co<SB>2</SB> isolated in solid argon of a broad, unstructured absorption extending from 425 to 485 nm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">More important, they obtained Raman progressions, using excitations in the 458–488 nm range, yielding <IT>ω</IT><SB>e</SB> = 296.8 ± 5.4 cm<SP>−1</SP>, <IT>ω</IT><SB>e</SB><IT>x</IT><SB>e</SB> = 2.2 ± 0.8 cm<SP>−1</SP> for the ground state, in agreement with the preceding gas phase measurement.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">2</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast, theoretical studies are numerous and their results conflicting.</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">An <IT>ab initio</IT> HF-CI study by Shim and Gingerich<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF> first predicted a <SP>5</SP>Σ+g ground state, with a very long <IT>r</IT><SB>e</SB> = 2.56 Å, and a very low vibrational frequency, <IT>ω</IT><SB>e</SB> = 162 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Several DFT studies have been performed, and differ in their conclusions regarding the ground state nature, suggesting either a <SP>5</SP>Δ<SB>g</SB> or a <SP>5</SP>Σ ground state.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6 cit7 cit8 cit9 cit10 cit11 cit12">6–12</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Barden <IT>et al.</IT> warn in their systematic study of TM dimers<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF> that many states with different electron configurations and spin multiplicities lie very close, thus the predicted ground state depends very much on the method used, which indicates the necessity for multi reference <IT>ab initio</IT> calculations for a correct approximation of the electronic wavefunction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">In absence of these, Gutsev <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF>. and Gutsev and Bauschlicher<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF> have used various DFT methods to predict energies, bond lengths, magnetic moments and vibrational frequencies for neutral and charged Co<SB>2</SB><SP>−</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">These DFT studies predict a <SP>5</SP>Δ<SB>g</SB> ground state with a relatively short bond length (1.98 Å), but the vibrational frequency (<IT>ω</IT><SB>e</SB> = 386–364 cm<SP>−1</SP>, depending on the functional used), and the dissociation energies (<IT>D</IT><SB>0</SB> = 2.51–2.24 eV) are well above the experimental values. <SP>5</SP>Σ−u and <SP>5</SP>Σ+g states of the same multiplicities were calculated 0.23 and 0.84 eV above the ground state and five other states of different multiplicities were also predicted to lie within 1 eV of the ground state, which underlines the high density of states presumable for Co<SB>2</SB>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Ideally, spectroscopic investigations of transition metal diatomics are best carried out in the gas phase, where rotationally resolved fluorescence<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF> or two-photon resonant ionization schemes,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF> as developed by Morse and coworkers, can bring precise knowledge concerning bond length electronic structure or even dissociation energy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In absence of these, careful matrix-isolation studies can nevertheless help in providing an overview of energies and relative intensities for a number of electronic and vibrational transitions spanning a broad spectral range.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">These studies are best performed in solid neon, a less perturbing and polarizing medium than the heavier rare gases, and where electronic transitions are shifted by less than 1% in most cases.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the course of investigations of the reactivity of cobalt atoms and dimers, we were able to isolate large quantities of Co<SB>2</SB> molecules in solid neon, and correlate several unreported electronic transitions to this molecule.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results of the present study allow for a more detailed insight into some of the low-lying electronic states of Co<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Experimental</HEADER><P><s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The experimental set-up has been described previously in detail.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Briefly, Co<SB>2</SB> molecules were prepared by co-condensing Co vapor and 77 K-precooled, high purity neon or argon (Air Liquide, France; 99,995%), onto one of six flat, Rh-plated copper mirrors maintained at less than 3 K using a pulse tube closed-cycle cryogenerator (Cryomech PT405, USA).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The metal atom source was enclosed inside another liquid nitrogen trap minimizing greatly the thermal radiation and outgassing impurities.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">A tungsten filament, wetted with Co (Alfa Aesar, Germany, 99.995%), was heated to 1400–1600 °C generating the metal vapor.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The metal deposition rate was monitored with the aid of a quartz microbalance and varied from 1 to 20 nmol min<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">For most samples, this corresponded to 50–1000 ppm Co/Ne molar ratios.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Absorption spectra were recorded between 30 000 and 80 cm<SP>−1</SP> on the same samples using a Bruker 120 FT spectrometer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">CaF<SB>2</SB>, CsI and polyethylene wedged windows were mounted on a rotatable flange separating the interferometer vacuum (10<SP>−3</SP> mbar) from that of the cryostatic cell (10<SP>−8</SP> mbar).</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the far IR, (80–500 cm<SP>−1</SP>) a globar (Si-C) was used, with a composite beamsplitter, a polyethylene window and a He-cooled Si–B bolometer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp9" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the mid-IR region (500–5000 cm<SP>−1</SP>), a Ge/KBr beamsplitter with a CsI window was used along with a liquid N<SB>2</SB>-cooled narrow band HgCdTe photoconductor.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp10" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the near IR (4500–9000 cm<SP>−1</SP>), a tungsten filament source, Si/CaF<SB>2</SB> beamsplitter and CaF<SB>2</SB> window, liquid N<SB>2</SB>-cooled InSb or room temperature InGaAs photodiodes were used.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Finally, for the 9000–16 000 cm<SP>−1</SP> and 15 000–30 000 cm<SP>−1</SP> visible regions, spectra were acquired using TiO<SB>2</SB>/Quartz beamsplitters, blue-or red-enhanced Si photodiode and either a W-filament or a Xe short arc source in combination with Schott BG38 or VG9 colored glass filters.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The resolution was varied from 0.05 cm<SP>−1</SP> to 1 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Selective excitations were performed for 10 to 40 min with a 200 W HgXe arc lamp using narrow (10 nm band width) bandpass interference filters, and focussed on the 10 mm target.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Irradiances were measured with an optical power meter, and were of the order of 7, 3, 7, 18 and 14 mW cm<SP>−2</SP> for 10 nm bands centered at 280, 365, 405, 435 and 546 nm, respectively.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Results</HEADER><P><s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp15" novelty="None" advantage="None">More than fifteen samples were grown, co-depositing Co atoms and precooled Ne or Ar gas with varying metal/rare gas molar ratios, deposit temperature and thickness.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">We optimized the conditions in order to grow half a millimetre-thick, yet highly diluted samples (from 50 to 500 ppm Co/Ne).</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Under these conditions, samples are almost completely absorbing in the UV range and the reported weak optical absorption for Co<SB>2</SB> in argon near 445 nm (22 500 cm<SP>−1</SP>)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3 cit4">3,4</REF> dominates the spectrum.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Even in solid neon, it remains very broad and without clear structure (Fig. 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">At lower energies, however, several weaker, new band systems appear, labelled from A to J in order of increasing energy (Fig. 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Their intensities varied always consistently when changing either the Co concentration or the matrix temperature, as well as upon selective photoexcitations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In neon the best samples were obtained depositing at relatively high concentration (250 to 500 ppm Co in Ne) at the lowest temperature achievable (2.8 to 3 K).</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">When performing careful concentration effects, it was found that all these absorptions grew with a second order dependence with respect to the cobalt concentration at low values (50 to 200 ppm), but the growth rate with respect to concentration leveled off at higher Co/Ne ratios.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Higher concentrations (500 ppm or more) or elevated deposition temperatures did not increase much the product yield, due to formation of higher clusters, as will be discussed below.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the visible range, weaker absorptions can be detected in the green and red, which cannot be so distinctly observed in argon.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">First, on the low energy side of the broad blue band appear two much weaker vibronic (I,J) systems with ≈10 cm<SP>−1</SP> line widths and onsets near 19 640 and 20 077 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Second, three relatively intense absorptions (F, G, H) appear to the red with drastically larger line widths (210 to 250 cm<SP>−1</SP>) compared to the I and J systems.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the infrared, several band systems can be observed, C, D and E spanning from about 2800 to 9000 cm<SP>−1</SP>, with varying line widths (2 to 6 cm<SP>−1</SP>) and also rather different relative intensities.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Next, a relatively intense but short progression (B) is found at lower energy with three components near 894, 1171 and 1446 cm<SP>−1</SP>, and last, a very weak but quite narrow absorption (A) is isolated near 551 cm<SP>−1</SP>, at the far infrared edge.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">No other absorption correlable to this species was found down to 80 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In solid argon, only the most intense band systems can be observed, and at slightly differing frequencies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">In general, observation is more difficult in argon, the bands being broader and the matrix medium more scattering in the near infrared and visible ranges.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Increasing the deposition temperature above 18 K helped the transparency, but intensities of all features that we correlate to Co<SB>2</SB> decreased.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">In both media, increasing the concentration led to growth of additional features (such as a weak band near 995 cm<SP>−1</SP>) which we can relate to larger Co<SB><IT>n</IT></SB> clusters.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition to systematic concentration studies, we checked that none of these absorptions could be due to reactions of Co with residual vacuum impurities (H<SB>2</SB>, H<SB>2</SB>O, N<SB>2</SB>, O<SB>2</SB>, CO<SB>2</SB>) by growing samples with added small amounts (500 ppm) with no other result than appearance of reaction products and decrease of the Co<SB>2</SB> bands.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">While adding 500 ppm of O<SB>2</SB>, the formation of Co<SB>2</SB>O<SB>2</SB> was observed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">When changing the Co/Ne concentration at constant O<SB>2</SB> content, we checked that the bands here reported for Co<SB>2</SB> electronic absorptions kept the same second order Co dependence than known Co<SB>2</SB>O<SB>2</SB> bands,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF> thus confirming that both species contains two Co atoms.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Ozin and Hanlan<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF> observed the progressive “bleaching” of the Co<SB>2</SB> UV bands upon 270 nm selective irradiation and concomitant growth of Co atomic absorptions, implying that the molecule reaches from the upper state a rapidly dissociating channel and produces back Co atoms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Also, Dong <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF>. failed to obtain resonance Raman signals when using 364 nm UV excitation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">This prompted us to perform UV excitation in these domains, while monitoring changes in the lower energy band systems, in order to check that all these absorptions are due to that same species.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Indeed, marked effects were observed, which are typified in Fig. 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac20" novelty="None" advantage="None">All bands presented a partly resolved structure, which is likely due to well-known matrix trapping site effects, as the less stable matrix sites could be annealed out by cycling the solid neon temperature up to 10 K and back (Fig. 2).</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Photoexcitations in the F band system at 580 nm or in the reported Co<SB>2</SB> absorptions at 435 or 405 nm caused a rearrangement between trapping sites or a small decrease in all band systems.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">All the reported band systems can be partially restored by cycling the matrix temperature up to 9 to 10 K to allow atomic diffusion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">More energetic excitation in the deeper UV range at 365, 280 or 265 nm caused progressive bleaching of all band systems reported here, which could again be partially restored, following temperature cycling and, presumably, atomic recombination.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">All other species detected in our samples by minor absorption bands did not present that specific behavior, and this confirms assignment of the new bands to the same species, identified previously as Co<SB>2</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Table 1 reports frequencies observed for all the new band systems in neon, along with relative integrated intensities for each system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">For the sake of simplicity, we have only retained the values observed for the most stable trapping site, which remains after complete annealing at 11 K. Note that after careful annealing, all bands appear narrower, but present an additional more or less resolved finer triplet substructure (3 to 0.2 cm<SP>−1</SP> splittings) for the stable trapping site.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">This structure did not appear to change from one sample to the next, nor following further annealing.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">Frequencies reported in Table 1 pertain to the central component of this structure.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Discussion</HEADER><P><s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The new transitions observed for Co<SB>2</SB> differ widely in energy, vibrational parameters and relative intensities.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In absence of rotationally resolved, gas-phase data, assignment of the different electronic states can only rely on comparison with theoretical predictions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">To facilitate such comparisons, it is necessary to analyze each spectral region and extract energies and spectroscopic parameters providing clues for future state identification.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">The narrow absorption at 551 cm<SP>−1</SP> does not fit into any regular pattern with bands observed in the same energy range, and is much narrower than the absorptions near 893 cm<SP>−1</SP> and above (about 0.15 <IT>versus</IT> some 3.5 cm<SP>−1</SP> for each triplet component, as observed after annealing).</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" advantage="None">It thus seems likely to correspond to an isolated A–X (0, 0) vibronic band for an electronic transition of much lower probability (Δ<IT>Λ</IT> ≠ 0, 1 or even Δ<IT>S</IT> ≠ 0), with state A corresponding to a very low-lying state with an equilibrium distance very close to that of the ground state, as indicated by the lack of observation of (1, 0) component.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None">The next three bands fall into a regular progression, with monotonically decreasing intensities, and energies can be well reproduced with parameters <IT>T</IT><SB>e</SB> = 901 ± 3 cm<SP>−1</SP>, <IT>ω</IT><SB>e</SB> = 280.6 ± 1.3 and <IT>ω</IT><SB>e</SB><IT>x</IT><SB>e</SB> = 1.5 ± 0.5 cm<SP>−1</SP> for upper state B. The harmonic frequency is about 15 cm<SP>−1</SP> smaller than the ground state value, as reported by Dong <IT>et al.</IT> from their Raman study in solid argon,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF> which is consistent with a slightly elongated bond length.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">To quantify this effect, we have simulated the expected intensity pattern using well-known procedure for computation of the Franck–Condon factors,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF> supposing Morse potentials for ground and excited states with the parameters derived from spectroscopic measurements, and varying stepwise the bond length variation (Fig. 3).</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None">Following this approximation, one would estimate a bond lengthening of the order of 4.5 ± 1 pm.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The next band series spread between 2837 and 9000 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">A close inspection reveals however, that these 33 bands can be grouped in a straightforward manner into three interleaved vibronic progressions, presenting no obvious sign of mutual perturbation, and analyzed as due to three systems C–X (<IT>n</IT>,0) with <IT>n</IT> = 0 to 3, D–X (<IT>n</IT>,0) <IT>n</IT> = 0 to 8 and E–X (<IT>n</IT>,0) <IT>n</IT> = 0 to 19, and the transition energies reproduced with the spectroscopic parameters reported in Table 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that the electronic energies are gradually increasing from C to E, but the vibrational frequency for the upper state E is slightly larger (257 cm<SP>−1</SP>) than for states C or D (246.4 and 251.7 cm<SP>−1</SP>, respectively).</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res29" novelty="None" advantage="None">Nevertheless, differences in relative intensities within the progressions indicate substantial changes of the Franck–Condon factors, compatible with progressively increasing bond lengths.</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Following the same procedure as described above, simulations based on Morse potentials are proposed in Fig. 4, with bond lengthenings (7, 15 and 22 ± 2 pm) giving the best overall agreement on relative intensities within each band system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">These estimates should be regarded as only indicative, as the molecular potentials depart obviously from Morse-type functions at large vibrational excitations (see for instance the larger intensity of bands with <IT>v</IT>′ &gt; 12 for system E ← X).</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">For system E, bands with high vibrational quanta in the upper state give also sign of broadening (fwhm ≈ 6 cm<SP>−1</SP>), but nevertheless remain well-defined in comparison to absorptions in the visible range.</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res30" novelty="None" advantage="None">From relative intensity considerations and comparisons with results recently obtained with other transition metal diatomics,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19">19</REF> it appears likely that transitions from ground to B, C and E states are fully allowed, but that to state D seems less probable.</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac21" novelty="None" advantage="None">Recently, Jules and Lombardi<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF> have extended to transition dimers empirical rules correlating force constants and equilibrium internuclear distances, such as Badger’s or Pauling’s rules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is interesting to note that Pauling’s relationship, reported to be the most successful, would predict, for the excited state B bond lengthening, of 5.1 pm <IT>vs.</IT> 4.5 ± 1 estimated here, or 8 ± 2 pm for the state observed near 600 cm<SP>−1</SP> in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">ref. 2</REF> and here, in acceptable agreement.</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res32" novelty="None" advantage="None">For states C, D and E, however, the same rule would predict internuclear distance changes of 16.5, 14.6 and 12.7 pm, quite different from what is estimated here (7, 15 and 22 ± 2 pm, respectively).</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac22" novelty="None" advantage="None">Other cases of departure of Badger-type empirical rules have been discussed for excited states of TM metal dimers, such as for Re<SB>2</SB>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res33" novelty="None" advantage="None">Absorptions corresponding to systems F, G and H in the visible are intense and almost two orders of magnitude broader than the IR systems, recorded in the same experimental conditions and even after careful annealing.</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res34" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is indicative of a strongly allowed character for these transitions and of very short lifetimes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res35" novelty="None" advantage="None">Due to their large homogeneous line widths and close proximity, detection of vibrational structure is difficult for F and G, although shoulders are detectable for both.</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res36" novelty="None" advantage="None">For H, the homogeneous line width is slightly smaller (fwhm ≈ 230 cm<SP>−1</SP>) and two shoulders are detectable, which might represent a vibronic structure with <IT>ω</IT><SB>e</SB> ≈ 265 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res37" novelty="None" advantage="None">The two next transitions, with origins near 20 000 cm<SP>−1</SP> are again much weaker but sharper, at least near their onsets.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 5 compares the experimental data with simulation based again on Morse potentials, derived from the parameters presented in Table 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res38" novelty="None" advantage="None">The data are consistent with states with less elongated bond distances and relatively higher vibrational frequencies than states D and E. Note that after 20 750 cm<SP>−1</SP>, bands in both systems I and J (corresponding to <IT>v</IT>′ = 4 and 3, respectively) appear to broaden abruptly, and to progressively blend into the broad, intense absorption centered at 22 200 cm<SP>−1</SP>, observed previously.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3 cit4">3,4</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">Two points seem interesting to discuss in relation to previous gas phase studies of transition metal diatomics.</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None">First the change in line widths between the IR band systems A to D situated below 1.1 eV, and the systems in the visible range, for which the progressive disappearance of any vibronic structure is conspicuous.</annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac23" novelty="None" advantage="None">Most of the accurate data on transition metal diatomics is obtained using two photon ionization schemes of jet-cooled molecules, these techniques yield rotationally resolved absorption data in bound excited states.</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac23" novelty="None" advantage="None">It also enables observation of abrupt changes in excited state lifetimes<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF> or drop in ionization signal<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF> as soon as the excitation energy exceeds the molecular binding energy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac24" novelty="None" advantage="None">The underlying basis is that, for this type of molecule, the density of excited states is very high, and, whenever above the binding energy, an excitation can no longer be considered as occurring to a single potential surface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Mixing of bound and dissociative states leads to rapid predissociation as soon as excitation energy exceeds that of the separated atoms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">For molecules trapped in inert solids, this should translate into an abrupt decrease in excited state lifetimes and dramatic increase of the absorption widths blurring the vibronic structure, because of the large interaction with the matrix cage.</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac25" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is what has been observed for dimer absorptions in domain slightly above the binding energy for instance with Cu<SB>2</SB><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23 cit24">23,24</REF> or Ti<SB>2</SB>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25">25</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">If excitation energies are much in excess, then it can no longer be dissipated in the neon matrix lattice and opening of the matrix cage may lead to dissociation as well.</annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res39" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is clearly what sets in with 405 nm excitation or happens rapidly with 365 or 280 nm excitations, while part of the molecules can be reformed following atomic diffusion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res40" novelty="None" advantage="None">Given the estimated low binding energy of Co<SB>2</SB> (1.7 ± 0.25 eV),<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF> the observation of band systems I and J with well-defined and relatively sharp vibronic structures at energies up to 2.56 eV is thus surprising.</annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This suggests either that some excited states still relatively inefficiently couple to dissociative channels, or that the binding energy is larger than previously thought.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res41" novelty="None" advantage="None">Secondly, a parallel between the excited states at 600 and 5000 ± 50 cm<SP>−1</SP> of Co<SB>2</SB> observed in the Co<SB>2</SB><SP>−</SP> photodetachment spectrum<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">2</REF> and those observed here in solid neon at 551 and 4450 cm<SP>−1</SP> comes to mind.</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac26" novelty="None" advantage="None">Leopold and Lineberger<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26">26</REF> discuss their results concerning electron photodetachment of Fe<SB>2</SB><SP>−</SP> and Co<SB>2</SB><SP>−</SP> in terms of detachment of the least bound electron from a (3d)<SP><IT>n</IT></SP>(4s)<SP>2</SP> configuration of the anion toward two states of the neutral with (3d)<SP><IT>n</IT></SP>(4sσ<SB>g</SB>)<SP>2</SP> (4sσ<SB>u</SB>) configurations, the 4sσ<SB>u</SB> unpaired electron being either low or high spin–coupled to the d electrons.</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res42" novelty="None" advantage="None">For Co<SB>2</SB>, this would thus imply a (3d)<SP>15</SP>(4sσ<SB>g</SB>)<SP>2</SP>(4sσ<SB>u</SB>) ground state configuration (high spin) with a lower spin excited state 600 cm<SP>−1</SP> above.</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Based on intensity considerations, it was also advanced that the upper states near 5000 cm<SP>−1</SP> should have a bond length differing substantially from that of the anion, and perhaps arise from electron photodetachment from orbitals of different atomic parentage, thus involving a different configuration of the bonding d electrons.</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res43" novelty="None" advantage="None">The very different overall intensities and Franck–Condon factors observed for A–X and E–X transitions are consistent with this picture.</annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res44" novelty="None" advantage="None">The 551 cm<SP>−1</SP> transition is very sharp and weak, indicative of a low-probability transition, consistent with a long-lived upper state of different spin multiplicity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res45" novelty="None" advantage="None">The E-X band system centered around 5700 cm<SP>−1</SP> clearly corresponds to an upper state with an elongated bond length, and its intensity is suggestive of an allowed, Δ<IT>Λ</IT> = 0, ±1, Δ<IT>S</IT> = 0 transition.</annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res46" novelty="None" advantage="None">Assignments proposed on the basis of DFT results by Gutsev and Khanna<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF> of the ground and first excited states to the <SP>5</SP>Δ<SB>g</SB> and <SP>5</SP>Σ<SB>u</SB> states (0.23 eV separation with 382 and 328 cm<SP>−1</SP> harmonic frequencies and 198 and 212 pm bond length, respectively) do not seem consistent with our observations in solid neon.</annotationART></s> <s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res47" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that the first two states in these calculations correspond to (3d)<SP>16</SP>(4sσ<SB>g</SB>)<SP>2</SP> electronic configurations, different from those suggested on account of photodetachment spectra.</annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res48" novelty="None" advantage="None">Many more states can be expected even at low energy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In view of the great complexity of the electronic structure in transition metal molecules, and the disparity between experimental results and conclusions drawn from single determinant calculations,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10 cit11 cit12">10–12</REF> it seems that careful theoretical studies using multi reference configuration interaction methods such as those developed recently for Fe<SB>2</SB><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit27">27</REF> are very much needed to improve our understanding of the cobalt dimer.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
