<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b406562j" hasDoc="yes" version="1168" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">The importance of being tetrahedral: the cadmium pyramids Cd<SB><IT>N</IT></SB>; <IT>N</IT> = 4, 10, 20, 35 and 56<XREF TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" /></annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Using quasirelativistic density functional theory, we show the surprising stability of the tetrahedral cadmium pyramids Cd<SB>4,</SB> Cd<SB>10</SB>, Cd<SB>20</SB>, Cd<SB>35</SB> and Cd<SB>56</SB>.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER /><P><s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">While gold clusters Au<SB><IT>N</IT></SB>, up to <IT>N</IT> = 13 appear to be planar,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF> and those with <IT>N</IT> up to 19 have low-symmetry three-dimensional structures, Au<SB>20</SB> was recently found to be tetrahedral.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">2</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Actually, 20 is one of the “magic numbers” 8, 20, 40, 70 and 112 for electrons in a tetrahedron,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF> stabilised by both electronic and atomic shell structure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the divalent Group-12 elements Zn and Cd, with two valence electrons per atom, anomalously strong abundance peaks are found for clusters of 6, 10, 18, 20, 28, 30, 32, 35, 40, 41, 46, 54, 57, 60 and 69 atoms.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit5">4,5</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The peaks for Cd<SB><IT>N</IT></SB> with <IT>N</IT> = 10, 20 and 35 are very pronounced.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">While other than tetrahedral magic numbers occur, we here study the question whether the systems with the tetrahedral magic numbers are actually tetrahedral.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Strong alternative possibilities are amorphous or low-symmetry structures, which, using interatomic model potentials, have been found to be highly favoured by especially Au, Zn and Cd clusters.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6 cit7 cit8">6–8</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In an extensive pair-potential study of Zn and Cd clusters of up to 125 atoms, Doye<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF> found that only Zn<SB>4</SB> and Cd<SB>4</SB> possessed tetrahedral symmetry.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">All the other potentially tetrahedral pyramids M<SB><IT>N</IT></SB>; <IT>N</IT> = 10, 20, 35, 56, 84 and 120, were assigned low or no-symmetry global minima.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">As noted by Doye,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF> the pair-potential used, being fitted to the bulk metal, is not expected to be optimal for small cluster sizes.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None">Here we present a reinvestigation of the smallest zinc and cadmium pyramids, using rigorous quantum chemical methodology.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The calculations were performed with the Turbomole program package, version 56<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF>. at the density functional theory (DFT) level, using the non-empirical PBE functional.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">We used Turbomole’s standard triple-zeta quality basis sets including an f-polarization function, TZVPP, and the resolution of the identity density-fitting approximation.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Stuttgart effective core potential<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF> modelled the scalar relativistic effects of cadmium.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">To study the stability of the pyramids, we first optimised the molecular structures of the species using <IT>T</IT><SB>d</SB> symmetry.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The structures of the optimised Cd-pyramids are shown in Fig. 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">After optimisation, a frequency analysis was carried out to ensure a local minimum on the potential energy surface (PES).</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Some calculated properties are tabulated in Table 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">It can be seen that both zinc and cadmium clusters exhibit clear trends for most of the properties presented.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The energy gap between the highest occupied molecular orbital (HOMO) and the lowest unoccupied molecular orbital (LUMO), an important stability factor, is, as expected, seen to decrease with increasing cluster size.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the two smallest pyramids, Zn and Cd are seen to have similar gaps, but after that, the spacings between the frontier orbitals of the Cd pyramids are larger than those of the corresponding Zn species.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The pyramidal forms always have a larger gap than the lower symmetry isomers, this difference being larger for Cd.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reasonable HOMO–LUMO gap of especially the smaller cluster sizes does not of course mean that they are energetically the most favourable structures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">For comparison, we also reoptimised the structures of <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">ref. 8</REF><SUP TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn2" /> at DFT level, imposing the suggested symmetry.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The energy difference between the <IT>T</IT><SB>d</SB> symmetric isomers and the more disordered isomers is denoted by Δ<IT>E</IT><SB>Gupta</SB> in Table 1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The energy order of the Zn clusters is as expected and predicted before; the tetrahedra lie higher in energy for <IT>N</IT> &gt; 4 and the energy difference increases with cluster size.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The cadmium clusters, on the other hand, show a markedly different behaviour.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">For Cd, the tetrahedra are favoured over the low-symmetry alternatives for Cd<SB>10</SB> and Cd<SB>20</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore; the <IT>T</IT><SB>d</SB>-structures of Cd<SB>35</SB> and Cd<SB>56</SB> are only moderately destabilised with respect to the disordered structures of .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">ref. 8</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">To further establish the stability of the pyramidal Cd<SB>10</SB> and Cd<SB>20</SB>, the low-symmetry isomers were allowed to relax to even lower symmetry.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">For Cd<SB>10</SB>, this led to a change to <IT>C</IT><SB>3v</SB>-symmetry and a stabilisation of the higher-lying, low-symmetry conformer by 7 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The symmetry of Cd<SB>20</SB> was lowered to <IT>C</IT><SB>s</SB> and the energy difference fell by 16 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>, from 50 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> to 34 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The cadmium pyramids have large planar surfaces.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">As the surface atoms have fewer bonding partners than atoms in a more contracted, amorphous structure, higher energies could be expected.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the other hand, in solid Zn and Cd, the <IT>c</IT>/<IT>a</IT> ratio is anomalously large.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ultimate reason for this trend does not seem to be well established.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">A given atom prefers to have six nearest neighbours in a hexagonal lattice, and six others, further away in the two neighbouring planes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">As seen from Fig. 1, this is exactly what the present tetrahedra strive to do, visibly buckling outwards.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Also, as noted before,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF> in order to increase their coordination number, the surface atoms tend to contract their bond lengths.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The shortest bonds in the pyramids are indeed found between surface atoms, the bond length systematically decreasing with pyramid size, as seen in Table 1.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Especially striking is the stability of the tetrahedral Cd<SB>20</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Here we have to point out that no rigorous conformer search for Cd<SB>20</SB> has been performed, so only an upper limit for the energy difference between full and lesser order has been obtained.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None"><IT>A priori</IT>, nothing prevents a conformer even lower in energy than the pyramid from existing.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">We believe this to be unlikely, however, at least at the level of theory used in this work.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Comparing Cd<SB>20</SB> with the Au<SB>20</SB> cluster of Li <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">2</REF>. reveals many similarities; the most stable structure of both seems to be a tetrahedral pyramid, they both fulfil a “magic number” electron-shell closing rule for their suggested potentials, their HOMO–LUMO gap is nearly identical and both have previously been assigned disordered minima.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Why are the small Cd pyramids so stable?</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The stability goes against the paradigm of Soler <IT>et al</IT>.,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF> stating that the tendency for amorphisation should increase downwards (and to the right) in the periodic table.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">One difference between Zn and Cd is that relativistic effects are more important for cadmium.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">To check this, we performed a single point all-electron,<SUP TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn3" /> non-relativistic calculation on Cd<SB>20</SB>, using the relativistic structures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">With relativistic effects omitted, the energy difference in favour of the pyramidal form decreases from 34 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> to only 10 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">This finding is similar to what has been noted for gold clusters.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">For gold, relativistic effects stabilise planar structures over 3D ones.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13 cit14">13,14</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The bond lengths seem to be indifferent to the inclusion of relativistic effects.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The bonds of the all-electron structure of <IT>T</IT><SB>d</SB>-Cd<SB>20</SB> are slightly shorter, but the difference is less than 1 pm.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In any case, the underlying reason for the stability of the Cd pyramids has to be a many-body effect, not accounted for by empirical potentials.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">One possibly decisive effect is the nonmetal to metal transition threshold.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Zn clusters have been found to show stronger metallicity than Cd clusters,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15">15</REF> which again turn metallic at smaller <IT>N</IT> than Hg clusters.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">In fact, the next pyramid in the Cd series, Cd<SB>84</SB>, is at least 126 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> higher in energy than the no-symmetry isomer of .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">ref. 8</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">A transition from moderate to large energy difference between order and disorder is then seen between <IT>N</IT> = 10–20 and <IT>N</IT> = 56–84 for the Zn and Cd pyramids, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="New" advantage="None">We also briefly considered the tetrahedral Hg<SB><IT>N</IT></SB> pyramids.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">They have much longer bond lengths than the Cd pyramids, and are best characterized as van der Waals systems.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot4" novelty="None" advantage="None">A further point is thermal accessibility.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">For <IT>N</IT> = 56, the energy difference of 28 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> corresponds to a mean vibrational energy 3(<IT>N</IT> − 6)<IT>kT</IT>/2 or 0.37 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> mode<SP>−1</SP>, or a temperature of 45 K. Thus, at higher temperatures, both forms may be accessible.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">This of course also applies in the cases where the pyramidal forms are more stable.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">If the low-symmetry structures have higher entropies than the tetrahedral ones, they will be favoured further at finite temperatures by their free energy <IT>G</IT> = <IT>H</IT> − <IT>TS</IT>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Concluding, we find that the Cd<SB><IT>N</IT></SB> clusters with <IT>N</IT> = 4, 10 and 20 indeed seem to prefer tetrahedral symmetries, while those with <IT>N</IT> = 35 and 56 have low-lying tetrahedral minima, only slightly above the alternatives.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ultimate driving force behind this remains unknown but could be related to the structure of the bulk metal, whose lattice parameters <IT>a</IT> resemble the present surface bond lengths.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">Among the numerous disordered Cd clusters, it is pleasing to find these beautiful exceptions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">We duly note, however, that an exhaustive scan of the potential energy surface has not been performed; at present, this is still computationally unfeasible.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
