<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b407500e" hasDoc="yes" version="1194" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Structure-based mechanism of photosynthetic water oxidation</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The recently-published 3.5 Å resolution X-ray crystal structure of a cyanobacterial photosystem II (PDB entry 1S5L) provides a detailed architecture of the oxygen-evolving complex (OEC) and the surrounding amino-acids [K. N. Ferreira, T. M. Iverson, K. Maghlaoui, J. Barber and S. Iwata, <IT>Science</IT>, 2004, <B>203</B>, 1831–1838].</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The revealed geometry of the OEC lends weight to certain hypothesized mechanisms for water-splitting, including the one propounded by this group, in which a calcium-bound water acts as a nucleophile to attack the oxygen of a Mn<SP>V</SP>O group in the crucial O–O bond-forming step [J. S. Vrettos, J. Limburg and G. W. Brudvig, <IT>Biochim. Biophys. Acta</IT>, 2001, <B>1503</B>, 229–245].</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">Here we re-examine this mechanism in the light of the new crystallographic information and make detailed suggestions concerning the mechanistic functions (especially the redox and proton-transfer roles) of calcium, chloride and certain amino-acid residues in and around the OEC.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None">In particular, we propose an important role for an arginine residue, CP43–Arg357, in abstracting protons from a substrate water molecule during the water-splitting reaction.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Photosystem II (PSII) is a dimeric, multi-subunit, transmembrane protein complex, of molecular weight <IT>ca</IT>. 650 kDa, that is found in the thylakoid membrane of plant chloroplasts and in cyanobacteria.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">It catalyzes photosynthetic water oxidation and is therefore responsible for the presence of oxygen in the earth’s atmosphere.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">PSII’s primary role in the photosynthetic chain is to use energy obtained from sunlight to produce a charge separation, leading to reduction of the membrane quinone pool.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">This reducing power, augmented by further photonic energy in photosystem I, is used to assimilate carbon dioxide in the dark reactions of photosynthesis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ultimate source of these low-potential electrons is water, which is oxidized to dioxygen in the oxygen-evolving complex (OEC) of PSII according to the four-electron reaction given in eqn. (1):<EQN>2H<SB>2</SB>O → O<SB>2</SB> + 4 H<SP>+</SP> + 4 e<SP>−</SP></EQN></annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The electrons produced by this water-splitting reaction reduce the previously photo-oxidized chlorophyll P<SB>680</SB>, the site of primary charge separation in PSII, from which electrons are passed through a series of cofactors to a membrane-mobile plastoquinone.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">P<SB>680</SB><SP>+</SP>˙ is the strongest known biological oxidant, having a reduction potential recently estimated to be around +1.3 V.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The OEC is incrementally oxidized by P<SB>680</SB><SP>+</SP>˙ in one-electron steps through a five-state redox cycle, called the Kok or S-state cycle (the states being labeled S<SB>0</SB> to S<SB>4</SB>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Oxidizing power is accumulated in the OEC until, upon reaching the transiently-stable S<SB>4</SB> (most oxidized) state, two molecules of water are oxidized to a single molecule of dioxygen, and the OEC returns from S<SB>4</SB> to S<SB>0</SB>, its most reduced state.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The structure of the OEC, and the mechanism by which it catalyzes water oxidation, have together been the subject of prolonged investigation using many different spectroscopic and biochemical techniques (see <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2 cit3 cit4 cit5">refs. 2–5</REF> for some recent reviews).</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">It has been established that the OEC consists of four Mn ions, Ca<SP>2+</SP>, and a redox-active tyrosine residue which shuttles electrons from the OEC to P<SB>680</SB><SP>+</SP>˙.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The presence of one or more Cl<SP>−</SP> ions has also been strongly suspected.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Until very recently, however, detailed structural information has been scarce.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The first X-ray crystal structure of a cyanobacterial PSII, obtained to 3.8 Å resolution (<IT>R</IT> factor 59%) in 2001, revealed the positions of the transmembrane α-helices, but left unresolved the precise locations of the cofactors, the identities of the individual amino-acids and the arrangement of the atoms in the OEC.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast, the recently-published structure of PSII at 3.5 Å resolution (<IT>R</IT> factor 30%) assigns for the first time a precise structure to the OEC, and identifies its ligating amino-acids.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The complex is seen to take the form of a cuboidal Mn<SB>3</SB>CaO<SB>4</SB> cluster, with a fourth Mn ion ‘dangling’ off one of the corner oxygen atoms.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="New" advantage="None">We will discuss in detail this structure and its implications later in the paper.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">First, however, we shall consider some concepts and experimental results that are important in understanding the water-splitting mechanism, and summarize our existing mechanistic proposal in these terms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Then we will compare our proposal with the new crystal structure, and describe in what ways our proposal is supported or contradicted by this crystallographic information.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our mechanism is largely corroborated by the crystal structure, but the structure is incompatible with our incorporation of Babcock’s proposal that the nearby tyrosine, Y<SB>Z</SB>, abstracts protons as well as electrons from the OEC.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">We propose instead that an arginine residue close to the OEC plays the basic role in the water-splitting reaction, and offer an electrostatic explanation of how this occurs.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>The role of proton-coupled electron transfer (PCET) in S-state advancement</HEADER><P><s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The OEC catalyzes the oxidation of water to dioxygen and protons.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">It follows, therefore, that progression through its S-state cycle must involve the movement of protons as well as electrons within the OEC.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The existence of proton-coupled electron transfer (PCET) in certain S-state transitions is suggested by several strands of experimental evidence, namely, (1) pH-dependences that correspond to the protonation/deprotonation of nearby residues, (2) H/D kinetic isotope effects (reviewed in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9 cit10">refs. 9,10</REF>), and (3) temperature dependences that reveal high activation energies in those steps that are proposed to involve proton transfer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, constituents of the OEC (Mn, Ca<SP>2+</SP> and Cl<SP>−</SP>) have been removed or replaced, and nearby amino-acid residues mutated, to alter proton transfer in a revealing fashion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results of some of these experiments are summarized below.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac20" novelty="None" advantage="None">The OEC exhibits a pronounced pH-dependence in its steady-state oxygen-evolving activity, with a maximum around pH 6.0–7..0<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11 cit12">11,12</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac21" novelty="None" advantage="None">The pH-dependence of each individual S-state transition has also recently been obtained.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac22" novelty="None" advantage="None">Only the S<SB>1</SB> → S<SB>2</SB> transition was found to be independent of pH between 4.1 and 8.4.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac23" novelty="None" advantage="None">This transition was proposed to involve electron transfer (ET) alone, with the result that a positive charge accumulates on the oxidized cluster.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac24" novelty="None" advantage="None">Charge build-up in this step is indicated by electrochromic shifts seen in UV-visible absorbance spectra obtained from nearby chlorophylls,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14 cit15 cit16 cit17">14–17</REF> although it has been suggested that these observed Stark effects may be explained by invoking a change in the electric dipole moment of the OEC instead of an increase in its overall charge.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac25" novelty="None" advantage="None">All other transitions are blocked at low pH by a process with a p<IT>K</IT><SB>a</SB> ≈ 4.8, which was ascribed to the protonation of a carboxylic acid involved in the proton expulsion pathway.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF> </annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac26" novelty="None" advantage="None">At high pH, the S<SB>3</SB> → [S<SB>4</SB>] → S<SB>0</SB> transition is deactivated with a p<IT>K</IT><SB>a</SB> ≈ 8.0, and the S<SB>2</SB> → S<SB>3</SB> transition with a p<IT>K</IT><SB>a</SB> ≈ 9..4<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac27" novelty="None" advantage="None">This high-pH deactivation was interpreted as being the result of Y<SB>Z</SB> having decreased in reduction potential, rendering it unable to oxidize the higher S-states.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac28" novelty="None" advantage="None">The importance of the changing protonation state of Y<SB>Z</SB> has been emphasized by a number of researchers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac29" novelty="None" advantage="None">The large discrepancy between the p<IT>K</IT><SB>a</SB> of the oxidized and reduced form of the residue (p<IT>K</IT><SB>ox</SB> ≈ –2, p<IT>K</IT><SB>red</SB> ≈ 9) has been used to argue that, energetically, it is very likely that its redox reactions are coupled to proton transfer.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac30" novelty="None" advantage="None">Y<SB>Z</SB> has thus been suggested to exist in its oxidized state principally as the neutral, oxygen-centered radical, and in its reduced state as the neutral, protonated, phenolic form.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac31" novelty="None" advantage="None">That the oxidized form is the neutral radical is supported by evidence from electron paramagnetic resonance (EPR) experiments<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19 cit20 cit21 cit22">19–22</REF> and from Fourier-transform infra-red (FTIR) spectroscopy.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac32" novelty="None" advantage="None">FTIR spectroscopy also suggests that the reduced form of Y<SB>Z</SB> is protonated at physiological pHs.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac33" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, site-directed mutagenesis of D1–His190, and subsequent chemical rescue studies, have shown that this base is required for effective oxidation of Y<SB>Z</SB>˙.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24 cit25 cit26 cit27 cit28">24–28</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac34" novelty="None" advantage="None">These results suggest that each time the OEC reduces Y<SB>Z</SB>–O˙, ET is accompanied by proton transfer to form Y<SB>Z</SB>–OH.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac35" novelty="None" advantage="None">Equally, each oxidation of Y<SB>Z</SB>–OH by P<SB>680</SB><SP>+</SP>˙ is accompanied by the loss of a proton from Y<SB>Z</SB>–OH to D1–His190, re-forming the neutral tyrosyl radical.<SUP TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" /></annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac36" novelty="None" advantage="None">There is disagreement, however, on the ultimate source and destination of these protons.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac37" novelty="None" advantage="None">Some groups (including Babcock and co-workers) have proposed that the protons are exchanged to and from the bulk lumenal solution,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF> and other groups (including Junge and co-workers) claim evidence that the same proton stays near Y<SB>Z</SB> and exerts an electrostatic effect on its surroundings.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29">29</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac38" novelty="None" advantage="None">The important ramifications of this debate will be explored later in the paper.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac39" novelty="None" advantage="None">Kinetic deuterium isotope experiments have been conducted which reveal that the rate of oxidation of Y<SB>Z</SB> has a <IT>k</IT><SB>H</SB>/<IT>k</IT><SB>D</SB> = 2.9–3.4 at pL 6.5 in manganese-depleted core complexes, but that Y<SB>Z</SB> oxidation is almost H/D insensitive in oxygen-evolving centers, at least on the nanosecond timescale.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30 cit31 cit32 cit33 cit34 cit35">30–35</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac40" novelty="None" advantage="None">This suggests that oxidation of Y<SB>Z</SB> in the intact OEC requires only minimal proton movement, which has been explained by positing a hydrogen-bonding network, stabilized by the complete cluster, which facilitates proton movement around Y<SB>Z</SB>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23 cit36 cit37">23,36,37</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac41" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, calcium in particular is necessary for maintaining this hydrogen-bonding network.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit38">38</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac42" novelty="None" advantage="None">Acetate, a well-known inhibitor of the OEC, binds competitively with chloride<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit39">39</REF> and may exert its inhibitory effect by disrupting proton transfer around the OEC.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit40">40</REF> </annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac43" novelty="None" advantage="None">The different temperature-dependences of the S-state transitions also offer clues about proton transfer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac44" novelty="None" advantage="None">In catalytically competent PSII, the S<SB>1</SB> → S<SB>2</SB> transition proceeds at temperatures as low as 140 K,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit41">41</REF> whereas the S<SB>0</SB> → S<SB>1</SB> and S<SB>2</SB> → S<SB>3</SB> transitions advance only at temperatures above 220 K<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit42 cit43">42,43</REF> and have correspondingly greater activation energies (59.4 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> for S<SB>0</SB> → S<SB>1</SB>, 26.8 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> for S<SB>2</SB> → S<SB>3</SB>, and 9.6 kJ mol<SP>−1</SP> for S<SB>1</SB> → S<SB>2</SB>).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit44">44</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac45" novelty="None" advantage="None">The S<SB>2</SB> → S<SB>3</SB> transition is also shown by EPR to be inhibited in samples depleted of calcium or chloride<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22 cit45">22,45</REF> or inhibited by acetate;<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit46">46</REF> the Kok cycle stalls under illumination at the S<SB>2</SB>Y<SB>Z</SB>˙ state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac46" novelty="None" advantage="None">In other words, the OEC cluster remains in the S<SB>2</SB>-state, and the Y<SB>Z</SB>˙ species, which would normally oxidize the OEC cluster, is unable to do so, perhaps because the reduction potential of the modified S<SB>3</SB> cluster state is higher than that of Y<SB>Z</SB>˙.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac47" novelty="None" advantage="None">This stalling has been interpreted as indicating that, in order to reach the S<SB>3</SB>-state of the OEC, a well-ordered hydrogen-bonding network must exist through which protons or hydrogen atoms are able to move around the OEC, lowering the reduction potential of S<SB>3</SB> by coupling its formation to proton-abstraction<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF>. </annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Concerted electron transfer/proton transfer (ETPT) in the OEC</HEADER><P><s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac48" novelty="None" advantage="None">Some years after first identifying Y<SB>Z</SB> as the OEC’s immediate oxidant,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit47">47</REF> Babcock and co-workers suggested that Y<SB>Z</SB> intimately combined its ET and proton transfer (PT) roles by abstracting <IT>hydrogen atoms</IT> from the OEC.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit48">8,48</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac49" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hydrogen atom transfer is a special instance of concerted electron and proton transfer (ETPT).</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac50" novelty="None" advantage="None">ETPT is itself a type of PCET and is defined by the simultaneous (rather than consecutive) transfer of electrons and protons.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit49">49</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac51" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the basis of spectroscopic information, Babcock <IT>et al</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac51" novelty="None" advantage="None">noted that Y<SB>Z</SB> was sufficiently close to the catalytic cluster to abstract hydrogen atoms on the observed timescale of the reaction, and that the low dielectric of the environment made favorable such a charge-neutral process.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac52" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, the strong coupling of Y<SB>Z</SB>’s p<IT>K</IT><SB>a</SB> to its redox state (see above) was considered to provide essential thermodynamic driving force for the oxidation of the higher S-states of the OEC.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac53" novelty="None" advantage="None">This aspect of the hydrogen atom transfer theory was influenced by the work of Krishtalik, who had considered water-splitting from a theoretical standpoint some years previously<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit50">50</REF> and whose thinking had already persuaded some researchers that ETPT was likely to be important in the reaction.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit51">51</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac54" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Babcock group proposed that the reduced tyrosine passed its acquired electron to P<SB>680</SB><SP>+</SP>˙ and its proton to the hydrogen-bonded D1–His190 residue, from whence the proton passed through a channel of charged residues to the protein surface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac55" novelty="None" advantage="None">As mentioned above, some researchers (notably Junge) found evidence that the Y<SB>Z</SB> proton always stayed close to the residue, and considered this observation fatal to the proposal of hydrogen atom transfer.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29">29</REF> </annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac56" novelty="None" advantage="None">Babcock and co-workers supposed that Y<SB>Z</SB> abstracted hydrogen atoms from the OEC cluster in every one of the S-state transitions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit48">48</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac57" novelty="None" advantage="None">While in general adopting the idea of hydrogen atom transfer, we (along with several other groups) pointed out that there is reason to believe that the tyrosyl radical only abstracts hydrogen atoms from the cluster in the later S-state transitions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac58" novelty="None" advantage="None">This theory is consistent with a considerable body of evidence suggesting that there is a discontinuity in the means of S-state advancement beyond the S<SB>2</SB> state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac59" novelty="None" advantage="None">Firstly, as mentioned above and considered in detail later, it is the transitions beyond S<SB>2</SB> that are blocked by the absence of calcium or chloride, and by the presence of acetate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac60" novelty="None" advantage="None">Secondly, ET between the OEC and P<SB>680</SB><SP>+</SP>˙ is significantly slower (and biphasic) in the S-state transitions beyond S<SB>2</SB> than in the early S-states.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit52">52</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac61" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thirdly, the reorganization energies of the two higher S-state transitions have been found to be significantly higher than those of the two previous transitions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit53">53</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac62" novelty="None" advantage="None">Finally, the sub-microsecond ET rates from the cluster to P<SB>680</SB><SP>+</SP>˙ (<IT>via</IT> Y<SB>Z</SB>) vary much more with temperature in post-S<SB>2</SB> transitions than they do in the pre-S<SB>2</SB> steps.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit54">54</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac63" novelty="None" advantage="None">We rationalized these findings by positing a switch in the mode of proton and electron transfer at the S<SB>2</SB> stage of the cycle, a change activated by the positive charge developed on the OEC in the S<SB>1</SB> → S<SB>2</SB> transition.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac64" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the S<SB>0</SB> → S<SB>1</SB> transition we inferred the action of PCET, in which an electron and a proton move consecutively, and in the transitions after S<SB>2</SB> we inferred the action of ETPT, in which the two particles move together and simultaneously.</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac65" novelty="None" advantage="None">The same conclusion has been independently reached,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9 cit55">9,55</REF> largely on the basis of proton release measurements in the different S-states.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit51 cit56">51,56</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac66" novelty="None" advantage="None">It might be hoped that PCET and ETPT would be distinguishable by measuring the effect of H/D exchange on the ET kinetics of the different transitions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit49">49</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac67" novelty="None" advantage="None">Unfortunately, the results of such experiments have so far proven equivocal and from them no consensus has yet emerged<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit32 cit34 cit57 cit58">32,34,57,58</REF>. </annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Mechanisms of water oxidation</HEADER><P><s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac68" novelty="None" advantage="None">A great number of specific mechanisms for the catalytic action of the OEC have been proposed over the years (for a list of some of these see .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit59">ref. 59</REF>)</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac69" novelty="None" advantage="None">In accordance with the results of experiments conducted on various PSII preparations and on model inorganic compounds, the oxidizing power of the OEC is now presumed to accumulate largely, if not entirely, on the four Mn ions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac70" novelty="None" advantage="None">The exception to this consensus has been the S<SB>2</SB> → S<SB>3</SB> step, which has been suggested by some to involve manganese oxidation<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit10">8,10</REF> and by others the oxidation of a species near to the cluster,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit60 cit61">60,61</REF> perhaps a manganese-bridging oxo group.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit62">62</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac71" novelty="None" advantage="None">Manganese-bridging oxo ligands have also often been proposed to react with one another in the O–O bond forming step.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit63 cit64">63,64</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac72" novelty="None" advantage="None">Alternatively, one of the constituent atoms of dioxygen has been proposed to come from a manganese-bound terminal water molecule, perhaps deprotonated by basic <IT>μ</IT>-oxo ligands.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit65">65</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac73" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our proposal is amongst those that hypothesizes the role in catalysis of a unique, highly-oxidized Mn<SP>V</SP>O species, along with a specific mechanistic role for calcium.</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac74" novelty="None" advantage="None">This type of mechanism is also favored by Pecoraro and co-workers.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit66">66</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac75" novelty="None" advantage="None">Siegbahn, using density functional theory calculations, has proposed a related mechanism in which a Mn-oxyl species is involved in the O–O bond-forming step<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit67 cit68">67,68</REF>. </annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>The Brudvig group proposal for the water oxidation mechanism</HEADER><P><s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 1 outlines the S-state cycle previously propounded by this group.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac76" novelty="None" advantage="None">Experimental and theoretical justification of our assigned manganese oxidation states have been published previously.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac77" novelty="None" advantage="None">A recent EPR study of a di-manganese model compound, replicating the S<SB>1</SB> multiline signal, supports our assignment of the manganese oxidation states in the S<SB>1</SB> state.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit69">69</REF> </annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The distinctive aspects of our mechanism are as follows:</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">(1) The Ca<SP>2+</SP> ion plays a precise, mechanistic role in the reaction by coordinating one of the substrate water molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">This ligation both aligns the water properly for the O–O bond-forming reaction and optimally tunes the p<IT>K</IT><SB>a</SB> of this substrate water.</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">This water nucleophilically attacks an oxo oxygen derived from the second substrate water molecule.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">(2) This second substrate water is coordinated to a Mn ion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">During the course of the S-state cycle, this Mn ion is successively oxidized, while at the same time its ligated water is deprotonated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">By the S<SB>4</SB> state, a Mn<SP>V</SP>O group has been achieved, whose oxo group is electrophilic enough to engage in an S<SB>N</SB>2-type reaction with the calcium-bound substrate water.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">(3) The manganese-bound substrate water was proposed to be deprotonated by Y<SB>Z</SB>, acting not only as an oxidant but also as a base throughout the reaction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">As discussed above, we have suggested that, in the S<SB>0</SB> → S<SB>1</SB> transition, ET is coupled to PT but the transfers are consecutive rather than simultaneous, and that the S<SB>1</SB> → S<SB>2</SB> transition involves only ET.</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast, we have proposed that in the final two cluster redox transitions (S<SB>2</SB> → S<SB>3</SB> and S<SB>3</SB> → S<SB>4</SB>), Y<SB>Z</SB> performs a concerted electron and proton transfer, abstracting a hydrogen atom from the OEC.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod11" novelty="None" advantage="None">This aspect of our mechanism is a modification of Babcock’s proposal of hydrogen atom transfer in all S-state transitions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The switch from PCET to ETPT, activated by charge build-up in the S<SB>1</SB> → S<SB>2</SB> transition, was proposed to explain the apparent mechanistic discontinuity at the S<SB>2</SB> → S<SB>3</SB> transition (see above).</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>The role of calcium in the water-splitting reaction</HEADER><P><s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac78" novelty="None" advantage="None">Calcium has been revealed in the new crystal structure to be integrated into the OEC cluster, which agrees with the absolute requirement for Ca<SP>2+</SP> in O<SB>2</SB>-evolution<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit70">70</REF> and, specifically, to its mechanistic role in water oxidation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac79" novelty="None" advantage="None">Recent <SP>18</SP>O-isotope exchange experiments<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit71">71</REF> and pulsed EPR studies<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit72 cit73">72,73</REF> have corroborated calcium’s mechanistic role, as well as our proposal that the ion binds water early in the S-state cycle.</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac80" novelty="None" advantage="None">Several metals have been substituted into the Ca<SP>2+</SP>-binding site in the OEC, but only Sr<SP>2+</SP> confers any catalytic activity, and that only partially.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit74">74</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac81" novelty="None" advantage="None">Other (inhibitory) metal ions, which are similar in their size and charge to Ca<SP>2+</SP> and bind strongly to the site, have aqua-ion p<IT>K</IT><SB>a</SB>s significantly lower than that of Ca<SP>2+</SP>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit74">74</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac82" novelty="None" advantage="None">Their inability to play a part in water oxidation suggests that they bind OH<SP>−</SP> in the active site, which may be too strongly bound to the metal, and too strongly charged, to act as an effective nucleophile towards the Mn<SP>V</SP>O oxygen atom.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit67">67</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac83" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have argued that calcium provides a bound water molecule, rather then a bound hydroxide ion, as the nucleophile in the O–O bond-forming reaction.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac84" novelty="None" advantage="None">This interpretation is supported by experiments in which trivalent cations have been substituted, with inhibitory effect, into the Ca<SP>2+</SP>-binding site.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit74 cit75">74,75</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac85" novelty="None" advantage="None">The strongly size-selective metal-binding site does not discriminate between di- and trivalent cations, indicating that the trivalent ions, which are strong Lewis acids, bind a hydroxide ligand and so are incorporated into the cluster with a net +2 charge.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac86" novelty="None" advantage="None">A similar proposal has been made to account for the observation by X-ray absorption spectroscopy (XAS) that only very small structural effects are induced by Dy<SP>3+</SP>/Ca<SP>2+</SP> substitution in the OEC.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit76">76</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac87" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the Dy<SP>3+</SP>-substituted OEC is unable to attain the positively-charged S<SB>2</SB> state,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit77">77</REF> indicating that the charge of the metal in this site does play a part in the cluster’s reactivity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac88" novelty="None" advantage="None">Similarly, calcium is found to be released from the cluster more readily in the higher, positively-charged S-states than in the lower S-states.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit78">78</REF> </annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac89" novelty="None" advantage="None">Calcium also appears to have a role in maintaining the hydrogen-bond network necessary for proton transfer around the OEC.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22 cit38">22,38</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac90" novelty="None" advantage="None">The inhibitory effect of calcium-depletion is exerted by blocking the S<SB>2</SB> → S<SB>3</SB> transition,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit79 cit80 cit81">79–81</REF> an observation consistent with the necessity for proton transfer through a hydrogen-bonded network in this step.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac91" novelty="None" advantage="None">These results point to three roles for calcium in the OEC.</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac91" novelty="None" advantage="None">The first is as a Lewis acid, binding and activating one substrate water as a nucleophile in the O–O bond-forming reaction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac92" novelty="None" advantage="None">The second is in maintaining the hydrogen-bonding network around the OEC, which appears to be necessary for progression beyond the S<SB>2</SB> state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac93" novelty="None" advantage="None">The third is a general electrostatic role, in which the metal modulates the charge distribution, and thus the reduction potential, of the cluster<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit76">76</REF>. </annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>The role of chloride in the water-splitting reaction</HEADER><P><s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac94" novelty="None" advantage="None">Chloride, like calcium, appears specifically to be required for the S<SB>2</SB> → S<SB>3</SB> transition,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit45">45</REF> and has also been implicated in facilitating proton movement around the OEC.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit82 cit83">82,83</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac95" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the OEC’s chloride requirement is certainly less stringent than its calcium requirement.</annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac96" novelty="None" advantage="None">It seems that chloride-depleted samples may be reconstituted to a catalytically active form by a variety of anions, including bromide and nitrate.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit84 cit85">84,85</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac97" novelty="None" advantage="None">Chloride’s necessity in O<SB>2</SB> evolution has recently been seriously called into question by Andreasson and co-workers.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit82">82</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac98" novelty="None" advantage="None">These authors claim that observed chloride-depletion effects are largely artefactual, caused by protein alteration linked to the sulfate treatments employed in removing chloride from the complex.</annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac99" novelty="None" advantage="None">Nevertheless, the balance of evidence suggests that one Cl<SP>−</SP> ion is normally associated with the functional OEC.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit86">86</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac100" novelty="None" advantage="None">The proximity of the chloride ion to the OEC is unknown, with some groups hypothesizing that it is ligated to the tetramanganese cluster<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10 cit87">10,87</REF> and others postulating that it is further removed.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit84">84</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Recent work in assigning an extended X-ray absorption fine structure (EXAFS) signature to chloride bound to Mn-oxo model clusters will help to resolve this question.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit88">88</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac101" novelty="None" advantage="None">In our previous proposal, chloride was present as a bridging ligand between Ca<SP>2+</SP> and the substrate-binding Mn ion (see Fig. 1).</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>The new X-ray crystal structure of the OEC<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF></HEADER><P><s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac102" novelty="None" advantage="None">The new crystal structure of the OEC is shown in panel A of Fig. 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac103" novelty="None" advantage="None">It appears that the catalytic site takes the form of a metal-oxo distorted cube, comprising four metals and four bridging oxygen ions, with one of these corner oxygens (a μ<SB>4</SB> ligand) binding a fifth metal on the cuboid’s exterior.</annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac104" novelty="None" advantage="None">Using X-ray anomalous difference maps at different wavelengths, the cuboid is proposed to contain three Mn ions and one Ca<SP>2+</SP>, making a Mn<SB>3</SB>CaO<SB>4</SB> cluster, and the exterior ‘dangler’ metal ion is taken to be the fourth manganese.</annotationART></s> <s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac105" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although this exact arrangement had never been previously proposed on the basis of spectroscopic investigations, the Mn ions had indeed been proposed to exist as a ‘3+1 tetramer’, largely on the basis of EPR spectroscopies and EXAFS measurements.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit89">89</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac106" novelty="None" advantage="None">D1–Tyr161 (‘Y<SB>Z</SB>’), which has long been established as the immediate oxidant of the OEC in the cluster’s catalytic redox cycle,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit47">47</REF> is 5.0 Å from Ca<SP>2+</SP>, the nearest cluster atom.</annotationART></s> <s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac107" novelty="None" advantage="None">This short distance is compatible with fast electron transfer from the cluster to Y<SB>Z</SB>, and also, potentially, with proton transfer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac108" novelty="None" advantage="None">D1–His190, which has been previously identified as Y<SB>Z</SB>’s hydrogen-bonding and proton-exchange partner (see above), is revealed in the structure to be excellently positioned for this function.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac109" novelty="None" advantage="None">Several other hydrophilic residues have been found close to the OEC, whose possible roles in hydrogen-bonding and proton transfer will be discussed below.</annotationART></s> <s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac110" novelty="None" advantage="None">Of particular importance is the side-chain of CP43–Arg357, which is shown to be very close to our proposed active site of the cluster.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac111" novelty="None" advantage="None">Finally, crystallographic analysis revealed non-protein electron density in the space above Ca<SP>2+</SP> and Mn(4), which was best fitted as a bicarbonate, carbonate or nitrate ion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac112" novelty="None" advantage="None">Because nitrate was not expected to be present, this space in the structure has been tentatively occupied with a bicarbonate ion<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF>. </annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Comparison of previously proposed mechanism to new crystal structure</HEADER><P><s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is important to emphasize that the recent X-ray structure provides an imperfect image of the OEC in an indeterminate redox state that cannot do more than suggest a catalytic mechanism <IT>in vivo</IT>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the active site of the metal cluster may be guessed at with some confidence from the crystal structure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="143"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">There are three principal reasons for suspecting that amongst the metals, the ‘dangler’ Mn(4) ion and the Ca<SP>2+</SP> ion play key roles, binding unseen reactant water molecules between this pair of metal ions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="144"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Firstly, the distance and angle between the two metals make the O–O bond-forming reaction between two such bound waters geometrically plausible (see below).</annotationART></s> <s sid="145"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Secondly, Mn(4) lies at one end of a row of charged amino-acid residues (beginning with D1–Asp61) which leads to the lumenal protein exterior, an arrangement which stands out in a generally hydrophobic area of the protein.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="146"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">These residues would be well-suited to moving protons out of the active site only if Mn(4) were intimately involved in the catalytic reaction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="147"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thirdly, Mn(4) and Ca<SP>2+</SP> are together the closest of the metal ions to Y<SB>Z</SB>, which acts in its radical form as the immediate oxidant of the OEC.</annotationART></s> <s sid="148"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Taking these telling points together, the positions, proximity and alignment of Ca<SP>2+</SP> and Mn(4) favors those proposed mechanisms (such as ours) that have envisaged a direct role for Ca<SP>2+</SP> and one of the manganese ions in coordinating the substrate water molecules.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>The coordination of the metal atoms in the OEC</HEADER><P><s sid="149"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The new crystal structure shows that the four Mn ions have between them, besides the four bridging oxo groups of the cuboidal cluster, only six ligating amino-acid residues.</annotationART></s> <s sid="150"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac113" novelty="None" advantage="None">These residues had all previously been identified as integral to the OEC on the basis of mutational studies,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit90 cit91">90,91</REF> except for Glu354 of the CP43 subunit, which was unexpectedly found in the new crystal structure to ligate Mn(3).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF> </annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="151"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac114" novelty="None" advantage="None">Manganese in proteins is almost invariably five- or six-coordinate, and the metal generally has a preference for octahedral geometry, especially in the higher oxidation states.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit92">92</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="152"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac115" novelty="None" advantage="None">Calcium is typically six- to eight-coordinate.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit93">93</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="153"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">This implies that there are probably coordination sites on each of the metals that are occupied (at least in some oxidation states) by small, unseen molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="154"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac116" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the absence of evidence to the contrary, it may be assumed that most of these small molecules are waters or hydroxides.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="155"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The two manganese ions on the opposite side of the cluster from our proposed active site, Mn(1) and Mn(2), are structurally important but not directly involved in our proposed mechanism.</annotationART></s> <s sid="156"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">They are assigned to the two manganese ions that remain in the +4 oxidation state throughout our proposed cycle, and the details of their coordination need not concern us here.</annotationART></s> <s sid="157"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The catalytically important metals in our mechanism are Mn(4), Mn(3) and Ca<SP>2+</SP>, and so we must closely examine their probable coordination.</annotationART></s> <s sid="158"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">They comprise what we take to be the ‘active face’ of the OEC cluster.</annotationART></s> <s sid="159"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Our proposal for the coordination (in the S<SB>0</SB> state) of these metals and nearby amino-acid residues is shown, superimposed on the crystallographic data, in panel B of Fig. 2.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="160"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Mn(4) is seen to have three ligands in the crystal structure: the μ<SB>4</SB> cluster oxygen atom, D1–Asp170 and D1–Glu333, these last two each binding <IT>via</IT> their carboxylate side-chains in monodentate mode.</annotationART></s> <s sid="161"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The three ligands are aligned 90 ± 5° to each other in the same plane, and it seems reasonable to take them as three of the metal’s equatorial ligands, constituting part of a near-regular octahedral coordination.</annotationART></s> <s sid="162"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Maintaining this geometry, the fourth equatorial ligand, <IT>trans</IT> to D1–Glu333, we take as one of the substrate water molecules.</annotationART></s> <s sid="163"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The angle, relative to the Mn<SB>3</SB>CaO<SB>4</SB> cluster, of the bond joining Mn(4) to the μ<SB>4</SB>-O atom is such that the putative substrate water on Mn(4) is tilted towards the coordination sphere of the Ca<SP>2+</SP> ion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="164"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod12" novelty="None" advantage="None">We assume that there is a non-substrate water ligand in one of the Mn(4) axial positions (pointing towards the viewer in panel B of Fig. 2), which is well positioned to hydrogen-bond to D1–Asp61, the first residue of the apparent hydrophilic proton exit pathway.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="165"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The sixth and final supposed ligand of Mn(4), the second axial ligand, points away from the area of chemical activity and therefore does not concern us.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="166"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac117" novelty="None" advantage="None">Mn(3) is coordinated to three oxygen atoms within the cuboidal cluster, and by CP43–Glu354 in a seemingly bidentate fashion.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="167"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The alignment of these ligands again indicates octahedral geometry, with at least one (axial) ligand unseen in the crystal structure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="168"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">This axial position, which points towards the CP43–Arg357 side-chain on the active face of the cluster, we have tentatively occupied with a non-substrate hydroxide ligand.</annotationART></s> <s sid="169"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac118" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is because in our proposed mechanism this Mn ion is always in the +3 or +4 oxidation state, and would be expected to prefer to coordinate hydroxide rather than water.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit94">94</REF> </annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="170"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac119" novelty="None" advantage="None">The only ligands of Ca<SP>2+</SP> revealed in the crystal structure are the two μ<SB>3</SB>- and the single μ<SB>4</SB>-oxo atoms of the OEC cuboidal cluster.</annotationART></s> <s sid="171"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac120" novelty="None" advantage="None">No proteinaceous ligands are explicitly identified, although the carboxyl terminus of the D1 subunit, D1–Ala344, is found to be very close (2.01 Å) to the metal.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="172"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac121" novelty="None" advantage="None">There is good evidence to suggest that the OEC is ligated by this terminus<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit95">95</REF> and we therefore assume that D1–Ala344 does indeed ligate Ca<SP>2+</SP> in a mono- or bi-dentate fashion.</annotationART></s> <s sid="173"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac122" novelty="None" advantage="None">Judging by a recent survey of carboxylate binding to Ca<SP>2+</SP> in proteins, the former mode is a little more likely.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit96">96</REF> </annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="174"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Assuming D1–Ala344 carboxylate-terminal coordination of Ca<SP>2+</SP>, this metal presumably also has bound to it a certain number of unseen, small molecules: a minimum of one (bidentate carboxylate coordination, total metal coordination number 6) and a maximum of four (monodentate carboxylate coordination, total metal coordination number 8).</annotationART></s> <s sid="175"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">As described above, there is good evidence to suggest that one of these small molecules is the second substrate water molecule.</annotationART></s> <s sid="176"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have added this on the active face of the OEC cluster, that is, the face comprising Ca<SP>2+</SP>, Mn(3) and Mn(4), and near to CP43–Arg357.</annotationART></s> <s sid="177"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">In our previous proposal, Cl<SP>−</SP> was present as a bridging ligand between the substrate-binding Mn ion and Ca<SP>2+</SP>, a position occupied in the new structure by the μ<SB>4</SB>-O atom of the cuboidal cluster.</annotationART></s> <s sid="178"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">There is no evidence for Cl<SP>−</SP> around the OEC in the new crystal structure, although chloride is a weak X-ray scatterer compared to the metal ions of the cluster and might easily be overlooked.</annotationART></s> <s sid="179"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac123" novelty="None" advantage="None">Acetate, which competes with chloride for the same binding site in the OEC,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit39">39</REF> binds close to Y<SB>Z</SB>˙.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit97 cit98">97,98</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="180"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">Calcium depletion and chloride depletion both cause the reaction cycle to stall at the same stage in the cycle, giving similar stable EPR S<SB>2</SB>Y<SB>Z</SB>˙ signals, which suggests that these ions are functionally connected in the OEC.</annotationART></s> <s sid="181"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">We therefore propose as previously that chloride is present in the OEC bound to calcium, but instead of a <IT>μ</IT>-Cl we propose a terminal chloride situated between the metal and Y<SB>Z</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="182"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">This would place the Cl<SP>−</SP> ion roughly 2.5 Å from Y<SB>Z</SB>, in accordance with recent pulsed EPR data which estimated a distance of <IT>ca</IT>. 3 Å between Y<SB>Z</SB> and OEC-bound acetate.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit97">97</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="183"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both calcium and chloride are important, we suggest, in maintaining a hydrogen-bonded network around the OEC, and this aspect of their function will be dealt with later.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>The identity of the catalytic base in the water-splitting reaction</HEADER><P><s sid="184"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj5" novelty="New" advantage="None">Despite the generally good agreement between the structural requirements of our proposed mechanism and the new crystallographic information, a problem arises in the identity of the catalytic base and the subsequent exit of protons from the active site.</annotationART></s> <s sid="185"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">We had hypothesized that Y<SB>Z</SB> acts as both an oxidant and as a base in the course of the Kok cycle (see above).</annotationART></s> <s sid="186"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">Protons derived from the substrate waters were thought to pass from Y<SB>Z</SB> to D1–His190, Y<SB>Z</SB>’s well-established hydrogen-bonding partner, and from this residue through a series of hydrophilic amino-acid residues to the protein exterior.</annotationART></s> <s sid="187"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac124" novelty="None" advantage="None">The new crystal structure shows that D1–His190 is indeed ideally placed to hydrogen-bond to the Y<SB>Z</SB> side-chain.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="188"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod14" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, there are no further hydrophilic species in the structure positioned so that they might accept a proton from the imidazole ring and eventually pass it to the protein surface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="189"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" advantage="None">The apparent proton-exit pathway, comprising a chain of promisingly positioned hydrophilic residues, begins at D1–Asp61 (on the other side of the cluster’s active face from Y<SB>Z</SB>) and leads directly away from Y<SB>Z</SB>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="190"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None">If we take the crystal structure at face value we are therefore forced to one of two conclusions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="191"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None">The protein in this region may be sufficiently plastic that certain amino-acid residues move, at one time or another in the catalytic cycle, from the arrangement seen in the crystal structure to one that establishes a proton-transporting wire leading from D1–His190 to the protein surface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="192"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res29" novelty="None" advantage="None">Alternatively, Y<SB>Z</SB> might in fact accept neither protons nor hydrogen atoms from the OEC.</annotationART></s> <s sid="193"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res30" novelty="None" advantage="None">Instead, as the Kok-cycle proceeds, Y<SB>Z</SB> might repeatedly exchange the same proton with D1–His190, receiving the proton as Y<SB>Z</SB> is reduced, and donating it as Y<SB>Z</SB> is oxidized.</annotationART></s> <s sid="194"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" advantage="None">Such ‘proton-rocking’ between Y<SB>Z</SB> and D1–His190 has indeed been proposed on the basis of the temperature-dependence of ET kinetics<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit99">99</REF> and by Junge and co-workers on the basis of extensive proton release measurements.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29">29</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="195"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac125" novelty="None" advantage="None">This mode of PCET is also widely believed to take place at the homologous tyrosine in the D2 subunit, Y<SB>D</SB>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit100">100</REF> </annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="196"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res32" novelty="None" advantage="None">The new crystal structure has shifted the balance of evidence, although not definitively, towards the proton-rocking hypothesis for Y<SB>Z</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="197"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac126" novelty="None" advantage="None">Nevertheless, acknowledging the structure’s imperfect resolution and bearing in mind the evidence for conformational change around the OEC during the catalytic cycle<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit101">101</REF> it remains possible to argue that Y<SB>Z</SB> is able to abstract protons or hydrogen atoms from our proposed active site, a mere <IT>ca</IT>. 5 Å distant.</annotationART></s> <s sid="198"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res33" novelty="None" advantage="None">As for the fate of the abstracted proton, Y<SB>Z</SB> and D1–His190 are both less than 4 Å from D1–Gln165, which, in turn, is less than 4 Å from CP43–Arg357, a residue plausibly linked to the proton exit pathway beginning at D1–Asp61 (see below).</annotationART></s> <s sid="199"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res34" novelty="None" advantage="None">Future structures obtained in definite oxidation states might show that Y<SB>Z</SB> is indeed linked <IT>via</IT> these residues to the lumenal surface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="200"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res35" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the meantime, our attention is focused on identifying another species capable of playing the basic role previously allotted to Y<SB>Z</SB> in the water-splitting mechanism, and which is linked to the crystallographically observed proton exit pathway.</annotationART></s> <s sid="201"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res36" novelty="None" advantage="None">Moreover, in so adapting our proposal we improve its mechanistic plausibility and its agreement with experimental results.</annotationART></s> <s sid="202"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the first time we are able to propose a precise electrostatic mechanism to explain the mechanistic discontinuity proposed to exist in the Kok cycle at the S<SB>2</SB> state.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>The role of CP43–Arg357 in the water-splitting reaction</HEADER><P><s sid="203"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">We propose that the nearby CP43–Arg357 side-chain is central in organizing the flow of protons from the OEC during the later part of the catalytic cycle.</annotationART></s> <s sid="204"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is only with the publication of the recent crystal structure that this residue’s proximity to the OEC has emerged: the terminal nitrogens of the CP43–Arg357 side-chain are each a little over 4 Å from the active face of the cluster.</annotationART></s> <s sid="205"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The residue’s functional indispensability had already been established by observing that the O<SB>2</SB>-evolving activity of PSII from <IT>Synechocystis</IT> sp.</annotationART></s> <s sid="206"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac127" novelty="None" advantage="None">PCC 6803 is abolished if one mutates the homologous CP43 arginine (Arg342) to serine.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit102">102</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="207"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac128" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, the residue is conserved in the same genetic position in all known CP43 sequences.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="208"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">We propose that CP43–Arg357 is necessary for two, interconnected reasons.</annotationART></s> <s sid="209"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res37" novelty="None" advantage="None">First, it helps to organize the hydrogen-bonding network of metal-ligated waters and hydroxides around the OEC cluster.</annotationART></s> <s sid="210"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res38" novelty="None" advantage="None">Second, in its neutral form it abstracts protons from the manganese-bound substrate water in both S-state progressions beyond the S<SB>2</SB> state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="211"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res39" novelty="None" advantage="None">These protons then leave to the lumenal bulk solution through the pre-organized hydrogen-bonding network.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="212"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res40" novelty="None" advantage="None">The arginine sidechain is a well-known, important and versatile component of hydrogen-bonding networks in proteins.</annotationART></s> <s sid="213"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res41" novelty="None" advantage="None">Cytochrome <IT>c</IT> oxidase, for instance, contains a hydrogen-bonded network incorporating two highly-conserved arginines which are important in optimizing both electron and proton transfer around the active site.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit103 cit104">103,104</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="214"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res42" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the new structure of the PSII OEC, the guanidinium side-chain of CP43–Arg357, straddling the active face of the metal-oxo cluster, is positioned to hydrogen-bond not only to the two putative substrate waters (ligated respectively to Ca<SP>2+</SP> and Mn(4)), but also to the putative non-substrate ligands (probably water or hydroxide) of Mn(3) and Mn(4).</annotationART></s> <s sid="215"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res43" novelty="None" advantage="None">Because the positions and nature of these ligands are unknown, we have not attempted to propose detailed hydrogen-bond distances and angles.</annotationART></s> <s sid="216"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res44" novelty="None" advantage="None">Nevertheless, a network of hydrogen-bonds similar to that shown in Fig. 4, to be discussed later, seems eminently plausible.</annotationART></s> <s sid="217"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res45" novelty="None" advantage="None">It may be that not all of these bonds are extant at any one time, but that the components of the network move a little through the course of the reaction cycle, making some connections and breaking others.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="218"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res46" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both of the substrate water ligands, bound respectively to Ca<SP>2+</SP> and Mn(4), may plausibly be fitted into the structure within a few angstroms of the terminal nitrogens of the arginine side-chain, which points almost directly at these spaces in the structure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="219"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res47" novelty="None" advantage="None">Arginine’s postulated hydrogen-bonding interactions with the substrate waters are significant because our mechanism implies that these waters are prevented from hydrogen-bonding to one another.</annotationART></s> <s sid="220"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res48" novelty="None" advantage="None">Such a bond would fix a hydrogen between the two oxygen atoms, preventing their close approach in the O–O bond-forming step.</annotationART></s> <s sid="221"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res49" novelty="None" advantage="None">CP43–Arg357’s ability to hydrogen-bond with the other, non-substrate ligands of Mn(3) and Mn(4) presents a plausible route through which protons may travel from the substrate waters to D1–Asp61, the beginning of the proton exit pathway (see Fig. 4, later).</annotationART></s> <s sid="222"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res50" novelty="None" advantage="None">As the Kok cycle progresses beyond the S<SB>2</SB> state, therefore, concerted ETPT may be imagined to take place in a bifurcated manner: electrons pass from the cluster to oxidized Y<SB>Z</SB>˙, and protons, abstracted by basic CP43–Arg357, pass to the lumen through a hydrogen-bonded network <IT>via</IT> D1–Asp61.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="223"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res51" novelty="None" advantage="None">While arginine’s ability to hydrogen-bond is not in doubt, it is not well-known as a general acid/base catalyst in protein active sites.</annotationART></s> <s sid="224"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac129" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, there are now well-established examples of it serving in such a fashion, namely in the fumarate reductases<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit105 cit106">105,106</REF> and in two families of polysaccharide lyases.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit107 cit108">107,108</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="225"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac130" novelty="None" advantage="None">Simply on the basis of comparing the p<IT>K</IT><SB>a</SB> of the side chain in the free amino-acid (<IT>ca</IT>. 12)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit109">109</REF> with the pH of the chloroplast lumen (as low as 5)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit110">110</REF> one would not anticipate the existence of a neutral, deprotonated arginine at the OEC.</annotationART></s> <s sid="226"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res52" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the electrostatic environment anticipated at the OEC in its higher oxidation states makes the momentary existence of the neutral arginine highly plausible.</annotationART></s> <s sid="227"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac131" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is known that the p<IT>K</IT><SB>a</SB> of an amino-acid residue may be dramatically altered by the effect of nearby electrostatic charges (see, for instance, .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit111">ref. 111</REF>)</annotationART></s> <s sid="228"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Specifically, we propose that the increase in positive charge of the OEC during the S<SB>1</SB> → S<SB>2</SB> transition, along with the positive charge of the D1–His190 residue present in the S<SB>2</SB>Y<SB>Z</SB>˙ state, is sufficient in catalytically-competent PSII preparations to deprotonate the side-chain of CP43–Arg357 and poise it to abstract protons from the substrate water in subsequent steps.</annotationART></s> <s sid="229"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp10" novelty="None" advantage="None">This proposition is described schematically in Fig. 3, which shows the OEC cluster surrounded by four important amino-acid residues: Y<SB>Z</SB>, the immediate oxidant of the cluster; D1–His190, Y<SB>Z</SB>’s hydrogen-bonding and proton transfer partner; CP43–Arg357, which we propose acts as a base in the later S-states; and D1–Asp61, which constitutes the beginning of the crystallographically revealed proton exit pathway.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="230"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The simple S<SB>1</SB> → S<SB>2</SB> transition is illustrated in the left hand side of Fig. 3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="231"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The S<SB>1</SB> state of the cluster is, we assume, uncharged.</annotationART></s> <s sid="232"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The side-chain of CP43–Arg357 we take here to be positively charged, in accordance with its normal high p<IT>K</IT><SB>a</SB>, and D1–Asp61 we always take to be in its negatively-charged carboxylate form.</annotationART></s> <s sid="233"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod18" novelty="None" advantage="None">First of all, Y<SB>Z</SB>–OH reduces P<SB>680</SB><SP>+</SP>˙ and, in a coupled reaction, transfers its tyrosyl proton along a hydrogen-bond to the imidazole ring of D1–His190, making this side-chain positively charged.</annotationART></s> <s sid="234"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The newly-formed Y<SB>Z</SB>–O˙ now oxidizes the OEC cluster from the S<SB>1</SB> to the S<SB>2</SB> state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="235"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res53" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this S-state transition, no proton transfer is associated with oxidation of the cluster, and so the cluster acquires a positive charge.</annotationART></s> <s sid="236"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res54" novelty="None" advantage="None">As Y<SB>Z</SB>–O˙ is reduced, the proton it recently lost to D1–His190 rocks back along the hydrogen-bond to bind again to the Y<SB>Z</SB> side-chain.</annotationART></s> <s sid="237"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res55" novelty="None" advantage="None">The bottom left-hand panel of Fig. 3 shows a neutral Y<SB>Z</SB>–OH residue alongside the cluster and the CP43–Arg357 side-chain, both of which are now positively charged.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="238"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod20" novelty="None" advantage="None">We start with this S<SB>2</SB> state on the right-hand side of Fig. 3.</annotationART></s> <s sid="239"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res56" novelty="None" advantage="None">As before, the first step in the S-state transition is the oxidation of Y<SB>Z</SB>, coupled to proton transfer to D1–His190.</annotationART></s> <s sid="240"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res57" novelty="None" advantage="None">Now, however, the mechanism differs from the S<SB>1</SB> → S<SB>2</SB> case.</annotationART></s> <s sid="241"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res58" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the S<SB>2</SB>Y<SB>Z</SB>˙ state, both D1–His190 and the OEC cluster are positively charged.</annotationART></s> <s sid="242"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res59" novelty="None" advantage="None">The positively-charged CP43–Arg357 side-chain is <IT>ca</IT>. 4 Å from the cluster and less than 9 Å from the imidazolium ring of D1–His190.</annotationART></s> <s sid="243"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res60" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, these two repulsive electrostatic interactions occur in a site that is deeply buried from bulk solvent and is therefore presumably a low-dielectric environment.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit112">112</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="244"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res61" novelty="None" advantage="None">We propose that, in order to diminish these unfavorable electrostatic interactions, the guanidinium group of CP43–Arg357 deprotonates to the lumenal bulk solution <IT>via</IT> D1–Asp61, to which arginine is connected through hydrogen-bonded non-substrate ligands of Mn(3) and Mn(4) (see above).</annotationART></s> <s sid="245"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res62" novelty="None" advantage="None">Having deprotonated, the neutral arginine side-chain constitutes a powerful base close to the Mn(4)-bound substrate water ligand.</annotationART></s> <s sid="246"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res63" novelty="None" advantage="None">This redox-active Mn(4) is now able simultaneously to lose an electron to Y<SB>Z</SB>–O˙ and a proton to CP43–Arg357 in a concerted ETPT reaction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="247"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res64" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reduction of Y<SB>Z</SB>–O˙ is, as always, coupled to proton transfer from D1–His190.</annotationART></s> <s sid="248"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res65" novelty="None" advantage="None">The final panel of the figure shows the S<SB>3</SB> state, which is electrostatically poised to undergo a similar ETPT reaction in its next transition, S<SB>3</SB> → S<SB>4</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="249"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res66" novelty="None" advantage="None">The cluster begins with a positive charge in both of the transitions after S<SB>1</SB> → S<SB>2</SB>, and each S<SB><IT>n</IT>&gt;1</SB>Y<SB>Z</SB>˙ state provides sufficient positive charge to create transiently the guanidine base required for electroneutral oxidation of the cluster.</annotationART></s> <s sid="250"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res67" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ET-coupled change in p<IT>K</IT><SB>a</SB> of the arginine side-chain (from a value below the ambient pH in the protonated form to a value higher than the ambient pH in the deprotonated form) admirably satisfies Krishtalik’s energetic requirement for water oxidation, which was proposed by Babcock to be fulfilled by the changing p<IT>K</IT><SB>a</SB> of Y<SB>Z</SB>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18 cit50">18,50</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="251"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp11" novelty="None" advantage="None">We similarly suggest that oxidation of the cluster in the higher S-states is thermodynamically coupled to the simultaneous protonation of a strong, nearby base, but that the base is the guanidine side-chain of CP43–Arg357 rather than the tyrosinate side-chain of Y<SB>Z</SB>. </annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="252"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res68" novelty="None" advantage="None">Although there is no unambiguous experimental support for our proposed role of CP43–Arg357 in the Kok cycle, ET kinetic data have been interpreted in terms of a species near Y<SB>Z</SB> (CP43–Arg357 is a little over 7 Å from Y<SB>Z</SB>) shifting its p<IT>K</IT><SB>a</SB> upon Y<SB>Z</SB> oxidation from a value ≥9 to around 6, and thus deprotonating to the protein exterior.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit113">113</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="253"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res69" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is possible that this species is CP43–Arg357.</annotationART></s> <s sid="254"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac132" novelty="None" advantage="None">Also in agreement with our proposal are ET and proton release kinetic data which have shown correspondence between a lag phase of ET from the metal–oxo cluster to Y<SB>Z</SB>˙ and a rapid phase of local electrochromism occurring in the time range of rapid deprotonation.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit51 cit114">51,114</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="255"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res70" novelty="None" advantage="None">Lavergne and co-workers have interpreted these results as indicating that Y<SB>Z</SB>˙ reduction by the OEC cluster is controlled by the deprotonation of a group closer to the cluster than it is to Y<SB>Z</SB>, so that, by acting as a base, this group increases the driving force of the reduction of Y<SB>Z</SB>˙.</annotationART></s> <s sid="256"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res71" novelty="None" advantage="None">This interpretation perfectly describes our proposal for the role of CP43–Arg357, which is shown in the crystal structure to be <IT>ca</IT>. 3 Å closer to the cluster than it is to Y<SB>Z</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="257"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac133" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is important to note that these ideas, which concern the coupling of Y<SB>Z</SB>–OH oxidation to the alteration of the p<IT>K</IT><SB>a</SB> of a nearby species, require that the proton lost by Y<SB>Z</SB>–OH remain in the OEC in order to exert its electrostatic effect.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29">29</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="258"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res72" novelty="None" advantage="None">Such ideas are given credibility by the new crystal structure, which shows no clear way for protons to escape from the hydrogen-bonded pair of residues, Y<SB>Z</SB> and D1–His190.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="259"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res73" novelty="None" advantage="None">The hydrogen-bonding network around the OEC is stapled in place by the CP43–Arg357 side-chain, organizing the flow of protons from the substrate water to D1–Asp61 as electrons flow to Y<SB>Z</SB> in the later S-state transitions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="260"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp12" novelty="None" advantage="None">We suggest that it is the disruption of this network by chloride depletion, calcium depletion or acetate inhibition that prevents the OEC from being oxidized beyond the S<SB>2</SB> state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="261"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res74" novelty="None" advantage="None">Such disruption means that CP43–Arg357 is unable easily to deprotonate to bulk upon attainment of the S<SB>2</SB>Y<SB>Z</SB>˙ state, with the result that proton abstraction cannot be coupled to the further oxidation of the cluster.</annotationART></s> <s sid="262"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res75" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reduction potential of Y<SB>Z</SB>˙ is then not high enough, at least at normal pH values, to continue the Kok cycle.</annotationART></s> <s sid="263"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res76" novelty="None" advantage="None">The proton lost in the S<SB>0</SB> → S<SB>1</SB> transition evidently does not require such an ordered hydrogen-bonding network, and so we propose that this proton is lost from a Mn(4)-ligand that is directly connected to the proton exit route, rendering the hydrogen-bond network less important in this step.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>The role of calcium and chloride in hydrogen-bonding around the OEC</HEADER><P><s sid="264"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res77" novelty="None" advantage="None">In our proposal the substrate water and chloride bound to Ca<SP>2+</SP> are linked into the hydrogen-bonded network as described above and indicated in Fig. 4.</annotationART></s> <s sid="265"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res78" novelty="None" advantage="None">Metal-bound chloride is an established hydrogen-bond acceptor<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit115">115</REF> and, consonant with its proposed role in proton translocation (see above), chloride in our proposed position would be able to accept a hydrogen-bond from the substrate water bound to the dangler Mn(4).</annotationART></s> <s sid="266"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res79" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both bromide and iodide could partially fulfill this function, although metal-bound fluoride, in line with its inhibitory effect, exhibits markedly different hydrogen-bonding behavior from that of its heavier congeners.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit116">116</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="267"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res80" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is conceivable that acetate bound at the OEC would break up the hydrogen-bonding network by binding to calcium in place of chloride (possibly also displacing a substrate water) and by presenting its methyl group to neighboring species.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>The role of bicarbonate in the water-splitting reaction</HEADER><P><s sid="268"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj6" novelty="New" advantage="None">There is currently considerable debate concerning the role of bicarbonate in the donor-side reactions of PSII.</annotationART></s> <s sid="269"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac134" novelty="None" advantage="None">The debate stretches back to Otto Warburg, who proposed that bicarbonate was a substrate in the oxygen-forming reaction, and the ion’s role in the OEC has since been intermittently investigated.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit117">117</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="270"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac135" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, isotope-exchange experiments show that water molecules, rather than carbonate or bicarbonate, are the substrates in the oxygen-forming reaction.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit118">118</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="271"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac136" novelty="None" advantage="None">There is evidence, notably from Dismukes and co-workers, that bicarbonate is involved in the assembly of the OEC.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit119">119</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="272"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac137" novelty="None" advantage="None">Investigations into the effects of bicarbonate on the OEC are complicated by the diverse effects of bicarbonate on PSII, particularly on the acceptor-side.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit120">120</REF> </annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="273"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res81" novelty="None" advantage="None">The appearance in the new crystal structure of electron density that may be modeled as bicarbonate, carbonate or nitrate near to the Mn<SB>3</SB>CaO<SB>4</SB>–Mn cluster is certain to provoke renewed discussion of bicarbonate’s role in the OEC.</annotationART></s> <s sid="274"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res82" novelty="None" advantage="None">Given that, in the structure, the modeled bicarbonate occupies the apparent active site of the OEC, and that bicarbonate is not a substrate in the oxygen-evolving reaction, it is hard to see what mechanistic conclusions may be drawn from its presence.</annotationART></s> <s sid="275"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res83" novelty="None" advantage="None">We treat it as an adventitious anion binding in an inactive form of the OEC and have therefore neglected it in our mechanism.</annotationART></s> <s sid="276"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res84" novelty="None" advantage="None">We do not rule out a role for bicarbonate in the operation of the OEC, perhaps in regulating proton currents by forming part of the hydrogen-bonding network, but there is no evidence for its direct involvement in the water-splitting reaction.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Mechanism of water oxidation</HEADER><P><s sid="277"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res85" novelty="None" advantage="None">We show in Fig. 4 the Mn<SB>3</SB>CaO<SB>4</SB> cluster and some surrounding amino-acid residues as the OEC cycles through our proposed mechanism of water oxidation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="278"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res86" novelty="None" advantage="None">The changing redox state of Y<SB>Z</SB>, which is alternately reduced by the cluster and oxidized by P<SB>680</SB><SP>+</SP>˙, is indicated alongside the reaction arrows.</annotationART></s> <s sid="279"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res87" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that the S<SB>0–3</SB> states are drawn in the S<SB><IT>n</IT></SB>Y<SB>Z</SB>˙ state, which means that the Y<SB>Z</SB>˙ radical is poised to oxidize the cluster.</annotationART></s> <s sid="280"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res88" novelty="None" advantage="None">The transiently-stable S<SB>4</SB> state never co-exists with the Y<SB>Z</SB>˙ radical and so is shown in the S<SB>4</SB>Y<SB>Z</SB> state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="281"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res89" novelty="None" advantage="None">The two Mn ions on the bottom face of the cuboidal cluster are not redox-active and remain in the +4 oxidation state throughout the cycle.</annotationART></s> <s sid="282"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res90" novelty="None" advantage="None">Mn(3) and Mn(4) change their oxidation states as described previously in Fig. 1.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="283"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res91" novelty="None" advantage="None">The first transition, S<SB>0</SB> → S<SB>1</SB>, involves the oxidation of Mn(4) and the concomitant loss of a proton from its non-substrate water ligand.</annotationART></s> <s sid="284"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res92" novelty="None" advantage="None">This water is directly hydrogen-bonded to the D1–Asp61, the start of the proton exit pathway, and so this PCET is able to occur in the absence of a normal hydrogen-bonded network around the rest of the OEC (Cl<SP>−</SP> depletion or acetate inhibition) and even in the absence of a normally-constructed cluster (Ca<SP>2+</SP>-depletion).</annotationART></s> <s sid="285"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res93" novelty="None" advantage="None">The second oxidation of the cluster, to reach the S<SB>2</SB>Y<SB>Z</SB> state, involves ET only and so the cluster develops a positive charge.</annotationART></s> <s sid="286"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res94" novelty="None" advantage="None">This reaction, involving no proton transfer at all, occurs particularly easily.</annotationART></s> <s sid="287"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res95" novelty="None" advantage="None">Oxidation of Y<SB>Z</SB> to reach the S<SB>2</SB>Y<SB>Z</SB>˙ state is swiftly followed by deprotonation of CP43–Arg357, allowing concerted, bifurcated ETPT now to take place.</annotationART></s> <s sid="288"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res96" novelty="None" advantage="None">Y<SB>Z</SB> accepts an electron from Mn(4), while at the same time neutral arginine abstracts (along a hydrogen-bond) a proton from the metal’s bound substrate water.</annotationART></s> <s sid="289"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res97" novelty="None" advantage="None">Oxidation of Y<SB>Z</SB> by P<SB>680</SB><SP>+</SP>˙ forms the S<SB>3</SB>Y<SB>Z</SB>˙ state of the OEC.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="290"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res98" novelty="None" advantage="None">Owing to the positive charge on the cluster, the next transition follows a similar mechanism.</annotationART></s> <s sid="291"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res99" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this S<SB>3</SB> → S<SB>4</SB> step, transiently-neutral CP43–Arg357 abstracts the second and final proton from Mn(4)’s substrate water, forming Mn<SP>V</SP>O.</annotationART></s> <s sid="292"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res100" novelty="None" advantage="None">The subsequent S<SB>4</SB> → S<SB>4</SB>′ transition is the crucial O–O bond-forming step, and involves the formation of a peroxo intermediate at Mn(4), which is concomitantly reduced from Mn<SP>V</SP> to Mn<SP>III</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="293"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res101" novelty="None" advantage="None">We assume that the arginine side-chain remains protonated in this step, because Y<SB>Z</SB> stays reduced until the formation of S<SB>0</SB> and therefore does not exert any electrostatic effect on CP43–Arg357.</annotationART></s> <s sid="294"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res102" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore the proton that is lost in the spontaneous S<SB>4</SB> → S<SB>4</SB>′ step we take to move to bulk, without the intercession of any specific base, through a hydrogen-bonded proton-relay network <IT>via</IT> D1–Asp61.</annotationART></s> <s sid="295"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res103" novelty="None" advantage="None">The nearby D1–Gln165 residue may play a role in this step by accepting a hydrogen-bond from the calcium-bound substrate water as it nucleophilically attacks the Mn<SP>V</SP>O group.</annotationART></s> <s sid="296"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res104" novelty="None" advantage="None">Finally, the unstable Mn<SP>III</SP>-bound peroxo intermediate S<SB>4</SB>′ decays to produce dioxygen and the OEC is reset to the S<SB>0</SB> state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="297"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res105" novelty="None" advantage="None">Because Mn(4) in this step is reduced all the way to weakly-acidic Mn<SP>II</SP>, it is plausible that the proton lost from the peroxo intermediate simply moves to the Mn(4) hydroxo ligand next to D1–Asp61, reforming the metal’s non-substrate water ligand.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Conclusions</HEADER><P><s sid="298"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res106" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this paper we have considered the mechanism of water-oxidation by the OEC with reference to the newly-published crystal structure of PSII.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">7</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="299"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res107" novelty="None" advantage="None">The structure generally agrees well with our existing mechanistic proposal,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF> and is consistent with the involvement of two substrate water molecules bound respectively to Ca<SP>2+</SP> and Mn(4).</annotationART></s> <s sid="300"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the structure does not reveal a proton-exit route from Y<SB>Z</SB>, which casts doubt on this residue’s ability to act as a catalytic base.</annotationART></s> <s sid="301"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">CP43–Arg357 is apparently well-suited to play this role instead.</annotationART></s> <s sid="302"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The arginine side-chain is close to the active face of the metal-oxo cluster, and its protonation state is plausibly coupled to the redox state of Y<SB>Z</SB> in the higher S-state transitions, during which the metal-oxo cluster is positively charged.</annotationART></s> <s sid="303"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">We propose that these transitions (S<SB>2</SB> → S<SB>3</SB> and S<SB>3</SB> → S<SB>4</SB>) proceed by bifurcated, concerted electron/proton transfer (ETPT), with an electron passing from Mn(4) to Y<SB>Z</SB>˙, and a proton simultaneously passing from the Mn(4)-bound substrate water to the transiently-neutral CP43–Arg357 side-chain.</annotationART></s> <s sid="304"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Such highly-coupled electron and proton transfer requires an organized hydrogen-bonding network around the OEC, linking the substrate waters both to CP43–Arg357 and to D1–Asp61, the start of the crystallographically-resolved proton-exit pathway.</annotationART></s> <s sid="305"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Proton-coupled electron transfers in other S-state transitions do not involve neutral CP43–Arg357 as a base and have less stringent organizational requirements, in line with experimental data.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
