<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b407728h" hasDoc="yes" version="1168" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None"><IT>In situ</IT> XRD and HRTEM studies on the evolution of the Cu/ZnO methanol synthesis catalyst during its reduction and re-oxidation</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">During the formation of the CuZnO solid solutions, the foreign anions in anion-modified (a.m.-) oxides give rise to: (i) extended stacking faults of (002) ZnO lattice plane, which are occupied by copper ions in the form of small clusters; and (ii) vacant inner holes of the a.m.-ZnO crystal.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The main part of copper ions in the clusters is reduced to Cu<SP>0</SP> with hydrogen at 473 K. According to HRTEM studies, the reduction of Cu<SB>0.08</SB>Zn<SB>0.92</SB>O results in the formation of copper metal species of two types: (i) particles of 3–10 nm in size on the a.m.-ZnO surface; and (ii) small (no more than 3 nm in size) atomic copper metal clusters in defect voids of the a.m.-ZnO structure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The copper metal clusters are coherent inclusions in the bulk of the ZnO, and the large copper metal particles are epitaxially bonded to the surface of the ZnO matrix.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Copper metal particles on the surface of a.m.-ZnO are reoxidized to Cu<SP>+2</SP> at 523 K in the helium flow containing 0.05 vol% oxygen, and they come back to the extended stacking faults.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The copper metal clusters in the holes of a.m.-ZnO are inaccessible to the oxygen and are not reoxidized.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Methanol is used as the principal feedstock for production of many organic compounds, among which are formaldehyde, acetic acid, methyl-methacrilate MMA, dimethyl-terephthalate DMT, methyl-<IT>tert</IT>-butylether MTBE and chloromethanes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Due to its high energetic density and no problem in its storage and handling, methanol is also considered an important liquid power-supplier in fuel cells.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Copper–zinc and copper–zinc–aluminium oxide catalysts, which are very selective and active enough at low-pressure conditions, are mainly used for the methanol synthesis.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">A variety of techniques were applied by numerous researchers<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2 cit3 cit4 cit5 cit6 cit7 cit8 cit9 cit10">1–10</REF> for studying the active state of the copper–zinc catalysts but the nature of the active sites is still disputable in literature.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">The present research is focused on the structure of the active state of the methanol synthesis catalysts by means of studying the model copper–zinc catalysts, including the as-prepared sample, as well as those after hydrogen reduction and mild re-oxidation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None">The chosen samples are the solid solutions of copper ions in anion-modified zinc oxide Cu<SB>0.08</SB>Zn<SB>0.92</SB>O and solid solutions of copper and aluminium ions in anion-modified zinc oxide Cu<SB>0.2</SB>Al<SB>0.1</SB>Zn<SB>0.7</SB>O.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">They are known to be the precursors for active catalysts for synthesis of methanol.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11 cit12 cit13 cit14">11–14</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">It has been shown before that these solid solutions of copper (and aluminium) cations in the zinc oxide structure can only be obtained <IT>via</IT> low-temperature (not higher than 773–823 K) decomposition of Cu(Al)Zn hydroxycarbonates of hydrozincite or aurichalcite clay structure<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12 cit15">12,15</REF> to produce OH- and CO<SB>3</SB>-containing zinc oxide (anion-modified, a.m.-ZnO).</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ad-anions provide stabilization of copper cations in the zinc oxide structure, <IT>i.e.</IT> dissolution of the copper cations in the a.m.-ZnO.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Al<SP>3+</SP> cations dissolved in zinc oxide cause an increase of the clusters in number thus preventing formation of the copper oxide phase as the copper concentration increases.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">ES studies of the solid solutions at 5000–50000 cm<SP>−1</SP> showed copper cations forming oxygen-containing small clusters Cu<SP>2+</SP>–O–Cu<SP>2+</SP> with the strongly distorted, almost flat-square, oxygen coordination of Cu<SP>2+</SP>.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The hydrogen treatment at temperatures below 573 K results in the reduction of the majority of the copper ions from the a.m.-ZnO followed by the copper diffusion to the a.m.-ZnO surface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">XRD data allow the hypothesis that metallic copper forms 3–4 nm crystallites which are epitaxially bonded to the ZnO.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The epitaxy of Cu<SP><SB><SP>0</SP></SB></SP> crystallites over ZnO support was directly shown by the <IT>in situ</IT> HREM.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit9">9</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The data of <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18 cit19">refs. 18 and 19</REF> also give the grounds for the supposition that the reduction of copper cations from a.m.-ZnO solid solution is reversible: the epitaxial Cu<SP>0</SP> particles are easily re-oxidizable and can return to the a.m.-ZnO structure under the action of low partial pressures of oxygen.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reversible reduction–oxidation of copper–zinc oxide was also observed recently in .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">ref. 20</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Meanwhile, the air treatment transforms the epitaxial Cu<SP>0</SP> particles to CuO phase.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The goal of the present study is to give a better understanding of the structural evolution of the methanol synthesis catalysts during their reduction and re-oxidation by means of <IT>in situ</IT> XRD and HRTEM.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="New" advantage="None">The nature of the copper species migration is in the focus of the investigation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The catalytic activity of both Cu/ZnO and CuAl/ZnO catalysts is proportional to the copper concentration in the a.m.-ZnO.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">11</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This allows to assume a similar nature of the Cu/ZnO and CuAl/ZnO catalysts action in the methanol synthesis, while introduction of Al<SP>3+</SP> contributes to increasing the solubility of Cu<SP>2+</SP> in a.m.-ZnO and improves the thermal stability of the catalyst.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj5" novelty="New" advantage="None">Since the electron microscopic studies can give more clear results for the double oxide system (<IT>i.e.</IT>, without aluminium), these studies were first performed for the Cu<SB>0.08</SB>Zn<SB>0.92</SB>O sample.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Meanwhile, we considered it important to present in this paper the <IT>in situ</IT> XRD data for the reduction–oxidation evolution of the Cu<SB>0.2</SB>Al<SB>0.1</SB>Zn<SB>0.7</SB>O sample as well.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">The study uses exactly the same samples of Cu<SB>0.08</SB>Zn<SB>0.92</SB>O and Cu<SB>0.2</SB>Al<SB>0.1</SB>Zn<SB>0.7</SB>O, which were studied earlier in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11 cit12 cit13 cit17 cit18 cit19">refs. 11–13 and 17–19</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Experimental procedures</HEADER><P><s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Samples of a.m.-CuO, a.m.-ZnO, a.m.-Cu<SB>0.08</SB>Zn<SB>0.92</SB>O and a.m.-Cu<SB>0.2</SB>Al<SB>0.1</SB>Zn<SB>0.7</SB>O were prepared by calcination of the corresponding hydroxycarbonates in flowing air at 623 K for 4 h.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Hydroxycarbonate precursors of Cu/ZnO and CuAl/ZnO catalysts were synthesized <IT>via</IT> the continuous co-precipitation method.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Solution of sodium carbonate and mixture of appropriate quantities of 0.5 M solutions of copper, zinc and aluminum nitrates were added dropwise at 343–348 K and pH = 6.8–7.0 to an appropriate buffer solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Dwell time was 30 min.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Copper nitrate 3-hydrate (Saki Chemical Plant, Russia, &gt;99% pure), zinc nitrate 6-hydrate (Donetsk Chemical Plant, Ukraine, &gt;98% pure) and aluminum nitrate 9-hydrate (Donetsk Chemical Plant, Ukraine, &gt;99% pure) were used.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The precipitates were thoroughly washed to remove Na<SP>+</SP> and NO<SB>3</SB><SP>−</SP> ions, filtered out, and dried under IR-lamp overnight.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Reductive treatments were performed in flowing hydrogen at 473 K for 1 h, heating rate −2 K min<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The re-oxidations were performed in the flowing mixture of helium and oxygen (0.05% O<SB>2</SB>) at 2 K min<SP>−1</SP>, 523 K, until the termination of oxygen absorption.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">A Siemens D-500 and a Bruker-D8 diffractometers (Germany) with Cu Kα radiation were used for <IT>in situ</IT> X-ray diffraction (XRD) studies.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">A high-temperature reactor chamber<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF> was linked to the gas feeding system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">At first, in this chamber the full diffraction patterns were acquired for the as-prepared samples.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Then, the samples were reduced in flowing hydrogen at 2K min<SP>−1</SP> 473 K until the diffraction patterns (monitored by the intensity of Cu<SP>0</SP> (111) line) stopped changing, and the full diffraction patterns were acquired.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Then the reduced samples were reoxidized in the flowing mixture of helium and oxygen (0.05% O<SB>2</SB>) at 523 K until the diffraction patterns stopped changing.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Samples treated under present conditions were studied using high resolution transmission electron microscopy (HRTEM).</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Electron micrographs were obtained with JEM-2010 instrument with lattice resolution 1.4 Å and accelerating voltage 200 kV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Periodic images of lattices structures were analyzed using digital Fourier transformation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Local elemental analysis was performed with EDX method on Energy-dispersive X-ray Phoenix spectrometer equipped with Si (Li) detector with energy resolution not worse than 130 eV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Samples were fixed on ≪holey≫ carbon films supported on copper or molybdenum grids and investigated with the electron microscope.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="Old" advantage="None"><IT>In situ</IT> thermogravimetric (STA) data were obtained by means of the Netzsch STA 409 thermobalance.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The sensitivity of the weight measurements was about 0.01 mg (<IT>ca</IT>. 0.02% of the sample weight).</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met14" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The heating rate was 5 K min<SP>−1</SP>).</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Results and discussion</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="1.">Studies of the as-prepared samples</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="1.1.">XRD and STA studies</HEADER><P><s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 1 shows the diffraction patterns of as-prepared samples: a.m.-CuO (curve 1), a.m.-ZnO (curve 2), a.m.-Cu<SB>0.08</SB>Zn<SB>0.92</SB>O (curve 3).</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The diffraction pattern of as-prepared a.m.-Cu<SB>0.2</SB>Al<SB>0.1</SB>Zn<SB>0.7</SB>O is presented by curve 1 in Fig. 2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The lines of zinc oxide are only seen in the diffraction patterns acquired both for a.m.-Cu<SB>0.08</SB>Zn<SB>0.92</SB>O and a.m.-Cu<SB>0.2</SB>Al<SB>0.1</SB>Zn<SB>0.7</SB>O samples, as well as for a.m.-ZnO.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">So, only one phase with ZnO structure is observed in a.m.-Cu<SB>0.08</SB>Zn<SB>0.92</SB>O and a.m.-Cu<SB>0.2</SB>Al<SB>0.1</SB>Zn<SB>0.7</SB>O.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">No copper oxide phase is seen.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The STA method provides additional evidence for the absence of a copper oxide phase.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 3 shows a TPR profile recorded for the a.m.-Cu<SB>0.08</SB>Zn<SB>0.92</SB>O sample in flowing hydrogen.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Two effects are observed at 435 and 680 K. According to XRD data, the first effect is caused by the reduction of copper and formation of metallic particles.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The weight loss of 1.44% weight corresponds to the reduction of <IT>ca.</IT> 92% of the Cu<SP>2+</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The second weight loss at <IT>ca</IT>. 680 K is related to the removal of the ad-anions and the recrystallization of the metallic copper particles as well as of the a.m.-ZnO phase giving the regular zinc oxide.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The peculiarities of the transformation of the anion-modified oxides into regular oxides were discussed earlier in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22 cit23">refs. 22 and 23</REF>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The existence of the weight loss at 680 K in hydrogen flow proves that the sample Cu<SB>0.08</SB>Zn<SB>0.92</SB>O after calcination at 625 K contains the ad-anions, <IT>i.e.</IT> represents itself as the anion-modified mixed oxide.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The weight loss at above 750 K is accounted for by the reduction of ZnO and evaporation of metallic zinc.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="1.2.">Electron microscopic studies</HEADER><P><s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">HRTEM micrograph of anion-modified zinc oxide, a.m.-ZnO, is shown in Fig. 4 (left).</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">There are seen (002) planes of ZnO crystal lattice with a lattice spacing of 0.26 nm (the (002) planes are oriented normally to the plane of the micrograph).</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Microvoids are seen in the crystal bulk as rounded 2–3 nm spots of slightly light contrast.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">There is no visible anomalous contrast or distortion of the planes due to imperfection of the crystal lattice.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 4 (right) presents a HRTEM image of a.m.-Cu<SB>0.08</SB>Zn<SB>0.92</SB>O as-prepared.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">As was said above, this is the solid solution of copper ions in a.m.-ZnO.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Here, two types of the structural defects are observed in the micrograph.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The interplanar spacing ZnO (002) is unchanged (0.26 nm), <IT>i.e.</IT> the planes are also perpendicular to the plane of image.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, some planes are seen broken and shifted as a result of (002) plane shear dislocations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">These shearing dislocations cause the formation of stacking faults of (002) lattice planes to substitute for the atomic plane alternation characteristic of the hexagonal lattice.</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">The stacking faults are visible as dark bands along planes (002).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">The stacking faults are linked with the large pores of 5 to 10 nm in size, exposed to the external crystal surface.</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">The defects of the second type are microvoids that are seen in the crystal bulk as light-contrasted 2–3 nm rounded spots.</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">These defects are similar to those observed in a.m.-ZnO.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" advantage="None">From the electron micrography data, when considered along with the data on formation of the sample under consideration, it can be proposed that the observed elongated defects such as stacking faults are the residence regions of impurity anions and copper cations bound to them.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None">The microvoids may form in the crystal bulk as a result of the vacancy sink in the anion lattice during formation of the a.m.-ZnO crystal.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None">The microvoids don’t seem to include copper ions.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res29" novelty="None" advantage="None">So, the performed study of Cu/ZnO catalysts has confirmed the formation of copper and copper and aluminium ion solutions in a.m.-ZnO <IT>via</IT> the low-temperature decomposition of the appropriate hydroxocarbonate.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res30" novelty="None" advantage="None">A.m.-Cu<SB>0.08</SB>Zn<SB>0.92</SB>O and a.m.-Cu<SB>0.2</SB>Al<SB>0.1</SB>Zn<SB>0.7</SB>O samples represent themselves as solid solutions on the basis of a.m.-ZnO and don’t contain the CuO phase.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" advantage="None">The HRTEM data allow discussing the structural peculiarities of a.m.-ZnO based solid solutions and the regularities of copper ions allocation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res29" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is worth emphasizing once more that there is no visible anomalous contrast or distortion of the planes due to imperfection of the crystal lattice in a.m.-ZnO as-prepared, but microvoids are only seen in the crystal bulk of ZnO as the rounded 2–3 nm spots.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res32" novelty="None" advantage="None">Meanwhile, in a.m.-Cu<SB>0.08</SB>Zn<SB>0.92</SB>O as-prepared sample shearing dislocations cause the formation of stacking faults of (002) lattice planes in addition to the microvoids, similar to those observed in a.m.-ZnO.</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res33" novelty="None" advantage="None">Supposedly, these are the observed stretched defects such as stacking faults, where the ad-anions and copper cations are allocated.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.">Studies of patterns after reduction by H<SB>2</SB></HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.1.">XRD studies</HEADER><P><s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Diffraction patterns of a.m.-Cu<SB>0.08</SB>Zn<SB>0.92</SB>O and a.m.-Cu<SB>0.2</SB>Al<SB>0.1</SB>Zn<SB>0.7</SB>O after reduction in flowing hydrogen at 473 K are shown in Figs. 1 (curve 4) and 2 (curve 2), accordingly.</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res34" novelty="None" advantage="None">The lines assigned to copper metal appear.</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res35" novelty="None" advantage="None">The coherent scattering domains allow the estimation of the Cu<SP>0</SP> crystallite size as 3.5–5.0 nm and 3–4 nm, accordingly.</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res36" novelty="None" advantage="None">The observed Cu<SP>0</SP> XRD band intensities ratio shows the plausible imperfection of copper metal particles.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.2.">Electron microscopic studies</HEADER><P><s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 5 shows the micrographs of a.m.-Cu<SB>0.08</SB>Zn<SB>0.92</SB>O reduced with hydrogen.</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The general view of the picture is changed: (i) stacking faults have less contrast; and (ii) two kinds of Cu<SP>0</SP> particles are observed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res37" novelty="None" advantage="None">Some of Cu<SP>0</SP> particles are 3 to 10 nm in size on the surface of zinc oxide and there is also the fraction of small clusters almost equal in size (2–3 nm) which are seen as dark spots in the microvoids of zinc oxide.</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The small clusters are shown at a higher magnification in Figs. 5 (right) and 6 (left).</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res38" novelty="None" advantage="None">The dark spots in the HRTEM micrograph are seen to be made up of Moiré fringes parallel to ZnO (002) lattice plane with periodicity of about 1 nm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res39" novelty="None" advantage="None">They result from superposition of ZnO (002) and cluster Cu<SP>0</SP> (111) planes (<IT>d</IT><SB>002</SB> ZnO = 0.26 nm, <IT>d</IT><SB>111</SB>Cu = 0.21 nm).</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res40" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hexagonal packing is characteristic of these planes in both crystal lattices.</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res41" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fact that Moiré fringes of the fine Cu<SP>0</SP> particles are parallel to ZnO (002) lattice plane indicates the uniform orientation and the coherent lattices of Cu<SP>0</SP> intrusions and the ZnO crystal matrix.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res42" novelty="None" advantage="None">Two types of reflections are seen in the Fourier pattern (Fig. 6, right) of the coherent inclusion: one related to ZnO (the reflections are shown by downward arrows) and another – to Cu<SP>0</SP> (upward arrows).</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res43" novelty="None" advantage="None">Reflections of Cu<SP>0</SP> 111 and 100 are broadened that indicates the presence of stacking faults of (111) metal planes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res44" novelty="None" advantage="None">This structural feature of Cu<SP>0</SP> clusters may happen because the FCC (face centred cubic) structure of Cu is incorporated into HP (hexagonal packing) structure of ZnO.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res45" novelty="None" advantage="None">So, it follows from the obtained XRD results that the reduction of both a.m.-Cu<SB>0.08</SB>Zn<SB>0.92</SB>O and a.m.-Cu<SB>0.2</SB>Al<SB>0.1</SB>Zn<SB>0.7</SB>O leads to the copper metal formation in the form of imperfect particles of small size.</annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res46" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is in good agreement with our earlier data on Cu/ZnO catalysts.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res47" novelty="None" advantage="None">HRTEM studies make it possible to reveal that the reduction of a.m.-Cu<SB>0.08</SB>Zn<SB>0.92</SB>O results in the formation of copper metal species of two types: (i) particles of 3–10 nm in size on the a.m.-ZnO surface; and (ii) small (no more than 3 nm in size) metal copper clusters in microvoids of the a.m.-ZnO structure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res48" novelty="None" advantage="None">The copper clusters are coherent inclusions in the bulk of zinc oxide, and the large particles are epitaxially bonded to the surface of the ZnO matrix in accordance with earlier data.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res49" novelty="None" advantage="None">It should be noted that if such a microvoid is situated in the subsurface layer of ZnO, it seems to be observable by LEIS as a metallic copper particle covered with ZnO.</annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Such a state was observed in <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7">ref. 7</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.">Studies of samples oxidized in the flow of oxygen-containing (0.05 vol% O<SB>2</SB>) helium after reduction with hydrogen</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.1.">XRD studies</HEADER><P><s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Diffraction patterns of a.m.-Cu<SB>0.08</SB>Zn<SB>0.92</SB>O and a.m.-Cu<SB>0.2</SB>Al<SB>0.1</SB>Zn<SB>0.7</SB>O samples after reduction with hydrogen and oxidation by the oxygen–helium mixture are shown in Figs. 1 and 2, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The changes observed in the diffraction patterns of reduced samples in the course of oxidation (Fig. 1, curves 5–7 and Fig. 2, curves 3–4) are the same: the lines with <IT>d</IT> = 0.208 nm decrease in intensity to disappear within <IT>ca.</IT> 2 h.</annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res50" novelty="None" advantage="None">Some difference in the behavior of the samples is that the line with <IT>d</IT> = 0.208 nm is shifted to <IT>d</IT> = 0.212 nm as its intensity decreases in the diffraction pattern of the a.m.-Cu<SB>0.2</SB>Al<SB>0.1</SB>Zn<SB>0.7</SB>O sample.</annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res51" novelty="None" advantage="None">The line with <IT>d</IT> = 0.212 nm is the most intense in the pattern of Cu<SB>2</SB>O.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None">After re-reduction with hydrogen of the samples at 500 K, the diffraction pattern (Fig. 2, curve 5) is identical to those of the primarily reduced samples (Fig. 1, curve 4 and Fig. 2, curve 2).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None">When the samples are re-oxidized again (re-re-oxidation) in the flowing oxygen-containing helium, the characteristic lines of copper metal disappear again (Fig. 2, curves 6–8).</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, Figs. 1 and 2 illustrate the experimental observations of the reversible changes in copper state in the samples under study.</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res52" novelty="None" advantage="None">Copper ions in the structure of a.m.-ZnO are reduced with hydrogen to form copper metal, then Cu<SP>0</SP> atoms are oxidized in the flowing oxygen-containing helium to form Cu<SP>2+</SP> ions, which return back to the zinc oxide structure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res53" novelty="None" advantage="None">The obtained results on the evolution of the diffraction patterns during re-oxidation of the reduced a.m.-Cu<SB>0.08</SB>Zn<SB>0.92</SB>O and a.m.-Cu<SB>0.2</SB>Al<SB>0/1</SB>Zn<SB>0.7</SB>O samples are the direct proof of the reversible red-ox copper behaviour.</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">This phenomenon for Cu/ZnO sample has been shown by us before<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18 cit19">18,19</REF> and recently reported elsewhere.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res54" novelty="None" advantage="None">For a.m.-Cu-Al-ZnO, it is for the first time shown in the present work.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.2.">Electron microscopic studies</HEADER><P><s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 7 shows a HRTEM micrographs of the a.m.-Cu<SB>0.08</SB>Zn<SB>0.92</SB>O sample oxidized in the flow of oxygen containing (0.05 vol%) helium after the reduction with hydrogen.</annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res55" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the micrographs, some elongated defects of stacking faults type are seen in the a.m.-ZnO structure, which are similar to the defects in the pre-reduced sample (see Fig. 4, right) and 2–3 nm clusters of copper metal in the micro-voids of the a.m.-ZnO crystal (the second type of copper metal in the reduced samples).</annotationART></s> <s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res56" novelty="None" advantage="None">The surface copper metal particles (first type of copper metal in the reduced samples) are not observed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res57" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is important that many defective regions, containing stacking faults of ZnO (002) planes, are present.</annotationART></s> <s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res58" novelty="None" advantage="None">They are located in regions near the copper clusters (Fig. 7).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res59" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, HRTEM studies make it possible to reveal that oxidation of surface copper metal particles by oxygen (at its low partial pressure) brings major copper back to the bulk of a.m.-ZnO crystal.</annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res60" novelty="None" advantage="None">The copper cations are localized at the stacking faults in the a.m.-ZnO crystal.</annotationART></s> <s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res61" novelty="None" advantage="None">Copper metal particles of 2–3 nm in size in the microvoids in the bulk of the a.m.-ZnO structure are inaccessible to the oxygen.</annotationART></s> <s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res62" novelty="None" advantage="None">The portion of preserved Cu<SP>0</SP> after the treatment in O<SB>2</SB>-containing mixture is not so high, since it is not detected by XRD.</annotationART></s> <s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res63" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hence, HREM data also argue for the reversible reduction of copper–zinc samples, <IT>i.e.</IT> the main part of copper particles formed in the sample upon treatment with hydrogen can be re-oxidized to return to the structure of defective zinc oxide.</annotationART></s> <s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res64" novelty="None" advantage="None">The quantitative evaluation of the amount of Cu<SP>0</SP> in the re-oxidized samples needs the use of the other investigation techniques, <IT>e.g</IT>. the measurements of the temperature dependence of the magnetic susceptibility.</annotationART></s> <s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">We expect to present the relevant data on the magnetic susceptibility of the CuZn and CuAlZn samples in one of our next publications.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Conclusions</HEADER><P><s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res65" novelty="None" advantage="None">The solid solutions of copper and aluminum ions in anion-modified ZnO are formed in the course of low temperature decomposition of appropriate hydroxocarbonates.</annotationART></s> <s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res66" novelty="None" advantage="None">Copper metal as a defect particles of small size is formed as a result of the reduction with hydrogen.</annotationART></s> <s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res67" novelty="None" advantage="None">Copper cations reduction is reversible: the return of copper back to the a.m.-ZnO structure occurs during re-oxidation with oxygen at low partial pressures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res68" novelty="None" advantage="None">The HRTEM studies allow to reveal the sites of copper cations placed in the solid solution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res69" novelty="None" advantage="None">Important details of the reduction and reoxidation processes can be understood, among which are the following:</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res70" novelty="None" advantage="None">(i).</annotationART></s> <s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res70" novelty="None" advantage="None">For as-prepared samples it is shown that two types of defects can be observed in a.m.-Cu<SB>0.08</SB>Zn<SB>0.92</SB>O: shearing dislocations causing the formation of stacking faults of ZnO (002) lattice planes and microvoids in the crystal bulk in the form of 2–3 nm rounded spots.</annotationART></s> <s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res70" novelty="None" advantage="None">Only one type of defects is observed in a.m.-ZnO – microvoids in the crystal bulk of ZnO rounded 2–3 nm spots, the same as in a.m.-Cu<SB>0.08</SB>Zn<SB>0.92</SB>O.</annotationART></s> <s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res70" novelty="None" advantage="None">It may be thought that the observed stretched defects such as stacking faults are the residence regions of impurity anions and copper cations linked to them.</annotationART></s> <s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res70" novelty="None" advantage="None">Microvoids in the crystal bulk are not the residence places of copper cations.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res71" novelty="None" advantage="None">(ii) The reduction with hydrogen at temperatures below 573 K results in reduction of copper cations from stacking faults to Cu<SP>0</SP> atoms and their diffusion either to the surface of the anion-modified zinc oxide or to free microvoids nearby the elongated defects.</annotationART></s> <s sid="143"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res71" novelty="None" advantage="None">The particles on the a.m.-ZnO surface are of 3–10 nm in size and are epitaxially bonded to the surface of the a.m.-ZnO matrix.</annotationART></s> <s sid="144"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res71" novelty="None" advantage="None">The copper metal atoms in the microvoids form clusters limited by the size of the microvoids, <IT>i.e</IT>. less than 2–3 nm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="145"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res71" novelty="None" advantage="None">The copper metal clusters are coherent inclusions in the bulk of zinc oxide.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="146"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res72" novelty="None" advantage="None">(iii) The oxidation of surface copper metal particles by oxygen (at its low partial pressure) brings major copper back to the bulk of a.m.-ZnO crystal.</annotationART></s> <s sid="147"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res72" novelty="None" advantage="None">The copper atoms are localized at the stacking faults in the a.m.-ZnO structure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="148"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res72" novelty="None" advantage="None">Copper metal particles in the form of 2–3 nm clusters in the microvoids of the bulk of the a.m.-ZnO structure are inaccessible to the oxygen and are not oxidized.</annotationART></s> <s sid="149"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res72" novelty="None" advantage="None">The portion of preserved Cu<SP>0</SP> after the treatment in O<SB>2</SB>-containing mixture is not so high, since it is not detected by XRD.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
