<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b410283e" hasDoc="yes" version="1168" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Monitoring the formation of biosilica catalysed by histidine-tagged silicatein<XREF TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" /></annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Surface bound silicatein retains its biocatalytic activity, which was demonstrated by monitoring the immobilisation of silicatein using a histidine-tag chelating anchor and the subsequent biosilicification of SiO<SB>2</SB> on surfaces by surface plasmon resonance spectroscopy, atomic force microscopy and scanning electron microscopy.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER /><P><s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Nanoscale control of polymerization of silicon and oxygen determines the structures and properties of a wide range of siloxane-based materials.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">These materials typically require high temperatures, high pressures and the use of caustic chemicals.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2">2</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In comparison, biological systems can synthesise siloxane-based materials at ambient temperatures and pressures and produce an amazing diversity of precisely nanostructured morphologies.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Biosilicification in diatoms,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF> sponges<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5">5</REF> and grasses<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6">6</REF> represents typical examples in this context.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The study of biosilicification has led to the isolation of proteins that facilitate silica formation <IT>in vivo</IT>, in particular, silaffins in diatoms<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF> and silicateins in sponges<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit7 cit8 cit9">5,7–9</REF> have been studied and identified as constituents of biosilica (silica formed by proteins) showing an accelerated silica formation from monosilisic acid solution <IT>in vitro.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8">8</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">To verify the specificity and significance of the above proteins in biosilicification, a variety of synthetic polymers including polypeptides and di-block co-polypeptides have been investigated for their role in silicification in solution.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit10 cit11">8,10,11</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The process of silica formation in marine sponges is thought to be mediated by a family of catalytically active structure-directing enzymes, the so-called silicateins.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">It has been shown that silicateins facilitate the formation of SiO<SB>2</SB> in solution at neutral pH using tetraethoxysilane (TEOS) as a monomer,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit7 cit9">5,7,9</REF> whereas no polymerization of TEOS was observed at neutral pH in the absence of silicatein.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">To understand the operation of silicatein and the formation of the resulting silica structures at the molecular level by means of surface methods, we present the immobilization of silicatein which was isolated from marine sponge <IT>Suberites domuncula</IT>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In order to be able to immobilise silicatein onto surfaces we synthesised a chelator alkanethiol based on the idea that silicatein expresses a short affinity sequence of histidines (histidine-tag) that is capable of binding metal ion complexes such as nitrilotriacetic acid (NTA).</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">It's known that NTA, when complexed with Ni<SP>2+</SP>, selectively binds proteins whose sequence is terminated with a sequence of histidines.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The structure of the NTA-terminated alkanethiol, whose synthesis was adopted from similar structures reported recently,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF> is shown in Scheme 1.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The self-assembled monolayer formation of the chelating alkanethiol NTA and the immobilization of the protein to the gold (111) surface were monitored using the surface sensitive optical technique of surface plasmon resonance (SPR).</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The plasmon spectra were recorded against ethanol on bare gold slides, after self-assembly of chelating alkanethiol NTA and after immobilization of silicatein on the gold surfaces, both Ni<SP>2+</SP> coordinated as well as without coordination of Ni<SP>2+</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 1 displays the corresponding SP spectra of some experiments and a closer view of the corresponding minima reflectivity angle.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The shifts of the plasmon curves were calculated, corresponding to angular changes of 0.420° (monolayer of NTA alkanethiol on bare gold) and 0.720° (silicatein on a Ni<SP>2+</SP> coordinated surface).</annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In a separate experiment immobilization of silicatein without Ni<SP>2+</SP> could not be detected, supporting the chelating efficiency of histidine-tags in the presence of Ni<SP>2+</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">These shifts in the surface plasmon resonance angle were converted by complex Fresnel calculations to an average thickness of monolayer of NTA alkanethiol and silicatein layer assuming a refractive index of <IT>n</IT> = 1.5 for both layers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">NTA alkanethiol resulted in a 1.6 nm thick film, while silicatein immobilization increased the thickness by 2.8 nm, which matches the theoretical diameter of 3.0 nm for a protein with a molecular weight of 24 000 Da.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">SPR control experiments showed that silica is not released into the solution.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to confirm that the silicatein was immobilized on the surfaces functionalized with NTA alkanethiol self-assembled monolayers (SAMs), direct evidence by scanning force microscopy (SFM) was provided.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Figs. 2a–c show the SFM height images obtained in the intermediate contact mode of the Au (111) crystal surface, the NTA monolayer surface, and the surface of immobilized silicatein film, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The height and roughness analysis of the topologies of these surfaces supported strong evidence that the modification of Au(111) by NTA alkanethiol SAMs, and subsequently the immobilization of silicatein on the surfaces of NTA alkanethiol SAMs had both taken place.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The roughness of the Au (111) surface was 0.590 nm, which is rather flat, but the roughness of the NTA SAMs surface and the silicatein film surface were 1.415 and 2.384, separately, which were rougher compared with the Au (111) plane.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The increase of the roughness illustrates that the uncoated gold surface is atomically flat, but the NTA-coated gold samples and the silicatein films are only molecularly flat.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">We believe that the SFM image in Fig. 2c arises from the surface of an immobilized silicatein film chemisorbed on the NTA monolayers.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to confirm the activity of silicatein through the ability to precipitate silica from TEOS on the surface, we performed two sets of experiments: one, using a gold surface modified with NTA or NTA with Ni<SP>2+</SP> and a second, with gold surfaces functionalised with immobilized silicatein.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Under these similar sets of conditions for both experiments, we could find structured silica only on the silicatein immobilized surfaces, using SEM characterisation, as shown in Figs. 3b and 3c.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 3a shows the results after having performed the precipitation of silica on the surface modified by NTA thioalkane only.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Clearly, no formation of silica was observed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, the surface became black when exposed to the electron beam in the scanning electron microscope which indicated the presence of organic species, such as NTA alkanethiol, that decomposed upon exposure to the electron beam.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">On surfaces functionalised with silicatein, nanospheres of silica had been precipitated (Figs. 3b and 3c).</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Structures of interconnected nanospheres with a diameter of about 70–300 nm were observed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 3d shows the energy dispersive X-ray (EDX) analysis spectrum of the material synthesised on the surface, which gives evidence that it consists of silica.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Analyzing the EDX spectrum of the surface without immobilized silicatein during the silicatization process showed that no silica was formed here.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The formation of interconnected silica spheres in the vicinity of surface bound protein indicates that the active site of the immobilized protein is oriented towards the solution and that the reaction is diffusion controlled.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is corroborated by the silicification of TEOS with silicatein used as an additive in solution, which resulted in no precipitation of SiO<SB>2</SB> on NTA functionalised surfaces, as can be seen in the ESI.<SUP TYPE="FOOTNOTE_MARKER" ID="fn1" /></annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is obvious from the SEM pictures shown in Figs. 3b and 3c that the coverage of the surface with silica is heterogeneous.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">About 70% of the surface was covered with silica structures.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Whether this is due to the limited reaction time of 8 hours or an imperfect homogeneous immobilisation of the silicatein is the subject of ongoing investigations.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa3" novelty="None" advantage="None">To conclude, we present a novel NTA terminated alkanethiol which can be successfully self-assembled onto gold surfaces.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">These functionalised surfaces could immobilise histidine-tagged silicatein using the efficient chelating properties with Ni<SP>2+</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results presented here demonstrate that silicatein, previously shown active for catalysing and structurally directing the polycondensation of silicon alkoxides in solution when immobilised onto surfaces, is also capable of catalysing and templating the polycondensation of monomeric silicon alkoxides to form silica structures on surfaces.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">This work was funded by the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft within the priority program “Principles of Biomineralisation”.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
