<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b410112" hasDoc="yes" version="1168" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">The dihydrogen bond in X<SB>3</SB>C–H⋯H–M complexes (X = F, Cl, Br; M = Li, Na, K). A correlated quantum chemical <IT>ab initio</IT> and density functional theory study</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">Quantum chemical calculations were performed on nine dihydrogen-bonded complexes with haloform (F<SB>3</SB>CH, Cl<SB>3</SB>CH and Br<SB>3</SB>CH) as a proton donor and alkali metal hydride (HLi, HNa and HK) as a proton acceptor.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">MP2/6-311++G(d,p) and B3LYP/6-311++G(d,p) results show that the stabilization energies of these complexes are large and comparable to the stabilization energies of standard H-bonded complexes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Elongation and weakening (red shift) of the CH, HNa and HK bonds upon complexation were found while contraction and strengthening (blue shift) was observed in HLi.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The H⋯H bond was found to be ionic and its ionicity is larger than that of the H⋯Y bond in standard and improper H-bonds.</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The calculated free energy (Δ<IT>G</IT>) revealed that only potassium hydride complexes (F<SB>3</SB>CH⋯HK, Cl<SB>3</SB>CH⋯HK and Br<SB>3</SB>CH⋯HK) are stable under standard conditions (<IT>T</IT> = 298.150 K and <IT>p</IT> = 101.325 N m<SP>−2</SP>) in the gas phase.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">To elucidate the role of the electrostatic contribution, the optimization of the proton donor and proton acceptor molecules in the electric field of a partner was performed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The HLi bond is contracted in the electric field of the haloform while the HM (M = Na, K) bonds are elongated and the electrostatic field itself is sufficient explanation of these phenomena.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Natural bond order (NBO) and natural resonance theory (NRT) analyses were performed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The NBO analysis revealed that significant electron density was transferred from the σ bonding orbital of a proton acceptor to the antibonding σ*(CH) orbital of the proton donor.</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Symmetry adapted perturbation theory (SAPT) was utilized to decompose the total interaction energy into physically correct contributions.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="1.">Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The first examples of a new type of bonding realized between two hydrogens (X–H⋯H–Y), currently called a dihydrogen bond (DHB) were published in the late 1960s by M. P. Brown and coworkers,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1 cit2">1,2</REF> but the concept of this bond was introduced by Richardson<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit3">3</REF> in 1995.</annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Typically, the DHB occurs between positively and negatively charged hydrogens.</annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">This takes place when the first hydrogen is covalently bound to an element which is more electronegative than hydrogen and, simultaneously, the second hydrogen is bound to an element more electropositive than hydrogen.</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Usually, X = O, N, S, halogen or C, and Y = Ir, Mo, Re, Li, Na, K, B. Since the second hydrogen atom acts as a proton acceptor this kind of interaction is considered an unconventional hydrogen bond.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The DHB is analogous to a classical hydrogen bond.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The distance between the two hydrogen atoms is shorter than 2.4 Å (the sum of the van der Waals radii) and the strength of the DHB is normally between 4 and 6 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>, which corresponds to the average strength of a standard hydrogen bond.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4 cit5 cit6">4–6</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">In recent years, much attention has been paid to understanding DHBs.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit7 cit8 cit9 cit10 cit11 cit12 cit13 cit14 cit15 cit16">7–16</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The nature of classical H-bonding is well understood.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">In classical H-bonding the electron density (ED) is transferred from the proton acceptor (lone electron pairs or π-electrons) to the σ* antibonding orbital of the X–H bond of the proton donor which causes weakening of this bond, its elongation, and a concomitant decrease in the X–H stretching frequency.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">In 1980, Sandorfy <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF>. when measuring the association of fluoroparaffins with various proton acceptors, reported a shift in the C–H stretching frequency to higher values (so called blue shift).</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Further experimental evidence of the blue shift in the C–H stretching frequency appeared in 1989<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19">19</REF> and .1997<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Because the most important features (shortening of the C–H bond and blue shift of the respective stretching vibration frequency) were opposite to the characteristics of a standard H-bond, we called this bonding type improper, blue-shifting H-bonding.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">As mentioned before, the DHB of the X–H⋯H–Y type is considered to be an unconventional hydrogen bond analogous to a standard hydrogen bond.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">This means that, regarding a proton donor (X–H) we should observe analogous features to those found in the case of a classical H-bond (elongation and weakening of the X–H bond and a red shift of the respective stretching frequency).</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">The question remains however, what happens to the vibration characteristics of the proton acceptor upon formation of the DHB?</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">McDowell and Forde<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF> studied isotope effects in the BeH<SB>2</SB>⋯HCN complex and they found that proton acceptor (BeH<SB>2</SB>) harmonic vibrational frequencies (symmetrical as well asymmetrical stretching) are blue-shifted upon complexation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Grabowski<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14 cit23">14,23</REF> investigated complexes of HF as a proton donor with different proton acceptors.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">He showed that in the cases of HLi, HNa, H<SB>2</SB>Be and H<SB>2</SB>Mg the H–X (X = Li, Na, Be, Mg) bond involved in the DHB becomes shorter upon complexation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Berski, Lundell and Latajka<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF> have studied the XeH<SB>2</SB>⋯H<SB>2</SB>O complex and have shown that the stretching frequencies of the proton acceptor are shifted to higher values (blue shift) upon complexation.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The aim of this paper is to study the DHB in complexes formed by haloforms (F<SB>3</SB>CH, Cl<SB>3</SB>CH and Br<SB>3</SB>CH) as a proton donor, and alkali metal hydrides (HLi, HNa and HK) as a proton acceptor.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac20" novelty="None" advantage="None">Haloforms possess a negative gradient in their dipole moment, which means that upon contraction of the C–H bond, the dipole moment of the molecule increases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac21" novelty="None" advantage="None">Let us mention here that in the majority of systems this gradient is positive which indicates that the dipole moment of a system increases when the X–H bond increases.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac22" novelty="None" advantage="None">Consequently, when haloforms are bound to proton acceptors, they mostly form improper blue-shifting H-bonds.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus the question arises: what will happen when these proton donors are bound to an alkali metal hydride which most often exhibits a contraction of the Y–H bond?</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The other goal of the paper is to explain the nature of improper blue-shifting hydrogen bonds in complexes with HLi as a proton acceptor.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.">Theoretical methods</HEADER><P><s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Calculations were performed at the second-order Møller–Plesset perturbation theory (MP2) and density functional method (B3LYP)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24 cit25">24,25</REF> levels using the 6-31G(d,p) and 6-311++G(d,p) basis sets.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26 cit27">26,27</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The DFT method is known to yield reliable characteristics for H-bonding (contrary to stacking where it fails) and its advantage over the MP2 procedure is the fact that it possesses a well-defined one-electron density matrix (like in the Hartree–Fock method) as required for NBO analysis.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The equilibrium structures of the molecules and complexes studied were determined at the B3LYP and MP2 levels.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Natural bond orbital (NBO) analysis<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28">28</REF> was performed using the B3LYP electron densities.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">In the case of the MP2 method the NBO analysis is less reliable.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29 cit30">29,30</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The bond orders in the considered systems were obtained from natural resonance theory (NRT) analysis implemented in an NBO version 5.0 program.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit31">31</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None">To elucidate the role of the electrostatic contribution, optimization was performed on the proton donor and proton acceptor molecules in an electric field generated by point charges of the proton acceptor or proton donor placed where the atoms were in the complex.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The point charges were calculated using the Merz–Kollman<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit32 cit33">32,33</REF> fitting procedure at the MP2/6-311++G(d,p) level.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The stabilization energy of all complexes was calculated at the MP2/6-311++G(d,p) level and was corrected for basis set superposition error (using the Boys–Bernardi counterpoise correction<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit34">34</REF>) as well as for deformation energy.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Decomposition of the total intermolecular interaction energy into physically correct contributions was made by using the symmetry adapted perturbation theory (SAPT).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit35 cit36 cit37 cit38 cit39 cit40 cit41 cit42 cit43 cit44 cit45">35–45</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="Old" advantage="None">This approach, implemented in the SAPT program package,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit46 cit47">46,47</REF> is based on the standard Rayleigh–Schrödinger perturbation theory supplemented by a technique called symmetrized Rayleigh–Schrödinger (SRS) perturbation for treating the antisymmetry property of the wave function of the complex with respect to the monomers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="Old" advantage="None">All computations, except SAPT decomposition, were carried out with the Gaussian 03 package<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit48">48</REF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.">Results and discussion</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Structure</HEADER><P><s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 1 shows the optimized structures of the complexes investigated.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Their geometrical and vibrational parameters obtained at the MP2 and B3LYP levels of theory are presented in Table 1 (“Full complex” column).</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">As seen from the figure, the CHHM atoms in all of the studied complexes are collinear.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">From the data summarized in Table 1 it becomes evident that all C–H bonds in the proton donors (F<SB>3</SB>CH, Cl<SB>3</SB>CH, Br<SB>3</SB>CH) were systematically elongated upon complexation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both theoretical methods used predict geometrical changes in the same direction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The elongation of these bonds given by the B3LYP method was, in all cases, larger than that predicted by MP2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">Shifts in the C–H stretching frequency upon formation of the DHB are presented in Table 1, and, evidently, the red shift of these stretching frequencies is <IT>systematically</IT> observed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Table 1 further shows that the intermolecular H⋯H distances were shorter than 2.4 Å (the sum of the van der Waals radii) and <IT>systematically</IT> decreased in the order F<SB>3</SB>CH &gt; Cl<SB>3</SB>CH &gt; Br<SB>3</SB>CH as well as in the order HLi &gt; HNa &gt; HK.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, the longest H⋯H distance (1.965 Å) was observed in F<SB>3</SB>CH⋯HLi, while the shortest one (1.565 Å) was in the Br<SB>3</SB>CH⋯HK complex.</annotationART></s> <s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both methods exhibit the same trends: for chloroform and bromoform complexes the H⋯H distances calculated with the B3LYP method were larger than those calculated with the MP2 method, while in the case of the fluoroform complexes, the opposite situation was found.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">We were not able to interpret these changes and trends.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The H–M (M = Li, Na, K) bond in a proton acceptor can be contracted (HLi) or elongated (HK) upon complexation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">In complexes of these two molecules (HLi and HK) both theoretical methods exhibited changes in the same direction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">A different situation was found in the case of HNa molecules, where the MP2 method predicted elongation (0.0014, 0.0007 and 0.0028 Å) while the B3LYP method predicts contraction (−0.0009, −0.0022 and −0.0022 Å) upon complexation with F<SB>3</SB>CH, Cl<SB>3</SB>CH and Br<SB>3</SB>CH, respectively.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is obvious that contraction or elongation of the X–H bond is concomitant with an increase or decrease in the X–H stretching frequency (blue or red shift).</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">It must be stressed here that this relationship is valid for a large number of H-bonded and improper H-bonded complexes and up to now we are not aware of any exceptions.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Role of the electrostatic field</HEADER><P><s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The change in geometrical parameters induced by the electric field are presented in Table 1 in the “Electric field” column.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">Optimizing the structure of the proton donor in the electric field of a proton acceptor the electrostatic plus polarization effects are considered and the resulting geometry changes originate from the purely electrostatic (Coulombic) and polarization interactions between the proton donor and an electric field.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both theoretical methods predicted changes in the same direction, except for the C–H bond in bromoform complexes where the MP2 method predicted contraction while the B3LYP method predicted small elongation.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">The electric field produced by a proton acceptor yielded, in all complexes, contraction of the C–H bond (MP2 results).</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">This bond was systematically elongated in full complex calculations which indicates that non-electrostatic effects played a dominant role.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac23" novelty="None" advantage="None">A similar situation was previously found<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit49">49</REF> in the F<SB>3</SB>CH⋯Cl<SP>−</SP> complex, where the electric field caused a C–H bond contraction while full complex calculations yielded C–H bond elongation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Complexes studied thus represent another example where the standard H-bonding behavior (elongation of the C–H bond and a red shift of the C–H stretching vibration) could not be explained by the interaction of a molecule with the electric field and other effects should be considered.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" advantage="None">According to the data presented in Table 1, the X–C (X = F, Cl, Br) bonds were elongated in the electric field while these bonds were contracted in the full complex calculations.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None">The H–M bond (M = Li, Na, K), like the C–H bond, was contracted in an applied electric field.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, when performing full complex calculations this bond was either contracted (HLi) or elongated (HNa, HK) upon complexation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res29" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus it is again evident, that the electric field alone cannot explain the behavior of the HM bond in the complexes studied.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res30" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of the HNa and HK systems, non-electrostatic effects evidently play an important role and should be considered.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The last column in Table 1 (Full-electric) shows the changes in the bonds caused by non-electrostatic effects.</annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" advantage="None">Evidently, the changes are opposite to those caused by electrostatic effects.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res32" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of the C–H as well as the H–M (M = Li, Na, K) bonds, the electrostatic effects caused contraction while non-electrostatic effects caused elongation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res33" novelty="None" advantage="None">The opposite situation was found for X–C (X = F, Cl, Br) bonds, where electrostatic effects yielded elongation while non-electrostatic effects caused contraction.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Non-electrostatic effects</HEADER><P><s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res34" novelty="None" advantage="None">Electrostatic effects cause contraction of the C–H and H–M bonds while non-electrostatic effects caused their elongation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa4" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is now necessary to answer two questions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa5" novelty="None" advantage="None">First, what kind of non-electrostatic effects are responsible for this elongation?</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa6" novelty="None" advantage="None">And, second, are these non-electrostatic effects similar for C–H and H–M bonds?</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac24" novelty="None" advantage="None">According to the concept proposed by Alabugin <IT>et al</IT>.,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit50">50</REF> the change of the X–H bond length in the X–H⋯Y complexes is due to two main effects acting in opposite directions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res35" novelty="None" advantage="None">The hyperconjugative interaction is responsible for bond elongation while an increase in the s-character of the X atom hybrid orbital (known as Bent’s rule) and polarization of the X–H bond is responsible for bond contraction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res36" novelty="None" advantage="None">When the former effect dominates the X–H bond becomes longer and weaker (standard H-bonding), while when the latter effect is more significant, the bond becomes shorter and stronger.</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res37" novelty="None" advantage="None">Improper H-bonding is observed only when the hyperconjugative n(Y) → σ*(X–H) interaction is relatively weak and the respective NBO second-order charge-transfer energy is smaller than 3–5 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Table 2 summarizes the calculated second-order interaction energies between the donor–acceptor orbitals (<IT>E</IT><SP>2</SP>(σ(HM) → σ*(CH)).</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res38" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since the <IT>E</IT><SP>2</SP> energy was considerably larger than the mentioned limit (3–5 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>), hyperconjugative interaction was responsible for the C–H bond elongation in all of the complexes considered.</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res39" novelty="None" advantage="None">It should be stressed here that it was not a typical hyperconjugative interaction since electron density in these complexes was not transferred from a lone-pair orbital but from a σ(HM) orbital.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res40" novelty="None" advantage="None">Investigating the ED changes in the HM subsystems, we found an insignificant ED increase in the antibonding σ*(HM) orbital and a much larger decrease of ED in the bonding σ(HM) orbitals (see above).</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res41" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both effects, but mainly the latter one, were responsible for the elongation and weakening of the HM bond.</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res42" novelty="None" advantage="None">Let us mention here that a completely opposite situation was found for the σ(CH) and σ*(CH) orbitals.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Figs. 2 and 3 show changes in electron density (ED) in particular orbitals of the proton acceptor HLi (Fig. 2) and the proton donor F<SB>3</SB>CH (Fig. 3) caused by complexation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res43" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of HLi, the dominant change in electron density (decrease) occurs in the σ bonding orbital, while, with respect to the CHF<SB>3</SB>, it is the CH σ* antibonding orbital which is characterised by the largest change (increase).</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res44" novelty="None" advantage="None">From these figures it is also evident that electron density is transferred from HLi to the CHF<SB>3</SB>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res45" novelty="None" advantage="None">To determine which type of non-electrostatic effect plays a role in the change of the C–H bond length, we compared the bond length changes with the ED changes in antibonding Δσ*(CH) orbitals.</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res46" novelty="None" advantage="None">A linear relationship (value of the correlation coefficient of the linear regression <IT>R</IT><SP>2</SP> equals 0.994) between the elongation of this bond and an increase of ED in the σ*(C–H) orbital was found.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res47" novelty="None" advantage="None">This close correlation gives evidence that an increase in ED in the antibonding orbital of the C–H bond is responsible for elongation and weakening of this bond and, further, that it is a dominant non-electrostatic effect.</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res48" novelty="None" advantage="None">Concerning the HM (M = Li, Na, K) bond there is no doubt that the decrease in ED in the σ bonding orbital represents the main non-electrostatic effect responsible for the elongation and weakening of this bond that was observed.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac25" novelty="None" advantage="None">Berski <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit23">23</REF>. studied the xenon dihydride⋯water complex using DFT theory and concluded that there was no ED transfer (EDT) between subunits, and further, stabilization was mostly due to electrostatic interactions of the dipole–induced dipole type.</annotationART></s> <s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res49" novelty="None" advantage="None">Table 2 shows that the EDT between the proton acceptor and the proton donor is comparable to that in standard hydrogen bonding complexes and is much larger than in the case of improper blue-shifting hydrogen bonded complexes.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The NRT analysis allowed us to calculate the bond order and its character.</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Table 3 presents the total bond order and its covalent contribution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The difference between these values (“total” and “covalent”) gives an ionic contribution to the total bond order.</annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res50" novelty="None" advantage="None">As seen from this table the character of the H⋯H “bond” is ionic (the covalent contribution is negligible, less than 6%) and its value is between 0.015 and 0.057.</annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met14" novelty="Old" advantage="None">For the sake of comparison we performed NRT analysis for the standard (HOH⋯OH<SB>2</SB>, H<SB>3</SB>CH⋯Cl<SP>−</SP>, F<SB>3</SB>CH⋯Cl<SP>−</SP>) and improper blue-shifting hydrogen bonded complexes (H<SB>3</SB>CH⋯FH, F<SB>3</SB>CH⋯OH<SB>2</SB>, CH<SB>3</SB>CH<SB>3</SB>⋯OH<SB>2</SB>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res51" novelty="None" advantage="None">These calculations show that in both complex types the character of the hydrogen bond is purely ionic and is systematically smaller than 0.005.</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res52" novelty="None" advantage="None">The DHBs studied thus have the same character as standard or improper blue-shifting hydrogen bonds, but their ionicity is considerably higher.</annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res53" novelty="None" advantage="None">A negative value of the Δ(c − m) term indicates that all bond orders in the proton donor as well as in the proton acceptor decrease under complexation.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Charges on atoms</HEADER><P><s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Atomic charges on the monomers and the studied complexes are presented in Table 4.</annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met15" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Charges were determined with NBO analysis, MK (Merz–Kollman) and APT<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit51">51</REF> (atomic polar tensor) methods at the MP2/6-311++G(d,p) or B3LYP/6-311++G(d,p) levels.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res54" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hydrogen in the proton donor of the DHB complexes possessed a small negative (or positive) charge on the hydrogen atom (F<SB>3</SB>C–H (−0.02 e), Cl<SB>3</SB>CH (−0.04 e), Cl<SB>3</SB>CH (−0.06 e)), while hydrogen in the proton acceptor had a large negative charge on the hydrogen atom: HLi (−0.63 e), HNa (−0.60 e), HK (−0.69 e).</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res55" novelty="None" advantage="None">The values presented refer to APT charges.</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res56" novelty="None" advantage="None">The differences between the charges on the hydrogen atoms Δ<IT>q</IT>(H⋯H) lies between 0.7 and 1.0 e.</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res57" novelty="None" advantage="None">The smallest Δ<IT>q</IT>(H⋯H) was found in the sodium hydride with fluoroform complex (0.71 e), while the largest one was present in the potassium hydride with bromoform complex (0.97 e).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res58" novelty="None" advantage="None">By investigating the Δ<IT>q</IT>(C–H) values, we found that they decreased upon complexation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res59" novelty="None" advantage="None">Complexation made the charge on the H atoms more positive while the charge on the C atoms became less positive.</annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res60" novelty="None" advantage="None">An opposite situation was found in the proton acceptor subunit, where the value of Δ<IT>q</IT>(H–M) increased.</annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res61" novelty="None" advantage="None">The charge on the H atom became more negative upon complexation, while the charge on the M atom became more positive.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">When considering only the Δ<IT>q</IT> changes induced by complexation the following conclusions can be drawn:</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">• In the proton donor subunit, a decrease in Δ<IT>q</IT>(C–H) yields a weaker Coulombic attraction between the carbon and hydrogen atoms, which should cause elongation and weakening of the C–H bond.</annotationART></s> <s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res62" novelty="None" advantage="None">These effects were found in all investigated complexes.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">• In the proton acceptor subunit, an increase in Δ<IT>q</IT>(H–M) causes a stronger Coulombic attraction between the hydrogen and alkali metal atoms, which should yield contraction and strengthening of the H–M bond.</annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res63" novelty="None" advantage="None">This was found only in the lithium hydride complexes.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">We conclude this paragraph by stating that the behavior of the C–H and H–M bonds in the DHB complexes studied could not be explained only by changes in atomic charges.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Interaction energy terms</HEADER><P><s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met16" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Symmetry adapted perturbation theory was utilized for decomposition of the total intermolecular interaction energy into physically meaningful energy contributions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Table 5 shows the total SAPT interaction energy <IT>E</IT><SB>int</SB><SP>SAPT</SP>, the HF (<IT>E</IT><SB>int</SB><SP>HF</SP>) and correlation (<IT>E</IT><SP>corr</SP>, Σ<IT>E</IT><SP>corr</SP>) corrections to the interaction energy, as well as the stabilization energy (<IT>E</IT><SB>int</SB>) determined by the variation method.</annotationART></s> <s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met17" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The latter values are corrected for the basis set superposition error using the Boys–Bernardi counterpoise correction<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF> and also for the deformation energy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res64" novelty="None" advantage="None">Perturbation and variation stabilization energies are similar.</annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res65" novelty="None" advantage="None">The stabilization energies of the considered complexes (5–10 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>) are similar to those of standard hydrogen bonded complexes.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res66" novelty="None" advantage="None">As seen from Table 5, the absolute values of the <IT>E</IT><SB>int</SB> increase in the order: F<SB>3</SB>CH &lt; Cl<SB>3</SB>CH &lt; Br<SB>3</SB>CH and HLi &lt; HNa &lt; HK.</annotationART></s> <s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res67" novelty="None" advantage="None">The largest stabilization energy (9.52 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>) was found for the Br<SB>3</SB>CH⋯HK complex, with the smallest one (5.59 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>) for the F<SB>3</SB>CH⋯HLi complex.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res68" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the fluoroform containing complexes and in the Cl<SB>3</SB>CH⋯HLi complex, the absolute value of the polarization (electrostatic) term is larger than that for exchange–repulsion.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res68" novelty="None" advantage="None">In our recent paper,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit49">49</REF> we showed that the ratio of induction and dispersion energies (I/D index, presented in the last column of Table 5) represented a valuable tool for discriminating between standard and blue-shifted H-bonded complexes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res69" novelty="None" advantage="None">For standard H-bonded complexes this index is mostly higher than 1.0, while for blue-shifted H-bonded complexes it is mostly less than 1.0.</annotationART></s> <s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res70" novelty="None" advantage="None">The I/D index for the DHB complexes studied (<IT>cf</IT>. Table 5) is much larger than 1.0 which indicates that dispersion energy does not play as important a role in these complexes as in blue-shifted H-bonded complexes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res71" novelty="None" advantage="None">It should be mentioned that the values of the I/D ratio correlates with the size of the stabilization energy.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Thermodynamic properties</HEADER><P><s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac26" novelty="None" advantage="None">Wei-Liang Zhu <IT>et al</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit52">52</REF>. calculated the thermodynamic characteristics of the DHB complex formed by silicane and ammonium.</annotationART></s> <s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac27" novelty="None" advantage="None">The calculations were performed using the MP2 and B3LYP methods with different AO basis sets.</annotationART></s> <s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The authors concluded that diffusion and polarization functions had a significant effect on the calculated changes in the free energy (Δ<IT>G</IT>) and suggested that the basis set 6-311++G(d,p) should be used when the B3LYP method is employed.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="143"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met18" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The thermodynamic characteristics (enthalpy, Gibbs free energy, entropy and reaction rate constant) of the present DHB complexes were evaluated at the recommended level<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit52">52</REF> (B3LYP/6-311++G(d,p)).</annotationART></s> <s sid="144"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res72" novelty="None" advantage="None">The calculated Gibbs free energies of formation (Δ<IT>G</IT>) corrected by thermal and zero-point vibrational energies, range from −2.17 to 1.44 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="145"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res73" novelty="None" advantage="None">Only for potassium hydride complexes does the Δ<IT>G</IT> have negative values.</annotationART></s> <s sid="146"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res74" novelty="None" advantage="None">This means that only the F<SB>3</SB>CH⋯HK, Cl<SB>3</SB>CH⋯HK and Br<SB>3</SB>CH⋯HK complexes are stable under standard conditions (<IT>T</IT> = 298.150 K and <IT>p</IT> = 101.325 N m<SP>−2</SP>) in the gas phase.</annotationART></s> <s sid="147"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res75" novelty="None" advantage="None">The calculated enthalpy (Δ<IT>H</IT>) of formation, corrected by thermal energy, ranges from −5.12 to −8.62 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="148"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res76" novelty="None" advantage="None">The absolute value of Δ<IT>H</IT> increases in the following order: HLi &lt; HNa &lt; HK and F<SB>3</SB>CH &lt; Br<SB>3</SB>CH &lt; Cl<SB>3</SB>CH (with the exception of the potassium hydride complexes, where Δ<IT>H</IT> is largest for the Br<SB>3</SB>CH⋯HK complex).</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4.">Conclusions</HEADER><P><s sid="149"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res77" novelty="None" advantage="None">1) The stabilization energies of the complexes considered range from −5.59 to −9.52 kcal mol<SP>−1</SP> and are similar to those in standard hydrogen bonded complexes.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="150"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res78" novelty="None" advantage="None">2) The calculated Gibbs free energy (Δ<IT>G</IT>) is negative only for the potassium hydride complexes (F<SB>3</SB>CH⋯HK, Cl<SB>3</SB>CH⋯HK and Br<SB>3</SB>CH⋯HK), which means that only these complexes are stable under standard conditions in the gas phase (<IT>T</IT> = 298.150 K and <IT>p</IT> = 101.325 N m<SP>−2</SP>).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="151"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res79" novelty="None" advantage="None">3) According to NRT analysis the character of the H⋯H “bond” is 94% ionic and its total value ranges from 0.015 to 0.057.</annotationART></s> <s sid="152"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res80" novelty="None" advantage="None">This ionicity is larger than in standard and improper H-bonded complexes.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="153"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">4) Concerning the C–H and H–M (M = Li, Na, K) bonds in the DHB complexes investigated, electrostatic effects cause contraction while non-electrostatic effects cause elongation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="154"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The non-electroststic effects responsible for the elongation of the C–H and H–M bonds are completely different.</annotationART></s> <s sid="155"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Increasing the electron density in the antibonding orbital of the C–H bond causes elongation and weakening of this bond, evidently the dominant non-electrostatic effect.</annotationART></s> <s sid="156"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None">A decrease of the ED in the σ(HM) orbital represents the main non-electrostatic effect responsible for elongation and weakening of the HM bond.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="157"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None">5) In the case of the H–Li bond, the contraction of the bond upon complexation is explained by the electrostatic field.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="158"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None">6) The behavior of the C–H and H–M bonds in the DHB complexes studied can not be explained by the changes in atomic charge.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="159"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None">7) The ratio of induction and dispersion energies (I/D) is much larger than one and indicates standard hydrogen bonded character when the proton donor is considered.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="160"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None">8) MP2 and B3LYP yield similar results and an advantage of the latter procedure is the fact that it yields a reliable one-electron density matrix.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
