<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b411689e" hasDoc="yes" version="1168" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Protein solid-state NMR resonance assignments from (<SP>13</SP>C,<SP>13</SP>C) correlation spectroscopy</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">It is demonstrated that sequential resonance assignments can be obtained from (<SP>13</SP>C,<SP>13</SP>C) correlation spectroscopy on a uniformly labeled protein under magic angle spinning.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The experiment relies on weak (C′,Cα) coupling conditions using a defined range of MAS rates and can be employed at arbitrary magnetic field strength.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER /><P><s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Magic angle spinning<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF> (MAS) solid-state NMR is rapidly developing into a tool to study biomolecular 3D structure,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2 cit3 cit4 cit5">2–5</REF> protein aggregation<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6 cit7 cit8 cit9">6–9</REF> and ligand-binding to membrane receptors.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">For many structural studies, near-complete sequential resonance assignments are a prerequisite and have now been obtained for several (membrane) proteins.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11 cit12 cit13 cit14 cit15 cit16 cit17">11–17</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">MAS-based spectral assignment methods have thus far relied on a collection of (<SP>15</SP>N,<SP>13</SP>C) and (<SP>13</SP>C,<SP>13</SP>C) one-bond dipolar or scalar polarization transfer schemes (see, for example, <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">ref. 18</REF>) to determine inter-residue connectivities in the polypeptide of interest.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">While side-chain information may suffice to identify <SP>13</SP>C resonances in small peptides,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit10">10</REF> (<SP>13</SP>C,<SP>15</SP>N) isotope labeling and a triple channel (<SP>1</SP>H,<SP>13</SP>C,<SP>15</SP>N) NMR setup is mandatory in larger systems.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">In particular, several polarization transfer steps are necessary if sequential (Cα,Cα)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF> or side chain–side chain interactions are to be investigated in a single 2D experiment.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In principle, a reduction in the number of transfer units and hence an increase in efficiency of a sequential assignment protocol could be achieved if inter-residue side chain – side chain assignments are established using polarization transfer among local (C′,Cα) moieties only.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">For this purpose, polarization transfer must be mediated by a weak (inter-residue) coupling in the presence of two strong intra-residue (C′,Cα) interactions (Fig. 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">At the same time, the mixing scheme of choice should be applicable at arbitrary magnetic field strength <B><IT>B</IT></B><SB>0</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">While the latter aspect suggests a transfer unit that is insensitive to isotropic or anisotropic chemical shielding interactions, broadband polarization transfer schemes have been shown to be unfavorable if weak couplings are to be studied in the presence of larger dipolar interactions.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19 cit20 cit21 cit22 cit23">19–23</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Indeed, a series of quantum-mechanical (QM) model calculations assuming the four-spin topology given in Fig. 1 reveals that broadband zero or double-quantum transfer schemes fail to generate sizable inter-residue polarization exchange.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Instead, we consider in the following the phenomenon originally termed ‘nuclear cross relaxation induced by specimen rotation’ by Andrew and co-workers.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24 cit25">24,25</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Here, the rate of polarization exchange in a dipolar coupled spin pair is enhanced if a multiple <IT>n</IT> of the MAS rate <IT>ω</IT><SB>R</SB> (divided by the Larmor frequency <IT>ω</IT><SB>0</SB>) is equal to the chemical shift difference Δ<IT>Ω</IT>, <IT>i.e.</IT> Δ<IT>Ω</IT> = <IT>nω</IT><SB>R</SB>/<IT>ω</IT><SB>0</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Under proton decoupling conditions, this ‘rotational resonance’ (RR) mechanism has been successfully used to determine structural constraints in a variety of pair-wise (see, for example,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit6 cit26 cit27">6,26,27</REF>) and, more recently, uniformly labeled amino acids and polypeptides.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28 cit29 cit30 cit31 cit32">28–32</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Unlike broadband mixing, the transfer dynamics are in this case explicitly dependent on isotropic resonance offsets and the magnitude and orientation of anisotropic dipolar and chemical shielding (CSA) interactions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">While analytical solutions exist for the case of a dipolar-coupled two-spin system under exact RR conditions,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit33 cit34">33,34</REF> a theoretical treatment of dipolar polarization transfer under off-RR conditions in a four-spin system is more complicated.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">We hence resort to QM (four-spin) calculations that probe the signal intensity of the inter-residue transfer C′(<IT>i</IT> − 1) → Cα(<IT>i</IT>) in the presence of two strongly coupled intra-residue (C′,Cα) spin pairs.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Our simulations were conducted for a range of isotropic chemical shift differences Δ<IT>Ω</IT>(C′,Cα) (Fig. 1) assuming standard dipolar and CSA<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit35 cit36">35,36</REF> interactions under variable molecular orientations.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">As an example, the maximum Cα(<IT>i</IT>) signal intensity is plotted in Fig. 2a as a function of the MAS rate for static magnetic fields <B><IT>B</IT></B><SB>0</SB> corresponding to 400, 600 and 800 MHz <SP>1</SP>H resonance frequency.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None">Assuming an initial density operator that reflects longitudinal magnetization on the C′(<IT>i</IT> − 1) spin only, polarization transfer to Cα(<IT>i</IT>) was monitored in the initial rate regime (0.8 ms mixing time) setting Δ<IT>Ω</IT>(C′(<IT>i</IT> − 1),Cα(<IT>i</IT>)) = Δ<IT>Ω</IT>(<IT>i</IT> − 1,<IT>i</IT>) = 122 ppm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Intra-residue pairs with Δ<IT>Ω</IT>(<IT>i</IT> − 1,<IT>i</IT> − 1) = 111 ppm and Δ<IT>Ω</IT>(<IT>i</IT>,<IT>i</IT>) = 112 ppm were assumed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">As visible from Fig. 2a, inter-residue polarization transfer (including the complete four-spin system) is possible around the <IT>n</IT> = 2 (400–800 MHz) and <IT>n</IT> = 1 (400 MHz) RR conditions for the considered MAS rates.</annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Similar results are obtained if the magnitude or relative orientation of dipolar and CSA tensors is varied.</annotationART></s> <s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Even in the degenerate case, <IT>i.e.</IT> Δ<IT>Ω</IT>(<IT>i</IT> − 1,<IT>i</IT>) = Δ<IT>Ω</IT>(<IT>i</IT>,<IT>i</IT>) = Δ<IT>Ω</IT>(<IT>i</IT> − 1,<IT>i</IT> − 1), sizable polarization transfer is possible.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Comparative calculations assuming a (C′(<IT>i</IT> − 1),Cα(<IT>i</IT>),C′(<IT>i</IT>)) three-spin topology show that the latter result is only found if two sequential (C′,Cα) spin pairs are considered.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">According to our QM four-spin study, the polarization transfer profile shown in Fig. 2a within the inter-residue (C′,Cα) pair hence largely follows the general transfer characteristics of an isolated two-spin system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Normalized to the initial polarization, efficiencies of up to 20% for inter-residue polarization transfer are predicted from the simulation.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Setting the MAS rate at exact RR conditions would result in severe line broadening effects and hence must be avoided.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, sequential resonance assignments should be possible at variable <B><IT>B</IT></B><SB>0</SB>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">A band-selective (C′(<IT>i</IT> − 1),Cα(<IT>i</IT>)) polarization transfer profile can be created by changing the MAS rate during mixing<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit38">38</REF> or by incorporation of an additional radio frequency field on the <SP>13</SP>C channel.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13 cit31 cit39 cit40 cit41 cit42">13,31,39–42</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes">While these methods permit the use of MAS rates away from RR conditions they also strongly modulate or remove the chemical-shift dependence of the polarization scheme.</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="New" advantage="None">Preserving the general chemical shift selectivity and, at the same time, broadening the transfer profile can be achieved by removing proton decoupling during mixing.</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">The influence of the dipolar coupled proton reservoir has been described using first order perturbation theory<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24 cit43">24,43</REF> and is, in the context of our experiment, commonly referred to as proton-driven spin diffusion (PDSD, .<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit44">ref. 44</REF>)</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">PDSD mixing is possible for a variety of MAS rates and is characterized by an exponential rather than (damped) oscillatory (as in the two- or four-spin case) polarization transfer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the other hand, the rate of polarization exchange depends on the zero-quantum line-shape function exhibiting a maximum at Δ<IT>Ω</IT> = <IT>nω</IT><SB>R</SB>/<IT>ω</IT><SB>0</SB> in line with the theoretical four-spin simulations shown in Fig. 2.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">‘Weak coupling’ conditions can hence be created if an MAS rate close to the (but not at the exact) RR <IT>n</IT> = 2 transfer condition (<IT>i.e.</IT> around 125 ppm/2, Fig. 1) is selected and PDSD is active.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">As a result, polarization transfer is significantly slower than under exact RR conditions (Fig. 2a) but the desired mixing characteristics are preserved.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition to the C′(<IT>i</IT> − 1) → Cα(<IT>i</IT>) transfer, proton-driven spin diffusion also allows for subsequent polarization transfer from Cα(<IT>i</IT>) to side chain resonances of residue i.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">A standard two-dimensional PDSD experiment (see, for example, <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit11">ref. 11</REF> for further experimental details) hence should not only contain intra-residue correlations but also inter-residue cross peaks such as (C′(<IT>i</IT> − 1),Cα(<IT>i</IT>)), (Cα(<IT>i</IT> − 1),Cα(<IT>i</IT>)) and (Cα(<IT>i</IT> − 1),Cβ(<IT>i</IT>)).</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In Fig. 3, this effect is demonstrated on the uniformly (<SP>13</SP>C,<SP>15</SP>N) labeled tripeptide Ala–Gly–Gly for an MAS rate of 7 kHz on a 400 MHz instrument.</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">For a mixing time of 10 ms (Fig. 3a), only intra-residue (<SP>13</SP>C,<SP>13</SP>C) correlations are detected in agreement with the spectral assignments reported previously<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit45">45</REF> and in line with the general PDSD transfer profile.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Increasing the mixing time to 50 ms (Fig. 3b) leads, in addition, to the occurrence of sequential (C′,Cα) (left), (Cα,Cα) (middle) and (Cα,Cβ) cross peaks.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Inter-residue polarization transfer is enhanced if MAS rates close to the RR conditions are selected (Fig. 2b) in accordance with the QM model calculations (Fig. 2a).</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Line-broadening effects can be detected that are strongest at <IT>n</IT> = 1 conditions but range between 0–20% (compared to the <SP>13</SP>C line width far off RR conditions) if MAS rates close the <IT>n</IT> = 2 condition are selected.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Further experimental evidence that inter-residue polarization transfer indeed results from indirect (Cα ↔ C′ ↔ Cα) interactions comes from a 2D control experiment, in which C′ resonances are decoupled by a weak on-resonance rf field during mixing (data not shown).</annotationART></s> <s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this case, both C′ and Cα peaks are strongly attenuated indicative of a coupled spin state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">Additional experiments using variable mixing times reveal that the maximum intensity of the sequential (C′,Cα) and (Cα,Cα) cross peaks is detected for mixing times in the order of 50 ms and 100 ms, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">For reasons of spectral resolution and dispersion, the latter interactions are, along with additional side-chain correlations, most informative for sequential (<SP>13</SP>C,<SP>13</SP>C) resonance assignments.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">To investigate the use of weakly coupled (C′,Cα) correlation spectroscopy in larger systems and at higher magnetic fields, we conducted experiments on two uniformly labeled proteins.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None">In Fig. 4, results are shown for the 76-residue protein ubiquitin obtained on a 600 MHz WB instrument (Bruker Biospin Germany) using an MAS rate of 9.375 kHz (<IT>i.e.</IT> 125 ppm/2, see Fig. 1) and a mixing time of 100 ms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">Line broadening effects can be neglected and a variety of inter-residue Cα–Cα and Cα–Cβ cross peaks are readily observed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None">These dependencies are highlighted in Fig. 4 for the 4 amino-acid segment E64-L67.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Inter and intra-residue correlations are indicated on the left and right side of the diagonal, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">The backbone Cα–Cα ‘walk’ is facilitated by the occurrence of sequential (Cα,Cβ) and (Cβ,Cβ) correlations that can be used to cross validate the assignment procedure.</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None">We note that the resulting spectral assignments have been confirmed by additional NC correlation experiments<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit47">47</REF> and largely agree with chemical shift values reported recently by McDermott <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit16">16</REF></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Fig. 5 contains results obtained on an 800 MHz narrow-bore instrument (Bruker Biospin, Germany) on a uniformly (<SP>13</SP>C,<SP>15</SP>N) labeled sample of the 38-residue protein Kaliotoxin.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit48">48</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Again, the MAS rate was placed close to the <IT>n</IT> = 2 condition (12.5 kHz) and a mixing time of 150 ms was employed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" advantage="None">A variety of sequential (Cα,Cα) correlations can be readily identified.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None">Cross validation using a series of NCACB and NCOCA experiments reveals that these correlations again correspond to (<IT>i</IT>,<IT>i</IT> − 1) connectivities, for example of the eleven-residue stretch E3-Q13 highlighted in Fig. 5.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None">In conclusion, we have described a set of experimental conditions that permit establishing inter-residue correlations under MAS conditions from a single (<SP>13</SP>C,<SP>13</SP>C) correlation experiment.</annotationART></s> <s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res29" novelty="None" advantage="None">For a given <B><IT>B</IT></B><SB>0</SB> field, the technique relies on establishing weak (C′,Cα) coupling conditions using a defined range of MAS rates.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res30" novelty="None" advantage="None">Once sequential (C′,Cα) transfer is achieved, additional correlations (mediated by proton-driven spin diffusion) between side chain moieties are possible.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" advantage="None">As confirmed by further test experiments, simply increasing the selected mixing time leads to the occurrence of additional inter-residue correlations, including (i,i + 2) peaks.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Such extensions can greatly facilitate the spectral assignment process and are only limited by <IT>T</IT><SB>1</SB> relaxation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since no <SP>15</SP>N evolution and mixing periods are required, the overall signal to noise ratio can be significantly improved.</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Experiments can be performed on uniformly labeled protein samples at various magnetic fields.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res32" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the presented applications, the MAS rate was selected based on statistical considerations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res33" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the presence of (C′,Cα) chemical shift variations, for example, due to the influence of secondary structure or hydrogen bonding, adjustments of MAS rate and mixing time may be necessary.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res34" novelty="None" advantage="None">Such conditions were successfully applied to the proteins considered here and reveal that weak (C′,Cα) coupling conditions can be established for a variety of experimental setups.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res35" novelty="None" advantage="None">Compared to sequential resonance assignments obtained from chemical-shift selective (N,C) correlation spectroscopy,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit47">47</REF> 2D (<SP>13</SP>C,<SP>13</SP>C) data recorded under weak coupling conditions contain both intra- and inter-residue correlations.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res36" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, both contributions can be easily separated by recording an additional 2D spectrum for short mixing times (see Fig. 3) or by using MAS rates <IT>ω</IT><SB>R</SB>/<IT>ω</IT><SB>0</SB> ≫ Δ<IT>Ω</IT>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The transfer scheme can be easily incorporated into other, multi-dimensional correlation schemes without loss in spectral resolution.</annotationART></s> <s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res37" novelty="None" advantage="None">In particular, these experiments may provide a useful reference for the analysis of proton-mediated (<SP>13</SP>C,<SP>13</SP>C) correlation experiments.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit51">5,51</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res38" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition to the applications discussed here, weak coupling conditions may also be employed to monitor correlations between C′ spins and methyl or aromatic side-chain carbons.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
