<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b413535k" hasDoc="yes" version="1213" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">Bio-mimicking galactose oxidase and hemocyanin, two dioxygen-processing copper proteins</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The modelling of the active sites of metalloproteins is one of the most challenging tasks in bio-inorganic chemistry.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Copper proteins form part of this stimulating field of research as copper enzymes are mainly involved in oxidation bio-reactions.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, the understanding of the structure–function relationship of their active sites will allow the design of effective and environmental friendly oxidation catalysts.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">This perspective illustrates some outstanding structural and functional synthetic models of the active site of copper proteins, with special attention given to models of galactose oxidase and hemocyanin.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="1">Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The study and modeling of the active site of copper-containing proteins is a field of great interest within the scientific community.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit1">1</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Indeed, proteins containing copper ions at the active site are mainly involved as redox catalysts in a range of biological processes, such as electron transfer, dioxygen transport and oxidation of various bio-substrates (Fig. 1).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit2 cit3">2,3</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, new and very effective bio-inspired homogeneous catalysts for common reactions under mild conditions may be discovered.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit4">4</REF> </annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Copper-containing proteins are widely found in plants, insects, and mammals and have been divided into seven classes according to the structure of their active site,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit5 cit6 cit7">5–7</REF> namely type-1, type-2, type-3, multicopper, Cu<SB>A</SB>, Cu<SB>B</SB>, and Cu<SB>Z</SB> clusters.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">The present review primarily deals with the background of the structural and functional modeling of the type-2 and the type-3 active sites of, respectively, galactose oxidase (GOase) and hemocyanin (Hc).</annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">These two metalloproteins have received considerable attention, and some recent outstanding developments have been reported in the literature, updating the future outlook of copper chemistry.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit8 cit9 cit10 cit11">8–11</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this perspective, a number of biomimetic coordination compounds are presented together with their potential applications in catalysis, or drug discovery.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2">Galactose oxidase: A type-2 copper protein</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.1">Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Galactose oxidase (GOase) is an enzyme with a type-2 copper site, first isolated in 1959,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit12">12</REF> that selectively catalyzes the oxidation of primary alcohols to the corresponding aldehydes and simultaneous reduction of molecular oxygen to hydrogen peroxide.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The active site of GOase involves a mononuclear copper(ii) species with a distorted square pyramidal geometry.</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">As the oxidation reaction requires 2 e<SP>−</SP> and copper is a 1 e<SP>−</SP> redox metal ion, one of the phenol ligands is most likely involved in the oxidative transformation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Indeed, in the active form of the bio-catalyst, the equatorial plane is formed by two nitrogen atoms from two histidine imidazoles, one oxygen atom of an <IT>ortho</IT>-S-modified tyrosyl radical and one oxygen atom of a water molecule.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The axial position is occupied by a second tyrosinate ligand (Fig. 2, species <B>A</B>).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The catalytic mechanism of GOase has been extensively studied (Fig. 2).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit14">14</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The primary alcohol first coordinates to the active species <B>A</B>, leading to the metal–phenoxyl radical complex <B>B</B>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">This species undergoes proton abstraction from the substrate by the axial tyrosinate, followed by a rapid intramolecular electron transfer from the intermediate ketyl radical anion with reduction of Cu<SP>II</SP> to Cu<SP>I</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The copper(i) species <B>C</B> reacts with dioxygen to form the hydroperoxo copper(ii) complex <B>D</B> with the release of the aldehyde.</annotationART></s> <s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Finally, hydrogen peroxide is released to give back the active form of the enzyme.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Over twenty years, a number of structural models have been reported in the literature<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit15 cit16">15,16</REF>, but it appears to be more difficult to model the catalytic activity of GOase<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit17">17</REF>. </annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.2">Structural and functional models of GOase</HEADER><P><s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The first effective biomimetic catalysts were described in 1998 by Stack <IT>et</IT><IT>al</IT>. <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF> and by Wieghardt <IT>et al</IT>. <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19">19</REF></annotationART></s></P><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.2.1">[Cu(ii)BSP]</HEADER><P><s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Stack <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit18">18</REF> described a Cu(ii) species, namely [Cu(ii)BSP] where BSP symbolises a salen-type ligand with a binaphthyl backbone and thioether functions (Fig. 3), able to catalyse the oxidation of benzylic and allylic alcohols under dioxygen at room temperature.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The [Cu(ii)BSP] complex has spectroscopic characteristics similar to those of GOase.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">0.01 to 0.06% of this copper catalyst can convert neat benzylic and allylic alcohols to their respective aldehydes or ketones in the presence of a basic co-catalyst (Table 1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Up to 1000 turnovers (TON) were achieved and no further oxidation of the aldehyde products was observed.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">The oxidation reactions can also be performed in acetonitrile solutions, although the catalyst is much less efficient in this solvent (Table 1).</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.2.2">[Cu(ii)(2,2′-thiobis(2,4-di-<IT>tert</IT>-butylphenol))]</HEADER><P><s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">Wieghardt <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19">19</REF> similarly reported the catalytic oxidation of primary and secondary alcohols by a dinuclear Cu(ii)–phenoxyl complex at 20 °C under air.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reaction of Cu<SP>I</SP>Cl with 2,2′-thiobis(2,4-di-<IT>tert</IT>-butylphenol) and triethylamine (1∶1∶2) in dry methanol under air leads to a mononuclear blue copper complex (Fig. 4).</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">This coordination compound was synthesized to model the active site of GOase.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Its crystal structure shows a non-expected complex where the sulfur atom of the ligand coordinates to the uncommon tetracoordinated Cu<SP>II</SP> ion (Fig. 5b).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, only one triethylamine is coordinated to the metal center while two were required to mimic the N donors of the histidine residues, and no methanol molecule is present as substrate model (Fig. 5).</annotationART></s> <s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, a diamagnetic copper compound is formed in THF solution which exhibits spectral features characteristic for coordinated phenoxyl groups (<IT>λ</IT><SB>max</SB> ≈ 404 nm, <IT>ε</IT> = 8.0 × 10<SP>3</SP> L mol<SP>−1</SP> cm<SP>−1</SP>; Raman: <IT>λ</IT><SB>exc</SB> = 458 nm, <IT>ν</IT>(C–O˙) = 1451 cm<SP>−1</SP>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This complex is most likely dinuclear in solution with two bridging phenolate groups and two phenoxyl ligands as depicted in Fig. 6.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">0.2% of the [Cu<SP>I</SP>Cl(2,2′-thiobis(2,4-di-<IT>tert</IT>-butylphenol))(NEt<SB>3</SB>)<SB>2</SB>] catalyst prepared <IT>in</IT>-<IT>situ</IT> at 50 °C in THF was used to oxidise several alcohols at room temperature in air and the most important results are summarized in Table 2.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, ethanol was converted to acetaldehyde with a yield of 63% (TON = 315), but the reaction is not chemoselective.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Indeed, several side-products resulting from C–C coupling were detected (Table 2).</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac20" novelty="None" advantage="None">The same results were observed for the oxidation of benzyl alcohol with the formation of 60% (TON = 300) benzaldehyde, small amounts of 1,2-glycol and α-hydroxyketone, and 3–4% of α-diketone (Table 2).</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac21" novelty="None" advantage="None">Contrary to GOase, this copper catalyst is also able to oxidise secondary alcohols.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac22" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, 2-propanol and diphenylcarbinol can be used as substrates but, in both cases, only the 1,2-diol derivatives resulting from an oxidative C–C coupling are formed with a yield of 61 and 68%, respectively (Table 2).</annotationART></s> <s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac23" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast, the aerobic oxidation of 2-butanol exclusively leads to the formation of butan-2-one (yield = 39%; TON = 195), suggesting two different reaction pathways for the formation of the carbonyl compounds and for the formation of the 1,2-glycols (Fig. 7).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit19">19</REF> </annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Ethanol, benzyl alcohol or 2-butanol coordinate to the proposed dinuclear copper complex (Fig. 6) to produce the active species <B>I</B> (Fig. 7).</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod12" novelty="None" advantage="None">After H abstraction by one of the two phenoxyl groups, a radical is created which is oxidised to the corresponding carbonyl derivative by the second phenoxyl radical.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod13" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of 2-propanol and diphenylcarbinol, two alcohol molecules coordinate to the dinuclear moiety resulting in species <B>II</B> (Fig. 7).</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The H abstractions by the two phenoxyl ligands generate two secondary radicals which can undergo C–C coupling to give the 1,2-glycol products.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac24" novelty="None" advantage="None">GOase obviously represents an attractive target for the development of bio-inspired approaches aimed at designing selective and environmentally friendly, green oxidation catalysts. <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit20">20</REF></annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.2.3">CuBr<SB>2</SB>(Bpy)–TEMPO<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF></HEADER><P><s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac25" novelty="None" advantage="None">The two pioneering bio-mimicking catalysts described above have inspired the scientific community resulting in a number of oxidation Cu-catalysts being reported over the past five years.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit22">22</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac26" novelty="None" advantage="None">Nevertheless, none of these catalytic systems are able to selectively convert primary alcohols to the corresponding aldehydes like the natural enzyme.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit13">13</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac27" novelty="None" advantage="None">Recently, some of us developed a catalytic procedure for the selective aerobic oxidation of primary alcohols to aldehydes based on a CuBr<SB>2</SB>(Bpy)–TEMPO system (Bpy = 2,2′-bipyridine).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21 cit23">21,23</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac28" novelty="None" advantage="None">The reactions are carried out under air at room temperature and are catalysed by a [copper<SP>II</SP>(bipyridine ligand)] complex and 2,2,6,6-tetramethylpiperidinyl-1-oxy (TEMPO) and base as co-catalysts (Fig. 8).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac29" novelty="None" advantage="None">Several primary benzylic, allylic and aliphatic alcohols have been successfully oxidized with excellent conversions (61–100%) and selectivities as no by-products were detected (Table 3).</annotationART></s> <s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac30" novelty="None" advantage="None">These results show that the oxidation of activated alcohols is faster than aliphatic ones, demonstrating that the hydrogen abstraction from the α-carbon atom by TEMPO (Fig. 9b) is most likely the rate-determining step.</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac31" novelty="None" advantage="None">No reaction was observed with 1-phenylethanol, an activated secondary benzylic alcohol, or with octan-2-ol which can be associated with the activity of GOase.</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod15" novelty="None" advantage="None">Indeed, the proposed active species for this catalytic oxidation can be considered as a model of the active site of GOase (Fig. 9).</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac32" novelty="None" advantage="None">The bipyridine N atoms mimic the two histidine ligands, while TEMPO plays the role of both the phenolate and the phenoxyl groups and is most likely involved as a hydrogen acceptor.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit21">21</REF> </annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac33" novelty="None" advantage="None">Competitive experiments were performed in order to confirm this high selectivity towards primary alcohols.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac34" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, mixtures of benzyl alcohol with octan-2-ol or 1-phenylethanol were reacted and no carbonyl products corresponding to the oxidation of the secondary alcohols were observed at all (Table 3).</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac35" novelty="None" advantage="None">This lack of reactivity of secondary alcohols may be explained by two factors affecting the catalytic cycle.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod16" novelty="None" advantage="None">(1) Steric effects between the methyl groups of TEMPO and the alcohol can hinder the formation of the active species (Fig. 10a), crucial for the C–H abstraction.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod17" novelty="None" advantage="None">(2) In addition, in the case of primary alcohols, the second β-hydrogen atom can be H-bonded to the oxygen atom of TEMPOH, stabilising the radical intermediate (Fig. 10b).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">This bpy/TEMPO-based catalytic system should be regarded as the first synthetic functional model of galactose oxidase as both, the achieved chemoselectivity and the proposed reaction mechanism are close to those of the biological copper enzyme.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Nevertheless, this functional model is not able to compete with the natural enzyme in terms of catalytic efficiency.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac36" novelty="None" advantage="None">Indeed, the rate of turnover is only 0.006 s<SP>−1</SP> while it is 800 s<SP>−1</SP> for GOase.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit24">24</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The goal of future research investigations is therefore to improve the proficiency of the catalyst to obtain an economically interesting system for an industrial application.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3">Hemocyanin: A type-3 copper protein</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.1">Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac37" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hemocyanin (Hc) is a protein with a type-3 copper site, initially studied in the early 70's<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit25">25</REF> and the crystal structure of its active form was first reported in .1993<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit26 cit27">26,27</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac38" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hcs are copper-containing respiratory proteins, freely dissolved in the hemolymph of many arthropod and mollusc species.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit28">28</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod18" novelty="None" advantage="None">This function is related to the capacity of Hc to reversibly bind molecular oxygen at the active site that is a dinuclear copper center.</annotationART></s> <s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The protein is thus found in two different forms, <IT>i.e</IT>. deoxy-Hc, containing a [Cu(i) Cu(i)] pair with a Cu–Cu distance of 4.6 Å, and oxy-Hc.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod20" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the latter form, dioxygen was found to bridge between both copper(ii) ions separated by a distance of 3.6 Å, reflecting an electron transfer process from Cu(i) to dioxygen, where the peroxide dianion is coordinated as a bidentate ligand in a µ-η<SP>2</SP>:η<SP>2</SP> fashion (Fig. 11).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod21" novelty="None" advantage="None">The active site of Hc involves a dinuclear copper species.</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod22" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the active form of the biomolecule, the equatorial plane of each Cu<SP>II</SP> ion is formed by two nitrogen atoms from two histidine imidazoles and the two oxygen atoms of a dioxygen molecule.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod23" novelty="None" advantage="None">The axial position is occupied by a third histidine ligand (Fig. 11).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac39" novelty="None" advantage="None">Extensive synthetic efforts have been made to prepare Cu<SP>II</SP> dioxygen complexes using different types of ligands in order to provide a better insight into the binding mode of molecular oxygen in oxyhemocyanin.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac40" novelty="None" advantage="None">In this context, various binding modes of dioxygen have been brought to light and their characteristic spectroscopic features are reported in Table 4.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.2">Structural and functional models of Hc</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.2.1">Monucleating ligands</HEADER><P><s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac41" novelty="None" advantage="None">As early as 1988, Karlin <IT>et al.</IT> described the first structurally characterized Cu<SB>2</SB>O<SB>2</SB> species using a tripodal N<SB>4</SB> ligand, namely tris(2-pyridylmethyl)amine (Fig. 12).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29">29</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac42" novelty="None" advantage="None">This dioxygen adduct is intensely purple coloured while oxyhemocyanin is intensely blue.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac43" novelty="None" advantage="None">The complex shows strong absorptions at 440, 525, and 590 nm and an additional d–d band at 1035 nm, and Raman vibrations at 832 cm<SP>−1</SP> and 561 cm<SP>−1</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac44" novelty="None" advantage="None">These spectroscopic data are not characteristic of the µ-η<SP>2</SP>:η<SP>2</SP> dioxygen binding mode observed in oxy-Hc (see Table 4), and have been assigned to peroxo-to-copper charge transfer transitions, and to an intraperoxide O–O stretch and a copper–oxygen stretch, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac45" novelty="None" advantage="None">The 832 cm<SP>−1</SP> stretching vibration clearly indicates the oxidation state of the dioxygen moiety to be O<SB>2</SB><SP>2−</SP>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac46" novelty="None" advantage="None">X-ray data of the thermally and moisture sensitive material were obtained at –90 °C.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac47" novelty="None" advantage="None">It contains an end-on <IT>trans</IT> µ-1,2 peroxo group (<IT>viz.</IT> µ-1,2-O<SB>2</SB><SP>2−</SP>) bridging the two copper(ii) ions (Fig. 12; Table 4) (Cu⋯Cu = 4.36 Å).</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac48" novelty="None" advantage="None">This peroxo compound is only stable below −70 °C.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit30">30</REF> </annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac49" novelty="None" advantage="None">A very important step forward in type-3 copper protein biomimetics was reported in 1989 when Kitajima <IT>et al.</IT><REF TYPE="P" ID="cit31">31</REF> reported a copper–dioxygen complex obtained from an anionic tripodal N<SB>3</SB> ligand, <IT>i.e</IT>. tris(3,5-diisopropylpyrazolyl)borate ligand (Fig. 13).</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac50" novelty="None" advantage="None">This deeply purple coloured compound is a stable solid at room temperature or even in non-coordinating solvent (<IT>e.g</IT>. CHCl<SB>3</SB>, CH<SB>2</SB>Cl<SB>2</SB>) below −10 °C.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit32">32</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac51" novelty="None" advantage="None">This good stability of the Cu<SP>II</SP>–dioxygen adduct is probably due to the isopropyl groups of the ligand which shield the coordinated molecular oxygen (Fig. 13).</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac52" novelty="None" advantage="None">The most remarkable feature observed in its X-ray structure appeared to be the side-on µ-η<SP>2</SP>:η<SP>2</SP>-peroxo coordination that holds the two copper units together.</annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac53" novelty="None" advantage="None">Moreover, the physical properties reported are qualitatively and quantitatively comparable to those of oxy-Hc (See Table 4).</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac54" novelty="None" advantage="None">This complex indeed shows UV-Vis absorptions at 349 nm (<IT>ε</IT> = 21,000) and 551 nm (<IT>ε</IT> = 800), while for oxyhemocyanin the values are: 340 nm (<IT>ε</IT> = 20,000) and 580 nm (<IT>ε</IT> = 1,000).</annotationART></s> <s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac55" novelty="None" advantage="None">The low value of the O–O stretch of 741 cm<SP>−1</SP> (resonance Raman) also matches the value reported for oxyhemocyanin (744–752 cm<SP>−1</SP>).</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.2.2">Dinucleating ligands</HEADER><P><s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac56" novelty="None" advantage="None">The assumed advantage of using dinucleating ligands to prepare dioxo complexes is their ability to overcome the entropic barrier by keeping two N<SB>3</SB> or N<SB>4</SB> donor sets close to each other, at a chosen distance defined by the spacer length.</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac57" novelty="None" advantage="None">The spacers used to connect two coordinating units can be alkyl chains,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit33">33</REF> phenoxo bridges,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit34">34</REF> xylyl bridges<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit35">35</REF> or cyclohexyl bridges.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit36">36</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac58" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, Karlin <IT>et al.</IT> prepared a dinucleating ligand by linking two mononucleating tris(2-pyridylmethyl)amine (TPA) ligands through an ethylene bridge.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit37 cit38">37,38</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac59" novelty="None" advantage="None">A similar <IT>trans</IT> µ-1,2-peroxo-dicopper(ii) species could be obtained with this ligand (Figs. 12 and 14), which shows the characteristic UV-Vis absorptions (420 nm, 540 nm, and 600 nm) and Raman resonance (O–O stretch at 830 cm<SP>−1</SP>) for this type of dioxygen binding mode (Table 4).</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac60" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, this bis-TPA peroxo complex has a half-life time of 20 s at room temperature, while the TPA-peroxo species is only stable below −70 °C.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac61" novelty="None" advantage="None">This significant enhancement of the stability clearly reflects the benefit achieved through the bridging of two TPA moieties.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit39">39</REF> </annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac62" novelty="None" advantage="None">Very recently, Kodera <IT>et al</IT>. <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit40">40</REF> took advantage of all the research investigations performed in this field to synthesize a ligand featuring almost every beneficial characteristic which are: (1) a N<SB>3</SB> donor set in order to obtain the biomimetic side-on µ-η<SP>2</SP>:η<SP>2</SP> dioxygen binding mode of oxy-Hc; (2) a bridge between two monucleating units to increase the stability of the peroxo complex prepared; (3) and sterically hindered alkyl groups close to the N donor atoms to further enhance the stability of the µ-1,2-O<SB>2</SB><SP>2−</SP>-dicopper(ii) adduct.</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac63" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, Kodera <IT>et al</IT>. prepared the ligand 1,2-bis[2-(bis(6-methyl-2-pyridyl)methyl)-6-pyridyl]ethane which possesses all these essential features.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac64" novelty="None" advantage="None">Indeed, a µ-η<SP>2</SP>:η<SP>2</SP> peroxo complex could be synthesized from this ligand which was found stable, at room temperature, for 3.6 h in dichloromethane solution.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit40">40</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac65" novelty="None" advantage="None">As expected, the peroxo complex exhibits the typical spectroscopic data of the binding mode encountered in oxy-Hc (Table 4) that are UV-Vis absorption bands at 366 nm and 537 nm, and a Raman O–O stretch at 765 cm<SP>−1</SP>. </annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac66" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, the dioxygen binding is reversible which confers to this biomimetic compound, the status of best synthetic model of hemocyanin reported so far.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.2.3">Macrocyclic ligands</HEADER><P><s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="None" advantage="Yes">One step further than dinucleating ligands is the macrocyclic system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="None" advantage="Yes">The believed benefit of using macrocyclic ligands in coordination chemistry is the high predictability of their metal complexes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac67" novelty="None" advantage="None">In principle, macrocyclic ligands can be designed to hold the proper donor groups in a preorganized rigid three-dimensional environment.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit41 cit42">41,42</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac68" novelty="None" advantage="None">Therefore, the macrocyclic ligand usually has a lower degree of conformational freedom in solution which may prevent the formation of unexpected or unwanted compounds upon coordination to the metallic centres.</annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac69" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, highly reactive copper-peroxo species trapped in a macrocycle, might be stabilised.</annotationART></s> <s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac70" novelty="None" advantage="None">Recently, the use of the macrocyclic ligand MePy22Pz (Fig. 15) by some of us also produced a room-temperature stable Cu<SB>2</SB>O<SB>2</SB> species.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit43">43</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac71" novelty="None" advantage="None">Single crystals suitable for X-ray diffraction could not be obtained, but the spectroscopic data (<IT>viz.</IT> UV-Vis and resonance Raman) are comparable to those observed by Karlin (Section 3.2.1).</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac72" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, a <IT>trans</IT>-µ-1,2-peroxo-dicopper(ii) structure has been assigned, which is room temperature stable for 0.5 h in dichloromethane and air-stable for months in the solid-state (Fig. 16)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit44">44</REF>. </annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.3">New applications</HEADER><P><s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac73" novelty="None" advantage="None">Synthetic models of tyrosinase<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit45">45</REF> or catechol oxidase<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit46">46</REF> have found many applications in catalysis.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit47">47</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac74" novelty="None" advantage="None">An important and rising field of application is the design of copper-based anti-cancer drugs.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit48">48</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac75" novelty="None" advantage="None">This perspective will highlight just a few of these last ones.</annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac76" novelty="None" advantage="None">One way to eradicate cancer cells is to cleave their DNA,<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit49">49</REF> like the cleavage of the DNA strands through the oxidation of the sugar moieties (Fig. 17).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit50">50</REF> </annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac77" novelty="None" advantage="None">This type of cytotoxic activity is shown by some copper complexes which act as synthetic chemical nucleases.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit51">51</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac78" novelty="None" advantage="None">One goal in the field of anti-cancer drug discovery is to synthesize metal complexes able to cleave both strands of a DNA molecule.</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac79" novelty="None" advantage="None">Indeed, a single-strand break (SSB, Fig. 18a) leads to damaged DNA which can often be easily repaired by the cellular enzymatic machinery.</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac80" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the other hand, if both DNA strands are broken (DSB, Fig. 18b), the restoration of the initial double-stranded supramolecule becomes almost impossible, the two DNA pieces being far apart.</annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac81" novelty="None" advantage="None">Consequently, a drug able to perform DSBs will be very effective, as are the known natural bleomycin<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit52">52</REF> and neocarzinostatin.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit53">53</REF> </annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac82" novelty="None" advantage="None">The relaxation of supercoiled circular DNA (form I) into relaxed (form II) and linear (form III) forms is commonly used to quantify the relative cleavage efficiencies of different complexes (Fig. 19).</annotationART></s> <s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac83" novelty="None" advantage="None">A single-strand break (SSB) leads to form II while more than one SSB result in form III which is practically not repairable for the cellular enzymes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac84" novelty="None" advantage="None">A very effective cytotoxic drug would be a synthetic nuclease capable of performing a direct DSB (Figs. 18b and 19).</annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac85" novelty="None" advantage="None">Indeed, more the one SSB on the same DNA molecule is statistically barely probable.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac86" novelty="None" advantage="None">Recently, Karlin <IT>et al</IT>. <REF TYPE="P" ID="cit54 cit55 cit56">54–56</REF> tested the peroxo complexes described in Sections 3.2.1 and 3.2.2 (See Figs. 12 and 14), as DNA cleaving agents.</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac87" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results are depicted in Fig. 20.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac88" novelty="None" advantage="None">Both coordination compounds are active, but the mononuclear complex obtained from the tripodal ligand tris(2-pyridylmethyl)amine (TPA) is not effective in linearizing supercoiled DNA, as only the circular form II is detected on the agarose gel (Fig. 20a).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit54">54</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac89" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast, the dinuclear copper complex obtained from the ethylene-bridged TPA ligand (see Fig. 14) is capable of mediating the conversion of supercoiled DNA (Form I) to its linear form III (Fig. 20b).<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit54">54</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac90" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results suggest that the dinuclear complex is able to perform more than one SSB (possibly a DSB) on the same DNA molecule while the mononuclear complex obviously cannot (See Fig. 19).</annotationART></s> <s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac91" novelty="None" advantage="None">In addition, this significant difference in activity is consistent with their relative abilities to activate molecular oxygen (See Sections 3.2.1 and 3.2.2)<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit54">54</REF>. </annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4">Concluding remarks</HEADER><P><s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac92" novelty="None" advantage="None">The study and modeling of the active site of dioxygen-processing copper proteins such as galactose oxidase or hemocyanin was started some fifteen years ago with the pioneering work of Karlin<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit29">29</REF> and Kitajima.<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit31">31</REF></annotationART></s> <s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac93" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the first outstanding applications ensuing from these research investigations have only been reported some ten years later, in 1998.</annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac94" novelty="None" advantage="None">Nevertheless, over the past six years, an increasing amount of applied synthetic models of the type-2<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit57">57</REF> and type-3<REF TYPE="P" ID="cit58">58</REF> active site of copper proteins have been described in the literature almost weekly.</annotationART></s> <s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, a considerable development can be expected in the coming years in this still incipient field, demonstrating the importance of bio-mimicking nature.</annotationART></s> <s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Copper oxidation chemistry is assured a great future.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
